<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: trip report | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/trip-report/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-03-05T16:46:40+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[24 hours in Sipoonkorpi National Park (A Microadventure)]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/microadventure-sipoonkorpi-national-park.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-16T10:34:01+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/microadventure-sipoonkorpi-national-park</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you prefer the Outdoors over Cities but need to go to Helsinki - squeeze in a Microadventure to Sipoonkorpi National Park the next time you are in the Capital of Finland!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337489450/in/dateposted/" title="Chilling at Sunset"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/976/40337489450_c4f9faa8f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling at Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Last week I was going to Helsinki for <a href="https://pingfestival.fi">PING Festival 2018</a> and I decided to sneak in a wee Microadventure in <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/sipoonkorpinp">Sipoonkorpi National Park</a> before the event. Sipoonkorpi is a new-ish National Park and less than an hour by bus away from the centre of Helsinki, so it makes for an excellent place to escape the city for a while and enjoy this unique park with its forests, hills and beautiful nature. If you prefer Video over photos and want to see some enchanting Drone Footage, relaxed hiking and me brushing my teeth just hit play:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZXMh_jyu2es?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I took the train to Helsinki, a great way to do some work and watch the latest Episode of Neo Magazine Royale, and then jumped on the Tram to the Clarion Helsinki to drop of the stuff I needed for the following few days in Helsinki and Ruka. Then it was off with the Bus to Sipoonkorpi National Park, which lays on the outskirts of Vantaa, one of the three cities which makes up the Helsinki Metropolitan area. I got off in the middle of nowhere at a scenic road. I followed the sign to the Tractor Museum and then just walked down the road where I saw the blue “Sipoonkorpi National Park” sign. Shortly after I saw the Luontopolku sign, this trail can be walked in either direction but as it was early in the day and I had an idea where I wanted to sleep and what I wanted to see when I followed the trail first north.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144268101/in/dateposted/" title="Entering the National Park"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/830/42144268101_25ab3fb891_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Entering the National Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337492750/in/dateposted/" title="And there&#x27;s the Nature Path!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/907/40337492750_bcf8920e3b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And there&#x27;s the Nature Path!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337484140/in/dateposted/" title="Wood Anemone"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/40337484140_6437bfc456_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wood Anemone" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Right away I loved the little trail - Wood Anemone were everywhere along the narrow trail which went through a very young forest which was beautiful, and then one got a first taste of the granite slick rocks which I later see a lot in the Högberget section of the trail. This section was short and after a short while I was out on the forest road again, before entering a more shaded pine forest on the other side. This section ended also again in that same forest road, and then the trail went on the road further till a parking lot where quite a few cars were parked and a few boulderers where just shouldering their crashpads to go hug some pebbles in the National Park’s surroundings. I followed the trail towards the Kalkkiruukki Laavu, which was very busy with day hikers grilling sausages and enjoying the fantastic warm weather.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144269461/in/dateposted/" title="Kalkkiruukki Laavu"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/980/42144269461_56fc976e99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kalkkiruukki Laavu" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337485940/in/dateposted/" title="Signs &amp; Portents"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/824/40337485940_d2cae06a34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Signs &amp; Portents" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144265471/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking too fast"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/970/42144265471_a7323be439_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking too fast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I sat down for an hour or so, drunk a coffee and shot some video scenes, and complained on Instagram that my NEW Katadyn BeFree 1l bottle was apparently already broken as I got it (<a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel/status/996281448062705664">see it here on Twitter</a>). I packed up and then the trail continued for a few kilometres through dark pine forests, past rocks, climbing up and down and over streams. The path was wide and great condition, and here and there one could see where the winter XC trail goes. I had a chat with two women who where hiking with their dog and inquired about Ticks, and according to them these little pests are not a problem here (I didn’t encounter any).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423898904/in/dateposted/" title="Only a short stroll to Högberget"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/825/41423898904_bcb18926b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Only a short stroll to Högberget" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423901054/in/dateposted/" title="Högberget from above!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/828/41423901054_08a0cfefe6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Högberget from above!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144265851/in/dateposted/" title="Högberget!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/954/42144265851_4e53c82b72_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Högberget!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then I arrived at Högberget! These are probably the most popular spot of the National Park, I saw a lot of people here, enjoying the view from the higher rocks towards the city and sea beyond (I didn’t see the Baltic, but it should be possible to see it on a clear day). These slick granite rocks are really nice and I decided that I wanted to sleep under the stars somewhere over there, though as there was no water close by I first needed to find a water source - and I wanted to finish the trail before looking for a place to sleep. As the days are long in Finland now - the sun sets somewhere around 22:30 - I had enough time to do everything, and still could find a nice spot to roll out my mat &amp; quilt and have something to eat.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144266671/in/dateposted/" title="Trails"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/905/42144266671_660cc89c18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trails" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423898614/in/dateposted/" title="Death &amp; Young"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/969/41423898614_ac932c684f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Death &amp; Young" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423900404/in/dateposted/" title="Dessert &#x3D;)"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/972/41423900404_48864e2a62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dessert &#x3D;)" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41243046955/in/dateposted/" title="Goes on"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/963/41243046955_841eb20bc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Goes on" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144267591/in/dateposted/" title="I go to bed"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/42144267591_5618124f3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I go to bed" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I slept shortly that night - because I got up at 1:00 o’clock to photograph the stars, and low-and-behold, I got very lucky as I even captured some Northern Lights! In May! The next morning I slept in as long as I could before the sun was just too warm, made breakfast, shot a video about the As Tucas Sestrals quilt and then ran back to the Bus stop to catch the Bus back to Helsinki - I had a Design Tour to attend and didn’t want to meet that!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144264151/in/dateposted/" title="Barefoot Breakfast"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/909/42144264151_c1f8fe7e5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Barefoot Breakfast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144277081/in/dateposted/" title="After-hike Burger"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/907/42144277081_2cf23f1d17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="After-hike Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All in all it was a fantastic little trip: Beautiful warm T-Shirt weather, stars and Northern Lights, beautiful nature and lots of fresh green on the ground and trees! If you come to Helsinki, Espoo or Vantaa (or life there!) and have an extra day, do it like me: Take along your Ultralight backpack, some food and hop on the Bus to Sipoonkorpi National Park!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144269981/in/dateposted/" title="Calazo Sipoo Map!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/976/42144269981_6e86295399_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Calazo Sipoo Map!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-there--what-you-need">How to get there &amp; what you need</h2>

<p>I took Bus 717A from next to the Helsinki Railway Station to Sotunki, Google Maps or the Reittiopas Website are recommended to find the times when the bus goes and see where you have to get off (which is <em>Kalkkiuunintie</em> and should be displayed in the Bus, too). From there follow the sign which says <em>Trollberga</em> and <em>Traktori- ja Konemuseo</em> and after around 250 m you’ll see the blue Sipoonkorven Kansallispuito sign above. From the bus stop the complete nature path is around 8 km in length, and you can hike it either direction. A water bottle and some snacks are recommended for a day trip, if you want stay for the night bring a mattress, quilt and bivy which are appropriate for the season, and possibly a tarp or tent if you do not want to stay in one of the lean-to shelters. <strong>Questions?</strong> Ask me on Twitter of Facebook!</p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1746" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731746" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1746"></script>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this trip report &amp; video <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sea Stack Climbing in Ireland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-20T23:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ashfall Quartz. Ebb. Tide. Swell. Mix it together, throw in a rubber dinghy and you have the stuff for a Sea Stack climbing adventure.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002240157" title="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7626/17002240157_6342150a0a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="The sea worthy vessel to cross over to the sea stack" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>From the distance Berg Stack looks like a wee little rock in the North Atlantic Ocean, just off the cost of An Port in County Donegal, Ireland. We - Iain, our guide, a photographer and an US American journalist - slept the last night in the Port Cottage and now a blue sky &amp; sunshine have us frolicking in the superb weather. <em>“Lets go and check out the swell and tide”</em> Iain announces. We pack up our climbing gear and the 40€ rubber dinghy, bought at a Toy Shop - three at a time, they’re not that durable and walk the <a href="http://www.walkni.com/iat/">IAT</a> path up to the sea stack.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589476163" title="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8697/16589476163_e1526639df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack on the right, Vertical Picnic stack on the left" /></a></p>

<p>What looked like a wee sea stack from the lawn of the cottage turns out to be a 25 m high sea stack with a large ledge at the bottom, beautiful cracks and pin scars lining it from bottom to top and a Great black-backed gull with its nest on top. Oh, and an angry Atlantic Ocean with a two to four metre swell, making for not a good time to cross. We still inflate the unnamed dinghy, Iain gives me the instructions of how to assist him when he will board the sea worthy vessel to establish a tyrollean traverse on Berg Stack so I can get over, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17023512169" title="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8693/17023512169_4922bee743_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Iain from Unique Ascents having a look at the sea, Berg Stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The we sit &amp; wait. Observe the swell. Finally Iain decides we’ll come back at high tide later in the afternoon, when the sea should be calmer. Adrenaline that was build up in anticipation disappears, shoes go back on and we go for a nice hill walk, checking out Cnoc na Mara - the Sea Stack we had originally planned to go up, but with this sea that would have been too much risk. The views are spectacular, the valley deserted and I can make out a dozen of superb spots for a wild camp.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021928808" title="A look up Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5322/17021928808_206ed924b5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look up Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>Sea stack climbing is less about climbing, really. Sure, it helps if you can climb well and know how to place gear - it’s all trad - but it is just as much about the skill set an Alpinist has: Patience, Risk Assessment, Speed &amp; Efficiency. Maritime skills &amp; knowledge are also essential, knowing when the tide is coming in, how high the swell is, if it is safe, being patient. Finally, a bit of daring for an adventure is also needed. After all, if you think paddling in a toyshop rubber dinghy on the Atlantic is insane, then sea stack climbing is nothing for you.</p>

<p>We’re back on the main land and observe the sea. It is high tide, the swell is still high but every now &amp; then there’s a calm moment - and one of these Iain uses to paddle over to Berg Stack. An euphoric cry echoes over the sea and you can see how a load is off his shoulders. He sets up an anchor for the tyrollean traverse, and during the next calm moment he’s back on the main land. We discuss the strategy and then it all goes quick: the dinghy is back in the water and Iain is in it, surfing the swell, a 240 cm sling connecting him to the tyrollean. A calm moment comes, he paddles in and I jump in - and just as quick out again off on Berg Stack. We both howl a cry of victory, a victory over the tide and swell.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021935758" title="Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5343/17021935758_1ab7fb492e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berg Stack" /></a></p>

<p>From here on it’s all basic rock climbing: Harness and rock shoes come on, Iain racks up and we tie into the rope. I stand barefoot on the ledge, the swell crashing on the rocks around. Iain leads up a variation the <em>Cormorant</em> which he probably has climbed a dozen times and before long an “Off belay” call echoes down to me. It is a nice route with great hand and foot holds up till the middle to the arête, then it goes around the arête and up a wet corner, which is also the toilet of the Great black-backed gull and its offspring which were kind enough to let us top out there. A moment later I stand on the top of Berg Stack next to Iain, high-fiving him, and again we both let out a howl of victory. But this is not a sports climb where you just clip into the chain and then rappel off. No, this is a sea stack. And the sea is angry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002250497" title="Roping up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7651/17002250497_95a7de41ea_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Roping up" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17002062747" title="Me on Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8706/17002062747_44b293c870_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Me on Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17209684205" title="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5448/17209684205_822563f419_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain on top of Berg Stack, Vertical Picnic stack in the background" /></a></p>

<p>The easiest way off the top back to the ledge is to down-climb a corner to about two meters above the rushing sea, and then traverse the sea stack on superb ledges &amp; holds back to where we started. We short-rope and five minutes later stand next to our dinghy. The sea is lower, more rocks can be seen as the ebb comes in, but the swell is still high. <em>“Lets wait till the tide is out and then walk off”</em> Iain says, and so we deflate the dinghy which has served us so well on the way here, pack up and wait. Wait for the water to retreat, for the swell to let us escape from this rock.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16589483823" title="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5342/16589483823_e771dc38d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Iain down climbing from Berg Stack" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183741396" title="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8700/17183741396_a98415b910_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our dinghy on the ledge, the crossing with a bit of swell" /></a></p>

<p>The sea does not see a reason for letting us off, it wants to keep us. The swell is high and white foam rushes over the barnacle-covered rocks, which would otherwise allow us to easily walk off. The sun throws its last rays on the main land, we can see the hut from our ledge and the comfort of the warm fire in the cozy cottage and slowly we’re getting cold &amp; hungry. Low tide arrives, but the swell still throws up large, foamy waves over the rocks we should have just walked off.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17183747146" title="Cold feet by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7633/17183747146_b904d8e834_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Cold feet" /></a></p>

<p>Iain goes first, jumps the large gap and makes it just to the top of a big rock when a wave comes in. He brings me my approach shoes and throws them over, as I do not fancy jumping barefoot on wet, slimy rocks and risking a broken ankle. Waiting for the right moment I too make the jump, and a final victory cry echoes from the rocks - the land has me again. We pack up and in the falling dusk walk to the cottage, where a warm fire and cool beer are waiting for us. My appetite for sea stack climbing is awakened, but first I’ll need to hike further on the International Appalachian Trail to Northern Ireland, to return another day for more sea stack climbing adventures.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17022143920" title="Patience by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/17022143920_703730e92f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patience" /></a></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>
<p>There’s a <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/sea_stack_guide">free Sea Stack Guide book</a> if you want to go sea stack climbing - it has almost all sea stacks in it. A selection of sea stacks you also find in the <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/rock-climbing-in-ireland/">Rock Climbing in Ireland</a> book. I would suggest you do your first sea stack with Iain from <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/">Unique Ascents</a> and learn the ins &amp; outs from him about the sea and getting safely on and off the sea stack. He’s also a great guy and you’ll have a lot of fun on a day out with him. You’ll need a sea-worthy vessel - maybe <a href="http://www.packrafting-store.de/Rentals:::34.html">loan a packraft</a>, but be sure you also know how to use it and have an idea about the tide, swell and weather forecast. If a sea stack is too much adventure, check out the <a href="http://www.uniqueascent.ie/undiscovered_donegal">Donegal rock climbers guide</a> and visit one of the local crags, though there are also <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=CfM3DTcHcS8">calm days on Berg Stack</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17208905321" title="Port Donegal Cottage by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8763/17208905321_de9c296ae9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage" /></a></p>

<p>If you plan to climb in the area around An Port stay in the <a href="http://port-donegal.com/">Port Donegal Cottage</a> - either book via their website or on <a href="http://www.ownersdirect.co.uk/accommodation/p8069109">Owners Direct</a>. It has a wonderful cozy feel and relaxing in the bathtub after a day out on the sea will be so good that you don’t wanna go out. It sleeps eight and with some luck Roland, the owner, will be around and delight you with his stories from far away places.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17021740458" title="Port Donegal Cottage Inside by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7725/17021740458_6b9517e048_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Port Donegal Cottage Inside" /></a></p>

<p>The nearest village via a road is Ardara where you find several accommodation options like the <a href="http://www.bayviewcountryhouse.com/">Bayview Country House</a> and also shops and the <a href="http://www.nancysardara.com/">Nancy’s of Ardara Pub</a> for a after-climb pint, though it adds at least 45 minutes driving to your approach. For rest days go to Glencolmcille in the neighbouring valley and visit the <a href="http://glenfolkvillage.com/">Folk Museum</a> where you can see how people lived in the last centuries in the area, grab a good cup of coffee and a bite.</p>

<p>Gear wise you will need Trad gear as there are no bolts. Bring cord and slings if you want to abseil and need to build an anchor. Most of all, be patient with the sea and be open for the adventure!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Family Adventures in Pyhä-Luosto]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-08T23:41:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The common human relationship with winter seems to go like this: As a child you love winter. In your twenties you could life without it. And from your thirties onwards you fall in love with winter &amp; snow again. In our family we’re all winter lovers, and as winter didn’t really visit us in Vaasa we decided to find it up north at <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/eng/">Pyhä Tunturi</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075087012" title="That one next, dad! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7599/17075087012_e945efd6da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="That one next, dad!" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="prologue">Prologue</h2>

<p>Climate change is a real bummer for winter lovers in Southern Finland. While I did get to ski and fatbike in the snow a bit back home, winter in Vaasa was a mix of snow + cold and then rain + warm temperatures which resulted in a less than nice winter. With a week of winter vacation that we could each take of, M and me decided to search winter in Lapland. After some discussions of what we wanted we quickly settled on the <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/eng/">Pyhä Ski Resort</a> as the best destination for us this year as it had plenty of fun winter activities to offer for all three of us, from skiing and hiking over sledding to ice climbing and fatbiking, with great <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/accommodation/">accommodation</a> options, too.</p>

<p>A car was rented, <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/hmorkel?s=8">AirBnB accommodation</a> in Oulu was organized and the luggage was packed. It was a nice Sunday morning as we started the drive north, and it was around Oulu - 300 km from Vaasa - that we saw the first signs of Winter again. The next day we continued via a stop in Rovaniemi onwards to Pyhä, and already from a distance we could see the iconic fjells of the ski resort and <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/pyha-luostonp">National Park</a>, with lots of snow around us and a beautiful bluebird sky promising a great week of winter fun! We checked in to the <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1128&amp;submenu=3657">Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartment</a>, heated up the Sauna and enjoyed seeing the stars in the crisp, black sky.</p>

<h2 id="winter-fun-for-kids">Winter fun for Kids</h2>

<p>We found Pyhä a great location for our three year old. He loved the snow and we were daily at the sled hill, which was a five minutes walk from the <a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/pyha-luostonluontokeskus">Nature Centre Naava</a> (which is in the centre of the village and hence an easy reference point). The two sled hills were good fun and E didn’t get tired of sledding for many hours each day, with little rest breaks at the conveniently located open hut at the foot of the hill. Being allowed to throw another log of wood on the fire was equally nice as making snow angles and sledding together <em>superfast</em> with dad.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889011560" title="Pyhä Sled Hill by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7713/16889011560_3351fc57fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Pyhä Sled Hill" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076568685" title="Sled Hill break hut by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8752/17076568685_cb2b65aa11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sled Hill break hut" /></a></p>

<p>There’s a ski school for kids in Pyhä too, though we decided to wait for another year to put him on downhill skis. There were lots of kids skiing, though, and the Family slopes were full with parents and kids of all ages. Close to our apartment was also a reindeer enclosure and visiting Rudolph and his friends was every time again fascinating. E also enjoyed looking how other people skied down the hills so fast, and going up with the Polar Express to the top of the fjell made him smile from ear to ear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075825821" title="Top of the fjell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8798/17075825821_e54ca475a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Top of the fjell" /></a></p>

<h2 id="skiing">Skiing</h2>

<p>M and me have the same shoe size, which was convenient as we loaned cross country skis and boots. M enjoyed skiing the tracks while I went a bit off-piste and explored the nearby National Park and swamp on skis. There’s surely a hundred kilometre or more of groomed cross-country skiing tracks at Pyhä and M liked the little huts and Laavus along the tracks, as they were ideal to have a short break and then ski back. The tracks vary in difficulty, from a super easy loipe that goes around a mire with zero elevations to more demanding loipes. You even can ski around the whole Pyhä-Luosto National Park on groomed tracks, which is - depending on the route you choose - between 70 or more kilometres. For early morning and late night skiers there’s also a pretty long illuminated track which is lighted up from 6 in the morning till 23 at night.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075080162" title="Skiing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8687/17075080162_2149394d66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Skiing" /></a></p>

<p>But of course cross-country skiing is just one sort of skiing you can do in Pyhä! It’s very well known in Finland to be <em>the</em> Backcountry destination, as you can take the lift up and then pretty much ski down where you please. Sadly my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">DPS Tour 1 skis</a> didn’t arrive in time otherwise I would have been out on the slopes and made some pretty turns after skinning up the hills. There are lots of great ski-touring options at Pyhä, so if that’s your kind of skiing make sure to take your gear along! Also for downhill and Freeskiers Pyhä is a great destination, with 9 lifts, 14 prepared slopes - the longest slope being 1800 m - and the same ski pass being valid at Ruka as well Pyhä is a great destination to go snowboarding and skiing. Add in that the lifts are working super efficient and queues were non-existent and you have the ingredients for lots of skiing and fun.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16890340699" title="Top of the fjell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8716/16890340699_d85b8eda66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Top of the fjell" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ice-climbing">Ice climbing</h2>

<p>One of the reasons why Pyhä won for us as a destination is that you can go <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/ice-climbing/customized-ice-climbing/">ice climbing at Tajukangas</a> which is a short stroll from the slopes and the Pyhätunturi Hotel. My friends from <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/">Bliss Adventure</a> run the ice climbing crag there, and I was very happy that my friend <a href="http://aleksimehtonen.fi/">Aleksi</a> and his colleague Mikko were there with me and were the belay masters while I was whacking some ice. And whacking ice I did!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16454119254" title="My first ice lead at Tajukangas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7665/16454119254_4f6f3c878e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="My first ice lead at Tajukangas" /></a></p>

<p>After a couple of warm-ups and checking out the routes I did my first ice lead ever, and while I was a bit nervous while tying in to my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.fi/en/mammut-genesis-8-5-half-rope-red/?pid=81">Mammut 8.5 Genesis Ropes</a> and racking up the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/petzl-laser-speed-ice-screw/">Petzl Laser Speed ice screws</a> as soon as I was on the ice and put my mind on the task ahead the fear was gone, tranquility and enjoyment flowing through me. As far as ice leads go this wasn’t the most difficult route ever, though I found the company and encouragement from Aleksi &amp; Mikko superb and they helped me to trust myself and lead on ice. Now I’m hungry for more and hope that next winter will be much better than this one, so that there will be much more ice climbing and leading!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075086492" title="My first ice lead at Tajukangas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8723/17075086492_4b88107d6d_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="My first ice lead at Tajukangas" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hungry">Hungry?</h2>

<p><a href="http://pyhawurst.fi/">Pyhä Wurst</a> is a cozy little Restaurant/ Café at the bottom of the Northern Slope. They serve, as the name suggest, a variety of different sausages, and all three of us really found our food extremely tasty. Our son devoured a Hotdog - his first one! - and would have liked a second one, while M and me enjoyed a Bratwurst Hotdog and a Riistakäristys. They place was very popular with skiers &amp; snowboarders, walkers, cross-country skiers and families alike, so check them out when you’re in Pyhä and would like to taste some good Wurst!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050601976" title="PyhäWurst by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8732/17050601976_5f89cb12f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="PyhäWurst" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.cafeloimu.fi/en/">Café Loimu</a> was another Café which we enjoyed visiting almost daily as they served some super-tasty pancakes and good coffee. They’re located in the same building as the Nature Centre Naava so kids can even go and explore the museum on their own while the parents can enjoy a moment in the Café. Café Loimu is right in the middle of the village and also has an Á la carte Menu if you want to eat a bit more than pancakes or a sandwich.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/restaurants/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1019&amp;submenu=138">Hotel Pyhätunturi Restaurant</a> has a gorgeous Panorama view over the surroundings and is an ideal place to conclude a nice day outdoors, especially if the Northern Lights decide to show up and play a show over the forests and mires. M ate the best Sautéed reindeer (<em>poronkäristys</em> in Finnish) in her life at the Restaurant and found it so tasty that she still talks about how good it was. I enjoyed <em>The Poro</em> which was equally delicious, while E had problems finishing his kids meal of spaghetti and meatballs. The atmosphere and service at the Hotel Pyhätunturi Restaurant were excellent and if you stay in Pyhä we strongly recommend that you visit the restaurant.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16457137153" title="The Poro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8686/16457137153_4fe83a661d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="659" alt="The Poro" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.huttu-uula.fi/">Restaurant Huttu-Uula</a> has won an Chaîne des Rôtisseurs award and is located at the foot of the Polar slope. Every Thursday it serves a <a href="http://www.huttu-uula.fi/files/uula_puffee.pdf">Lappish Food Buffet</a> with lots of delicious dishes from Lapland. The friendly atmosphere together with the good buffet food make this a recommended visit on a Thursday evening, though you should reserve well in advance as the Buffet is very popular and was fully booked out when we were there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889741440" title="Leipäjuusto by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7681/16889741440_7557737323_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Leipäjuusto" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fatbiking">Fatbiking</h2>

<p>Since I got my <a href="http://salsacycles.com/bikes/mukluk">Fatbike</a> cycling has been a lot of fun in winter. Riding over the frozen Baltic Sea, shredding over the single track in the forest and doing laps on the groomed trails are just a lot of fun, so of course I took the opportunity to go on a <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/fatbikes/">Fatbike Adventure at Pyhä</a>. I was very lucky that my friend Artturi was my guide for the morning, and after familiarizing myself with bike and hearing what Artturi had planned for us we hit the trails.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16888790748" title="Fatbiking, skiing or hiking? by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7676/16888790748_0235d89209_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fatbiking, skiing or hiking?" /></a></p>

<p>After some beautiful, flow-y single track trails we arrived at a large mire which was a lot of fun to ride across. We had a short break at a bird watching tower which allowed for wide views over the National Park, before continuing across the mire - fat tires rock in that terrain! Slowly narrow tracks brought us back to our starting point, and after a nice climb back up to the Hotel this little Fatbike adventure was done. You also can rent a Fatbike for half a day or longer from Bliss in case you want to explore the National Park on your own. Hats off to Bliss Adventure for offering this service, I think they’re spot on with it and I saw daily very happy fatbike cyclists riding on the trails and snow.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076575735" title="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8797/17076575735_d5ec086d2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16456411083" title="Selfietime! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7610/16456411083_2d9c29dd7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfietime!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076574115" title="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/17076574115_7c29a3b793_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park" /></a></p>

<h2 id="snowshoe-hiking">(Snowshoe) Hiking</h2>

<p>There is a dedicated <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/01/video-msr-lightning-ascent-review.html">snowshoe</a> hiking trail in Pyhä, though it was so hard packed that one didn’t need snowshoes to walk on it. So we had a nice little family hike to the Isokuru gorge and back, which includes a steep descent and climb from the nice Isokuru Kota. The hike seems to take the route of the summer nature trail as we passed quite a few signs which gave information about the forest and land, and is ideal if you’d like to be outdoors for a couple of hours.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050611986" title="Danger! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8813/17050611986_396e0e5472_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Danger!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16456419973" title="Family Hike by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8687/16456419973_19757d8746_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Family Hike" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075086052" title="Fire by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7633/17075086052_af66532256_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="nature--silence">Nature &amp; Silence</h2>

<p>Despite all the activities you can do in Pyhä, there are two things in Pyhä-Luosto everywhere, and they’re for free: Nature and Silence. Even with a Baltic Ski Cup going on while we were in the village, we just needed to walk for five minutes towards the <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/en/pyha-luostonp">National Park</a> and there was a calmness that was just once in a while interrupted by birdsong or the wind blowing through the trees. Pyhä-Luosto National Park is home to the southern most big fjells in Finland, beyond them towards the south starts the flat land. Though this does make them popular I had at no time the feeling that there were too much people around me, for example the lines at the lifts were pretty much non-existent despite there being a bunch of people, and also in the Cafés and Restaurants there were never masses of people. As someone who values silence a lot I found Pyhä a great place, with easy access to nature and the possibility to <em>“escape”</em> the main slopes and head into the National Park, where even on blue bird days I didn’t meet more than a handful of people.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16869172217" title="Silver by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7613/16869172217_7c288c4b9e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Silver" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050598466" title="Snow &amp; Birch by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8690/17050598466_e512ff6074_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Snow &amp; Birch" /></a></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p><strong>Where to stay?</strong></p>

<p>We stayed at a <a href="http://www.ski-inn.fi/majoitus.asp?prodtype=30&amp;lang=eng&amp;tunturi=&amp;day=&amp;endDay=">Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartment</a> which was ideally located right next to the slopes. The apartment was super family-friendly and had two bedrooms, a small kitchen, living room, balcony, a own Sauna and a drying cabinet to dry wet garments and gear (super handy with kids!). There are plenty more options in town, from the nice <a href="http://www.ski-inn.fi/majoitus.asp?prodtype=41&amp;lang=eng&amp;tunturi=&amp;changeMonth=">Ski-Inn Hotel Pyhätunturi</a> to many, many cozy <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=cabins&amp;submenu=3660">cabins</a> and even a <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1106">caravan site</a> if you’re coming with your own accommodation. You’ll surely find something to your liking, keep an eye out for deals, though, as at e.g. the Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartments ski passes can be included in the price saving you a bunch of money!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16869175557" title="PyhäSuites by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7703/16869175557_09002a90bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="PyhäSuites" /></a></p>

<p><strong>How to get there?</strong></p>

<p>As we don’t own a car we rented one for a week and drove up north. Vaasa - Pyhä is around 660 km and with a toddler along we decided to split the journey in two and spend a night in Oulu. If you come from abroad you might want to fly directly to Rovaniemi and take the <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/info/?file=content_exec&amp;id=2292&amp;submenu=3890">SkiBus</a> to Pyhä, or take the (overnight) train from Helsinki and then jump on the SkiBus. In the village you can walk pretty much everywhere within 15 minutes, and there’s a variety of shops to suit your needs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157651506091295/">More Photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16454124174" title="No sledding by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8787/16454124174_baa0f5cd6b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="No sledding" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075081902" title="Aurora Borealis by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7644/17075081902_4025b6fd68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Aurora Borealis" /></a></p>

<p><em>Thanks to the Pyhä Ski Resort and their Partners which invited us up north.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Högakustenleden - The High Coast Trail]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-13T18:50:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/01/hogakustenleden-the-high-coast-trail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Högakustenleden - or High Coast Trail in English - is a new trail that passes through the UNESCO World Heritage site of the same name. The scenic trail passes through villages &amp; towns, along the coast, through the forest and a beautiful National Park and if you have a free week makes for a great walk along the Swedish coastal hills.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034082038" title="Jon Nils Berget is the highest point on the trail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7571/16034082038_6e226a048a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jon Nils Berget is the highest point on the trail" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>November marks usually the last month of the year where I go out on a Press Trip to do research for <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/magazines/">magazine</a> articles. It’s far from the perfect backpacking month in the North and I had planned to hike the High Coast Trail in August, but changes in schedules meant it’d be the final backpacking trip of the year. Happily my good friend Martin agreed to accompany me, and so we met up late on a Sunday night in a <a href="http://umea.kfum.se">Hostel in Umeå</a>, him after flying in, me after taking the <a href="http://www.wasaline.com">ferry from Vaasa</a>. The next morning we enjoyed the breakfast at the Hostel and walked to the bus station from where we had a comfortable and fast bus ride to the bus stop at Hornöberget just before the High Coast Bridge, the start point of the trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16221689035" title="Start at the High Coast Bridge in Hornöberget by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7551/16221689035_e5fb4a7ab7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Start at the High Coast Bridge in Hornöberget" /></a></p>

<p>We followed the street for a bit, took to a forest road and soon saw our first Högakustenleden trail marker and were on a proper trail. It was a short one, though, because the next several kilometres took us along on village roads, along the street, across bridges until we finally walked along the Baltic Sea and came upon a proper trail into the forest. It wasn’t all pleasurable forest trails, though, we also passed a few deforested areas until we finally reached Sör-Lövvik, the end of section 1. The <a href="http://lovvikbedandbreakfast.se">Lövvik B&amp;B</a> looked inviting just along the trail, and while it was still early in the day we somehow wouldn’t have minded to stop there or at the free cottage in the village, but as it was closed for the winter we just continued until Fjärdbotten.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601850203" title="Fishing Nets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7503/15601850203_bcabd0086a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fishing Nets" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035884247" title="On streets by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7487/16035884247_65a120cd5d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On streets" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16195855506" title="And trail markers to keep us on course by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7542/16195855506_1793df18c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And trail markers to keep us on course" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219888711" title="A B&amp;B in Lövvik by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16219888711_bd1004d1a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A B&amp;B in Lövvik" /></a></p>

<p>We hiked for a while along the road and then took a turn onto a forest path. We found a stream to refill our water bottles and continued until the Laavu at Halsviken Bay. The place looked nice, and with dusk upon us we yet again were tempted to put the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">HMG UltaMid</a> up for the night. We resisted the early finish and continued on the trail, which then went through a boulder field along the shore. Sleet from the sky, strong winds and spray from the sea make walking on boulders a pleasurable past time, which only can be improved by onsetting darkness. We somehow managed to no break any feet or legs and were rather happy as we reached the forest road and road to Fjärdbotten. It was dark and raining as we arrived there, not knowing what to expect.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035659269" title="Boulder-hoping in the dark and rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7546/16035659269_bb0576bfb7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boulder-hoping in the dark and rain" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034258558" title="Night Selfie by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8603/16034258558_8d5ccdb6a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night Selfie" /></a></p>

<p>Fjärdbotten was a great camping place. Around six wooden cottages with tables, benches, beds and some with a stove in them were too good a chance to pass up. Martin quickly put a clothes line up, we hang our wet gear up to dry, got a fire started and then the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/primus-eta-lite-gaskocher/">Primus Lite+</a> came out and boiled us hot water for dinners and Minttu Kakaos! Well fed we soon dived into our sleeping bags and had a good night’s sleep.</p>

<p>The next morning was drizzly but looked like it might clear up. After we explored the Fjärdbotten summer farm and checked out the other cottages and got water from the well we had a warm breakfast &amp; coffee, boiled water for our <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">Thermos</a> and then soon were out on the trail again. The decision to stay at Fjärdbotten was a good one, and it was a very nice place.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035560289" title="Breakfast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16035560289_94649b7d5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Breakfast" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601808053" title="Inside our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/15601808053_901c543d1e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inside our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034318520" title="Our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8600/16034318520_918a454e5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our hut at Fjärdbotten Summer Farm" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601795673" title="Fjärdbotten Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15601795673_efdbc0fec3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fjärdbotten Summer Farm" /></a></p>

<p>The next section took us on the highest point along the trail, Jon Nils Berget. We were lucky as the drizzle from the morning stopped after a few kilometres of hiking and we were treated by one of those fine, sunny days which you get after a night of rain. The trail was a mix of nice forest roads (they’re great to walk and talk on with a party of two!) where abandoned caravans were every few kilometres. As we reached Jon Nils Berget the sun came out and we really enjoyed this beautiful moment.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16195729126" title="Supertramp by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7575/16195729126_3621a39362_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Supertramp" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16237534596" title="Martin taking in the view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/16237534596_140c3a9356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Martin taking in the view" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219705131" title="Viewing the view stop by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7514/16219705131_dd6c0e5321_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Viewing the view stop" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035459759" title="And looking outta the window by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7523/16035459759_b39d89a0c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And looking outta the window" /></a></p>

<p>We had a quick tea and cookies break at the Nipstugan on Lidenipan, and the sun just continued to treat us with warmth and light on the way to Gavik, the end of the 3rd Section. Behind Gavik we hiked on a forest road along summer cottages which had been closed up for winter, and had a very late lunch as the sun was just setting somewhere in the West. Soon the headlamps came on as we hiked on dark and wet forest trails and snowy forest roads.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16034049618" title="Well, lets get moving by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8574/16034049618_5c2d180b64_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Well, lets get moving" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601684713" title="Back on asphalt by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7521/15601684713_a62f3aef77_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back on asphalt" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16033999978" title="Where the road stops by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7495/16033999978_94444f9be6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Where the road stops" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601652373" title="Views without trees by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8576/15601652373_c0ddf9bf12_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views without trees" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16220694082" title="Headlamp illuminated views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7490/16220694082_cb669dd0de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Headlamp illuminated views" /></a></p>

<p>The goal of Section 4 was Lappuden, which was hailed as <em>the</em> camping spot along the Högakustenleden. Well, it was not. As it was closed. Closed up for winter. After the luxury of the Fjärdbotten hut we were going to sleep outside, and as the lake and grass fields already were covered with thin ice we knew we’d be in for a cold night. Alas, not even a fire we were able to lighten up, for a lack of wood and a fire place. We still had a good night, even if my <a href="http://www.phdesigns.co.uk">PHD Minix Sleeping Bag</a> was a tad too less insulation for these temperatures. The next morning the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">fēnix</a> said -3°C and we packed up while the Lite+ boiled water for breakfast &amp; coffee. We were early on the trail again, and we were happy to leave the disappointment of Lappuden behind.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15601643623" title="Lappuden by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/15601643623_59636ae21f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lappuden" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035648837" title="Reindeer moss by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/16035648837_9c8c2cea2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reindeer moss" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15599059654" title="Quartz veins by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7525/15599059654_c6e420dee6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Quartz veins" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16035354489" title="Erikskojan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7547/16035354489_03b5cf6996_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Erikskojan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16221453515" title="Inside Erikskojan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7582/16221453515_d0cda2ee6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inside Erikskojan" /></a></p>

<p>The trail was again a mix of enjoyable forest trails, OK forest roads and less enjoyable asphalt streets, but happily the trails made up the majority os Section 5 to Ullånger. The highlight for Martin and me was the beautiful Erikskojan hut high up in the middle of the forest. It stood lonely there, and if I hadn’t pulled like someone who really wants to sit inside with his tea we probably would have drunk our hot tea on its steps as the door was very tightly closed =) Of all the huts we passed this was the one we both really would have loved to stay in for the night, as it was cozy and comfortable. Alas, we needed to continue onwards.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16195558186" title="Lovely deforestation views by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7568/16195558186_41f1ab48d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lovely deforestation views" /></a></p>

<p>As we hiked into Ullånger it was still lunch time, and we didn’t need long to decide on the Värdshuset Restaurang Snäckan to get our business. A Lunch Buffet is a Hiker’s dream, and tasty Swedish food was consumed in large amounts, topped off with coffee and cookies. It was fortunate that we didn’t need to hike a long distance to our next camping place, the Gårdberget Stugan just above Ullånger. We didn’t really know what to expect, but were delighted by the hut, which was decorated in a 70s style and had a big stove inside. A fire was roaring quickly while night fell, and we enjoyed the evening by talking and drinking a good Whisky.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16263362435" title="Gårdberget Stugan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7529/16263362435_bf07675705_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gårdberget Stugan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262537602" title="Mäjasjön Summer Farm by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8678/16262537602_c7326acd44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mäjasjön Summer Farm" /></a></p>

<p>The night over a powdery coat of snow covered the land and we enjoyed the walk in the morning through the silent forest. That silence was interrupted the closer we got to Sjöland and Skoved as the trail went along the highway. It was an interesting experience to hike with trucks and cars passing by at high speeds, and I do hope that the trail finds a different route in the future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262738312" title="Church door by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7555/16262738312_90e05236cb_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Church door" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16075793398" title="Truck by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7559/16075793398_dc2885d33f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Truck" /></a></p>

<p>We flew through Section 7 from Skoved to Skuleberget and the <a href="http://www.naturumhogakusten.se/">Naturum Höga Kusten</a> Centre. Sadly the Museum also was closed, and as we still had well over 15 km before us we also didn’t take the detour over the top of the Skuleberget. The hill was impressive, though, and it’s nice to see that local entrepreneurs have installed Via Ferratas on it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15643755233" title="Naturum Höga Kusten by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7561/15643755233_c0fd06d8dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Naturum Höga Kusten" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076092610" title="Skuleberget National Park South Entry by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7537/16076092610_7e0d2a9016_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park South Entry" /></a></p>

<p>Section 8 from Skuleberget to the Skuleberget National Park South Entry must have been one of the most frustrating ones on the trail. After the Naturum Höga Kusten Centre we had another quick lunch break outside and then followed the nice Kids Adventure/ Robber Trail, passed an Open Air Theatre and then crossed the highway once more to hike on trails and forest roads to the South Entry of the National Park. Some sections of the trail were flooded and it was impossible to keep your feet dry, which usually doesn’t bother me at all, but somehow that day it really annoyed me a lot. The trail wasn’t fun in the wet dirt &amp; mud, but happily I recovered as soon as the trail became dry again. As we came closer and closer to the Skuleberget National Park the better our moods got, and the view from the South Entry was indeed well worth coming there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16263434465" title="View at Skuleberget National Park South Entry by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8609/16263434465_9a283ba21d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="View at Skuleberget National Park South Entry" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16263398085" title="Skuleberget National Park Signs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8626/16263398085_8e31435fc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park Signs" /></a></p>

<p>As frustrating as that wet part of the trail previously was, so wonderful was the <a href="http://www.sverigesnationalparker.se/skuleskogen#.VLUOe8bJhJc">Skuleskogen National Park</a>. The National Park probably was the highlight of our trip, and we were a bit sad that we spend only such a short time in day light in it. We hiked on duck boards for kilometres, passed waterfalls and then hiked up to the impressive Slåttdalsskrevan, a 200 m long, 40 m deep and 7 m wide crevice. We explored it in the shine of our headlamps and then made us on the way down to the Tärnättvattnen Stuga in the middle of the National Park.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16237633986" title="Checking out the small waterfall, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7481/16237633986_fdcba0d04b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Checking out the small waterfall, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238289906" title="Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7464/16238289906_fa3b941b49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16237741036" title="Frozen, slippery, smooth granite at night by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7478/16237741036_d5b335e1dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Frozen, slippery, smooth granite at night" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16261636721" title="Frozen lake at Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7578/16261636721_4058a06423_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Frozen lake at Skuleberget National Park" /></a></p>

<p>The hut was gorgeous from the inside and outside, though as it often happens with such huts, they seem to accumulate rubbish and trinkets which previous visitors <em>left for others to enjoy</em> or simply <em>forgot</em>. We cleaned up, got a fire started and enjoyed the evening with the a <em>Feierabendbier</em> which we carried all the way from the Supermarket in Docksta till here to enjoy in this rustic hut. The next morning grey clouds still hung thickly in the sky and the sun wasn’t to be seen. We brought some more wood for the next visitors to the hut, cleaned up and packed and where on our way again.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076128100" title="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8566/16076128100_74c11ae583_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076804860" title="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7563/16076804860_db7f85d833_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tärnättvattnen Stuga, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15641095154" title="Signs in Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7528/15641095154_3e564daab1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Signs in Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076115510" title="Looking back towards Slåttdalsskrevan, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7572/16076115510_c722693948_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Looking back towards Slåttdalsskrevan, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077690687" title="Dot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8619/16077690687_48928e6a0a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dot" /></a></p>

<p>The way out of the National Park was again very beautiful, along frozen lakes, via Duckboards over swamps, over small streams and soft forest trails until the North Entry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15643662733" title="Stream crossing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8643/15643662733_6e3a184cbc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Stream crossing" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077649527" title="The sea, Skuleberget National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8636/16077649527_664f582c49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The sea, Skuleberget National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262745482" title="Skuleberget National Park North Entry by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7469/16262745482_6731323942_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skuleberget National Park North Entry" /></a></p>

<p>It was noon as we arrived in Köpmanholmen, and as every good tourist hiker does we immediately located the local Pizzeria and ordered their lunch Pizza. 60 SEK for a Pizza, salad, drink and coffee is a real bargain, especially considering that the Pizzas were about 40 cm (!) in diameter. We were stuffed as we walked out of the village and walked on a sandy road until the where we would enter the Balesudden Nature Reserve. It was a very beautiful reserve and not even a kilometre from the start of the forest trail we passed the prettiest Laavu on the whole Högakustenleden, up on the hill overlooking the Baltic Sea. Again we regretted that we needed to push on and couldn’t stay here, as the view and atmosphere was gorgeous.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15640967264" title="Party time by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7527/15640967264_7ba6d83d27_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Party time" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076221740" title="Sweden! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8676/16076221740_3f181081cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sweden!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16077751717" title="Högakustenleden Signs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8626/16077751717_bc80426d93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Högakustenleden Signs" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16262764232" title="Laavu with a view by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7521/16262764232_d025afbe1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Laavu with a view" /></a></p>

<p>Instead we pushed on through on and up through the Balesudden Nature Reserve, though with dusk coming upon us and a light drizzle we had our eyes mostly on the slippery trail in front of us. We passed a nice fireplace and camping spot near a bay until we happened upon the Bodviken Stugan, our hut for the night. The drizzle had become rain and I was happy as Martin offered to go chop the wood. I started the fire and rolled out my sleeping bag and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/therm-a-rest-neoair-xlite.html">mattress</a> and again fired up the Primus Lite+. Soon we were well fed and had a whisky in our cups, which ensured we had another good, relaxed and warm night.</p>

<p>In winter you can sleep long and still catch the sunrise. So after we had breakfast I took a little stroll around the hut to photograph the sunrise. It was just a brief moment where one could spot the sun, as it passed up from the sea to hide again behind the clouds. It was our last day on the trail, and we only had 21 km till Örnsköldsvik, with the last part in civilization, so that we took it easy. We passed a few more Laavus in the morning, hiked on forest roads and streets, up hills and had a quick break in the Småtjärnstugan, and then were very quickly in Svedje, the end of Section 12.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16238233526" title="Sunrise by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7565/16238233526_786eec69cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunrise" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15672818967" title="Natur Reservat by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7577/15672818967_bc83905b3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Natur Reservat" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16261709811" title="Bodviken Stugan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7553/16261709811_108f7dfe02_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bodviken Stugan" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076028498" title="Along the frozen lake by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7503/16076028498_a1176918ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Along the frozen lake" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16078073489" title="That way! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7494/16078073489_fed4a67d95_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="That way!" /></a></p>

<p>From here we passed through the town and climbed the local recreation area. As it was windy, 0°C and grey we just marched on towards Örnsköldsvik, the end of Section 13 of the Högakustenleden. Early in the afternoon we reached town. Done.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076823010" title="Örnskoldvik by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7566/16076823010_6ce886089b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Örnskoldvik" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16076101788" title="Örnköldsvik! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8616/16076101788_c758bc15da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Örnköldsvik!" /></a></p>

<p>While standing on the square in the centre a young Swede came talking to us, who recognized me as <em>the writer of Hiking in Finland</em>. It was a fun coincidence as he said he saw that we’d be hiking the trail that week and he met us just as we finished! Very cool! After inquiring about a good place to eat in the evening we walked to our hostel, <a href="http://www.vindarnashus.se">Vindarnas Hus</a>. It was a nice &amp; quiet hostel with Wifi, hot showers and good beds, and we chilled there in the evening until we headed out to eat at <a href="http://www.bishopsarms.com/Ornskoldsvik">The Bishops Arms</a> which not only had superb food but also impeccable service and great beers. It was a worthy finish to a great Högakustenleden thru-hike!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16221464365" title="Still plenty of signs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7539/16221464365_a08cce908d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Still plenty of signs" /></a></p>

<h2 id="planning-your-high-coast-trail-hike">Planning your High Coast Trail hike</h2>

<p>To see about 150 more photos check out the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157648982512379/">Höga Kusten Trail Album</a> on Flickr.</p>

<p>The funniest thing about the Högakustenleden was for Martin and me how the distances were way off from what the signs and the guide booklet said. It makes me wonder if the trail is actually hiked by the people who planned it and if they made the effort to check the distance, or if these were just made via some mapping tool. Because the Högakustenleden is supposed to be 128,6 km from Hornöberget to Örnsköldsvik, but I tracked with my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">Garmin fēnix</a> 141,8 km in the six days we hiked it. This isn’t uncommon and I regularly hike trails and sections which are longer/ shorter than they’re claimed to be, but still is something to keep in mind when you plan to hike the trail.</p>

<p>Also important to know is that the trail goes quite a bit along forest roads and streets. It does feel like at least 50% of the trail makes use of such infrastructure, and while it can make for fast hiking (5 km an hour and easy to chat while walking next to each other) it isn’t really very inspiring. Happily there are enough of nice forest trails, too, and the section through the Skuleskogen National Park was gorgeous. If you have time I’d recommend planning a day to just explore the National Park and then hike on.</p>

<p>Plan the travel there and back via <a href="http://reseplanerare.resrobot.se/bin/help.exe/sn?L=vs_resrobot&amp;tpl=webapp">Resrobot</a>, one of the best travel apps I have used. It helps you to find the best Bus/ Train/ Flight connections from e.g. Stockholm to Hornöberget and Örnsköldsvik and also lets you book the tickets right away.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.visitsweden.com/sweden/">Visit Sweden</a> and the <a href="http://www.hogakustenleden.com">Högakustenleden</a> + <a href="http://hogakusten.com/en/hk/high-coast-trail.html">High Coast Trail</a> websites offer a host of information about Sweden and the trail, especially the last page has a great overview map and a description of each section. You can order from there also the useful <a href="http://hogakusten.com/information/en/brochures.html">Trail Guide</a>, though don’t bother with the (free) map as it’s too large a scale to be useful for hiking. Speaking of maps, you really can hike it just with the maps in the Trail Guide. The trail is exceptionally well marked and so very beginner-friendly, sometimes every third tree has an orange dot or stripe.</p>

<p>We slept every night in one of the free huts or Laavus and were completely alone on the trail, we once encountered day hikers. But then we were hiking in November, so in the spring, summer and autumn that could look very differently. I recommend you take a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">shelter</a> along when hiking in those months, or make use of the various accommodation options along the trail. Basic ultralight gear choices would suit the trail well, you can practice pitching tarps and sleeping with a quilt here very well as you could always head to one of the Laavus or Huts. From Ullånger on you almost daily would pass a village with a supermarket, Café and Restaurant, so you could easily resupply along the trail (or buy a Swedish Beer for the evening each day =).</p>

<p>Along the trail you also could easily go packrafting, sea kayaking, climbing and Via Ferrata. While you could do some of these activities just besides the trail you’d need to plan an extra day for some others. Because of the good infrastructure (huts &amp; Laavus, Restaurants and Shops along the way) the trail could be a good choice for families who want to try backpacking with their kids.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiking &amp; Scrambling in the Polish Tatras - Part II]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-03T10:33:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/10/hiking-and-scrambling-in-the-polish-tatras-part-ii</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/mountaineering-and-climbing-in-the-polish-tatras.html">climbing &amp; mountaineering in the Polish Tatras</a> to hiking and backpacking. In the rain &amp; sunshine, up high in the mountains and low in the valleys.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397717831" title="Focus on the rain by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397717831_9014d3f632_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Focus on the rain" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="rain--misery">Rain &amp; Misery</h2>

<p>As we wake up at the <a href="http://www.piecstawow.pl/en/">Przedni Staw Polski Refuge</a> and I look out from my window the mist hides the mountains and the rain drops leave little circles on the lake. Everything is wet. Marcin and I silently get out of bed and move to the big common room, give in our orders for breakfast and enjoy the tasty food that comes through the small window from the kitchen. Slowly it gets busy, people packing, but with the rain keeping up a constant drum on the roof none leave the hut. At ten we’re the first ones to venture outside, curious looks on us in our rain gear, and as Marcin tells where we headed people just look even more confused.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214238360" title="A look back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214238360_3bfa19dbfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin gave me a few options: Walk the easy trail through the valley to the Schronisko Murowaniec refuge, or the shorter but high route across a pass at the end Orla Perć. We had light packs, good gear and so it was easy to make the decision to go via the pass. I either way was a bit disappointed that we didn’t take my original route, but plans are plans: Drawn on paper, dreamed up looking over maps in the warm comfort of home. When the weather turns it’s best to adapt them and stay safe - something I can now say in hindsight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400893955" title="Crossing snow by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/15400893955_db1585c08f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Crossing snow" /></a></p>

<p>We walk by the mist-enshrouded lakes, cross the stream via the little bridge and hear the waterfall thunder down towards the valley while we slowly ascend. I carry my camera underneath my jacket so I can keep on making photos, but in the drizzle and thick mist there isn’t much to see. We cross small streams, old snow, and steadily keep on walking uphill. Once in a while the mist has a gap and we can see a bit further - the other side of the valley, further up, down the valley.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397714501" title="Slippery by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3855/15397714501_32e8d0e031_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slippery" /></a></p>

<p>To be able to continue to take photos I left <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/hestra/">my gloves</a> in <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html">my pack</a> - a decision I regret the higher and windier it gets. I also ponder why I decided to put on my <a href="http://bit.ly/1BD2sfW">Alpha Comp Jacket</a> instead of my <a href="http://bit.ly/1rRRHpb">Patagonia Alpine Houdini</a> rain jacket as I start the get wet inside - or then it’s the sweat from hiking and scrambling up? At least I’m warm and the jacket and pants keep the wind outside.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214147809" title="Up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3901/15214147809_699c6e2391_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up" /></a></p>

<p>We scramble up steep passages, rain and small streams making things slippery - it’s a good thing I’m wearing my <a href="http://bit.ly/1cLPRJN">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a> boots, that way I have good grip on the wet rocks and half-way dry &amp; warm feet. Soaked we arrive at the pass and the wind howls past us. I shelter behind a big rock, but Marcin lets me know we should push on. So on we push.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14363720837" title="Wind. Rain. Honesty. by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/14363720837_7ac4627792_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wind. Rain. Honesty." /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400901985" title="At the top by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3893/15400901985_9d8d44d8b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the top" /></a></p>

<p>On the way up I thought about how nice it will be to go down in the downwind side. But I must have misunderstood Marcin, as we hike down on wet talus fields on the upwind side. At a narrow stretch of path between the talus I finally decide to go search for my gloves in my pack, as my hands started to be just too damn cold in the strong wind. When I finally have managed to get my soaking wet &amp; cold hands in the gloves they need a moment to warm up, but then it’s infinitely more comfortable. The same time I pack away my camera, so I can concentrate on the path. We down climbing a few sections and then slowly are getting lower.</p>

<p>We hike over snowfields and I can believe it as down, out of the treacherous wind, we see a solitary figuring coming our way, wearing a Poncho. Marcin chats with him, and as we continue to walk I hear a similar story like the ones I have heard the days before: First time in the mountains, wants to continue to the hut we started out from. A bit later we meet a couple who also have the same plan and think that now they’re at least three if they catch up with the guy, which makes it a bit safer. We pass a high-alpine lake and low pines are starting to appear. <em>“Not long anymore”</em> Marcin tells me - he must see that I’m not feeling too great: By now I’m drenched. Soon we are walking through a pretty pine forest in the mist. After a final small uphill we stand in front of the massive <a href="http://www.murowaniec.e-tatry.pl">Schronisko Murowaniec refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214246510" title="Schronisko Murowaniec by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3931/15214246510_1e268ebe57_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schronisko Murowaniec" /></a></p>

<p>We head inside and it is full of people - some dressed in dry clothes, others looking just as wet &amp; miserable as we. Marcin shows me the drying wall, where I hang my wet gear after I slipped into my dry layers. Then it’s feasting time - I’m starving and munch away a soup and pancakes, a hot tea and coffee give more warmth. We sit for a while at the hut, with people coming and going. My clothes still moist but a bit drier I put them back on after almost two hours inside. Outside it’s still as misty as before, but the rain has become just the faintest drizzle.</p>

<p>Steadily we go down, soon the rain stops while the mist lingers on. We descend on paths that get broader and broader to a wide meadow. The mist mixes with the clouds and hangs above us while we walk towards Kuznice, a suburb of Zakopane and the start of a gondola up to Kasprowy Wierch.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214316898" title="Down by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2947/15214316898_c764198aa9_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Down" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214153899" title="Green under grey by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214153899_189ef3dfff_b.jpg" width="863" height="1024" alt="Green under grey" /></a></p>

<p>Here Marcin and I separate for a while - he needs to run an errand in town and hopes to catch a bus from here - we’ll meet up at the refuge later. After checking out the the small settlement with the gondola station and resisting buying some more food I hike up the broad cobblestone trail and take the first possibility into the forest.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400906185" title="Cobblestone by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15400906185_c9f9fbcb40_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cobblestone" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214397527" title="Fast by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2948/15214397527_125435355d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fast" /></a></p>

<p>There’s several possibilities to visit shrines and monasteries along the trail, but I just want to reach the refuge to finally strip out of all the moist clothes, take a hot shower, dress in dry clothes and eat some good food. But the scenery is lovely on the way, and so I stop here and there to take photos.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400582682" title="Tranquility by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3915/15400582682_cba7c400f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tranquility" /></a></p>

<p>As the forest disappears another wide meadow comes into view, with the pretty <a href="http://schroniska.pttk.pl/kondratowa/pl">Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali refuge</a> sitting at its side. I go in and am welcomed by smiling faces in the common room. While I don’t speak a word of Polish I still am able to communicate with the wonderful owners of the refuge and she shows me the room I am staying in. I put down my pack, get rid of the wet clothes and then just am for a moment. Then the rest of the evening is just as I imagined it would be: Hot shower, dry, warm clothes, good food, early to bed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214400107" title="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3872/15214400107_6ca4d4a074_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Schronisko na Kondratowej Hali" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ridges-and-summits">Ridges and Summits</h2>

<p>I slept great after the day before, and as we get up at 6 in the morning the sky is blue and the sun is already shining across the summits opposite my window. Marcin and I head silently down, where the two ladies of the refuge have a breakfast waiting for us! We eat, pack, and are out of the hut by 7 and make our way to the pass.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214320388" title="Up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15214320388_576117b4da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>The sky is blue with the occasional white cloud running across it and we quickly are hot from the sun and hiking. At the final spring we refill the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/platypus/?pid=81">Platypus</a> bottles with cold, clear water and then walk on. Soon we are at the pass where we drop our packs into the shrubbery and almost run up to Giewont, so light we are!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397733501" title="Further up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3866/15397733501_cb1086ff52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Further up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377897226" title="Final bit up to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2945/15377897226_c0ec8a1c1d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Final bit up to Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214268900" title="Summit of Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3848/15214268900_d99bdd983e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit of Giewont" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400602172" title="Down from Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3853/15400602172_b9e263692a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Down from Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>It doesn’t take us long and we’re standing on the summit, underneath the massive iron cross which can be seen from Zakopane. The views are hazy but good nevertheless: Zakopane towards the north with the small villages surrounding the city towards east &amp; west, and you even can glimpse into Slovakia from here. On the way down we encounter a lonely, old chamois and then soon are back at our packs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214337218" title="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/15214337218_b8187c6356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ridge walk to Kondracka Kopa" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377902416" title="A look down at the valley by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3888/15377902416_901ef59a4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look down at the valley" /></a></p>

<p>The trail to Kondracka Kopa is a long, steady climb over a wide ridge. Clouds float over the ridge and surroundings summits, while alpine flowers are adding bright colours to the grey &amp; white of the sky. On my left I can see the lower hills of the Tatras and the meadow and refuge we slept in last night, and on the left zig-zags the trail down to the meadow from my original route. It does not take long and we’re on the summit of Kondracka Kopa, and now we will walk on the border of Poland and Slovakia while ticking off the next few summits.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214340958" title="Along the border by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2949/15214340958_71b3d109f2_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Along the border" /></a></p>

<p>We stay now almost all the time above 2000 m elevation while we hike in the clouds from Kondracka Kopa to Malolaczniak, Krzesanica, Ciemniak and then Twarda Kopa. Once in a while the clouds rip open and we can see the lower Tatras in Slovakia, narrow valleys, high walls, streams running towards the far off sea.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214423037" title="Towards Twarda Kopa by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3844/15214423037_2c456098d7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Towards Twarda Kopa" /></a></p>

<p>From Twarda Kopa we can see Giemont in the distance, now in the clouds - but more worrisome is the helicopter which flies up to it from the valley. We don’t know what happened, but hope no one died.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15400937025" title="A look back to Giewont by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2943/15400937025_742b942b3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A look back to Giewont" /></a></p>

<p>Marcin waits for me at a large summit cairn and suggests we take the green trail down to the next refuge. It’s just around 11 and we have the whole day really in front of us still, so I agree and we take a turn from the big main path and walk on a very narrow path in a hanging meadow towards the Western Tatras.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15214191449" title="Down 2 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3852/15214191449_334c07144a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="964" alt="Down 2" /></a></p>

<p>The views and the trail are spectacular. A narrow singletrack trail that’s demanding and exposed, but with gorgeous views on the lower-lying mountains, valleys, meadows - and in front of us, the Western Tatras. A pair of chamois give us a show as they are fighting in a couloir, but my view often just drifts to the horizon, where large mountains try to reach the sky with their summits. At a turn in the path we sit down and have a snack &amp; drink, while Marcin names the peaks and valleys and tells me anecdotes about geographical features.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15377924676" title="A look back up the green trail by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2941/15377924676_45d34c6126_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="A look back up the green trail" /></a></p>

<p>Too soon we reach the tree line, but the path continues to be lovely. It gradually widens and Marcin tells me that it has been an old road for an iron ore mine, and I again wonder about how much work it must have been to clear the forests to create it. While we talk we reach the meadow and a group of fully loaded foreign backpackers pass us, just as amazed about the beautiful scenery around them as we are. The trail now runs next to a stream, and it does not take long until we reach the <a href="http://www.schronisko-ornak.pl">Schronisko Ornak refuge</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15397759651" title="Schronisko Ornak by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2946/15397759651_65b41d3012_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Schronisko Ornak" /></a></p>

<p>It is busy outside and not even 13 o’clock. I check in with the help of Marcin and then accompany him down the valley - our hike ends here today, and I will be venturing on for the next two days on my own. The trail is now a wide dirt road and full of people, with plenty of trails going off on the right and left - trails which I will explore on my way back up to the refuge, I decide. And as Marcin tells me about the long caves up on the mountains which one can explore my afternoon suddenly looks like it will be filled with plenty of adventure!</p>

<p><em>To be continued.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
