<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: covid19 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/covid19/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-09-18T08:51:57+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sunday Walks]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/sunday-walks.html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-25T11:53:52+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/sunday-walks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sunday, fun-day, family hiking day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49930767241/in/dateposted/" title="In Bloom 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49930767241_6f6681ff83_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="In Bloom 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Nothing to disclose here 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>One good thing which came out of the COVID-19 Pandemic is that we now go hiking every Sunday with the family. All four of us look forward to the outing, and some rain in the forecast doesn’t cancel our plans. We have rain clothes, after all - and the kids are even happier as it allows them to jump in every puddle along the trail! Good thing that we life in the sunniest part of Finland and that it hasn’t rained a lot here yet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49930250338/in/dateposted/" title="Studying the map"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49930250338_fa05a493d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Studying the map" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The most import things for our family hikes are: Some breads as a snack, a Müsli bar treat which we share, some water or hot juice to drink and proper clothes for the occasion. As it gets warmer now in Vaasa, it’s nice to wear less - maybe a couple more weeks and I can slip on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49930252398/in/dateposted/" title="Flowering"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49930252398_54114d748a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Flowering" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49930252213/in/dateposted/" title="Running"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49930252213_fdd072f6e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Running" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Last Sunday we went to a close-by nature area, and hiked some two kilometres to a birdwatching tower. While the snow is gone since months (it was another terrible winter here in the south), spring comes late in this part of Finland and only during the past week the trees started to drive out the first buds and leaves. In another week everything will be over, and the trees will be green and summer will start!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49931073187/in/dateposted/" title="Layers"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49931073187_c82f947aff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Layers" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>An important aspect of our family hikes is to keep them short-ish and interesting. Both kids much prefer forest trails to gravel roads, and around 2 km one-way seems a good distance for us right now - with a break and then another 2 km back to the start. We parents also prefer the forest trails, they feel much nicer because you’re “closer” to nature. On this hike there were also no Mosquitos, and only little noise pollution from the nearby roads.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49930250643/in/dateposted/" title="Green"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49930250643_3691e04f41_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Green" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49931073682/in/dateposted/" title="Fern"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49931073682_3d475c6c0b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fern" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There were surprisingly many families out on this trail - which is good to see, as it means more people start to value their local nature, and maybe become more engaged in protecting the environment.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49930765536/in/dateposted/" title="Dot"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49930765536_245705b8b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dot" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In the end it was a relaxed, good little hike. We saw a white-tailed eagle from the bird watching tower (even without my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/05/vortex-optics-viper-hd-binoculars.html">binoculars</a>!) and lots of smaller singing birds, which were merrily chirping in the green woods. Our little family hikes make us all feel better, and especially I really value these little adventures outdoors.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49931073032/in/dateposted/" title="Selfie"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49931073032_4cece02dd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfie" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Staying Indoors, Coping with Anxiety & Depression]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/staying-indoors.html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-12T12:39:08+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/staying-indoors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So how do you all feel, around nine-ish weeks into the Lockdown (at least in Finland)?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49622382237/in/dateposted/" title="Wooden Boards"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49622382237_c482b24757_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wooden Boards" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Nothing to disclose here, except possibly some Affiliate links 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>I started to get the first signs of depression last week, I have to admit. I especially feel bad because I lost around 90% of my income, I had to postpone the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/03/european-trail-days-2020.html">European Trail Days Festival</a> and many work trips, with other cooperations also falling through. I am not one to normally write and share such personal things, but I want to show you that while things are OK here (we can pay the bills and have food on the table each day) AND Social Media posts look like Life is A-OK, I still feel the negative consequences of the COVID-19 Pandemic, and hence I decided to break with my normal approach and share these thoughts with you.</p>

<p>The first “hint of a depression” is giving me the feeling that I wanna fix it by buying stuff, to get a quick dopamine hit of knowing of getting something new and shiny. However, I also know this does not work for me. If at all, it is a very brief dopamine hit, then I start to check tracking updates a couple of times each day (which makes me more anxious), and when it then arrives I unpack it, smile, and am unhappy again. Shopping is not a sustainable fix for me, and I happy am pretty well able to refrain from shopping, also under normal circumstances.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48753720577/in/dateposted/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48753720577_1b04a4e48e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With going outdoors also being more difficult right now - both kids are at home, my wife is working from home and as I’m basically unemployed (I am finishing up a lot of projects, though) - it is also not easy for me to go backpacking, which usually is my medicine to these situations. I can’t go out to shoot videos or go hiking, as I have to take care of the kids. At 4 and 8 they are well able to take mostly care of themselves and they play nicely together, but every 15 to 45 minutes there is a “Dad” call which needs attention. And with me being the one who has little paying work, I take care of them.</p>

<p>Now as you might know, I got back into painting miniatures and playing tabletop and boardgames several years ago, and this is actually something which helps me to cope. In the evenings (and sometimes also during the day) I go to my hobby room, where I have a nice painting corner set up, and then I delve into painting terrain or miniatures. I can get lost in the little details, forget about the bad things, and have fun and relaxation while painting. I also got a 3D Printer which is a nice new toy, but also a lot of work. This hobby does give me happiness and keeps me busy, which is positive.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49886519247/in/dateposted/" title="Hobbying away."><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49886519247_02c6e64e43_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hobbying away." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Another thing which usually helps me is to do sports, like trailrunning. Sadly I have had very little motivation to put <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/08/my-trailrunning-gear.html">my running clothes and shoes</a> on and go for a 5 or 10 km run in the nearby forest. After a long day taking care of the kids and doing some work, there’s just little power left to motivate myself to go outside. Which is a shame, because I know it would make me feel much better, if I did so.</p>

<p>So, I really miss being outdoors. Under normal circumstances I am skiing, backpacking or bikepacking &amp; packrafting once a month for a week, but right now we do not have normal circumstances. By the way, I fully support Lockdown measures and social distancing, I think the Finnish government is doing a tremendous job of keeping the population safe and healthy. But yeah, I miss not being able to go hiking with my best friend - we planned to go hiking in Luxembourg or Belgium right about now - or that my ski seasons was cut so short.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49716645042/in/dateposted/" title="Happy!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49716645042_fc0974f19e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happy!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the positive side of this Pandemic, it’s really great to sleep till 8:00 in the morning - usually we have to get up earlier to bring kids to school and kindergarden, and being able to sleep “long” and have a relaxed breakfast and a slow start into the day is positive. But that’s really about the positive things I can think of. Well, there’s less pollution from air traffic, but that’s about it.</p>

<p>So, all this is more of a way to say: While Social Media <em>might</em> give the impression that everything is great with me (I try not to give that impression, but pretty photos might give it nevertheless), the truth is that I also feel the consequences of this situation mentally, but that thanks to my family and my indoors hobbies I am coping alright. I miss going on backpacking trips and travelling, but I do think it is necessary to protect the people who are at risk. I hope that it will be soon possible to go outdoors sort-of-normally, at the latest this summer, and that I will have a great autumn backpacking trip with my best friend - and I hope that for all people who love &amp; need the outdoors for their mental wellbeing like me.</p>

<p><em>If you also “feel blue” or anxious, feel free to reach out to me (DMs or Personal Messages on Twitter, Instagram and Facebook work fine). We’re in this together =)</em></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744517427/in/dateposted/" title="Ivalojoen Kultaja"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744517427_a50c0f6c6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ivalojoen Kultaja" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Planning your first Hike (Post COVID-19)]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/planning-your-first-hike.html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-23T09:13:28+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/planning-your-first-hike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Five weeks in self-distancing Mode, and many of us are sitting at home with itchy feet: When can we go hiking &amp; camping again? I’m using this time to think about &amp; plan the future hikes I wanna do, once the lockdown is lifted!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812710111/in/dateposted-public/" title="Planning!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812710111_6d4b456c63_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Planning!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Nothing to disclose here, except some Affiliate links 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>Air traffic is now 29% of what it was pre-COVID-19, trains and busses are also substantially less frequent, cars are standing at home unused, and on the other side you have National Parks, Wilderness Areas and our beautiful outdoors which is recovering, with animals appearing where they previously have been seen long ago and air pollution in cities is dropping, too. At home we also get busy thinking about the outdoors, and our post-poned outdoor adventures. I’m no different, and while I am sad about the cancelled ski trips this spring, I’m looking forward to the hiking, packrafting and bikepacking trips in the not-too-distant future!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812125413/in/dateposted-public/" title="Planning"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812125413_7ab1c1908b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Planning" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now, as I expect that planes will remain grounded (AMAZING for the environment and our #ClimateCrisis) I will continue to travel more by train and bus. I love to travel by train: You can walk around while the train rides, eat in the train restaurant when you get hungry, play games, the kids can jump around on the playground in the kids waggon, there’s functional toilets which are not the size of a shoebox, watch movies on Youtube or surf the internet, and one of the best things: Simply watch out of the window and observe the environment which passes you by. In Europe you can get quickly and affordably to most corners of the continent, and where the train tracks stop there’s usually a bus waiting to take you to the next destination.</p>

<p><em>By the way: <a href="http://tidd.ly/c0da99e4">Click this link</a> to win TWO Interrail tickets worth 800€ for when the lockdown is lifted and you can travel again!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812681426/in/dateposted-public/" title="ScotsRail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812681426_f61a95f083_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ScotsRail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, I currently also am stuck at home (relaxing while <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCwYqDhtJj1x3DXy4IPCxL2A/">painting tabletop Miniatures and terrain</a>) and besides the occasional day hike with the family or cycling along the coast I am already pondering where to go in the summer and autumn. It’s very, very likely in Finland, with small chances of heading to close-by Norway and Sweden, but unlikely to be further away. <strong>But hey!</strong> <strong>Finland is AWESOME!</strong> Beautiful, crystal-clear lakes for paddling, amazing forests full of tasty bilberries, soft trails and great camping spots, and once autumn comes by the beautiful colours of nature will delight us!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30173126067/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Bilberry fields forever!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1973/30173126067_f98ebaaf9c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bilberry fields forever!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The best thing that you can do right now, if you’re under lockdown and can not go wild camping, is to plan that next trip. <em>Anticipation is the greatest joy</em>, as we say in German. Get in a great mood by taking out your wish list of local, national trails you wanna hike or cycle, grab some maps and start planning. And not just the hike, also on how you get there (also if schedules might not yet be that reliable, so keep that in mind) - and remember my chorus of praise for trains above 😉 And as you have had to post-pone a few hikes, maybe also stay at a local B&amp;B or Hostel at the end of your backpacking trip, as a warm shower and a tasty meal before travelling home is what you deserve, and the local entrepreneurs will be grateful for your support after months of empty rooms.</p>

<p>That’s it. Planning that next hike helps you keep a positive outlook on this situation, and going over maps and pondering what to eat (and maybe ordering already some food for that trip) helps you to spend your time productively instead of watching Netflix. Maybe plan a hike that is 90% off-trail! Or a hike which visits all the sights you wanted to visit &amp; see already since a long time! Or a hike where you come out at a great Pizza place at the end 🍕 🤗 Right now there’s enough time to plan that next hike in great detail, and get the food &amp; supplies you need for it, so that when you can get back outdoors, <strong>you are ready!</strong></p>

<p>In that sense: Stay healthy, wash your hands and plan that next outdoor trip!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49805426157/in/dateposted-public/" title="Bushbuddy Ultra"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49805426157_e3a1f70c0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Bushbuddy Ultra" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Help Your Favourite Content Creators during the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/help-your-favourite-content-creators-during-the-covid-19-pandemic.html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-06T17:59:31+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/help-your-favourite-content-creators-during-the-covid-19-pandemic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Content Creators, Photographers and Small- and Medium-Sized Businesses suffer a lot under the current Corona Virus Pandemic. Here are my tips on how you can help them during these difficult times.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49716642567/in/dateposted-public/" title="The Start"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49716642567_15d2daaa60_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Start" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Nothing to disclose here, except some Affiliate links 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>While governments across the globe sign “Rescue Packages” into law, these millions and billions of €£$ do not end up in the hands of the people who most suffer from this loss of income. Nope, it goes to large, multinational firms and you, me and my entrepreneur colleagues, we still sit in front of a hill of invoices which want to be paid - and then there’s the thing with rent for the flat and food.</p>

<p><em>BUT</em> there are ways you can support your favourite local shops, Youtube channels and outdoor blogs: Use their Affiliate Links when you shop. Because lets realize: Those of us who are fortunate enough to be able to <em>work from home</em> still have an income, and might need to buy some things to make life at home more bearable, or you simply have enough time now to ponder which backpack to purchase for that next trip when we are allowed to go out again! So if there is an online content creator you really enjoy, support her or him! Check their affiliate links from their content, even ask them for them if you don’t find them and then click on them before you order something online. And if they have a <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a>, maybe check it out and see if you can support them with a few €$£ every month.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49716327811/in/dateposted-public/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49716327811_0353c656f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With local entrepreneurs &amp; shops you could either purchase things from their online shops or call in and order the things you need for take-away. Many Café’s, restaurants and small shops offer this service during this crisis, and it helps them to survive in these times where everything which is not an essential business has to shut down and close their doors. Especially those entrepreneurs which need to pay rent for their shop are having a lot of stress and sorrow, as they could lose their businesses if they are not able to pay the rent. I really hope that there are many rent lords who will not collect rent in these times, and let normal people and businesses not end up on the street.</p>

<p>As for travel businesses like Hostels, Hotels and Tour Operators - and I have many friends who operate such businesses and I can tell you that they are severely affected - you could book a trip or reserve a room for when this Pandemic is set to calm down. If you’re optimistic that could be for the autumn, in September or October, or if you think this Pandemic will last longer, then maybe for next winter or spring. As I was just up North I can tell you that the <a href="https://sevenfellshostel.fi">7 Fells Hostel</a>, the <a href="https://hetan-majatalo.fi">Hetan Majatalo</a> and the <a href="https://www.yllaslodge.com">Ylläs Lodge</a> really would appreciate your support during this time, as are my friends from <a href="https://adventurepartners.fi">Adventure Partners</a>, <a href="https://blissadventure.fi/">Bliss Adventures</a> and <a href="https://www.outdoorpassion.fi">Outdoor Passion Finland</a>.</p>

<p>If you were planning to attend a <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de/Kurse-und-Touren:::21.html?MODsid=99c87c38cddd237c6eed6767d3a35265">packrafting</a>, <a href="https://andrewskurka.com/guided-trips/">backpacking</a> or <a href="http://www.davidlintern.com/tuition-scotland">photography course</a> which got post-poned or cancelled, book a course to a later date - either in the autumn or next spring. Because: Looking forward to your next trip is definitely something which is a positive thing in your life right now! And to be inspired for your next trip, why not <a href="https://shop.kelsey.co.uk/subscription/TGO?promo=TGO">take out a subscription</a> of your <a href="https://sidetracked.bigcartel.com/product/sidetracked-subscription-issue-17-18-19">favourite outdoor magazine</a>?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://tidd.ly/f2bcba3e" title="Outdoor Indoors"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49741946567_877933c086_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoor Indoors" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>And here’s a dozen of shops with Affiliate Links from me which you can use if you need food, clothes, a backpack, camera gear or similar while you’re indoors and planning for the next trip into nature!</em></p>

<p>We hikers, cyclists, climbers and skiers love us some maps. <a href="https://awesome-maps.com/?ref=l25zUCEMqMjF">Awesome Maps</a> look amazing, are inspiring and helping you pick a destination for that next trip, and with the code <em>HIKINGINFINLAND</em> you to get a 10% Discount on your map.</p>

<p><a href="http://tidd.ly/c2f0efeb">Bergzeit.de</a> is a fine online outdoor shop with a wide variety of gear, from skis to backpacking gear, and has a good Outlet if you’re looking for deals!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://awesome-maps.com?ref=5bf3c25a56dc2" title="Awesome Maps made my Man Cave prettier!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49741624443_b3b9ca2e90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Awesome Maps made my Man Cave prettier!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Don’t want to go to the shop to buy stuff? With the <a href="http://bit.ly/2L5feSO">ANYCUBIC PHOTON S 3D Printer</a> you can print your own items (linelocs, <a href="http://instagram.com/skullsandpaints/">miniatures</a> and tent stakes come to mind).</p>

<p>You feel like you wanna up your video and photo game on that next hike, before the next Pandemic? <a href="https://click.dji.com/ABvscxvUTRfruAlojmLdvQ?pm=link">DJI</a> is <em>THE</em> Maker of Drones and Gimbals 🎥 like the <a href="https://click.dji.com/ABYqIuh03jVt9qn7rOSTHQ?pm=link">OSMO Pocket</a>  or the <a href="https://click.dji.com/AJW5LOIRYgUjVsxHnKozeA?pm=link">OSMO Action</a> Cam, not to mention the amazing <a href="https://click.dji.com/AGoYOMOVaEfwiUhN3nns_A?pm=link">Mavic Mini Drone</a>. The latter you can even fly indoors!</p>

<p>If you feel that you have too much stuff and need to get rid of things, then <a href="http://bit.ly/2qSlrqu">GearTrade.com</a> helps you sell your used gear - extra funds for the next trip!</p>

<p>As you now have a lot of time to edit photos from past trips, why not get <a href="https://macphun.evyy.net/c/1244795/715203/3255">Luminar 4</a> for all your Photo Editing and never pay again subscription fees like with other services?!</p>

<p>If you need trailrunning shoes or hiking pants, then take a look at what <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde.eu</a> has. A great shop with a large selection and very competitive prices, it’s a good shop if you’re still looking for some kit for the next overnighter or long backpacking trip.</p>

<p>Likewise, in North America you could direct your browser to <a href="http://bit.ly/2OSSowP">Backcountry.com</a> which pretty much sells everything for your adventure, near and far 😃</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49741946342/in/dateposted-public/" title="Outdoors"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49741946342_a199f2e6cf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Outdoors" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And now lets look at some of my favourite brands and their online offerings!</p>

<p><a href="http://bit.ly/2ORYUpk">Black Diamond</a> makes my favourite Windjacket, the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody.html">Alpine Start Hoody</a>, and they just launched a new line of approach shoes which are really good for hiking in the mountains, too.</p>

<p>Talking of shoes, <a href="https://www.lunasandals.com?rfsn=35669.8168e">Luna Sandals</a> makes my favourite sandals, the Luna OSO (Flaco). They even have a special Edition of that shoe available right now, if you like it colourful!</p>

<p>If I’m not wearing Sandals then you will find <a href="https://bit.ly/3dT91WV">La Sportiva</a> shoes on my feet. I’m a La Sportiva Ambassador since several years and am really happy to have these fantastic shoes and ski boots on my feet during my adventures, like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/03/la-sportiva-crossover-2-dot-0-gtx.html">La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX</a>.</p>

<p>I’m also a huge <a href="http://bit.ly/2qV5lwl">Patagonia</a> fan as the brand makes sustainable, durable and high-quality outdoor apparel and gear, while also taking care of the environment and its employees. A brand definitely worth supporting during these times.</p>

<p>If you’re still in need of a ultralight backpack, take a look at what <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de">HUCKEPACKS</a> has to offer. The PHOENIX Lite is currently my favourite backpack, and the new <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/specials/beipack-special/">BEI Pack</a> is a really cool looking fanny pack! This small cottage definitely needs your support right now, so if you can support them - DO IT!</p>

<p>And finally, as a Houdini Friend you won’t be too surprised that I recommend their apparel, too. <a href="http://houdinisportswear.com/">Houdini Sportwear</a> is with a few exemptions pretty much all I wear - right now for example my pants, shirt and fleece jacket are from them, and it are garments that I wear day-in, day-out, at home, in the city and outdoors. All Houdini garments this season are <a href="https://houdinisportswear.com/en-eu/sustainability/sustainability-status-100">100% recycled, recyclable, renewable, biodegradable or Bluesign certified</a> and I love their simple aesthetic and functional cuts.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32245630428/in/album-72157702356861281/" title="At the Baiau Bivouc Hut"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4810/32245630428_e58769c129_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="At the Baiau Bivouc Hut" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And for all other things, from Toilet Paper to Pasta 🍝, visit your local version of Amazon IF you can not find it from a local small shop or supermarket:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/b?_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=hikefinland-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=c91185d56214864f6b056b4de7153b0b&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;node=706814011">Amazon.com</a> for all your shopping needs in North America</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/b?_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=hikiinfinl07-21&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=2e4d094ebc72add598917754d3108074&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=6738&amp;node=116189031">Amazon.co.uk</a> for all your shopping needs in Scotland, Wales, Northern Ireland and England</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.amazon.de/b?_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=hikiinfinl-21&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=a253ef34c2673bfab32f4a6d37d1a180&amp;camp=1638&amp;creative=6742&amp;node=3772226031">Amazon.de</a> for all your shopping needs in Germany</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Finally, while our family has a minimal lifestyle - we own a small house, have no car and have low fixed costs - we still have to pay bills amounting to a few thousand Euros each month. So any support you can give to content creators like me - by using the above affiliate links or supporting me via Patreon - helps to pay these bills and makes surviving this difficult time easier. Any and every help is support - even if it is just sharing this Post on Facebook or Twitter with your friends and fans! As always, <strong>THANK YOU</strong> for reading my musings on the outdoors here at <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/">Hiking in Finland</a>! Stay safe, healthy and wash your hands ❤️ 😊</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I travelled during the COVID-19 Pandemic]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/i-travelled-during-the-covid-19-pandemic.html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-01T13:36:13+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/i-travelled-during-the-covid-19-pandemic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No, this is not an April’s Fool joke. I really travelled during the COVID-19 Pandemic, and it was not fun.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49716323861/in/dateposted-public/" title="On the road to Lapland with OnniBus"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49716323861_d7bd8a33cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the road to Lapland with OnniBus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Nothing to disclose here, except some Affiliate links 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>Two weeks ago I wrote about <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/03/hiking-and-travel-during-covid-19.html">Hiking and Travel during COVID-19</a>, and now I’m back and want to share my experiences with you of how it was to travel in this time and age. In case you wonder: Yes, <strong>this was a work trip</strong>. I went on this trip because it means I can put food on the table for April and May. It is the only larger income for the foreseeable future, and yes, my family and me were discussing long and in-depth if I should go. Deep inside I probably hoped that OnniBus would just cancel the journey to Levi, then I’d be able to easily postpone the trip. But I kept on checking their website, and on the evening of the 19th of March it was clear: My Bus to Lapland rides, and my buses south too. So I put the last things into my Pulka, strapped the skis on top, filled up my Thermos with hot juice and went to the Bus Station.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49720079711/in/dateposted-public/" title="COVID-19 Bus Selfie"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49720079711_1ecf6aedb0_b.jpg" width="769" height="1024" alt="COVID-19 Bus Selfie" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>My Bus from Vaasa left at 2:30 in the middle of the night, and with me were another five or six people on the bus - all well spaced out. I put on my <a href="https://amzn.to/3dEOEN7">noise-cancelling headphones</a>, put the relaxing sound of a rainy night playing, and fell asleep. I awoke at 7:00 in the morning in Oulu, where I had an hour time before my Bus to Levi would leave. The sun was shining outside, it was -7°C and inside in the waiting hall of the bus station were four other people. Everyone was sitting on his or her own bench, with several meters of distance between us. As I was going to sit another 9 hours in the Bus I pulled my Pulka to the bus platform and started walking up and down in the sun.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49719505363/in/dateposted-public/" title="Oulu Matkakeskus"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49719505363_34eacd27c9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Oulu Matkakeskus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In the Bus to Levi we were a few more people - maybe between ten and twelve. Again there were several rows distance between each passenger, and at the few longer stops everyone let the others disembark with a lot of distance. People stayed away from each other, and no one was wearing face-masks. As we reached the border with Sweden after Kemi you could see the border guards stoping cars which tried to pass between Finland and Sweden, something I have not seen ever before.</p>

<p>As I arrived in Levi I was surprised about the bustle in town. The lifts were operating, people were out skiing, fatbiking, and going for a stroll in the beautiful sunny weather. I waited 10 Minutes for my Bus for Hetta, and we were a total of three passengers on this Bus. Then, finally, at almost 17 o’clock I had arrived in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html">Hetta</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49715782283/in/dateposted-public/" title="Hetan Majatalo"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49715782283_ed3bc81a4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hetan Majatalo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This part of the journey worked surprisingly well. I was happy to be in sunny Lapland, with cold and sunny weather in the forecast. I was looking forward to go <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/03/impressions-from-the-hetta-pallas-hiking-trail.html">skiing on the Hetta - Pallas Trail</a>, and leave this crazy situation behind me for a while at least.</p>

<p>The next morning I left Hetta, and loved skiing on the XC tracks. It was exhausting, but the sun was shining, there was little wind, and the views were great. My phone was in Airplane mode, both so it preserved battery and that I’m not bothered by what is going on elsewhere on this planet 🌍. For the next days I had a wonderful time (being happily ignorant of developments in Finland and elsewhere) although it also has been <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B-XgJhSDDOy/">utterly exhausting</a> at times.</p>

<p>On Tuesday I arrived at the rustic Montellin Maja hut, and thought it would be a good time to check my Emails. That’s where the stress started: I had several messages from OnniBus that they decided to cancel all Ski Busses from Levi &amp; Ylläs to the south, BUT there was one Bus still going - you needed to be in touch if you wanted to get a seat on it. A few stressful hours ensued, while I was skiing in windy &amp; sunny weather first to the large Nammalakuru Hut and then onwards to the Rihmakuru Kota. As I arrived at the latter I had received a reply that I was rebooked on the Bus on Saturday morning going south, and so I could enjoy this wonderful Kota with it’s <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel/status/1242769710699159552">amazing tiny stove</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49715787928/in/dateposted-public/" title="Hannunkuru Sauna"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49715787928_ac3c16c7a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hannunkuru Sauna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next few days I spent skiing and fatbiking in Ylläs while enjoying the hospitality of the <a href="https://sevenfellshostel.fi/">7 Fells Hostel</a>. On Saturday morning I took a Taxi to the Bus Stop, and was happy to see that there were a few more travellers making the journey south. That meant at least the bus was not cancelled. <em>Or that’s what we thought.</em> It was 10:20 and there was no Bus in sight. 10:30, still no Bus. 10:40, no Bus. A Blizzard was raging at the Bus Stop, and it was cold. We were wondering with the other passengers what is going on - it’s just a short 16 km to Levi, and such a delay seemed very strange. Was the Bus coming?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49720358282/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ylläs OnniBus Stop"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49720358282_d639ceb6d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Ylläs OnniBus Stop" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>At 11:20, an hour late, the OnniBus rolled to the Bus Stop. Everyone was reliefed and smiling - we would get home at last! We loaded all our stuff inside, and off we were. There still was lots of space - the next passengers to me sat three rows behind me - and somehow we also arrived not too late in Oulu. I saw the train going to Seinäjoki stand already at the platform, and decided to try to catch it, even if I only had a ticket for Sunday night on the same train. I got in, stored all my stuff, and sat down alone as the only passenger in the whole waggon. My ticket was accepted with a smile and several hours later I disembarked in Seinäjoki. I waited a short while alone on the platform while Dusk was painting the sky in beautiful hues of orange, red and blue, till my train to Vaasa arrived. The same thing again - I was the only passenger in the whole waggon, and had a friendly chat with the conductress. I arrived well back in Vaasa at home, kissed my kids good night after over a week, and had a relaxed evening with my wife. But <strong>I wouldn’t go on such a trip again under these circumstances.</strong></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49720326892/in/dateposted-public/" title="Seinäjoki Railway Station"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49720326892_663093297c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Seinäjoki Railway Station" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>What would have been a fabulous trip and an amazing experience under normal circumstances warped into a stressful and uncertain trip during this COVID-19 Pandemic. Being reliant on Public Transportation in these times is highly unreliable, and adds a level of stress which I wouldn’t want to experience when I go on a trip. Being uncertain about if you get home, or when and how, just distracts from your enjoyment of the nature and landscape you went to explore &amp; experience. As the COVID-19 Pandemic is set to limit travels (in Finland) at least till the end of May I know that I will not go anywhere where I can not get on my bike from the front of my house, or where I can hike or paddle easily.</p>

<p>Going outdoors is a place for me where I want to be able to recuperate, and even if I can stay offline and shut out the rest of the world, if you need to get home with the bus or train afterwards that thought will stick with you, even as your phone stays in Flight Mode. So my conclusion is simple: Travelling during the COVID-19 pandemic, even within your own country - is not worth it. Stay local, explore your own backyard forests and lakes, and use your bike, feet and <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de/Neu/Anfibio-Rebel-2K::889.html">packraft</a> to get to new places. The hills will still be there when this Pandemic has passed, and you will enjoy them a lot more than now, in these uncertain times. And why not <a href="http://tidd.ly/f2bcba3e">camp in the garden this Eastern</a> instead of travelling far?</p>

<p>If you enjoyed this article <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49716341331/in/dateposted-public/" title="Huts are closed!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49716341331_60913559fc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Huts are closed!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
