<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: opinion | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/opinion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-11-30T17:19:49+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Buy New Gear (But if you MUST...)]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/11/dont-buy-new-gear.html"/>
    <updated>2018-11-19T20:28:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/11/dont-buy-new-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The most absurd shopping week of the year is starting, and I think you should not buy anything.</p>

<p>(<em>Look who is talking, right?!</em>)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32086560028/in/dateposted/" title="Too much Gear?"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4894/32086560028_e51f8b24ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Too much Gear?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Lets be realistic: Unless you started with the hobby of backpacking, climbing, packrafting or trailrunning <em>just last weekend</em> you likely own already everything you need. And if you were hiking for the first time in your life this month - well, the garments and pack you wore are just fine for the next three hiking weekends at least. So in stead of investing your hard earned €$£ over the next weeks into things you very likely don’t need, invest it into something good. Support a NGO like <a href="https://protectourwinters.org">Protect our Winters</a> or <a href="https://www.onepercentfortheplanet.org">1% For The Planet</a>, go eat out with your friends or family, or use that money to go on a trip (<a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/destinations/">Here you can find some inspiration</a>). Hell, you even could become a <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon of this website</a> and support my writing, photography and videos!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41836779814/in/album-72157669754047208/" title="Long Exposure along the Causeway Coast Way in Portstewart"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1755/41836779814_c84c8513da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Long Exposure along the Causeway Coast Way in Portstewart" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Saying no to bargains and shiny new gear is hard (as you can see above, I have had a hard time in the past). If you absolutely have to shop I’d appreciate if you use any of the following affiliate links. These have <strong>ZERO extra costs for you</strong> and I get a wee commission from your purchase. There’s a wide list of possibilities, from shopping at your favourite flavour of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/b?_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=hikefinland-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=c91185d56214864f6b056b4de7153b0b&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;node=706814011">Amazon</a>, to more specialised stores like <a href="http://bit.ly/2qQ5KjQ">evo</a> and <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> where you can shop for high-quality equipment &amp; garments and support me at the same time. So, in no particular order, if you get the shopping bug and want to do something good to me without any extra costs to you, use these links for your Black Friday/ Cyber Monday/ Holiday shopping:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://awesome-maps.com?ref=5bf3c25a56dc2">Awesome Maps</a> for beautiful maps that you can put up at home (use the code <em>HIKINGINFINLAND</em> to get a 10% Discount)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/b?_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=hikefinland-20&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=c91185d56214864f6b056b4de7153b0b&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;node=706814011">Amazon.com</a> for all your shopping needs in North America</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/b?_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=hikiinfinl07-21&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=2e4d094ebc72add598917754d3108074&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=6738&amp;node=116189031">Amazon.co.uk</a> for all your shopping needs in Brexitlandia</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.amazon.de/b?_encoding=UTF8&amp;tag=hikiinfinl-21&amp;linkCode=ur2&amp;linkId=a253ef34c2673bfab32f4a6d37d1a180&amp;camp=1638&amp;creative=6742&amp;node=3772226031">Amazon.de</a> for all your shopping needs in Germany</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.airbnb.com/c/hmorkel?currency=EUR">AirBnB</a> is a great place to find afforable and cozy accommodation before or after a hike</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> is THE outdoor shop in the UK</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2OSSowP">Backcountry.com</a> sells everything for your adventure, near and far</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde.de</a> is my favourite German online outdoor shop</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.booking.com/index.html?aid=1603688">Booking.com</a> is a good place to find Hotels and flights ✈️</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2OPNY9R">Campsaver.com</a> usually has a lot of discounts</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2FsCABy">Cotopaxi</a> makes sustainable and trendy outdoor gear</li>
  <li><a href="https://click.dji.com/ABvscxvUTRfruAlojmLdvQ?pm=link">DJI</a> is <em>THE</em> Maker of Drones and Gimbals 🎥</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2qQ5KjQ">evo</a> takes care of your skiing and snowboard needs</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2FsDIoM">Garage Grown Gear</a> is home to a variety of cottage-made gear</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2qQ6LbE">Good To-Go</a> makes delicious meals for your next outdoor adventure</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2zgLfkS">GORUCK</a> makes the most durable backpacks in the world</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2qSlrqu">GearTrade.com</a> helps you sell and buy used gear</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2OSpzjS">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> is your source of ultralight &amp; durable gear for your next adventure</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2zgLlZM">Jaybird</a> makes superb headphones for active people</li>
  <li>Get <a href="https://macphun.evyy.net/c/1244795/320119/3255">Luminar 2018</a> for all your Photo Editing - with the Coupon Code <em>MORKEL</em> you’ll save an additional $10!</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2FwUt1Y">Lifeproof</a> protects your phone on your adventures</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.lunasandals.com?rfsn=35669.8168e">Luna Sandals</a> makes my favourite sandals!</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2OPVVfe">My Trail Co</a> is GoLite with a new name and their old designs</li>
  <li>With <a href="http://bit.ly/2ziu4iJ">On Running</a> Shoes you’ll be faster than the wind</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2qV5lwl">Patagonia</a> makes sustainable, durable and high-quality outdoor apparel and gear</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.peakdesign.com?rfsn=1845073.d8e1f">Peak Design</a> makes the Capture Clip, my favourite way to carry my camera 📷</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2ORimR2">Pictureline</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2FwHrBI">REI.com</a> is one of the largest Outdoor Co-ops in the world ⛺️</li>
  <li>Into HDR Photography? Then get <a href="https://macphun.evyy.net/c/1244795/513351/3255">Aurora HDR 2019</a>! And with the Coupon Code <em>MORKEL</em> you’ll save even $10 more!</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2qU0T11">Sierra Designs</a> makes lightweight tents, sleeping bags and backpacks</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2OOBUpf">Stio</a> creates gear for all your mountain needs - from skiing to downhill biking</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2ziLeNs">Trek Light Gear</a> sells hammocks, blankets and other outdoorsy kit</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2zglkJU">Trivago</a> is a Travel Portal 🏨</li>
  <li><a href="">ULA Equipment</a> is a UL backpack manufacturer out of Utah</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/2ORCWAN">Ultimate Direction</a> makes some of the lightest and most ergonomic trailrunning gear</li>
</ul>

<p>Or if you need some inspiration, check out some of my favourite backpacking gear:</p>

<script src="//z0a.de/outtra-739.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1746" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731746" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1746"></script>

<p><strong>Thank you!</strong></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39218815430/in/album-72157667114048408/" title="Getting there"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/815/39218815430_7d2e395259_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Getting there" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Changes]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/01/changes.html"/>
    <updated>2017-01-25T23:33:03+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/01/changes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The End of Hiking in Finland as we know it and the start of something new.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32476889446/in/dateposted/" title="Myllykoski Bridge"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/607/32476889446_9d1766bcb1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Myllykoski Bridge" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Sometime last autumn I purchased a new domain. My mind is set, I need a fresh start. After eight years of blogging at Hiking in Finland I need a new challenge. It’s a bad time to do this, but if I don’t do it not now I never might. Hiking in Finland is the most-read English-language blog from Scandinavia, there’s over 30.000 Regular Readers a month, add in the close to 20.000 Followers and Fans on the different Social Media channels and you can understand the dilemma of changing something that’s so successful and generates part of my income (Yes, I work full time on the blog since 2014).</p>

<p>Things that led to this is that I do far more nowadays than hiking in Finland - just last year I was ski-touring in Norway &amp; Switzerland, on adventure travel trips in Macedonia, Greece and Mexico, on active family holidays in Vorarlberg, backpacking in South Tyrol and cycle touring in Finland. So the name is out-dated and limits me, but I also moved away a bit from what this blog was about in the beginning - ultralight backpacking. While I maintain that Ultralight is Not Dead I also have started to look over the borders - I have entered a partnership with Helsport for example, and while I always try to carry as little as possible and use the lightest gear for the occasion it’s not the be all and end all of all things like it was more in the past.</p>

<p>But mostly I feel I have become complacent. The status quo is a dangerous place to get lazy and before other’s think <em>It’s the same old</em> I myself might just kill the status quo, reinvent and embark on a new journey. It might be rough on the edges at the beginning, some of you might not like it, but I am sure that with a new challenge I am able to grow myself and the blog to a new level that’s more creative &amp; honest.</p>

<h2 id="design-or-why-does-hif-look-not-like-it-used-to">DESIGN or why does HiF look not like it used to?</h2>
<p>Last November I managed to destroy the backend of Hiking in Finland - right before the #HiFAdventCalendar should have started and while I was in Mexico. Some bacteria or virus knocked me out for two weeks once I returned from Mexico and I barely was able to publish the daily doors on the ad-hoc blog I created. As I got healthy again I had a big hacking session and managed to get HiF back online the way you see it now - still not really how it used to look like or how I would like it to look, but better than a 404. During February and March I will try to update the layout and looks, but first there’s some other priorities.</p>

<h2 id="yeps-theres-gonna-be-a-new-blog">Yeps, there’s gonna be a new blog</h2>
<p>Hiking in Finland will continue &amp; will be regularly updated in the future, but my new website Hike Climb Travel will see a lot more action. Hike Climb Travel is much broader in name as Hiking in Finland and reflects that I do much more than hiking &amp; backpacking in Finland. Hiking in Finland will be home to my adventures at home and neighbouring countries, while Hike Climb Travel will be my outlet for everything that does take place outside of my beautiful home country. It will kick off some time in February, with a pretty, responsive layout, a great brand identity and some great stories to get you hooked. The best way to stay informed about when the new blog goes online is to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow me on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a>, but no worries, I also will let it be known here.</p>

<p>For some time I will try to work on both blogs, but time will show if that is possible &amp; smart or if I just move everything over to the new website. Thus, if there’s a favourite article here on the Olde Blog, now is a good time to save it as a pdf for future references. Some content will will also be moved over, so no worries that it’s gonna be all lost down the aether.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32396336051/in/dateposted/" title="Staring off into the distance"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/443/32396336051_9d5ed3cd01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Staring off into the distance" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="twir-is-not-dead">TWIR is (Not?) Dead</h2>
<p>A couple of weeks back I asked on Instagram and Facebook for one reason why you follow me and a large part of the answers included TWIR. But a lot has changed since I started The Week In Review six years ago: I got married, have two wonderful kids and a house that still needs a wee bit of renovation (not to mention the garden). I feel I have neglected my family the last years every Sunday for several hours while writing the TWIR, and with a little daughter of one year I (maybe too late) realised it is time to kill The Week in Review, reclaim my Sundays and spend them with the people that matter the most to me - my wife and kids.</p>

<p>Also, The Week In Review is a popular post but it never generated much of income for me. I tried to monetise it in some tasteful ways by affiliate links to offers that matter to you, and a couple of times the Packrafting Store sponsored an issue, but these were not putting enough €$£ into my pocket for the time I invest into the TWIR. Because I know that so many of you love the TWIR and rely on it to find new, relevant content that matters, I am open to suggestions on how we could keep the Week In Review alive - but it would be published then on Mondays as I want to have a weekend. Maybe a PayPal subscription would be an option, but that would mean some of you would need to start to pay for the TWIR content. If you think that’s something you’d be willing to do, leave a comment underneath - and also other ideas and feedback is welcome.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31674881554/in/dateposted/" title="Ice River floating"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/700/31674881554_9d690dd7bb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ice River floating" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All in all I am very happy to have this off my chest. I felt bad leaving you loyal readers in the dark about this since last December, but now that I typed it down and re-read it a couple of times it feels good and I am happy to hit publish and see how you take these changes. Thus, comment away - here or on the Social Media channels you can find me on!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Perfect Cup of Outdoor Coffee]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/10/the-perfect-cup-of-outdoor-coffee.html"/>
    <updated>2015-10-09T23:51:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/10/the-perfect-cup-of-outdoor-coffee</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Because coffee outdoors is trendy and we all long to be regarded as cool &amp; fashionable you see an increasing amount of coffee paraphernalia being carried outdoors. While that’s appropriate for glamping, in my opinion it is uncalled for in the pack of an ultralight backpacker. Why I think that way and which tasty, ultralight coffee options there are, you find out in this article.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21860097560/in/dateposted/" title="Cowboy coffee"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5824/21860097560_6f4dcb00e8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Cowboy coffee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I own an <a href="http://amzn.to/1LDfy7p">Aeropress</a> since before it was trendy, we have a <a href="http://amzn.to/1GzOC0X">Chemex</a> and regularly order <a href="https://www.kaffaroastery.fi">coffee beans</a> for a tasty cup of self-grinded afternoon coffee at home. If we don’t grind our own coffee we pick up the Fair Trade &amp; Environmentally labelled coffee from the supermarket, all for a good cup of Joe. So you could say we like good coffee. But why would I say that that doesn’t need to be transported to the outdoors?</p>

<p>Well, one thing is to <strong>simplify</strong>, to keep it light and simple. We often go outdoors to enjoy a simpler life, and carrying a whole lot of coffee making equipment outdoors seems to result in the opposite. Because even if I value a good cup of coffee, I feel carrying a grinder and an Aeropress outdoors just adds complexity to my outdoor coffee experience. Besides, I already drink Aeropress coffee at home every day, so I don’t feel a need to carry the kit along on a trip. I mean, I go outdoors to enjoy nature, the fresh air and the exercise, and also to escape the ordinary “home life” - <strong>why would I carry the same stuff along which I use every day at home?</strong></p>

<p><em>“But there’s no good alternative”</em> some coffee enthusiasts might argue. I beg to differ. In my opinion there are three fantastic, ultralight options to enjoy a good cup of coffee outdoors: Cowboy Coffee, Jiva Coffee Cubes and Starbucks Via.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22048263625/in/dateposted/" title="Outdoor Coffee"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5829/22048263625_e0cb02cafd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Outdoor Coffee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="jiva-coffee-cubes">Jiva Coffee Cubes</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.jivacubes.com">Jiva Coffee Cubes</a> are the newest ultralight coffee on the market. I supported their crowdfunding campaign last year and got a wee package with a varied assortment of their cubes. They come in seven coffee tastes, from the Classic Coffee Cubes over the Mocha Cubes to French Vanilla Coffee Cubes, there should be something from them that will be to your liking. A 24 pack of coffee cubes costs $15 ($63 cent per serving) and one cube weighs 9 g. They are made of coffee and <a href="https://www.jivacubes.com/colombian-expedition-part-2-panela/">Panela</a>, which is unrefined whole cane sugar. Their coffee cubes are slightly more sweet but not in a bad way (I drink my coffee black without anything) - I actually like the taste a lot, and find it on level, if not better, than Starbucks Via.</p>

<p>Even if they are heavier than Via, I find them a great choice for backpacking trips. They pack small and are easy to use, and for coffee lovers who like to add sugar to their cuppa the Jiva Cubes could mean that they can leave the sugar at home. The many different tastes all are equally good, though I like the stronger Cubes for some extra caffein punch in the mornings. They need a bit of time to dissolve and you want to give your cup a good stir for the best taste experience. I recommend to order one of their <a href="https://www.jivacubes.com/shop/assorted-sample-pack/">assortment boxes</a> to give them a try and see if you like them.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22035884612/in/dateposted/" title="Jiva Coffee Cubes"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/733/22035884612_79b609b431_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Jiva Coffee Cubes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="starbucks-via">Starbucks Via</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/marken/weitere-produkte-food/starbucks-via-ready-brew-colombia-12x23g.php#.VhdhQrRGBA4">Starbucks Via</a> is since many years <em>the</em> choice for ultralight backpackers. At 3 g a serving they really are ultralight, and they are super easy to make: Open packaging, pour the powder in your cup, add hot water and you are done. You don’t even need to stir! At 0,67€ per serving they are slightly more expensive than the Jiva Cubes, but they are one third of the weight and in a pinch you can use the packaging as a spoon to stir your cuppa. The taste is great in my opinion, the only downside is that they can be a tad difficult to find in Europe.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/k5rvTvbxWpg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="cowboy-coffee">Cowboy Coffee</h2>

<p>You love your self-grinded coffee you drink at home? Then just take it along on your next hike and drink it cowboy style! It’s the easiest, lightest and probably best way to enjoy a good cup of coffee outdoors. Besides hot water, a cup and your coffee all you need is a wee bit of patience to let the coffee settle on the bottom of your cup after you poured the hot water over it, and you’re ready to enjoy it. There’s several guides online (<a href="http://bedrockandparadox.com/2014/10/10/how-to-make-cowboy-coffee/">read Dave’s</a>) if you’re new to this, but it is difficult to do anything wrong with this method. It actually is the same way that coffee is drunk in many countries, from Turkey to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/via-dinarica-day-1.html">Bosnia and Herzegovina</a>, where real coffee is served “Cowboy Style”. The taste is excellent (even better when prepared near a camp fire!) and you will quickly realize that an Aeropress isn’t needed on your backpacking trips!</p>

<p>If you don’t like the <em>“gritty”</em> Cowboy-Style, try the <a href="http://bit.ly/1jfEDZc">GSI Java Dripper</a> or a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/ortlieb-kaffeefilter-halter/">Filter Holder</a>. These weigh only just a couple of grams, pack small and are an acceptable, lightweight tool to make a cup of coffee without getting any coffee grounds into your mouth. Now you have everyhting you need to know to enjoy the perfect cup of outdoor coffee, thus <strong>go and have a cuppa - outdoors!</strong></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22048263875/in/dateposted/" title="Coarse grind coffee"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/743/22048263875_6e7eb5671c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Coarse grind coffee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Don’t agree? Comment away, but remember to <strong>be nice &amp; civilized</strong>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
