<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gregory | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/gregory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2019-03-06T17:03:00+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gregory Optic 48]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/10/gregory-optic-48.html"/>
    <updated>2018-10-05T23:39:19+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/10/gregory-optic-48</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first backpack for backpacking I bought from my own money was a Gregory backpack in 1999. It is thus with much joy that I return to carrying a Gregory pack - just this time it is much, much lighter than 20 years ago!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199759745/in/dateposted/" title="Storådörren Valley from the other side n better weather"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1903/44199759745_b4b7e1753e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Storådörren Valley from the other side n better weather" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from Gregory. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>The <a href="">Gregory Optic 48</a> is a lightweight backpack that can carry heavier loads up to 17 kg in good comfort, though it really shines when used with a lightweight load of 9 to 11 kg. Smart details like easily accessible side mesh pockets, good hipbelt pockets and a large front mesh pocket make this a great entry of the 40 year old brand into the lightweight backpacking niche. <a href="https://youtu.be/NQsQYYp34qU">Watch the video</a> to see the pack in action:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NQsQYYp34qU?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The pack arrived during the summer at the Hiking in Finland HQ and has been out for dayhikes and a 90+ km off-trail trip in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/09/impressions-from-are-and-valadalen.html">Vålådalen</a>, Sweden.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30173121037/in/dateposted/" title="A break"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1948/30173121037_70bdb338c9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A break" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>As you can imagine, the function of a backpack is to carry your gear. The Gregory Optic 48 wants to do this in comfort, in a light package, and one that last you a life time.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30173126507/in/dateposted/" title="Taking in that view"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1969/30173126507_822b2a8317_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Taking in that view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Straight from the Gregory Optic Website, here’s the list of features this pack has:</p>

<ul>
  <li>An included raincover</li>
  <li>A removable lid and an included lid flap</li>
  <li>An internal hydration sleeve and a port</li>
  <li>A Sunglass stow on the shoulder strap</li>
  <li>Spacious front mesh pocket</li>
  <li>Side mesh pockets with quick access waterbottle stow</li>
</ul>

<p>The backpack is available in a small, medium and large back length and you should measure your back to get the right size.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45061734512/in/dateposted/" title="Break on the pass"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1927/45061734512_5baf247e39_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Break on the pass" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>I didn’t find any technical innovations in the pack, all the features have been seen before, also in packs of a similar or lighter weight. Gregory probably disagrees, as they find their AeroSpan Suspension an innovation (it is a lighter version of their VaporSpan suspension).</p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>As I told in the video, the first backpack I ever bought from my own money was a Gregory (Model Weekender, some 60+ l if I remember correctly, in green and black) way back in 1999. I used this pack for 11 years, backpacking in Central America (I lived in Honduras for one year as I was 18/ 19), hiking in Finland, and for lots of travelling. That pack was bombproof and if I wouldn’t have lost it in an accident I still might be using it. Also the Optic 48 inspires the same durability, it’s made from a 100D High Tenacity Nylon in the main body and a 210D High Tenacity Nylon in the bottom, with a 7001 Hollow Aluminium Frame and the hipbelt and shoulder straps use a Multi-Density - Lifespan EVA for cushioning. I have no doubt that you could thru-hike several long trails with this pack and it wouldn’t look worse than on the first day on the trail!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199753085/in/dateposted/" title="Whoop whoop!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1971/44199753085_7c07579527_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Whoop whoop!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The main pack with all straps and the lid pocket weighs 1181 g in back length L, the lid flap weighs 34 g and the rain cover 90 g. I haven’t weigh the lid but if you don’t need the extra storage + organizational space it gives you I imagine you can save another 150 g or so. I also think that by cutting down the straps to my length I could save a maybe another 30 or so grams. This puts the Optic 48 in the lightweight backpack category for me.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I’ll base my assessment of the pack mostly on my 90 km hike in Vålådalen, as that was when I carried a lot of gear with the pack for four days. I have used the pack on day hikes, though as I then carry usually not a lot of weight I find that not representable. On that backpacking trip in Vålådalen I did some very long days - the longest was 38 km, of which were 21 km off-trail. Yes, on that day I really felt the pack and got quite familiar with it, and as you can imagine I was happy when I found around 22:00 clock in the beam of my headlamp a good spot to pitch the tent and lay down.</p>

<p>OK, so the pack. I really like the very stretchy mesh side and front pocket, especially the front pocket can take a lot of gear - first I carried my hardshell pants and jacket in them, then later on the flysheet of the tent and the rubbish (empty packaging from meals and snacks). Also the side pockets are really big, I carried in one both my tripod and the Gorillapod, and in the other one my 1l BeFree Bottle and my Kuksa cup. The side pockets I also can access with the pack on my back, which is good when I want to have my cup to drink from a stream. The hipbelt pockets are also very well designed, they open &amp; close easily with one hand and are big enough for several snacks each.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45061743222/in/dateposted/" title="Another break with a view"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1917/45061743222_96056b5c9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Another break with a view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45061746652/in/dateposted/" title="Ventilated back"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1976/45061746652_9e6346f6a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ventilated back" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199764915/in/dateposted/" title="Comfortable shoulder straps"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1931/44199764915_1fb8849e52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Comfortable shoulder straps" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45061747792/in/dateposted/" title="Great hipbelt"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1923/45061747792_489fa998b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Great hipbelt" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44390662784/in/dateposted/" title="Open Lidpocket"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1917/44390662784_1588a76159_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Open Lidpocket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44390663364/in/dateposted/" title="Side Pocket Two"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1972/44390663364_e7e9762490_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Side Pocket Two" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Optic 48 is easy to pack, I can stow my UL kit with plenty of room to spare for food and camera gear in it. I have not used the raincover ever, for me this is unnecessary and even hiking in the rain and strong wind the gear stayed dry in it. The top of the pack is really easy to open and close, if you have a lot of kit with you you could strap some of it on top, affix it with the strap and lid, and be good to go. At the front I had my trekking poles attached, which worked OK - the baskets on my poles are small and tended to slip through the loop at the bottom, but the adjustable strap at the top kept them securely in place. If your trekking poles have larger baskets than mine, you’re fine! I really haven’t used the side compression straps or the possibility to strap something underneath the pack, but it’s good to know they’re there.</p>

<p>The harness, shoulder straps and ventilated back work well together, especially the harness and straps are very comfortable and carry well, though I do wish the shoulder straps would be a bit more apart at the top, which should make them even more comfortable. As I left the Vålådalen Fjällstation I was carrying 17 kg of weight (that is including food for four days, 1 l of water and an unreasonable amount of camera gear). Yes, the pack felt heavy, but not uncomfortable. Once the straps were correctly adjusted the weight was transferred nicely to the hipbelt and shoulders, and even when I was boulder hopping I never felt unsafe or burdened. Generally I don’t see much use in ventilated back panels, maybe it is because I either way sweat a lot, I am not hiking in 30°C or more temperatures or something else, I don’t know. The idea certainly is good, I just don’t know if they work.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199758105/in/dateposted/" title="Content stays dry - also with a raincover!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1939/44199758105_7a30aa298c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Content stays dry - also with a raincover!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30173127497/in/dateposted/" title="Windy"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1938/30173127497_d4df16f7eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Windy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>While the shoulder straps do work for me, I think they could be made even better by making them wider at the top where they connect to the pack. As they are the straps are rather close together, which can be uncomfortable for some people. I also would like if the shoulder straps would be slightly more narrow so that it would be easier to connect my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/gear-of-the-year-2015-peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Design Capture Clip V3</a> to it, right now it is a rather tight fit. And if a future Gregory lightweight pack gets rid of the ventilated back and puts the shoulder straps further apart I think they could have a really amazing pack!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199763275/in/dateposted/" title="The Shoulder Straps"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1950/44199763275_9943a38b67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Shoulder Straps" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I am very happy with how the Optic 48 has carried a rather heavy load in Sweden, kept the gear inside dry and was comfortable also on very long &amp; strenuous days. It is a lightweight pack which is best suited to people who carry heavier loads (for example who go out backpacking to take photos and carry a tripod, heavy lenses and accessories, in addition to the camping kit) and those who want a backpack which will last them a long time, no matter how careless they treat the pack when they are out. With its easily accessible side and hipbelt pockets you don’t need to take the pack off when you want to eat or drink something, and the lid with its two zippered pockets offers a good place to store smaller items like your phone, keys, wallet, spare batteries and the map + notebook. The well cushioned shoulder straps and hipbelt feel great and are a nice change to thinner UL carrying systems. In conclusion, I’m looking forward to take the Optic out again in the future on long hikes where I carry heavier loads - and everyone who does not carry 5 kg of camera gear likely will really enjoy this backpack on their wilderness hikes!</p>

<p>For all the wonderful outdoor women there’s a women’s version available - the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/gregory-womens-octal-45-mountaineering-backpack/?pid=10239">Octal</a>! <strong>#GRLPWR</strong></p>

<p>And as always, more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157702073100795">Flickr Album</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30173127217/in/dateposted/" title="Good view, fast hiking"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1954/30173127217_50123b62aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Good view, fast hiking" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>If you are in the market for a lightweight backpack that carries well and last you a life-time then definitely consider the Optic 48! You can buy it right now with a 20% Discount at <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/gregory-optic-48-mountaineering-backpack/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek</a> and <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/gregory-optic-48-tourenrucksack/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> in Europe, at <a href="http://bit.ly/2QtUCnA">Backcountry</a> in North America or directly from <a href="https://eu.gregorypacks.com/fi-en/optic-48-l--lava-grey/91640-1490.html">Gregory</a>.</p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this review &amp; video <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199762475/in/dateposted/" title="Tent break"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1959/44199762475_4658c32641_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tent break" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assorted Ice Climbing Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/04/assorted-ice-climbing-gear.html"/>
    <updated>2013-04-19T21:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/04/assorted-ice-climbing-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Besides boots, crampons, ice axes and a backpack there’s a few more pieces of gear an ice climber needs - ice screws, belay devices, slings, quick draws, and and and. In this article I highlight some of the assorted ice climbing gear which I have used during this years ice climbing exploits.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661762203/" title="Assorted climbing gear by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8250/8661762203_070d206c29_b.jpg" width="680" height="1024" alt="Assorted climbing gear" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="black-diamond-express-ice-screws">Black Diamond Express Ice Screws</h2>
<p>The Gold Standard in ice screws, the Black Diamond Express have the best price/ quality ratio and perform superbly on the ice. Easy to screw into the ice with one hand thanks to the crank and with to two carabiner holes to clip in, the Express ice screw helps you to secure yourself quickly when the going gets tough. Petzl will bring out a similar design next winter which performs very well, and Grivel’s <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/grivel-ice-screw-360-kurbeleisschraube/">360 ice screws</a> too is great. However, at the moment Black Diamond makes the lightest screws and they’re very well priced, thus these excellent ice screws shouldn’t be missing on any ice climbers rack.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-express-ice-screw-eisschraube/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-express-ice-screw.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15pvcgK">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115SnGQ">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJ4OcT">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8587935487/" title="Secured by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8241/8587935487_cc1e3ed8d0_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Secured" /></a></p>

<h2 id="slings">Slings</h2>
<p>Slings are an important piece of gear when climbing ice whenever you don’t toprope. A 120 cm sling is essential to build a belay station together with two ice screws, and a daisychain or another 120 cm sling are needed to secure yourself at a belay station. They also can be very useful when setting screws and taking care that the rope isn’t making a wide curve (Imagine it a bit like this sign <strong>&lt;</strong> where the three points are ice screws and the line is the rope. With a sling and two ‘biners in the middle point you can make the rope run in a more straight line). Also when rappeling down slings come in handy, and they of course also can be used in rock climbing. A piece of gear that definitely needs to come along.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schlingen-reepschnur/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/schlinge-reepschnur.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15ptb3X">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/Zv14fB">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115RtdF">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662799740/" title="Slings &amp; Daisychain by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8245/8662799740_908fe80d94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Slings &amp; Daisychain" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quick-draws">Quick draws</h2>
<p>When you’re leading a climb you’ll need quick draws (Read Tomás superb article on <a href="http://www.scandinavian-hiking.com/2011/08/relatively-ultralight-quickdraws-petzl.html">Ultralight Quick Draws</a>). As so often, lighter quick draws means you either can take more or then safe a substantial amount of weight for the same performance. Some clip in easier and are better handled with gloves, so keep that in mind when building your rack.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/express-sets/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/express-sets.html?priceMin=&amp;priceMax=&amp;query=&amp;sort=&amp;_artperpage=">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/15puIat">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176mNNe">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176mZw0">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662796740/" title="Quick draws by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8259/8662796740_9938e7249a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Quick draws" /></a></p>

<h2 id="carabiners">Carabiners</h2>
<p>I thought I’d be set with my two <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-phantom-schraubkarabiner/">DMM Phantom</a> locking ‘biners, though I was wrong. And so I bought a few more locking carabiners, in slightly bigger sizes, because they’re easier to operate with gloves on. If you’re not toproping then a about five locking carabiners are good to have along: Three to set up a belay, one to clip yourself in with a sling, and one if you’re belaying someone else. A spare or two in these situations can’t hurt, either.</p>

<p>As for non-locking carabiners, I have been using the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/dmm-phantom-schnappkarabiner/">DMM Phantom gate ‘biner</a> and still think they’re superb. The gate opens easy, they’re light yet strong - a great biner to have along to rack gear.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/schraubkarabiner/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/karabiner.html?Limit%5B%5D=Schraubkarabiner&amp;Limit%5B%5D=HMS-Karabiner&amp;priceMin=&amp;priceMax=&amp;query=&amp;sort=&amp;_artperpage=&amp;f=1">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/ZAAOxi">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJ9vn8">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/115W5QI">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662797582/" title="Carabiners by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8251/8662797582_9b811ef47f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Carabiners" /></a></p>

<h2 id="camp-speed-helmet">CAMP Speed helmet</h2>
<p>I used the CAMP Speed helmet during all climbing, and really like the comfort of this helmet - light and protective, easy to adjust the size when I wear a beanie or not, not to hot nor too cold. I can wear shades or my googles underneath them, a Headlamp like the Petzl Nao fits easily on it, and it also fits under all my jacket’s hoods. However, with the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-vapor-hybridhelm/">Black Diamond Vapor</a> and Petzl Siricco helmets available, the Speed is no longer the lightest option, something too keep in mind when you’re buying a helmet (I used the Petzl Siricco and really like it, especially the magnetic closure that’s easy to operate with one hand is very good).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/camp-speed-kletterhelm/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/camp-brg-5.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176wpYi">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661816397/" title="CAMP Speed Helmet by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8258/8661816397_2b4e3ce0b3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="CAMP Speed Helmet" /></a></p>

<h2 id="poc-iris-3p-googles">POC Iris 3P Googles</h2>

<p>Because my helmet doesn’t have a visor to keep ice and water from flying in my face, I was wearing the comfortable <a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">POC Iris 3P Googles</a>. They have a superb view and while they on occasion were fogging up, the fog cleared up quickly. I can wear them with my Speed Helmet without problems, but had problems to get a comfortable fit with the new Petzl Helmet. The googles’ lens are antiscratch and have a oleophobic &amp; hydrophobic treatment which means it keeps fat and water off your lens very easily - a very welcome function when climbing ice where you sweat and ice is coming at you. A great pair of googles that I can recommend if you climb ice or ski.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.jk-shop.fi/?cat=19">JK-Shop</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/176xmjq">Backcountry</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662911976/" title="POC Iris 3P Googles by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8266/8662911976_1d5db327e1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="POC Iris 3P Googles" /></a></p>

<h2 id="petzl-reverso-4">Petzl Reverso 4</h2>
<p>I usually use a Petzl Verso, though enlightenment struck as I tried the Reverso 4. It’s only a tad heavier than the Verso but offers so much more functions: You can secure two climbers that are climbing after you, and connect it to your belay with the ring. As with the Verso, you can belay and rappel. When not toproping then definitely a piece of gear to take along.</p>

<p>There’s plenty of belaying devices around, though one to consider is the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/s/Mammut--Smart----Alpine/kategorie--klettern/">Mammut Smart Alpine</a> which offers similar functionality as the Reverso though has the added benefit of breaking the rope dynamically in the case of a fall.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/petzl-reverso-4-sicherungsgeraet/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-reverso-4-belay-device.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/ZABoLu">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/11m0gIL">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13qZm2O">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8577735844/" title="Petzl Reverso 4 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8234/8577735844_86d4c770cb_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Petzl Reverso 4" /></a></p>

<h2 id="tendon-master-97-rope">Tendon Master 9.7 rope</h2>
<p>A superb rope for toproping, also on ice. It’s my rock-climbing rope which I diverted from its intended use to toproping on ice. Super smooth handling, light, great knot-ability, and with a middle marking, this is a great piece of kit which does the job very well.</p>

<p>For lead climbing on ice a twin or half rope is needed, though, and also there the market offers plenty of great ropes for us ice climbers. I used a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/beal-ice-twin-golden-dry-77-mm-zwillingsseil/">BEAL rope</a> which were very great to handle and didn’t soak out, and if you’re serious about ice climbing then you won’t get around getting a twin or half rope (<a href="http://www.highinfatuation.com/blog/straight-from-the-mammoths-mouth-half-ropes-are-not-twins/">Here’s an explanation on the difference</a>!).</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/tendon-master-97-mm-einfachseil/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/tendon-master-9-4-complete-shield-kletterseil.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r7uA8">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r6YCt">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/17sOoX6">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8486287141/" title="Tendon Rope by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8372/8486287141_7f341247e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Tendon Rope" /></a></p>

<h2 id="arcteryx-r320-harness">Arc’teryx R320 harness</h2>
<p>The Arc’teryx R320 has been my harness of choice and I like the racking capacity it has - plenty of gear fits on the four gear loops. For ice climbing a <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/petzl-caritool.html">Petzl Caritool</a> or <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/black-diamond-ice-clipper.html">Black Diamond Ice Clipper</a> would have been useful, though I made work without this season. It’s comfortable, the leg loops are big enough to step through in case you put on your crampons before your harness (happens!) and with it’s good design it feels well over pants and jacket. If one is serious about ice climbing, the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-i340a-klettergurt/">Arc’teryx I340A</a> of course would be a nice harness to have, though for the time being the R320 is very good for my needs and can be used all year around.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/arcteryx-r-320-hueftgurt/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/arcteryx-r-320a-klettergurt.html">Bergzeit</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/XJanYJ">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/Z1PB8H">CampSaver</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/11m0I9Q">REI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="black-diamond-ice-box">Black Diamond Ice Box</h2>
<p>A backpack is the best way to get your gear from home to the ice fall. But what when between the ice fall and home there’s a airplane? Backpacks with the sharp tools outside aren’t great for travelling - enter the <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633281180152/">Black Diamond Ice Box</a>. It fits four tools, one pair of crampons, up to ten ice screws, a mesh compartment for drying gear and still has plenty of space left for small stuff. For me very important too, is that its perfect to store the ice climbing gear safely and using minimal space at home, out of the reach of an exploring toddler. A great piece of kit for ice climbers that travel a lot and want to store their gear safely when not in use.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/black-diamond-ice-box/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/17sM0zG">Backcountry</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://bit.ly/13r3DTL">CampSaver</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8662893104/" title="Black Diamond Ice Box by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8248/8662893104_f8e2087b75_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Black Diamond Ice Box" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8661794319/" title="Black Diamond Ice Box by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8260/8661794319_4c98c70443_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Black Diamond Ice Box" /></a></p>

<p><em>Most of the ice-climbing related gear has been used for a week of ice climbing this season. These short reviews thus should be considered as an initial review, which will be updated during the next winter season when I have used the gear more. If you have questions, please use the comments to ask!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8576458309/" title="Abisko Canyon by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8392/8576458309_581552ba62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Abisko Canyon" /></a></p>

<p><em>Disclaiming the Disclaimer</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
