<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: reima | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/reima/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-12-08T22:29:50+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ReimaGo &amp; Kidventure]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/09/reimago-and-kidventure.html"/>
    <updated>2017-09-28T18:42:18+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/09/reimago-and-kidventure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After over six months with the ReimaGo Activity Sensor it’s time to take a look at it again and join the #MillionHoursOfJoy campaign!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36972722866/in/dateposted/" title="Picking Berries"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4370/36972722866_1508739d3c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Picking Berries" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Disclaimer: The ReimaGo Sensor and some of the garments have been provided by Reima for review. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>Remember my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/05/reimago.html">ReimaGo Review</a> from the spring? Well, we feel it’s time for an update on how the <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/ReimaGO/ReimaGO%C2%AE-sensori/p/599160-9990">sensor</a> and the <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/fi/app/reimago/id1083484265?mt=8">app</a> have performed and developed over the last six months.</p>

<h2 id="the-reimago-app">The ReimaGo App</h2>

<p>Back in our spring review the <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=hikingfinland&amp;utm_campaign=aw17">ReimaGo App</a> had 15 levels and we were almost through them in a matter of weeks (which means our son was very active and collected lots of points to move his avatar forward through the ReimaGo World). We already knew by then that our son was plenty enough outside (he only uses the Sensor in his outside jacket), but what we learned then too was that when it gets too warm for the jacket he doesn’t collect any points (even if he’s outside) - we were for example in the end of May for two weeks in Germany, and with it being the hottest May on record in Germany ever (we had every day over 30°C degrees, with five days even having over 35°C!) he never wore the jacket and wasn’t “active” those two weeks, even if we were every day outside. Sure, there’s a rubber hand strap that comes with the sensor, but we didn’t have it with us and even now we seldom use it. We really hope that for next year Reima releases some summer garments which have the ReimaGo pocket which can be worn in warm weather.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37368694161/in/dateposted/" title="The new World"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4499/37368694161_ccd35e92b3_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="The new World" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37321501926/in/dateposted/" title="An normal week"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4495/37321501926_434c68102c_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="An normal week" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37368694311/in/dateposted/" title="Active day &#x3D;)"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4473/37368694311_924f1d3b76_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Active day &#x3D;)" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Anyway, the ReimaGo App. It had a major update since the spring and now there’s over 40 Levels on the new globe map, which lets you travel around the world. This is positive as it makes the game of being outside more long-lasting - lets see if Reima will add more levels once the first kids start to reach the last levels. There’s now also a little story about the avatar (Goey) and how he animates kids to go outside, it’s a nice touch. Our son still loves to move his avatar forward and is happy each time he gets to finish a Level, and for us parents its still very good to see how much he is outside each day and week. The app also still is a good motivator to get him out if it isn’t a great day outside, which is pretty nice. A <em>“Lets go collect some ReimaGo points so you can finish that level”</em> works very well to motivate him to get dressed and go for a walk or play in the garden. The usability of the app still is the same, it’s OK but not mind-blowing - simple and does its job well. Finally, the app also lets you join the #MillionHoursOfJoy campaign easily, which I’ll talk about next.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37321501826/in/dateposted/" title="So lets look for the berries"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4497/37321501826_8822d5a798_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="So lets look for the berries" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="kidventure-aka-millionhoursofjoy">Kidventure aka #MillionHoursOfJoy</h2>

<p>I was along at the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-2017/">OutDoor Friedrichshafen</a> during the launch of the <a href="https://www.reima.com/int/kidventure?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=hikingfinland&amp;utm_campaign=kidventure">Kidventure campaign</a>. The idea is to challenge kids around the globe to spend more time outdoors, and hence to collect together a million hours of time spend in the outdoors. You can participate via the above linked Website if you have not yet a ReimaGo Sensor, or if you have the latter then it’s super easy to join the challenge by signing up via the app and then automatically all your hours of outdoor time will be donated to the project (as far as I can tell, you don’t lose anything either =). You also can use the #MillionHoursOfJoy Hashtag on Social Media when you’re out there with your kids - because remember <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/get-out-into-nature-because-itsgreatoutthere.html">#ItsGreatOutThere</a> =) If you compete in the campaign you also have the chance to win prizes each week, and the grand prize is a winter week in Lapland - a very nice experience for kids, as <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">we</a> <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html">know</a>! We think this is a great initiative - getting kids outdoors is always positive as it allows them to become better people; instead of sitting inside in front of a computer or TV kids should be outside and building huts, exploring the forests and be in nature. Thus, if you feel so too - join the campaign and go outside with your kids!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36698759573/in/dateposted/" title="#MillionHoursOfJoy Website"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4409/36698759573_3d96a44194_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="#MillionHoursOfJoy Website" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36698763053/in/dateposted/" title="ReimaGo App Welcome screen"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4339/36698763053_5f58aabfc9_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="ReimaGo App Welcome screen" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36698762003/in/dateposted/" title="Easy to join the #MillionHoursOfJoy campaign in the ReimaGo App"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4443/36698762003_0bff6ef723_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Easy to join the #MillionHoursOfJoy campaign in the ReimaGo App" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, it’s my pleasure to offer you a <strong>-15% Discount on ALL Reima garments</strong> until the 15th of October - that makes it even more affordable to get a ReimaGo Sensor and a jacket, fleece or pants to measure the activity of your kids or get those <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/09/reima-valikausivaatteet.html">Välikausivaatteet</a> or <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/02/reima-stavanger-overall.html">winter garments</a>! The Code is <strong>HIK17ING</strong> and applies to all products in the <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=hikingfinland&amp;utm_campaign=aw17">Reima Webshop</a> but can not be combined with other discounts. Direct your browser to the <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=hikingfinland&amp;utm_campaign=aw17">Reima webshop</a> and add the code at the end in the coupon field!</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Wj7qbfrdQEE?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36659982984/in/dateposted/" title="Bilberries!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4496/36659982984_0e745495df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Bilberries!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dressed for Autumn & Spring with Reima]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/09/reima-valikausivaatteet.html"/>
    <updated>2017-09-11T20:19:16+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/09/reima-valikausivaatteet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“We’re not gonna dress her up in pink clothes”</em> was what my wife and me agreed on when our daughter was born about two years ago. And for one and half years we re-used her big brothers clothes through all seasons. But then came spring and it became clear that we won’t be able to hold on to that idea - because our daughter loves pink <em>and</em> she didn’t fit the clothes we had. And so a pair of pink shoes, a pink beanie and a pink overall arrived from Reima, and we haven’t looked back since.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36348286213/in/dateposted/" title="Walking in the forest"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4409/36348286213_296220704d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Walking in the forest" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>Disclaimer: The Reima shoes, overall and beanie have been provided by Reima for review without requirements. And as you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><em>Välikausivaatteet</em> is Finnish for <em>In-between seasons garments</em> and refers to garments for the very brief but vibrant spring (those two weeks where everything bursts out green plus those many weeks or months of grey &amp; brown) and the colourful autumn. To be honest, though - the summer in Finland was for the third year in a row so wet, grey and just not summer-y that you could wear these <em>Välikausivaatteet</em> from May till when winter comes (thanks to climate change that likely is again January or February). Anyway, what makes these garments - and lets focus for a moment especially on the <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi//Reimatec%C2%AE--v%C3%A4likausihaalari-Nauru/p/510255C-4621-080">Reimatec Nauru Overall</a> - special is that they are less warm than winter clothes but still keep especially wind and rain at bay. The Nauru Overall is very waterproof and fairly breathable, the diagonal zipper makes it easy to put on and the hood can be removed when not needed. We picked it because it is pink, but not straight-out-Barbie Pink but a nice block print with different shades of pink - something that parents that are slightly opposed to this colour still can accept. Our daughter didn’t share this colour aversion and as the Nauru Overall arrived it was the best thing ever, something that she’d pull off the wardrobe and put on as soon as just the word “outside” was spoken! She really loves this overall, and it has been very good on all her little adventures so far - be it playing on the playground, strolling through the forest and picking bilberries or sitting in the Thule Chariot when we ride around town. The suit is also spacious enough that she can wear a fleece or wool overall underneath it when it gets a bit colder, and it has a great freedom of movement that allows her to climb, slide and run. She’s been now wearing it since five months and in that time it has been several times in the laundry, but it still looks great and with some luck she still will fit it when the next in-between-season arrived in 2018.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36972722866/in/dateposted/" title="Picking Berries"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4370/36972722866_1508739d3c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Picking Berries" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36991060382/in/dateposted/" title="Reimatec Välikausihaalari Nauru"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4333/36991060382_92a16bde7d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Reimatec Välikausihaalari Nauru" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As we needed some new shoes for her too, we decided to go pink all the way and ordered the <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/Taaperot/Keng%C3%A4t/Tennarit-ja-lenkkarit/Lasten-lenkkarit-Knappe/p/569300-4620-021">Knappe Shoes</a>. These have Velcro closures which she can open herself, and while she can not yet put the shoes on she can take them off when we come home. They have good grip on wet forest trails with roots and rocks, and also are fine to climb on boulders and at the playground. As it has been quite a bit rainy over here the shoes have kept her little feet dry and warm.</p>

<p>And to complete the pink outfit we got the the <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi//Lasten-pipo-Linna/p/518397-3728-050">Linna Beanie</a> (currently 50% off!). It’s made of Polyester, Elastane and Cotton in two layers, which means it’s too hot even for a Finnish Summer, but as I highlighted already in the beginning: There was not much of a warm summer here either way! It’s a cute little beanie that she likes to wear (beanies she doesn’t like to wear she takes off!) and it keeps her head warm and her hence in a good mood =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36972723266/in/dateposted/" title="Reima Kids Shoes Knappe"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4408/36972723266_785422e381_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Reima Kids Shoes Knappe" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36990782262/in/dateposted/" title="Crawling"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4439/36990782262_81b1f3b7f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Crawling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong> is that we have crossed into the segment of parents who dress their kids up in pink. It’s a rather large segment here in Finland (99% big) and as it makes her happy while keeping her warm &amp; dry we parents will slowly but surely get used to the colour pink - and it isn’t as difficult if the garments are as stylish as these ones! And on the plus side: She’s easy to spot when she disappears in the forest to search for berries =)</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article why not <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36764605390/in/dateposted/" title="Looking for berries"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4404/36764605390_3da673c97c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Looking for berries" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How active is my child? Testing the ReimaGo Activity Sensor]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/05/reimago.html"/>
    <updated>2017-05-18T19:39:19+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/05/reimago</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you wonder if your child is active enough? We tested the ReimaGo Activity Sensor to find an answer to that question!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34600213861/in/photostream/" title="Sensor, App and ReimaGo Softshell Jacket"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4181/34600213861_19496766d1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sensor, App and ReimaGo Softshell Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Like most parents we think our two kids are active and enough outside, but a real way of measuring this assumption we did not have - until around three weeks ago. Then the ReimaGo Sensor and some compatible garments arrived at the Hiking in Finland HQ - and then there was just one thing to do: Install the <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/fi/app/reimago/id1083484265?mt=8">ReimaGo App</a>, plug the <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/ReimaGO/ReimaGO%C2%AE-sensori/p/599160-9990">ReimaGo Sensor</a> in the <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/Koululaisten-lastenvaatteet/Ulkovaatteet/Ulkotakit/ReimaGO%C2%AE-softshell-takki-Hatch/p/531263-8800">ReimaGo softshell jacket</a> and… live life normally. We don’t own a car and go everywhere by bike or on foot, and so do our kids - so for us we wanted to see if during our normal, regular days our kids get enough outdoor exercise time or if we need to add more outdoor time to our schedule.</p>

<h2 id="the-reimago-sensor">The ReimaGo Sensor</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/ReimaGO/ReimaGO%C2%AE-sensori/p/599160-9990">ReimaGo Sensor</a> has been developed together with Suunto, another Finnish company which you might know from their high-quality wrist watches. The sensor makes use of Suunto’s Movesense technology. It’s a durable little button design that is waterproof to 30 m and attaches to compatible garments - either drop it into a small pocket or attach it to the designated place (see the underneath photo). The ideas is to use the sensor only outdoors - at least thus far the garments that the sensor connects with are all outdoor garments. This isn’t good news for kids who train e.g. indoor sports, but then nothing really stops you to put the ReimaGo Sensor just into a pocket when your child trains indoors. Maybe this is the next line of ReimaGo garments the company will launch - and with the OutDoor just a short four weeks away we probably know more soon!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34346883890/in/dateposted/" title="ReimaGo Sensor in the ReimaGo Softshell Jacket"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4172/34346883890_19c1e78167_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ReimaGo Sensor in the ReimaGo Softshell Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-reimago-app">The ReimaGo App</h2>

<p>The ReimaGo App turns the tracked data into a <em>“game”</em> that sets challenges and rewards children for their efforts. The game is less PokemonGo and more just that the child is collecting through its outdoor activities <em>energy</em> which lets it move its avatar through the various levels. All there is to the game is the pushing of a button to use the collected energy to move forward, and if you finish a level there’s a short animation and you get a digital Award for the finished level. After not even three weeks our son is already in Level 7 and there’s only 15 Levels, so I reckon that some time in June we will be done - unless there’s an update which adds more levels.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34346885600/in/dateposted/" title="ReimaGo Level 4"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4170/34346885600_2110a4d699_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="ReimaGo Level 4" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34600218181/in/photostream/" title="Animation after finishing Level 4"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4179/34600218181_84fe1c7a8d_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Animation after finishing Level 4" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34600217981/in/photostream/" title="Award after finishing Level 4"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4177/34600217981_f76b559065_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Award after finishing Level 4" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Besides the <em>Kids side</em> of the ReimaGo App there’s also a parents side. Here you can add rewards for time spent outdoors - like an ice cream after five hours outdoors, or you can take a photo of a reward you create yourself (<a href="http://amzn.to/2qvLo06">LEGO Ninjago</a> is very popular here right now and thus makes for a great incentive to play outdoors!). This we find a good way to keep the child interested in the app - though truth be told, our son still loves to check each evening his energy of the day and his eyes go big when he sees how much time he has spent outdoors!</p>

<p>At the beginning you set a daily target of outdoor time, and we started out with the recommended 1 hour per day (= 7 hours a week). In his first week our son was triple that outdoors, so now we have raised the time to 90 minutes daily. The length of the Levels corresponds to the daily amount set; to keep these times realistic makes for a better experience for the kids, so don’t go offer the top! We also added our first reward - going to eat an ice cream - so are looking forward to see his surprise when he gets this reward!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34732173965/in/dateposted/" title="ReimaGo App - Parents Side"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4187/34732173965_1057f67a0d_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="ReimaGo App - Parents Side" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34732174025/in/photostream/" title="ReimaGo App - Parents Side"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4188/34732174025_d2122dc4ae_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="ReimaGo App - Parents Side" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34692151846/in/photostream/" title="ReimaGo App - Parents Side"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4175/34692151846_4b23d6fc4d_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="ReimaGo App - Parents Side" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-experience">The Experience</h2>

<p>We really like the whole ReimaGo experience. The ReimaGo garments - we got a pants and a jacket - are as high-quality as we are used to from Reima, and our son also likes to wear them. Easy to use, easy to clean, good fit and great freedom of movement - in short, a great jacket and pants.</p>

<p>The Sensor and App are easy to set up and use - from adding the child’s account to the app over playing the game to adding rewards - and are well made with a pleasing design for kids and adults alike. The levels are different enough to keep it exciting, and the best thing obviously is that it really makes our son want to go play outdoors so that he can collect energy. Every evening after dinner we get the sensor, open tha ReimaGo app and then see how active he was today. He then uses his collected energy to move through the level and is might proud when he has finished it - looking forward to the next day!</p>

<p>Finally, what we also like is that with the App you can add multiple kids - each with their own sensor - to it and so can keep an eye on the whole tribe’s activity. And if you yourself don’t have a fitness tracker yet, obviously nothing could stop you to get a ReimaGo Sensor for yourself to see how active you are =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34346886040/in/dateposted/" title="Active day!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4183/34346886040_e9615a2fd6_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Active day!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34346886190/in/photostream/" title="And an active week!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4192/34346886190_a4386f8a1b_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="And an active week!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34600217781/in/photostream/" title="Finished another ReimaGo Level!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4177/34600217781_1bc808afc2_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Finished another ReimaGo Level!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bottomline">The Bottomline</h2>

<p>We were sceptical if we needed an activity monitor for our son - we felt he’s plenty outside, plus attaching a sensor to our child already felt a wee bit like trying to control him. But as the Sensor really only tracks his movement and time spent outside this concern was unfounded. The ReimaGo sensor is also more child-friendly than many other fitness trackers for kids on the market as it is easy to use, affordable and durable. That the sensor is hidden in the jacket or pants also makes it less intrusive than a wristband, and the gamification of the outdoor activity makes the whole go-out-and-play idea very appealing for the small kids, in comparison to a chart of numbers which normal fitness trackers give you. It has allowed us to see how active our child is (on average 2+ hours a day, so well above what the World Health Organization recommends) and encourage him to play outdoors - even if the weather isn’t sunshine and blue sky.</p>

<p>Overall we can recommend the ReimaGo sensor if you’d like to encourage your child to go play outside or would like to find out how much time she spends outdoors. The Rewards which you can add for your child in the App - from an ice cream, a camping trip or another present - help motivate kids to go play outside and keep them interested in the App. Ultimately I feel this helps us to motivate our kids for longer hikes, bike rides and backpacking trips, and spend more quality-family-outdoor-time together =)</p>

<h2 id="where-to-get-reimago">Where to get ReimaGo</h2>

<p>You can buy the <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/ReimaGO/ReimaGO%C2%AE-sensori/p/599160-9990">ReimaGo Sensor</a> and compatible garments like the <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/Koululaisten-lastenvaatteet/Ulkovaatteet/Ulkotakit/ReimaGO%C2%AE-softshell-takki-Hatch/p/531263-8800">ReimaGo softshell jacket Hatch</a> and the <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/Lapset/Lasten-ulkovaatteet/Ulkohousut/ReimaGO%C2%AE-v%C3%A4likausihousut-Kiddo-Singine/p/522225-9990">ReimaGo Singine pants</a> directly from the Reima online shop. Make sure to <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/c/reimago">browse all the ReimaGo garments</a> and make use of their <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/look/l21">Sensor + Jacket</a> or <a href="https://track.adtraction.com/t/t?a=1173541864&amp;as=1179503632&amp;t=2&amp;tk=1&amp;url=https://www.reima.com/fi/look/l23">Sensor + Fleece</a> offers which let you get the sensor for just 10€.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34600214521/in/dateposted/" title="ReimaGo Sensor, ReimaGo App and ReimaGo Softshell Jacket"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4172/34600214521_115220bc3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ReimaGo Sensor, ReimaGo App and ReimaGo Softshell Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The ReimaGo Sensor, Jacket and Pants have been provided by Reima for review. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reima Stavanger Overall]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/02/reima-stavanger-overall.html"/>
    <updated>2017-02-27T16:21:07+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/02/reima-stavanger-overall</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>The Green Super Suit</strong> we call it, because after <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/marmot-space-walk-jacket-and-edge-insulated-pants-review.html">testing several</a> <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/winter-fun-with-the-reima-mamid-jacket-and-procyon-pants.html">Jackets and Pants combos</a> we have found back to overalls this winter. And as it just dumped some 30 cm of snow and the winter holidays start here in Pohjanmaa it is time to shed some light on the Reimatec Stavanger Overall and why we love it!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33103187776/in/photostream/" title="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/622/33103187776_efcc9a0c04_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Last December the <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Lastenvaatteet/Lasten-ulkovaatteet/Lasten-haalarit-ja-setit/Lasten-Reimatec®%2B-toppahaalari-Stavanger/p/520190F-8430">Reimatec Stavanger Overall</a> arrived at the Hiking in Finland HQ and was immediately declared awesome by our son and very relieved parents (because they in a moment no longer needed to help dressing him up =). To understand this one needs to know that our son always needed a little assistance when he needed to put on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/winter-fun-with-the-reima-mamid-jacket-and-procyon-pants.html">Jacket and Pants</a> when it was time to go out. While he could put them on himself he prefrred to that mom or dad help him get dressed for the cold. As we have a one year old who can’t yet dress herself up this meant we were at once dressing up two kids, plus ourselves, before we could go out. This can get tedious to say the least, so when we saw that he was happy to put on the overall (in less than a minute, including <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Lastenvaatteet/Asusteet/Pipot-ja-hatut/c/k61">hat</a>, <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/brands/buff/for--kids/?pid=10239">Buff</a> and the <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Lastenvaatteet/Asusteet/Hanskat-ja-rukkaset/Talvirukkaset-ja--hanskat/c/k63">Reimatec Suunta mitts</a>) we were very happy parents indeed!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32988261492/in/dateposted/" title="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/4/3853/32988261492_093feeba9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32988256352/in/dateposted/" title="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/594/32988256352_8b3256ba30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32988255082/in/dateposted/" title="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/676/32988255082_c601125295_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So, now the kid has dressed himself up to go out into the cold, but how does the overall stand up to the use &amp; abuse a 5 year old can throw at it? Very well, we’d say. We were ice skating, building igloos, climbing on rocks, had running competitions and played hide &amp; seek, in temperatures from 0°C to -20°C. The waterproof &amp; breathable outer shell material has taken all these activities in stride and hasn’t failed us yet, keeping wind, snow and wetness at bay. It’s pretty durable, too - climbing on rocks with the knees and then sliding them back down hasn’t done any damage to the material.</p>

<p>It’s easy to clean, too - just throw it into the washing machine (add a suitable <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/toko-eco-softshell-wash-250-ml-detergent/?pid=10239">detergent</a>) at 40°C and an hour later you can hang it up to dry. Because of the insulation it needs around 12 to 16 hours to thoroughly dry, so keep that in mind.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32329153543/in/dateposted/" title="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/3/2937/32329153543_c4ea0971cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Warmth-wise the overall is toasty and is sufficient on its own up to temperatures of -5°C with our son. When it gets colder than -5°C we add a <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Koululaisten-lastenvaatteet/Lasten-lämpökerrastot/Yläosat/Lasten-fleecetakki-Frans/p/536097-3710">fleece jacket</a> and <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Lastenvaatteet/Lasten-sisävaatteet/Alaosat/Lasten-fleecehousut-Argelius/p/526243-6980">fleece pants</a> underneath the overall, and that’s no problem as there’s room to spare without restricting movement. Speaking of movement, snow angles, climbing on rocks and at the play ground, skiing and ice skating all were easy to do as the overall does not restrict the freedom of movement.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32761950190/in/dateposted/" title="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/601/32761950190_525fece769_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Also otherwise we really like the Stavanger Overall: The inside suspenders are great when dressing up and in breaks as our son can undress the overall but with the suspenders still over his shoulders he’s able to walk around without that the top is hanging on the floor. The width of the overall can be adjusted via two inside elastics, making it as wide or narrow as you need it. There’s only two pockets on it which is just the right amount, and the insulated hood with a fur collar can be removed (the fake fur, too). The leg cuffs can also be adjusted in width, while the elastic cuffs keep wind and snow from getting into the sleeves. The reflective details are easy to overlook, but there’s plenty of them, from top to bottom, which makes the wearer very visible on these dark winter nights and morning.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32761950830/in/dateposted/" title="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/746/32761950830_918aa8078a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Some words on the <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Koululaisten-lastenvaatteet/Asusteet/Hanskat-ja-rukkaset/Lasten-Reimatec®%2B--topparukkaset-Suunta/p/527252-9990">Reimatec Suunta mitts</a>, too. We got these at the same time than the overall but they haven’t been used as much - simply because it was way too warm for them most of this <em>“winter”</em>. Now that the thermometer has shown beautiful double digit minus degrees it was time to put them on, and for playing in the snow and walking to the kindergarden or to town these were great to keep the little hands warm. These mitts have a very warm fleece lining and a snug cuff which goes high, and they’re best from temperatures over -10°C in our experience. Anything above that and our son would run very hot &amp; sweaty in them. Because they’re so long it’s best to put the gloves on before the overall, this is simpler. There’s some help needed to get the hands in the gloves through the elastic cuffs of the overall, but compared with dressing a kid up completely it’s a minor thing!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32761952150/in/dateposted/" title="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/4/3929/32761952150_1a2e9a9ff8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong> is that with the <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Lastenvaatteet/Lasten-ulkovaatteet/Lasten-haalarit-ja-setit/Lasten-Reimatec®%2B-toppahaalari-Stavanger/p/520190F-8430">Reimatec Stavanger Overall</a> we have a happy son that can dress up alone at home &amp; in the kindergarden, allows him to play outside in the cold winter weather, be visible in the mornings and evenings when it gets dark, and it is easy to undress when going inside for a hot chocolate! A happy son of course means also happy parents, so the Stavanger gets from us six thumbs up! It’s a very durable and well-designed kids overall and we just hope our daughter will be fine with the green colour once she is big enough to wear it in some three years =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32761956230/in/dateposted/" title="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/615/32761956230_fac67bc725_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reimatec®+ Stavanger Overall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The overall and gloves have been provided by Reima for review. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Fun with the Reima Mamid Jacket and Procyon Pants]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/11/winter-fun-with-the-reima-mamid-jacket-and-procyon-pants.html"/>
    <updated>2016-11-07T19:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/11/winter-fun-with-the-reima-mamid-jacket-and-procyon-pants</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Winter is coming!</em> And that means for us Families here in the North: Dressing the Kids up warmly and heading out into the snow!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30201863754/in/dateposted/" title="Up the Sled Hill"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5734/30201863754_12a9f5a583_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Up the Sled Hill" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The Reima Mamid Jacket and Procyon Pants have been our choice of winter garments for our son, and this down-filled jacket and the warm and water-repellant pants have been great in keeping our little boy warm when the temperatures drop low. And low were the temperatures, not just here in Vaasa but also up North in Lapland on our <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">Family winter holiday in Pyhä</a> - which is a great place to take your kids for a relaxed &amp; adventurous winter holiday!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075087012/in/album-72157651506091295/" title="That one next, dad!"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7599/17075087012_e945efd6da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="That one next, dad!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Mamid jacket has everything you’d expect of your own jacket: Taped seams, windproof, water-proof and a toasty warm insulation of Reima 60 Down (that means there’s a mix of 60% Down to 40% feathers, which I found a good combination as when our son is a lot less careful when he is out playing, and the high feather percentage means the down can do its job and does not get compressed to easily). The hood with the fake fur is great when standing on a cold fjell top or at night when watching the stars and Northern Lights. It can be removed when not needed, which is useful for those chilly but sunny autumn and spring days. The waist can be adjusted by a drawstring on the inside so it is close to the body, and the sleeves have Velcro cuffs so no cold breeze or snow come in.</p>

<p>I don’t know what is the obsession with pockets on Kids garments, maybe the manufacturers just adapt adult designs and make them smaller? At least I feel that most <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/kids-gear/">Kids garments</a> have too many pockets. The Mamid for example would have been fine with just the two large flap pockets, eliminating the zippered pockets on the chest and inside. These just don’t get used by kids of the age 3 to 5 and add unnecessary material and costs to the garment. On the other hand, great are the reflective details on the jacket - though there could be possibly be some more, especially on the right sleeve there could also be a patch like on the left one. As for the freedom of movement, the Mamid was great for all our activities, from sledding to walking and climbing on rocks. The material is durable and abrasion-resistant and still looked like new after a season in the snow.</p>

<p>In short, if he’d not out-grown it so quickly he’d still be wearing it - also because he really liked his red winter jacket! Good thing his little sister will be able to wear it in a year or two and then I can go sledding with her =) The <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Koululaisten-lastenvaatteet/Ulkovaatteet/Ulkotakit/Talvitakit/Lasten-Reimatec®%2B--talvitakki-Serkku/p/531235-3830">Reimatec Serkku Winter Jacket</a> is the successor to the Mamid Jacket so if you’re still looking for a warm, durable and stylish jacket for your little one - we can recommend this one completely!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889011560/in/album-72157651506091295/" title="Pyhä Sled Hill"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7713/16889011560_3351fc57fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Pyhä Sled Hill" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That brings us to the pants which we got together with the jacket, the <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/Syysuutuudet/Lasten-toppahousut-Procyon/p/522207N-6980">Procyon pants</a>. These are also well-constructed, robust and still look very good after a winter season of abuse. While the suspenders are a bit tricky when our son was supposed to dress up himself, they ensured the pants stayed where they belong when we were outside, and the small bib added also a wee bit of warmth. There could have been some more reflective details on them (there are, but not enough in my opinion) as especially now in November it is so dark and more visibility is always good.</p>

<p>The pants have great freedom of movement, climbing and running in them was no problem, and the taped seams made them highly water-repellant and windproof. The stretchy inside trouser cuffs ensured no snow came into his boots and socks and are adjustable in width - together with the Velcro adjusters on the outside trouser legs these mean no snow or dirt has a chance. The two side pockets were again never used and could be eliminated, but otherwise these were great, warm pants when playing in the snow.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30201863854/in/dateposted/" title="Stay here!"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5346/30201863854_580e6c896f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Stay here!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Overall we were very happy with the two winter garments from Reima (and the many other ones we have bought!) and it is great to support &amp; work together with a Finnish Company which makes so good clothes for kids. Winter is arriving all over Europe, so now is a good time to get those warm, durable and stylish kids garments so the little ones can continue to play outside. <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/reima/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> have a wide selection of Reima garments, and you also can buy everything directly at the <a href="https://www.reima.com/">Reima Online Shop</a> or visit a <a href="https://www.reima.com/fi/myymalat">local Reima Retailer</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050611986/in/album-72157651506091295/" title="Danger!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8813/17050611986_396e0e5472_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Danger!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The Jacket &amp; Pants were sent for free to us and Reima asked me to have fun with it. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this . Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
