<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: osprey | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/osprey/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2019-03-29T13:14:26+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Osprey Exos 48 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/11/osprey-exos-48-review.html"/>
    <updated>2018-11-21T21:21:08+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/11/osprey-exos-48-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Autumn is my favourite backpacking time and in October I was fortunate enough to go backpacking in the Pyrenees. Along for this one week long trip through three countries was the Osprey Exos 48, a lightweight pack which carries extremely well.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45985410761/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos 48"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4803/45985410761_3405ef709d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Exos 48" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from Osprey. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>The Osprey Exos 48 is a lightweight backpack which carries loads up to 15 kg very comfortable. I found the 48 l of Volume enough for a week long backpacking trip with all my camera gear and Drone and think it would be an ideal backpack for people who look for a lighter backpack which doesn’t brake the bank. For all the details <a href="https://youtu.be/bd5ugrAAerE">watch the video</a> and read the review.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bd5ugrAAerE" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received my <a href="https://www.ospreyeurope.com/shop/eu_en/exos-48-2018">Osprey Exos</a> 48 in January 2018 and have used it on a several day trips and a week long backpacking trip in the Pyrenees of Andorra, Spain and France. Overall it has been used for close to two weeks.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45985397191/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos 48"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4848/45985397191_103f51bd2a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Exos 48" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The function of a backpack is to carry your gear in comfort from A to B. The idea behind a lightweight backpack is that it isn’t weighing 2+ kg empty, but significantly less, making the hiking part of a trip more comfortable. The backpack also should protect your gear from the elements and allow fast &amp; easy access to important pieces of gear which you need on the go.</p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Straight from Osprey’s Website, here are the features of the Exos 48:</p>

<ul>
  <li>AirSpeed™ ventilated trampoline suspended mesh backpanel</li>
  <li>ExoForm™ mesh hipbelt and harness</li>
  <li>Stow-on-the-Go™ trekking pole attachment</li>
  <li>FlapJacket™ top cover for use without lid</li>
  <li>Internal hydration sleeve + Compatible with Hydraulics™ and Hydraulics™ LT Reservoir</li>
  <li>Light weight peripheral frame</li>
  <li>Removable sleeping pad straps</li>
  <li>Single ice axe loop</li>
  <li>Removable top pocket with mesh pocket and key clip</li>
  <li>Sternum strap with emergency whistle</li>
  <li>Stretchy front + side pockets</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45261238724/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos 48"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4806/45261238724_51ee9999ab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Exos 48" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>There’s for me no technical innovations in this pack, though as the Exos came out several years ago it was one of the first lightweight backpacks with a ventilated back panel, and also the Stow-on-the-Go trekking pole attachment system was innovative back then.</p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>It is a very well made pack that surely will keep you happy for many, many hiking &amp; backpacking seasons to come, and the 48 l Volume pack is great if you’re looking for one backpack which does it all - from day trips to one week long hikes in the backcountry.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45261247534/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos 48"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4866/45261247534_fc2192f24c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Exos 48" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Osprey Exos 48 in Back length L weighs 1.185 g empty, and the removable lid is 120 g.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>So I have used the Exos 48 on my seven day backpacking trip through Andorra, Spain and France where I carried around 17 kg of weight at the start of the hike, that was with water, food for 7 days and around 6 kg of camera gear. It’s a lot of weight and as someone who really doesn’t like to carry heavy loads seeing that number is scary. However, the reality was that it was not so bad. In part the ExoForm shoulder straps and hipbelt are responsible for that, because they are so damn comfortable that even such a heavy load was acceptable to carry. With every meal consumed the pack also got lighter and hence it got easier and more comfortable to carry the backpack. The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity.html">difference between the Levity and Exos</a> I have shown in an article in the spring and now, after a lot of use of both packs, I have to say that I find the Exos for my needs the better pack, even if it is 400 g heavier.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45936141812/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos 48 and Osprey Levity 60"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4861/45936141812_5ee486b85d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Exos 48 and Osprey Levity 60" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>What makes it better for me is not just the additional volume of the pack (that 3 l extra of the Exos means I can carry my camera gear a lot easier inside the pack!), but especially the <strong>Stretchy Side Pockets</strong> of the Exos which are making it for me more useable. My friend Martin bought the Levity 60 after he read my review in the spring, but also the production model of that pack had not very stretchy side pockets (something that I complained about in my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review.html">Levity review</a>) and so I usually had to give him his water bottle and stow it away again. That’s not a problem if you hike with a friend, but if you hike Solo then it means stopping, taking the pack off, getting your water, packing it back and then putting the rucksack on again. With the Exos I can get everything in the side pockets while I move, which I really love.</p>

<p>I also feel that the little bit of extra volume of the Exos makes it more versatile pack for most people. The 48 l pack can be used on day hikes and on one-week long backpacking trips, and also people who just start out with lightweight backpacking and own more bulky &amp; heavier gear will find it easier to get it in the Exos and carry it in more comfort. I also liked that there were two lid pockets - that meant for me more organization as I could stow less important things like my Passport and keys, which I still want to keep close, in the Mesh pocket, while the more important stuff - phone, wallet, map, spare battery - goes in the top pocket. Funnily enough I’m flexible enough to also open and close the top lid pocket, which allows me to access the things in there with the backpack on my shoulders.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45985403731/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos 48"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4808/45985403731_8a53775cbb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Exos 48" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Airspeed backpanel, compression straps, Ice Axe loop and other features of the Exos work well, and the pack also is highly water-resistant - at least during rain and snow all the content stayed dry, also without a rain cover. The material is durable and one doesn’t need to treat the pack super-carefully, and the shoulder straps accept the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/collections/clips/?rfsn=1845073.d8e1f">Peak Design Capture Clip</a> just fine (it’s a tight fit, but it goes on there).</p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I’d take the flap off which protects the drawcord closure of the main compartment when one doesn’t want to use the lid pocket. That probably will make the pack around 25 g lighter, and it won’t get in the way when one uses the lid.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>At 1.185 g in Size L the Osprey Exos is a fantastic backpack for people who come from a more traditional approach of backpacking &amp; who are lightening up their load or for ultralight backpackers who want to have a backpack which carries really comfortably. The thick ExoForm shoulder straps make carrying loads of up to 15 kg an enjoyable affair, though the lighter the pack the more comfy it will be. I feel the ideal weight is around 12 kg with kit, food and water for this pack, so if that’s your usual weight with consumables you probably really will enjoy this pack. I liked the spacious and easy to access stretchy side pockets, the front pocket can swallow a lot of gear, and the two lid pockets helped me with keeping my stuff organized. I didn’t miss Hipbelt pockets at all, and could have done without the lid flap and Stow-on-the-Go trekking pole attachment thingy as I rarely use poles and always will use the lid, but other than that I found it an amazing pack. Add in that it’s fairly easy to find it for around 150€ or less and you’ll understand why it is such a popular backpack!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45936138852/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos 48"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4864/45936138852_d8ec98082b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Exos 48" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Get the Exos at your favourite local Osprey Retailer or online at <a href="http://bit.ly/2Bnz9Yy">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/2BmSDMT">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> in Europe. In North America order it at <a href="http://bit.ly/2OVGy4Z">Backcountry.com</a> (<em>currently 25% off!</em>), <a href="http://bit.ly/2OWkMhp">REI</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2qZBqmU">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2OWjH9i">Moosejaw</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/2OY2OLs">Summit Hut</a>. <em>This are Affiliate Links</em>.</p>

<script src="//z0a.de/outtra-982.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=17204" type="text/javascript" id="outtrapricecomparewdgt17317204" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapcwdgt="17204"></script>

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45985416881/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos 48"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4913/45985416881_79f5917762_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Exos 48" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Osprey Exos or Osprey Levity - Which backpack to get?]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-14T12:24:50+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With Osprey offering two (four if you include the female models!) lightweight backpacks which share a similar construction the Question arises: Which backpack should I get? With this wee article I’ll try to help you answer that question!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932158287/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos vs Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4785/25932158287_9162e6ac1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Exos vs Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from Osprey. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>If you’re a fan of lots of details and video, just go take a cup of ☕️ and maybe even some 🍫 and then watch this video:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rt6pKmvtGXA?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The Exos and Eja (the Eja being the Women’s Model) have been for many years super popular lightweight backpacks from Osprey. As the original Exos came out some six or seven years ago a big Roar went through the Ultralight community (it was more Niche back then =) and there were those that liked them &amp; used them and those who thought they’re too heavy. In 2018 the Exos is a well-established and liked pack, and as I said in my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review.html">Osprey Levity Review</a>: With Osprey packs hanging in stores around the globe it’s a lot easier to try on a pack and see if it fits you. I still think it is the perfect pack to introduce people to lightweight rucksacks and ultralight backpacking, so I’m really happy that these packs exist.</p>

<p>But there are several features which set these two packs apart (<em>Dear Women: Please excuse that I refer now only to the male packs. The Eja and Exos have all the same features but the Eja has a Women’s Specific Fit. Everything I write about the Exos also applies to the Eja, I’m just lazy writing Exos &amp; Eja the whole time!</em> =). Lets look at them via this easy <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vRD-l0X_-z9A-Ao3t4bmJX9UuATTLncTNQ1BjO4U1ds20nTyc5ZEapuyreha4OZRap3Q3gmqzoV5s2V/pubhtml">Table I made</a>:</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vRD-l0X_-z9A-Ao3t4bmJX9UuATTLncTNQ1BjO4U1ds20nTyc5ZEapuyreha4OZRap3Q3gmqzoV5s2V/pubhtml" title="Osprey Exos vs Levity vs Eja"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4783/40804038981_3683f77cdf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="492" alt="Osprey Exos vs Levity vs Eja" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I think besides the weight and price, which are easy to see in this table, it’s also to remind oneself that the Exos will likely be a tad more durable than the Levity and should carry a few kilogram more in comfort, due to the thicker shoulder straps and the longer &amp; more cushioned hipbelt. The Exos also has a plethora of options to attach and carry gear externally on the pack, something that the Levity is missing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932157207/in/dateposted/" title="Shoulder Straps Eja vs Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4795/25932157207_fdc970e15e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Straps Eja vs Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932158717/in/dateposted/" title="Material Differences"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4781/25932158717_1dab92fe55_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Material Differences" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932159357/in/dateposted/" title="Hipbelts!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4782/25932159357_3b11148591_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hipbelts!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Levity on the other hand has it’s light weight going for it - it’s after all 421 g lighter than an Exos. I also found it a plenty comfortable pack for a week of backpacking, but that’s me. I also really liked the simplicity of the pack - not a lot of extra straps and things, stuff which I generally don’t use and so don’t need.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39894513801" title="On the way to a Loch"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4619/39894513801_6506290024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the way to a Loch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Generally however I think that with the lower price, light weight and rich features of the Exos and Eja the majority of people are better off with these packs than the Levity. With 90€ cheaper than an Levity it’s a much easier investment into a new pack (and lets be honest, it’s nice to buy a high-quality piece of kit and not spend over 200 or 300€ for it!) and gives you some money to go on a weekend trip. If only the lightest Osprey pack will do, however, then it’s obviously the Levity one should go for!</p>

<p><em>Support this blog for no additional costs to you and buy your pack via one of these links.</em> In North America order your <a href="http://bit.ly/2FBmlNX">Exos</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2Gk9tgs">Eja</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/2GjS3R9">Levity</a> at these retailers, while in Europe you can buy your Osprey packs at Bergfreunde: <a href="http://bit.ly/2Dliu5M">Exos</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2FDoJnv">Eja</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/2BrfOml">Levity</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Questions?</strong> Hit me up in the comments underneath or ask on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a>!</p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1704" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731704" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1704"></script>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Osprey Levity 45 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-25T20:47:27+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When a major-player in the backpacking market like Osprey decides to make an ultralight backpack you can be sure that there’s going to go a ripple through the scene. I was lucky enough to receive a Osprey Levity 45 backpack in August 2017 for testing and have put the pack through it’s paces in the last six months. <em>Here’s what I liked &amp; didn’t like about the new ultralight backpack from Osprey.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39890791831/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 Review"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4674/39890791831_cc49c75a3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 Review" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from Osprey. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>The Osprey Levity 45 is a great lightweight backpack which carries loads up to 10 kg in comfort. The Airspeed suspension back frame should be especially useful for hikes in hot environments, while the highly water-resistant material of the pack has kept my gear dry while backpacking for a week in Scotland. I would have wished the front and side pockets would have been more stretchy, but other than that this backpack is well made and should be an ideal choice for those who have used heavier backpacks in the past and look to lighten up. For all the details watch the video and read the review.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YhuugW019oI?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received my <a href="https://www.ospreyeurope.com/gb_en/ventilated-pinnacle-coming-soon/">Osprey Levity</a> 45 sample in August 2017 and had it along on a dozen day trips in autumn and winter, as well as a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/10/impressions-from-the-scottish-cairngorms.html">one week backpacking trip through the Cairngorms in Scotland</a>. All in all I have used it over 25 days.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39892290381/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 at Coire Etchachan Shelter, Cairngorms, Scotland"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4694/39892290381_121c47701a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 at Coire Etchachan Shelter, Cairngorms, Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The function of a backpack is to carry your gear in comfort from A to B. The idea behind an ultralight backpack is that it isn’t weighing 2+ kg empty, but significantly less, making the hiking part of a trip more comfortable. The backpack also should protect your gear from the elements and allow fast &amp; easy access to important pieces of gear which you need on the go.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36941189873/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Loch Etchachan"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4497/36941189873_4fe952cbaa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Loch Etchachan" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Straight out of the Levity and Lumina (the Lumina is the female version of this backpack, though it comes out in Europe first in 2019) Owner’s Manual, here’s the features of these pack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A fixed top lid with one zippered pocket</li>
  <li>Two removable side compression cords</li>
  <li>Dual access fabric side pockets</li>
  <li>Bellowed front fabric pocket</li>
  <li>Top lid cord loop attachment points</li>
  <li>Sternum strap with integrated safety whistle</li>
  <li>Internal main compartment compression strap</li>
</ul>

<p>The pack is made from two materials, the Main material is a 30D Silnylon Ripstop while the accents (that’s the lid, bottom, front and side-pockets) are made from a more durable NanoFly™ 100D Nylon x 100D UHMWPE Ripstop. The more durable material is a non-branded version of what other backpack makers sell at a premium as Dyneema or Cordura, and both materials seem to have a DWR coating.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26017236288/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Main Body Material"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4621/26017236288_38c7b5ab15_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Main Body Material" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>I’m hard pressed to give Osprey here any points: Ultralight backpacks have been around for many years, using equally or more advanced materials (like the material still commonly known as Cuben fibre, Silnylon, XPac and mixes thereof). I could say that the Airspeed frame, which allows for air circulation between your back and the main compartment of the pack, is an innovation in such a light pack.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018722777/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Side Pocket Material"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4602/25018722777_77b3c48823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Side Pocket Material" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The pack is well-made as you would expect from a brand like Osprey - they know their trade and how to make backpacks. So expect when you go to the store to get a Levity that it will hold up to many years of backpacking.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180104254/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Front &amp; Side View"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4756/39180104254_dace146f14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Front &amp; Side View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Levity 45 weighs 751 g in Size M. Please keep in mind that this is a pre-production model and the ones hitting the stores are expected to weigh 810 g on average!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018723817/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Shoulder Strap Detail 3"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4756/25018723817_aefa139dcd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Shoulder Strap Detail 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The Levity 45 is with its 45 l volume a good pack for long weekend trips or one week-long backpacking trips without resupplying, as in carrying all the food for one week. It’s going to be a tight fit at the beginning of a trip, even with a UL baseweight, but the more you eat the lighter it gets 😜. The main compartment swallows all my gear - shelter, bivy, mattress, quilt, stove, spare clothes and puffy jacket - with room to spare for food, an extra lens and the Mavic Pro Drone. The shoulder strap is not too wide, which means I can attach my <a href="https://youtu.be/3res6PXJySY">Capture Clip</a> to the pack and have my camera always at the ready.</p>

<p>When packing the backpack it’s important to pack smart, as the main compartment is not a round barrel but has two corners at the bottom which can stay empty if you don’t pack with a system - I stuff my bivy and some socks into these fins, and then come quilt, mattress, etc. If you don’t do that you’ll end up with empty space, and if you go out with a full week worths of food then that empty space might be needed. So pack smart! On the inside you also find a reservoir sleeve for a hydration system if that’s how you roll, I haven’t tried that as I use 1 l Platypus bottles and a Kuksa for water.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018722537/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Content for a weekend"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4626/25018722537_a06b2aa659_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Content for a weekend" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The side pockets as well as the front pocket (which is bellowed, that means it does expand a bit) are not stretchy, which means you’re limited in terms of how much gear you can stuff in them. Of course the pockets on the Levity are more durable than mesh, but if you like to carry some extra stuff on a trip that doesn’t fit into the main compartment then mesh outside pockets were usually there to accommodate that stuff, but not here. For that the Levity has some loops on the lid, to which you could attach some extra gear. I haven’t tried that, and also imagine it’d be difficult to attach some apples or other fruits to these loops 🍎🍉🍒😄.</p>

<p>Back to the pockets, these were fine to carry my water bottles, snacks, a big-ass tripod and extra clothes. The side pockets can be accessed from the top or the side, I can so for example get my Kuksa out of the side pocket when I want to drink and put it back in. As they don’t stretch it can sometimes be a bit difficult to stuff gear in the side pockets when the main compartment is already filled with your gear, so keep that in mind if you carry a tripod. The zippered lid pocket is fantastic, has a keychain hook inside, and swallows an incredible amount of gear - I carried my GR1 pocket with batteries and cables in it, plus some more stuff - all goin’ easily in there.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857991462/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 2"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4697/39857991462_c2f77e4024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Airspeed backpanel does it’s job well, with the aluminium frame keeping the mesh to your back and allowing for airflow. What I really like, though, are the shoulder straps and hipbelt. These have been really well designed and are very comfortable, also if the pack is fully loaded with 10+ kg of gear &amp; food. The foam which is wrapped by a mesh is pretty durable and adapts well to your shoulders and body, making for a comfortable carry all day long. The same goes for the hipbelt, which is pretty minimal but wrapped nicely around my hips and helped transfer the weight to them. I think the carrying frame system of the Levity 45 is very well made, and if you hike in very warm environments then I think this pack should be nice, as with the Airspeed backpanel and the airflow it allows it should possibly make you sweat less.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857989532/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel &amp; Frame"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/39857989532_a3e79958b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel &amp; Frame" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39890792031/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4621/39890792031_77ff9d08e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The side compression cords which are on the pack felt a bit useless to me, I still think that the compression system of the ULA Ohm is one of the best ones out there. The compression strap on the inside is a nice idea, but I tend to forget that the inside strap needs to be connected to the buckle on the inside, so sometimes I just don’t use it. The drawcord works well, though the point where the cord exists the fabric looks a bit weak to me and could be a point of failure.</p>

<p>The material of the Levity seems to have a DWR coating, especially the not transparent material with the white grid (<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180105634/in/dateposted/">see here</a>) kept the rain at bay, while the transparent material started to let some water seep through after a week in the Highlands. To be 100% safe I still would recommend to pack critical gear (quilt, down jacket, dry socks) in a waterproof drybag.</p>

<p><strong>Addition</strong>: Osprey informed me that the stretchy pockets have been fixed for production - these were updated from the sample pack I received. And the point where the drawcord exits the fabric has been reinforced for added durability, so this shouldn’t be an issue either.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39894513801/in/dateposted/" title="On the way to a Loch"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4619/39894513801_6506290024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the way to a Loch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I will repeat myself here, but: I wish Osprey would have made the side and front pockets more stretchy so one can easier get things in &amp; out of them or over-stuff them.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>I have reviewed half a dozen <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">backpacks</a> here and used probably more than triple the amount in the last 10 years, but there’s just a handful of UL packs which have a ventilated backpanel, like some of the ZPacks packs (which are a bit lighter but more expensive), and of course you just could go with the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-exos-46-backpack-2600-3000cu-in">Osprey Exos</a> which also has an Airspeed backpanel.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857991492/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 1"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4674/39857991492_a76aedbd31_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Does the market need another <em>ultralight</em> backpack? If that’s a question which is in your mind after you read this, let me say: Yes. We ultralight backpackers life in our own little UL Bubble, where we don’t see a problem with ordering a pack off the internet from a cottage manufacturer halfway across the globe - but we’re really not the majority. The Osprey Levity brings ultralight backpacks into the big stores and so in front of the eyes of thousands of outdoor enthusiasts who will love this pack - not only because they can choose from three different back lengths, but also because they <em>can try the pack on before they buy it!</em> I remember me ordering my first pack online some eight or nine years ago, it was quite an adventure to find out the right length I’d need, getting it through customs and all that. It’s not a process that many people want to go through, and hence it’s amazing that we have a lightweight backpack like the Osprey Levity now in stores across the globe.</p>

<p>And yes, the Levity backpack itself is also really, really good. It has some things which Osprey can improve upon when the next version of the pack comes around in a couple of years, but overall Osprey has done their homework well and has produced a very good backpack which will satisfy many backpackers. It’s lightweight, made of durable and water-resistant materials, has Osprey’s <a href="https://www.ospreyeurope.com/gb_en/all-mighty-guarantee/">All Mighty Guarantee</a> which lets you send in a damaged pack and get it repaired, and is also very comfortable to carry with a 10 to 12 kg load. It has everything an ultralight backpack needs as well as a backpanel which increases airflow, which should make it perfect for those super-hot summers we are getting these last years across the globe.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>The Levity is AVAILABLE! Get it at <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/osprey-levity-45-walking-backpack/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/osprey-levity-60-walking-backpack/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> in Europe. In North America order it at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-levity-45-backpack%3Fs%3Da">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fproduct%2F126706%2Fosprey-levity-45-pack-mens">REI</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=358fd954-c6b8-44a1-9ca9-aaad445d2dfb&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.campsaver.com%2Fosprey-levity-45-pack.html">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=61fff111-8514-4179-a87e-5da7e9fb1264&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.moosejaw.com%2Fmoosejaw%2Fshop%2Fproduct_Osprey-Men-s-Levity-45-Pack_10364645_10208_10000001_-1_">Moosejaw</a> and <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=258f5de7-8908-4439-9828-304e836d85a8&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.summithut.com%2Flevity-45-3.html">Summit Hut</a>. And yes, please go try the Levity at your local Osprey Shop so you get a feel for what an ultralight backpack feels (I promise, you’ll love it!).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180105634/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4715/39180105634_ce44d6a11a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
