<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: family hiking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/family-hiking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2019-05-06T11:40:59+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scaling Gear: 1P to 3P]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/11/scaling-gear-1p-to-3p.html"/>
    <updated>2018-11-28T20:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/11/scaling-gear-1p-to-3p</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You used to go hiking on your own, but nowadays you have a partner and kids and they want to come along outdoors? No need to break the bank and buy more gear - this equipment works well for the Solo Backpacker that wants to take a friend along - or two!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763145235/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3700/9763145235_51b887b518_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Ten years ago I was mostly backpacking on my own. Even when out with friends, we usually each had our own tarp or shelter, an own stove, and so on. Then I met my wife, we had two kids, and now we once or twice a year go out camping as a family. As the kids are still small it are easy affairs with short hikes, lots of snacks and play time, and pretty much only in warm, comfortable weather. Many of my readers are in a similar situation, and as gear nerds the question comes up: “<em>Which equipment can I use for myself on a Solo trip <strong>AND</strong> also use when out with the family?</em>”. Over the past seven years I have done plenty of research, trial and error, and this are my findings on how to scale gear from 1 Person to 3 Persons or more.</p>

<h2 id="my-home-is-my-castle">My Home is my Castle</h2>

<p>When I’m out on my own I value space in a shelter. That’s dry space, protected at a minimum from rain and wind, and possibly even from bugs and moisture from the ground. Shelters which adapt well from one person to two or more are Pyramid shelters in my experience. The main benefit is that even large, spacious Pyramids can be very light - like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-ultamid.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid</a>, the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/02/locus-gear-khufu-sil-review.html">Locus Gear Khufu</a> or the <a href="https://mountainlaureldesigns.com/product/trailstar/">Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar</a>. If I use these on my own they are a little palace with all the space I want, though if my wife, a friend or a child is along we also both, with our backpacks and equipment, still fit comfortably into these shelters. Now if we’d go backpacking with the whole family we would need to size up - either to a larger Pyramide (like the <a href="http://bit.ly/2rhAIBL">UltaMid 4</a>) or to two shelters where one adult sleeps with one child. These shelters have the option to get an inner for insect and ground protection, which is useful if the mosquitos and other bugs are out. The biggest advantage to these kind of shelters is that they are very light in comparison to other options - a Pyramide can be around 500 g if made from Silnylon, and even lighter when made from Cuben (or Dyneema Composite Fabric as it is known nowadays). Lighter, but usually with less protection, are only Tarps. These offer beautiful views in good weather, but also their openess can be discomforting to those who are not used to sleep truly <em>outside</em>, so I wouldn’t recommend them for starters.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9771060672/in/album-72157634403205347/" title="Space two"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7330/9771060672_54c9b307ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Space two" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>An alternative to Pyramide-Style Shelters are tents. These are heavier, but come with an inner and outer, so insect protection is included, and one has a clean floor, too, which is useful when one has small kids which like to put everything into their mouth. Also, happily many tent manufacturers have realized that not all tents have to be blizzard-proof winter bunkers. As a Helsport Ambassador I really like the <a href="https://www.helsport.no/lofoten-superlight-camp">Lofoten Superlite Camp 3</a> which is also the tent I used on my last two week-long backpacking trips with my best friend. This tent can sleep three and weighs around 2 kg, which is really great. It also has a large porch where gear can be stored and food be cooked, and in bad weather one also could play there. While maybe a bit too heavy when backpacking alone (there’s so many great 1P Tents available athat are around 1 kg or less heavy) if you want a tent which can accommodate more when needed, a tent like the Lofoten Superlite Camp 3 is a really good option.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31146548867/in/dateposted/" title="Helsport Lofoten Superlite Camp 3 somewhere in the Spanish Pyrenees"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4875/31146548867_d03b5bee2f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Helsport Lofoten Superlite Camp 3 somewhere in the Spanish Pyrenees" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="happy-meals">Happy Meals</h2>

<p>Stoves are tricky, especially if more than two persons are trekking together. I own several stove systems and on the trips with my best friend we always use together one of these gas stoves, where the pots have a volume of up to 700 ml. This has worked perfectly for us the last seven years, and of course when I’m on my own using one of these it is perfectly fine, too (then I can boil the water for a coffee and Porrige in one go!). Also when out with three or four I think such a “Solo” Stove works well for a group up to four, as in that case one just boils two times - first the water for the kids, then the water for the parents. This obviously only works when one uses Dehydrated Meals, which in my experience again is fine for kids, too (especially if they get a tasty treat afterwards). Not having dishes to clean is wonderful, and eating out of the bag can be novel and fun for small adventurers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44734046631/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Lunch break"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1841/44734046631_e9a9e914d2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lunch break" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So using a Solo Stove System like the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/msr-windburner-10-l-personal-stove-system-stove-system/?pid=10239">MSR Windboiler</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2zuL85d">Jetboil MiniMo</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2zrANH9">GSI Outdoors Halulite Microdualist Complete Stove</a> or <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/primus-lite-gas-stoves/?pid=10239">Primus Lite+</a> works great on Solo trips and with up to three more friends. After that, or if one really wants to cook (and do the dishes!), it is better to use a larger stove and pot combo. Or, if one is fortunate to be hiking in Finland and is staying at a campsite with a fire place, one could just bring a large <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/msr-big-titan-kettle-pot/?pid=10239">Titanium</a> or <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/sea-to-summit-alpha-pot-pot/?pid=10239">Aluminium pot</a> which can be used over the fire to boil water for all or cook.</p>

<h2 id="warm-nights">Warm Nights</h2>

<p>Getting an additional sleep system (so a mattress and a quilt or sleeping bag) for your partner or kids is necessary - unless you’re an Ultralight Backpacker which owns a combination of quilts and sleeping mattresses for different seasons. In that case the really warm winter quilt + mat go to the partner or child, the second warmest setup goes to a child, and you yourself use the lightest summer setup - and if it is a wee bit colder, just wear a warm fleece pants &amp; jacket and you’re fine. As I’m such a gear nerd that I own several mattresses and quilts this method has worked really good for us and we could avoid buying quilts and mattresses for the kids thus far - especially since they are only a night or three out per year, I wouldn’t want to invest money into gear that gets used so little and possibly gets to small in a year or three. It’s much better to have them use the adult setups - this saves money for nice treats or trips (or most likely, both!).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42251988122/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="Back view"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/950/42251988122_a439f03406_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="other-gear-that-can-be-scaled">Other Gear that can be scaled</h2>

<p>We each own our own water bottles but we share one <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/katadyn-befree-filter-3l-water-filter/?pid=10239">water filter</a>. I don’t want to spend 60€ on an additional filter - and truth be told, the <a href="https://youtu.be/CneJY3F6zuY">Katadyn BeFree</a> has such a high flow rate that it’s fast enough to fill up four bottles in a 5 Minute break.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44269585090/in/dateposted/" title="Katadyn BeFree Waterfilter"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4868/44269585090_fb6454a470_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Katadyn BeFree Waterfilter" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now backpacks can not really be <em>“scaled”</em> BUT you can own a backpack which easily can fit more gear - as you likely will make the hike for your partner and/ or kids as comfortable as possible and carry some of their equipment. A rucksack with an expandable rolltop closure - like in many <a href="http://bit.ly/2r4YKzI">Hyperlite Mountain Gear backpacks</a> - and a good compression system - like the <a href="http://bit.ly/2P6UCbM">ULA Ohm</a> - makes it easy to have one backpack which works well with smaller solo backpacking loads and larger two, three person loads. This is something to keep in mind if you’re buying a pack - will you need to carry just your gear, or also the gear of another person on occassions?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16219705131/in/album-72157648982512379/" title="Viewing the view stop"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7514/16219705131_dd6c0e5321_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Viewing the view stop" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-conclusion">In conclusion</h2>

<p>Much of the gear presented here works very well for both a two or three person trip <em>AND</em> a solo hike - the latter likely at a slight weight penalty as you might be using a 2 Person Shelter for sleeping instead of a 1 Person one, a more voluminous backpack (which again comes in useful if you go on a long solo hike or add in packrafting gear), a larger stove system or filter. But on the plus side, this means whenever your friends, family or kids want to go out with you backpacking to find out <strong>Why you like being outdoors so much</strong> you have the kit to take them along and show them. And that, in the end, is really worth it to carry a few grams more for the rest of the year 😊</p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35153478073/in/album-72157654125779966/" title="Camp with the Locus Gear Hapi Sil"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4301/35153478073_466ffb73e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Camp with the Locus Gear Hapi Sil" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Family Hike on the Bodvattnet Runt]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/05/a-family-hike-on-the-bodvattnet-runt.html"/>
    <updated>2013-05-09T09:56:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/05/a-family-hike-on-the-bodvattnet-runt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Like many we were happy about the free days provided by the Easter weekend. So on Easter Monday all three of us drove to the <a href="http://www.kvarkenworldheritage.fi/visit-kvarken/">Kvarken Archipelago</a>, a UNESCO World Heritage site, for a walk in this unique place.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8721713177/" title="Father &amp; Son by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7300/8721713177_a8a622ca93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Father &amp; Son" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>We arrived after a 45 minute ride from Vaasa at the parking lot in Svedjehamn, and while we hoped that our son would continue his afternoon nap which he started in the car he was wide awake as I took him on my back in the <a href="http://www.manduca-baby-carrier.eu/">Manduca child carrier</a>. <em>This might proof interesting</em> we thought, but our worries were unfounded as E enjoyed being outdoors and didn’t complain or cry even once on our hike.</p>

<p>Already from the parking lot we were able to see an White-Tailed Eagle flying in circles high above us, and I quickly grabbed my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/05/vortex-optics-viper-hd-binoculars.html">Vortex binoculars</a> to get a closer look. M also wanted a view, so I handed her the binos and walked on. The Bodvattnet Runt is a 4 km long nature trail and runs around lagoon which is connected to the Baltic. Many fish use it to lay its eggs there, and hence it is also popular with the local bird population. At the beginning of April there weren’t that many there yet, though, as also the lagoon was still covered under thick ice.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8722844508/" title="Map by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7339/8722844508_a584bbc84e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Map" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8721716649/" title="Scenery by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7317/8721716649_eafca9ae50_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Scenery" /></a></p>

<p>We walked on a well worn trail on the snow, and only meet two small groups of other hikers until we would reach the bird watching tower later on. The trail weaved in and out of birch and spruce forests, and led up to a small ridge from where we had a fine view over the lagoon. In times past fishermen were starting their trips from here, but with the land rising (the Kvarken Archipelago rises about 1 cm each year) now their sheds were standing far from the water and only had historical value. They are beautiful: The weathered wood is gorgeous to look at, the old nets still intact and the lovely little details are signs which one doesn’t find often on modern buildings.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8722851748/" title="Sjöes &amp; Batjes by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7366/8722851748_53a712259c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Sjöes &amp; Batjes" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8721726297/" title="Batjes by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7400/8721726297_cc756abfc3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Batjes" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8722845984/" title="Door by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7297/8722845984_f9706cb1f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Door" /></a></p>

<p>We continue along the ridge which brings us down into another birch &amp; spruce forest. They were building new trails, and a lot of gravel was strewn over the future trail. In the forest we spotted a tree which is used by a woodpecker puts cones and from where he eats the seeds hidden in it - broken cones were littering the base of the tree, so it has seen much use recently. The trail again lead up to a ridge, out of the dense trees, and we now could see the Baltic Sea on our left.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8721721035/" title="On the trail by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7406/8721721035_db42d1b69c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="On the trail" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8721716127/" title="Bodvattnet Runt by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7419/8721716127_7a2b957336_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bodvattnet Runt" /></a></p>

<p>We made our way to the bird watching tower, a beautiful structure which fits, despite its modern appearances, well into the landscape. Made entirely of wood, it rises high above the surrounding landscape and one can see far - back till Vaasa, even. The binos came back out and we were looking for birds, and spotted a few ice fisherman sitting further out between the rising land.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8722850346/" title="Birdtower by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7311/8722850346_a9dde31e20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Birdtower" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8721718251/" title="Birdtower by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7426/8721718251_2298c53750_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Birdtower" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8721721485/" title="Surveillance by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7382/8721721485_88cd836d65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Surveillance" /></a></p>

<p>Back down I got a few snacks and a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/11/thermos-bottle.html">Thermos</a> out of the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/berghaus-octans-40-tourenrucksack/">Berghaus Octans 40</a> M was carrying. E was running around and exploring the surroundings, he really enjoys to be outside and a wide smile was on his face, each new discovery confirmed by a loud shriek and a smile in our direction. M and me enjoyed some chocolate bars and coffee, E came back once in a while to get one of his favourite cookies and then was again running around.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8722844776/" title="View by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7390/8722844776_6abbd38fe4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="View" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8721715757/" title="Signs by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7319/8721715757_f62126e6e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Signs" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8610096370/" title="Svedjehamn, Kvarken Archipelago by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8248/8610096370_8d07372198_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Svedjehamn, Kvarken Archipelago" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8609916055/" title="Svedjehamn harbour by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8121/8609916055_a79bbce51e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Svedjehamn harbour" /></a></p>

<p>We packed up, I took E on my back again and we set off for the last few hundred meters to the parking lot. We passed the harbour now, which with its worn and weather-beaten piers and red boathouses makes for nice return to “civilisation”. In the summer one of the red buildings functions as a Café, and I’m sure we will visit it the next time one of our family hikes takes us here - there’s no better way than to finish a hike with a good cup of coffee and a nice piece of cake =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157633438534075/">More photos on Flickr</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
