<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-05-18T15:06:03+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hanging Betwen Trees 🌳🌲🌴 - a Look at the ENO Sub6 Hammock]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/eno-sub6-hammock-review.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-18T21:20:54+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/eno-sub6-hammock-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Finland, Sweden and Norway we have plenty of 🌳🌲🌲🌳🌲🌲🌳🌳🌲🌲🌲, a logical conclusion is thus to carry a hammock when you want to relax in the forest! In the past hammocks have been bulky, heavy and difficult to set up - that is not the case if you carry the ultralight ENO Sub6 Hammock and the amazing ENO Helios Suspension System. They let you lay in your hammock in less than two minutes on your next backpacking trip or dayhike - reason enough for me to check them out!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175363991/in/dateposted/" title="Chilling"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/910/42175363991_ba6803793f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from Eagle Nest Outfitters. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5s5Kj85_nfM?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I have tried several hammocks over the last years, but never really fell in love with them. Either they were too bulky, too uncomfortable or just too troublesome to set up. That changed as the <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/shop/eagle-nest-outfitters-sub6-hammock-1005617-charcoal/">Sub6 Hammock</a> and the <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/shop/eagle-nest-outfitters-helios-suspension-system-1005620-grey/">Helios Suspension System</a> from <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/tuotemerkit/eagle-nest-outfitters/">Eagle Nest Outfitters</a> arrived at Hiking in Finland HQ. At first I couldn’t believe how tiny and light the hammock and tree straps were, so I went out in the garden to see if they really work.</p>

<p>Well, they do! I came back in, showed them to my wife (who loves hammocks!) and told her that I got a nice hammock in which she can relax the next time we go on a day hike or visit the beach. She too couldn’t believe how light and compact they were, but after another demonstration in the garden she was convinced!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28302880728/in/dateposted/" title="An Ultralight Hammock Combo!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/911/28302880728_bd3f35f69d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="An Ultralight Hammock Combo!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175361661/in/dateposted/" title="Helios Suspension System"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/976/42175361661_79b1b45aff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Helios Suspension System" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41274731205/in/dateposted/" title="Connect Hammock Here -&gt;"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/909/41274731205_e66969f801_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Connect Hammock Here -&gt;" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28302883568/in/dateposted/" title="It&#x27;s Sandals &amp; Shorts weather!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/903/28302883568_dd2029d670_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="It&#x27;s Sandals &amp; Shorts weather!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Since then I had the hammock along on some bike rides and day hikes and was always again amazed at how light and how easy to set up this combo is. That alone means it’s almost a no-brainer to take these two along instead of a sit pad, as they are smaller than a 500 ml water bottle (in Fact they are so small that I sometimes need to rummage through my backpack to find them =). It now takes me less than two minutes to put up the hammock to the trees and lay down in it, and after some practicing I also have it down to operate the stove from the hammock and prepare the coffee while chilling! It adds a whole new layer of relaxation in nature to my hikes, and I have found myself napping in the shade of the trees while the wind plays with the leafs far above me.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175346741/in/dateposted/" title="Boiling water from the hammock"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/968/42175346741_2d7f8f5f84_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boiling water from the hammock" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175348611/in/dateposted/" title="Chilling under the Underbelly"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/950/42175348611_9d1bb1992b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling under the Underbelly" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40368021030/in/dateposted/" title="Underbelly Gear Sling"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/911/40368021030_3c5e2acdb2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Underbelly Gear Sling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175359321/in/dateposted/" title="Lots of awesome ENO kit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/910/42175359321_4cc61b34fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lots of awesome ENO kit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But that ain’t all: ENO makes everything you would need for hammocking, including an underquilt so you don’t get cold, the Underbelly Gear Sling which is a Mini-Hammock for your backpack &amp; gear, a bug net to keep the Mosquitos out and a Tarp which keeps you dry. That means if you fall in love with hammocking after you’ve had the Sub6 along on some day hikes and feel like you want to sleep in it, you now can add the gear you need and are ready for sleeping elevated in the forest! I have a bunch of ENO hammocking gear here and plan to try hammock camping again this summer, and I have a feeling that I will like it much better this time around.</p>

<p><strong>In conclusion</strong> it is safe to say that for day trips in the forest and afternoons at the beach we have a tiny &amp; light addition to the backpack with the ENO Helios Suspension System and Sub6 Hammock. They are easy to put up, so very comfortable to chill in and don’t need a lot of space in the backpack. And with all the 🌲🌲🌳🌲🌲🌲🌳🌲 we have here in Finland it’s about time we elevate ourselves from the ground! If you’d like to try the SUb6 Hammock and Helios Suspension System yourselves, head over to <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/tuotemerkit/eagle-nest-outfitters/">Partioaitta</a> who carry the gear here in Finland!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27303496617/in/dateposted/" title="More chilling"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/909/27303496617_66ca635cf8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="More chilling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this trip report &amp; video <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[24 Hours in Sipoonkorpi National Park (a Microadventure)]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/microadventure-sipoonkorpi-national-park.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-16T10:34:01+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/microadventure-sipoonkorpi-national-park</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you prefer the Outdoors over Cities but need to go to Helsinki - squeeze in a Microadventure to Sipoonkorpi National Park the next time you are in the Capital of Finland!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337489450/in/dateposted/" title="Chilling at Sunset"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/976/40337489450_c4f9faa8f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling at Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Last week I was going to Helsinki for <a href="https://pingfestival.fi">PING Festival 2018</a> and I decided to sneak in a wee Microadventure in <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/sipoonkorpinp">Sipoonkorpi National Park</a> before the event. Sipoonkorpi is a new-ish National Park and less than an hour by bus away from the centre of Helsinki, so it makes for an excellent place to escape the city for a while and enjoy this unique park with its forests, hills and beautiful nature. If you prefer Video over photos and want to see some enchanting Drone Footage, relaxed hiking and me brushing my teeth just hit play:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZXMh_jyu2es?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I took the train to Helsinki, a great way to do some work and watch the latest Episode of Neo Magazine Royale, and then jumped on the Tram to the Clarion Helsinki to drop of the stuff I needed for the following few days in Helsinki and Ruka. Then it was off with the Bus to Sipoonkorpi National Park, which lays on the outskirts of Vantaa, one of the three cities which makes up the Helsinki Metropolitan area. I got off in the middle of nowhere at a scenic road. I followed the sign to the Tractor Museum and then just walked down the road where I saw the blue “Sipoonkorpi National Park” sign. Shortly after I saw the Luontopolku sign, this trail can be walked in either direction but as it was early in the day and I had an idea where I wanted to sleep and what I wanted to see when I followed the trail first north.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144268101/in/dateposted/" title="Entering the National Park"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/830/42144268101_25ab3fb891_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Entering the National Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337492750/in/dateposted/" title="And there&#x27;s the Nature Path!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/907/40337492750_bcf8920e3b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And there&#x27;s the Nature Path!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337484140/in/dateposted/" title="Wood Anemone"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/40337484140_6437bfc456_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wood Anemone" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Right away I loved the little trail - Wood Anemone were everywhere along the narrow trail which went through a very young forest which was beautiful, and then one got a first taste of the granite slick rocks which I later see a lot in the Högberget section of the trail. This section was short and after a short while I was out on the forest road again, before entering a more shaded pine forest on the other side. This section ended also again in that same forest road, and then the trail went on the road further till a parking lot where quite a few cars were parked and a few boulderers where just shouldering their crashpads to go hug some pebbles in the National Park’s surroundings. I followed the trail towards the Kalkkiruukki Laavu, which was very busy with day hikers grilling sausages and enjoying the fantastic warm weather.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144269461/in/dateposted/" title="Kalkkiruukki Laavu"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/980/42144269461_56fc976e99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kalkkiruukki Laavu" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337485940/in/dateposted/" title="Signs &amp; Portents"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/824/40337485940_d2cae06a34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Signs &amp; Portents" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144265471/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking too fast"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/970/42144265471_a7323be439_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking too fast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I sat down for an hour or so, drunk a coffee and shot some video scenes, and complained on Instagram that my NEW Katadyn BeFree 1l bottle was apparently already broken as I got it (<a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel/status/996281448062705664">see it here on Twitter</a>). I packed up and then the trail continued for a few kilometres through dark pine forests, past rocks, climbing up and down and over streams. The path was wide and great condition, and here and there one could see where the winter XC trail goes. I had a chat with two women who where hiking with their dog and inquired about Ticks, and according to them these little pests are not a problem here (I didn’t encounter any).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423898904/in/dateposted/" title="Only a short stroll to Högberget"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/825/41423898904_bcb18926b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Only a short stroll to Högberget" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423901054/in/dateposted/" title="Högberget from above!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/828/41423901054_08a0cfefe6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Högberget from above!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144265851/in/dateposted/" title="Högberget!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/954/42144265851_4e53c82b72_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Högberget!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then I arrived at Högberget! These are probably the most popular spot of the National Park, I saw a lot of people here, enjoying the view from the higher rocks towards the city and sea beyond (I didn’t see the Baltic, but it should be possible to see it on a clear day). These slick granite rocks are really nice and I decided that I wanted to sleep under the stars somewhere over there, though as there was no water close by I first needed to find a water source - and I wanted to finish the trail before looking for a place to sleep. As the days are long in Finland now - the sun sets somewhere around 22:30 - I had enough time to do everything, and still could find a nice spot to roll out my mat &amp; quilt and have something to eat.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144266671/in/dateposted/" title="Trails"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/905/42144266671_660cc89c18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trails" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423898614/in/dateposted/" title="Death &amp; Young"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/969/41423898614_ac932c684f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Death &amp; Young" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423900404/in/dateposted/" title="Dessert &#x3D;)"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/972/41423900404_48864e2a62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dessert &#x3D;)" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41243046955/in/dateposted/" title="Goes on"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/963/41243046955_841eb20bc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Goes on" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144267591/in/dateposted/" title="I go to bed"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/42144267591_5618124f3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I go to bed" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I slept shortly that night - because I got up at 1:00 o’clock to photograph the stars, and low-and-behold, I got very lucky as I even captured some Northern Lights! In May! The next morning I slept in as long as I could before the sun was just too warm, made breakfast, shot a video about the As Tucas Sestrals quilt and then ran back to the Bus stop to catch the Bus back to Helsinki - I had a Design Tour to attend and didn’t want to meet that!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144264151/in/dateposted/" title="Barefoot Breakfast"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/909/42144264151_c1f8fe7e5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Barefoot Breakfast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144277081/in/dateposted/" title="After-hike Burger"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/907/42144277081_2cf23f1d17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="After-hike Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All in all it was a fantastic little trip: Beautiful warm T-Shirt weather, stars and Northern Lights, beautiful nature and lots of fresh green on the ground and trees! If you come to Helsinki, Espoo or Vantaa (or life there!) and have an extra day, do it like me: Take along your Ultralight backpack, some food and hop on the Bus to Sipoonkorpi National Park!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144269981/in/dateposted/" title="Calazo Sipoo Map!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/976/42144269981_6e86295399_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Calazo Sipoo Map!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-there--what-you-need">How to get there &amp; what you need</h2>

<p>I took Bus 717A from next to the Helsinki Railway Station to Sotunki, Google Maps or the Reittiopas Website are recommended to find the times when the bus goes and see where you have to get off (which is <em>Kalkkiuunintie</em> and should be displayed in the Bus, too). From there follow the sign which says <em>Trollberga</em> and <em>Traktori- ja Konemuseo</em> and after around 250 m you’ll see the blue Sipoonkorven Kansallispuito sign above. From the bus stop the complete nature path is around 8 km in length, and you can hike it either direction. A water bottle and some snacks are recommended for a day trip, if you want stay for the night bring a mattress, quilt and bivy which are appropriate for the season, and possibly a tarp or tent if you do not want to stay in one of the lean-to shelters. <strong>Questions?</strong> Ask me on Twitter of Facebook!</p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1746" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731746" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1746"></script>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this trip report &amp; video <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 283]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/twir-283.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-11T23:53:45+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/twir-283</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Flickering green/ a hint of orange/ the night is gone.”</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41367965264/in/dateposted/" title="Northern Lights in May!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/944/41367965264_33b1cefbd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Northern Lights in May!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-news">Outdoor News</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/apr/17/poland-violated-eu-laws-by-logging-in-biaowieza-forest-says-ecj">Poland violated EU laws by logging in Białowieża forest</a>, court rules.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/40548564/better-technology-isnt-the-solution-to-ecological-collapse">Better Technology isn’t the Solution</a> to Ecological Collapse.</p>

<p>Great news for nature: The <a href="https://www.mnn.com/earth-matters/animals/blogs/eu-passes-total-ban-neonicotinoids-bee-harming-pesticides">EU passes a total ban on bee-harming pesticides</a>.</p>

<p>Yay, I <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">announced the Cottages Interviews 2018 Series</a>! If you like ultralight gear makers you definitely should <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">subscribe via RSS</a> to not miss these!</p>

<p>The <a href="https://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/outdoor-spirit-podcast-38-was-ist-eigentlich-dieses-glamping/">Outdoor-Spirit Podcast #38</a> is out and talks about Glamping. [German]</p>

<p>Should we be <a href="http://eveningsends.com/crowdfunding-rescues/">crowdfunding resuces</a>?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.gipfel-glueck.de/fit-fuer-die-berge-7-yoga/">Yoga for hikers</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Something to look forward to: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2018/may/05/happiness-curve-life-gets-better-after-50-jonathan-rauch">Life gets better after 50</a> (Why age tends to work in favour of happiness).</p>

<p>How to <a href="https://youtu.be/A9BgTdQ0AzM">Lightpaint with Steel Wool</a>.</p>

<p>An <a href="https://brazenbackpacker.com/2018/05/03/ode-to-the-instagram-hiker/">Ode to the Instagram Backpacker</a>.</p>

<p>Learn to understand the <a href="https://www.photopills.com/articles/understanding-golden-hour-blue-hour-and-twilights">Golden Hour, Blue Hour and Twilights</a>.</p>

<p>SmugMug <a href="https://www.smugmug.com/together/">bought Flickr</a>.</p>

<p>Revelate Designs launched a new seat pack, the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fproduct%2F131608%2Frevelate-designs-terrapin-system-saddle-pack-8-liters">Terrapin System 8L</a>.</p>

<p>Garmin unveiled the new <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fproduct%2F140110%2Fgarmin-inreach-mini-2-way-satellite-communicator">inReach Mini</a>.</p>

<p>Impressions from the <a href="http://www.goout.hk/2018/05/10/dlgm-ii/">DLGM II</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the new <a href="https://katabaticgear.com/shop/knik-liteskin-40l-backpack/">LiteSkin</a> backpacks from Katabatic Gear.</p>

<p>Buy a <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=47cd1998-e608-4548-aa0f-3d33e964ad3a&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.hyperlitemountaingear.com%2Fallproducts.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Backpack</a> and get a free Pod to organize your gear!</p>

<p>You want to vote with your £$€ when you buy gear and buy from companies which think about social and environmental matters? You can now shop by sustainability attributes on the REI website, for example by searching for “<a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fsearch.html%3Fq%3DMade%2Bin%2BUSA%26origin%3Dweb%26ir%3Dq%253AMade%2Bin%2BUSA%26page%3D1">Made in USA</a>” “<a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fsearch.html%3Fq%3Dfair%2Btrade%26origin%3Dweb%26ir%3Dq%253Afair%2Btrade%26page%3D1">fair trade</a>” or “<a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fsearch.html%3Fq%3Dorganic%2Bcotton%26origin%3Dweb%26ir%3Dq%253Aorganic%2Bcotton%26page%3D1">Organic Cotton</a>”.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/337979" title="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Salomon_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/825/28162269868_393289209f_z.jpg" width="640" height="336" alt="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Salomon_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Win a <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/salomon-hike-plus-outfit/">Salomon Multisport Outfit</a> in this Photo Contest.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/kNCR8Y" title="Bergzeit_Frischluftkick-adidas_terrex_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/903/28162269538_6fbf8b56d2_z.jpg" width="640" height="336" alt="Bergzeit_Frischluftkick-adidas_terrex_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Stay at the Explorer Hotel Kitzbühel and get a sweet adidas terrex apparel outfit in this <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/bergzeit-frischluft-kick-adidas-terrex-explorer-kitzbuehel/">contest</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4v74D4" title="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Deuter_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/951/41990925382_e1e4f900c9_z.jpg" width="640" height="336" alt="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Deuter_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Win a trip to the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/alpincamp/deuter-klettern-wilder-kaiser/">Wilder Kaiser Region</a> and Deuter kit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/3yiyy3" title="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel-Icebreaker_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/826/41990925062_c0741b94dd_z.jpg" width="640" height="336" alt="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel-Icebreaker_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And finally, win 500€ worth of <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">Icebreaker Cool-Lite garments</a> for your next adventure!</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fnew-arrivals%3Ffl%3Dtrue">new arrivals at Backcountry</a>.</p>

<p>Summer is here, and so are the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/walking-trousers/?listorderby=oxinsert&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">new hiking trousers</a> for this season.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=706625&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/706625/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Agnieszka is hitting the trail again! This year she will be <a href="https://acrossthewilderness.blogspot.fi/2018/05/continental-divide-trail-crazy-cook.html">hiking the Continental Divide Trail</a>. [Polish]</p>

<p>Drew hikes to <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2018/05/07/hiking-to-el-montanon-peak-santa-cruz-island/">El Montanon Peak</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://freedirtmonger.blogspot.fi/2018/05/desert-trail-death-valley.html">Desert Trail: Death Valley</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://photomomlinda.blogspot.fi/2018/04/sedona-hiking-hiline-trail.html">Hiking the Hiline Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Backpacking on <a href="https://ultralightpedestrian.com/2018/04/24/bornholm-rundt-langs-kyststien/">Bornholm</a>. [Danish]</p>

<p>It was a <a href="https://coastkid.blogspot.fi/2018/05/saturdays-big-sky-day.html">Big Sky Saturday</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://steviehaston.blogspot.fi/2018/05/the-dalliance-of-eagles-by-stevie.html">The Dalliance of Eagles</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/264661267?color=ffffff" width="640" height="338" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://urbanflyfisher.com/how-time-flies/">How time flies</a>.</p>

<p>A hike up <a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/hiking/mt-tenmoku/">Mt. Tenmoku 天目山</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fsc%2Fthru-hiking-the-oregon-coast-trail%3FINT_ID%3DIB23734">Thru-Hiking the Oregon Coast Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2018/04/7-auf-einen-streich-revierbeschreibung.html">7 Packrafting trips in Croatia</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2018/05/packrafting-en-rusia-ii-los-urales.html">Packrafting in Russia</a>. [Spanish]</p>

<p>Read the <a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2018/04/30/john-muir-trail-northbound-guide/">John Muir Trail Northbound Guide</a> before hiking it!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/bombtrack-romagna-bike-trail/">Bombtrack on the Romagna Bike Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/stories/roadside-intervention/">Bikepacking with Keith Richards</a>.</p>

<p>And some beautiful impressions from <a href="https://willemvandoorne.wordpress.com/2018/05/13/greenland-2017-part-ii-disko-island/">Willem’s 2017 Greenland adventures</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28214430548/in/dateposted/" title="Lunch with a View"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/946/28214430548_d6e7bd5625_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lunch with a View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Matthias embarked on an epic bikepacking tour across Europe - <a href="https://quasiout.de/dracula-skischanzen-und-juetlands-brise-packliste-fuer-mein-far-packing-2018/">here’s the gear he has along</a>. [German]</p>

<p>The Great Outdoors <a href="https://www.tgomagazine.co.uk/review/review-ordnance-survey-aventura-gps/">reviews the OS Aventura GPS</a>.</p>

<p>Read Kat’s <a href="http://attitude-over-ability.com/te-araroa-gear-debrief/">Te Araroa Gear Debrief</a> before heading to New Zealand.</p>

<p>Chris reflects on <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2018/05/40-years-on-gear-for-long-distance.html">Gear for Long-Distance Walks Then &amp; Now</a>.</p>

<p>Martin’s gear list for his <a href="https://www.gehlebt.at/hoamatroas-packliste/">1370 km Hoamatroas hike</a>. [German]</p>

<p>First impressions of the <a href="https://pig-monkey.com/2018/05/kojin/">Kojin Stove</a>.</p>

<p>Alex helps you sew a <a href="https://www.bergreif.de/2018/04/11/ultraleichten-myog-biwaksack-naehen/">breathable bivy bag</a> and a <a href="https://www.bergreif.de/2018/05/02/ultraleicht-1-personen-silnylon-tarp-naehen/">1P Tarp</a>. [German]</p>

<p>First impressions of the <a href="https://theultralightguru.wordpress.com/2018/03/23/first-impressions-on-the-atom-from-atompacks/">Atom backpack</a> from Atom Packs.</p>

<p>Ken reviews the <a href="https://ultralightandcomfortable.com/2018/04/26/gear-review-gossamer-gear-the-one-tent/">Gossamer Gear The One</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plan/five-bikepacking-tool-kits/">What’s in your tool kit</a>?</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing the Cottages Interviews 2018 Series]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-02T18:47:06+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Be prepared for more than a dozen of fresh cottage interviews coming this spring and summer to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com">Hikingi in Finland</a> =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40943661375/in/dateposted/" title="Announcing the Cottages Interviews 2018"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/832/40943661375_1cb2a9403e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Announcing the Cottages Interviews 2018" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Almost ten years after I started the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/interviews/">Cottage Interview Series</a> they are back! I always really enjoyed conducting these interviews and getting to know the people behind the gear, and what drives them. It’s just - around eight years ago I slowly ran out of companies to interview 😊 But during the last years more &amp; more new cottages came into existence, and many of them have a unique solution or design on how to make our bacpacking trips more fun - and lighter! Thus over the next several months I will be interviewing some of the newest Ultralight cottages across the globe to find out what drives them, but I also will be re-visiting some of the cottages I interviewed way back in the day and find out how they are doing in 2018!</p>

<p>If you are interested in what drives ultralight gear makers, what goes into designing and making an ultralight hammock, backpack, quilt or hoody - you will want to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">subscribe via RSS</a> to the blog or become a Fan &amp; Follower on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> where I also will announce the new articles. Excited? Better be - the first interview will go up in two weeks!</p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy reading Hiking in Finland <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">get me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on this blog to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 282]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/04/twir-282.html"/>
    <updated>2018-04-09T13:53:45+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/04/twir-282</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>A goal/ blue sky/ into the mist</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39218815430/in/dateposted/" title="Getting there"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/815/39218815430_7d2e395259_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Getting there" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-news">Outdoor News</h2>

<p>Marc-André Leclerc and Ryan Johnson have <a href="https://gripped.com/news/canadian-marc-andre-leclerc-has-passed-away-in-alaska/">passed away while on a climb in Alaska</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.gq.com/story/patagonia-versus-donald-trump">Patagonia vs. Donald Trump</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/G40ooKzI664">Climate Change is Killing this Alaskan Village</a>.</p>

<p>Take a minute to <a href="https://actions.sumofus.org/a/stop-hydroelectric-power-plants-on-albania-s-wild-rivers">Stop Hydroelectric Power Plants on Albania’s Wild Rivers</a>.</p>

<p>Join the <a href="https://swiftcampout.com">Swift Campout</a> on June 23rd and 24th - mark it in your calendars!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.atompacks.co.uk">Atom Packs</a> is a new cottage out of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>NEW: The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/04/trailblazers-locus-gear-djedi-dome-tent.html">LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent</a>.</p>

<p>Are you a content creator that loves the outdoors? Then meet like-minded people at the <a href="http://www.outdoor-show.com/od-en/press/blogger.php">Outdoor Show in Friedrichshafen</a>.</p>

<p>Support the <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gnarbox/gnarbox-20-ssd-rugged-backup-device-for-your-camer?ref=hendrikmorkel">GNARBOX 2.0 SSD</a> – Rugged backup device for your camera</p>

<p>Need something to read for the next weeks? Buy <a href="https://amzn.to/2GDDCKS">Bothy Tales: Footsteps in the Scottish hills</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/2uQkWCf">High and Low: How I Hiked Away From Depression Across Scotland</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tgomagazine.co.uk/skills/navigation-skills/digital-feature-the-future-of-mountain-navigation-and-mapping/">The future of Mountain Navigation and Mapping</a>.</p>

<p>Awesome use of Tax Money: <a href="https://www.citylab.com/life/2018/03/european-union-interrail-travel-ticket-for-teenagers/554978/">The EU is giving Teens a Month of Free Train Travel Across Europe</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/environmentalisms-racist-history">Environmentalism’s Racist History</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/03/02/climate/bears-ears-national-monument.html">Oil Was Central in Decision to Shrink Bears Ears Monument</a></p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/aIYtuqLs030">Astrophotography with the Sony A7 III</a>.</p>

<p>Andrew interviews the <a href="https://andrewskurka.com/2018/ultralight-jerk-instagram/">Ultralight Jerk</a>.</p>

<p>Martin joins the <a href="https://www.gehlebt.at/rother-neuheiten-2019/">Bergverlag Rother</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=beEcJ7toodo">Drawn To High Places</a>.</p>

<p>There’s <a href="https://swisspowder.wordpress.com/2018/04/03/april-2018-still-meters-of-snow-in-the-swiss-alps/">still Meters of Snow in the Swiss Alps</a> so ski-touring season isn’t over yet.</p>

<p>Agnes shares her tips on <a href="https://acrossthewilderness.blogspot.fi/2018/04/sposoby-na-urazy-jak-uniknac-kontuzji.html">how to prevent injuries</a>. [Polish]</p>

<p>Spring. A new Season means new Gear - check out the latest <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/new/category--outdoor-clothing/?pid=10239">outdoor apparel</a> and <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/trail-running-shoes/?pid=10239">trailrunning shoes</a> for your next hike!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=49341&amp;pw=73183">ULA Equipment Backpacks</a> have FREE US Shipping on ALL Orders!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/23D0Va" title="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_Buff_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/894/39530188810_8f6d929cb3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="538" alt="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_Buff_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Win tickets for the <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">Salomon Trails 4 Germany</a> and a full BUFF package.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/59zL6k" title="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Dynafit_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/872/26467825887_a8d9e9af96_b.jpg" width="1024" height="538" alt="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Dynafit_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Hike with <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/alpincamp/dynafit-watzmann-drei-zinnen/">Dynafit from the Großer Watzman to the Tre Cime</a> and get the full kit, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/X07m34" title="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Bergans_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/822/41296653012_50a7867236_b.jpg" width="1024" height="538" alt="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Bergans_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Photographers can <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/bergans-floyen-outfit/">win an outfit from Bergans</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=706625&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/706625/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Benjamin and family hike the <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2018/03/muggestutz-dwarf-adventure-trail/">Dwarf Adventure Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Paulina shares her <a href="https://www.littlegrunts.com/5-favorite-bay-area-hikes/">5 Favorite Bay Area Hikes</a>.</p>

<p>How about skiing <a href="https://walkingwomad.com/2018/03/08/winter-ski-tour-sarek-lapland/">11 days along the Padjelantaleden, through Sarek National Park and along the Kungsleden</a>?</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/VW77mXpkQQ0">Never coming home</a>.</p>

<p>Kelly heads <a href="https://kellycordes.com/2018/03/22/into-the-whiteout/">into the Whiteout</a> to go winter climbing in Scotland.</p>

<p>Geoff headed out to <a href="https://farnotfast.blogspot.fi/2018/04/march-backpack-bleaklow-and-kinder.html">Bleaklow and Kinder</a>.</p>

<p>Kathrin hiked through the <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/suedafrika-trekking-amatola-trail-erfahrungsbericht/">Amatola Mountains</a> in South Africa. [German]</p>

<p>Jill shares <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2018/03/photos-from-iditarod-trail.html">photos from the Iditarod Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/hiking/shikinejima-coastal-hike/">Shikinejima Coastal Hike</a>.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/10uM6IU8S6U?rel=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>A <a href="https://www.thehikinglife.com/2018/03/a-quick-dirty-guide-to-the-sierra-high-route/">Quick &amp; Dirty Guide to the Sierra High Route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2018/03/a-night-in-ben-alder-cottage.html">A night in Ben Alder Cottage</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://consequencesofmindfulness.com/2018/02/27/cigarettes-silhouettes-running-the-cancelled-lovit-100-mile-trail-run/">Running the Cancelled LOViT 100 Mile Trail Run</a>.</p>

<p>James hikes from <a href="https://backpackingbongos.wordpress.com/2018/04/02/the-arctic-trail-kautokeino-to-kilpisjarvi-pt4-mountains-and-waterfalls/">Kautokeino to Kilpisjärvi</a> in the 4th part of his Arctic Trail adventure.</p>

<p>Looks like a fun hike in Germany, the <a href="http://awesomatik.de/der-schluchtensteig-etappen-1-bis-3/">Schluchtensteig</a>. [German]</p>

<p>And <a href="http://www.highlux.co.nz/2018/03/colombia-salento-valle-de-cocora-bogota/">bikepacking in Colombia</a> looks amazing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37562880556/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Morning Glory"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4490/37562880556_2086b79487_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Morning Glory" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/E5LP_YFXJIM">f-stop gear Tilopa Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity.html">Osprey Exos or Osprey Levity</a> - Which Backpack to Get?</p>

<p>Quasi builds his <a href="https://quasiout.de/salsa-vaya-custom-bike-3-0-umbau-zum-bikepacking-tourer/">Salsa Vaya Custom Bike 3.0</a>.</p>

<p>Drew reviews the <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2018/03/31/gear-review-five-ten-access-knit-hiking-shoes/">Five Ten Access Knit Hiking Shoes</a>.</p>

<p>Sandra reviews the <a href="http://www.fastpacking.de/2018/03/21/gastbeitrag-testbericht-dd-superlight-pyramid-tent-und-pyramid-mesh-tent/">DD Superlight Pyramid Tent and Pyramid Mesh Tent</a>. [Germany]</p>

<p>Chris Townsend writes about the <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2018/04/tents-and-tarps-ive-used-for-long.html">tents and tarps I’ve used for long-distance walking over the decades</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/news/nordest-sardinha/">Nordest Sardinha Bikepacking Rig</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trailblazers: LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/04/trailblazers-locus-gear-djedi-dome-tent.html"/>
    <updated>2018-04-05T19:30:23+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/04/trailblazers-locus-gear-djedi-dome-tent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent is finally available for Sale - it is the first Dome tent made from the new waterproof-breathable Dyneema® Composite Fabric and tips the scales at a sweet 980 g!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/C55727" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/866/39440149990_460ed33c86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I have followed Jotaro’s development of the LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent over the last four years, being very interested in this amazing little tent. I find free-standing dome tents a great and useful design, and the lighter the package the better. During the past winter Jotaro hinted that the tent might soon be ready for production - and that moment has now arrived!</p>

<p>Watch the Video to get some insights on how the Djedi became a reality.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BMl0DWL6JCI?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Quite a great story, and also interesting to see a little bit into the LOCUS GEAR workshop! I caught up with Jotaro and here’s a wee background on the design and production process:</p>

<p>“Most people think it’s a Star Wars thing,” says Jotaro, “But originally ‘Djedi’ is an Egyptian God’s name. ‘Djedi’ starts with the letter D, and D is also the shape of the dome.” Jotaro needed almost four years to be happy with what he considered the ultimate dome tent: The strong, lightweight, waterproof and breathable Djedi Dome – the first Dome tent made with Dyneema® Composite Fabric with eVent. This fabric combines the advantages of two very popular fabrics in the ultralight niche - Dyneema Composite Fabric and eVent. The result is a lightweight fabric which is waterproof and exceptionally breathable.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0t67Fj" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/876/39439981060_0c69470051_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/22WjTt" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/900/39439979840_2dd51bf08c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>“I made eight different prototypes using different fabrics but was never satisfied,” says Jotaro. “Condensation is a major problem for anyone who camps. And if your inside walls and then possibly your down sleeping bag and other gear gets wet, the situation can even become life threatening at worst or less fun at best. So, for a dome tent it goes beyond being strong and extremely light. Breathability is the true ‘dream’ property.”</p>

<p>As Jotaro has being producing functional &amp; beautiful Dyneema Composite Fabric shelters for many years, it was a logical move to also use this fabric for the Djedi. Dyneema is the world’s strongest, lightest fiber that is fifteen times stronger than steel but floats on water. It has been used since many years by most key players in the ultralight outdoor industry to create lighter and more functional gear while driving innovation and performance levels of shelters and tents – to make them both stronger for protection and lighter for packing. The new breathability factor of the DCF-eVent fabric can now inspire the tent industry to yet newer heights.</p>

<p><em>You can order the <a href="http://locusgear.com/items/djedi-dcf-event-dome/?lang=en">LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent</a> directly from LOCUS GEAR in Japan and support an innovative ultralight cottage manufacturer.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/76Y394" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/874/41205932612_d9a30b3705_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/9g6aW1" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent in Kings Canyon National Park."><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/786/41249683601_4f56909c32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent in Kings Canyon National Park." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0C51wA" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/789/26376608687_a68bcff755_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions From the MDV Transalp]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/impressions-from-the-mdv-transalp.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-26T12:54:01+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/impressions-from-the-mdv-transalp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mid March: Italy, Switzerland, Austria, sunshine AND great powder snow - sounds impossible? Think again, as that’s exactly what we experienced on the Marker Dalbello Völkl Transalp tour!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40134314135/in/dateposted/" title="Almost at the summit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/802/40134314135_44eee10380_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Almost at the summit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Marker Dalbello Völkl who invited me on this trip. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40319033954/in/dateposted/" title="The kit for the TransAlp"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/790/40319033954_31a9831c1f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="The kit for the TransAlp" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Last Monday was a travel day. Last Tuesday was a powder day. Life is good, right until when it is not good anymore.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39218813480/in/dateposted/" title="A long slog up"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/797/39218813480_96e1030f3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="A long slog up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The TransAlp sounded like an Event that was made for me: A traverse of three countries on ski, from Livigno in Italy to the Kleinwalsertal in Austria via Switzerland. It’s exactly the kind of trips I enjoy and look for, so the invitation to the adventure from <a href="https://www.marker.net/de/">Marker</a>, <a href="https://www.dalbello.it/">Dalbello</a> and <a href="https://www.voelkl.com/">Völkl</a> was after a bit of pondering and some questions quickly decided upon.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40985738652/in/dateposted/" title="Michi enjoying the POW"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/818/40985738652_d099fe5537_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Michi enjoying the POW" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>What I couldn’t be aware of was that a flu I had decided to trouble me up at almost 3.000 m up in the Alps, and slow me down quite a bit in comparison with my more skilled tour partners.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27156585138/in/dateposted/" title="Talabfahrt Bliss"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/806/27156585138_8bbe55094b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Talabfahrt Bliss" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The full story will follow before the season ends, if you can’t wait you should head over to <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and read between the lines on how the trip went.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39218886610/in/dateposted/" title="The Road to AWESOMENESS"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/815/39218886610_93968eef1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="The Road to AWESOMENESS" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this trip report &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1721" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731721" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1721"></script>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39218825560/in/dateposted/" title="Wettersteinspitze"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/786/39218825560_c8ac835702_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Wettersteinspitze" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Osprey Exos or Osprey Levity - Which Backpack to Get?]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-14T12:24:50+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With Osprey offering two (four if you include the female models!) lightweight backpacks which share a similar construction the Question arises: Which backpack should I get? With this wee article I’ll try to help you answer that question!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932158287/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos vs Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4785/25932158287_9162e6ac1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Exos vs Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from Osprey. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>If you’re a fan of lots of details and video, just go take a cup of ☕️ and maybe even some 🍫 and then watch this video:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rt6pKmvtGXA?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The Exos and Eja (the Eja being the Women’s Model) have been for many years super popular lightweight backpacks from Osprey. As the original Exos came out some six or seven years ago a big Roar went through the Ultralight community (it was more Niche back then =) and there were those that liked them &amp; used them and those who thought they’re too heavy. In 2018 the Exos is a well-established and liked pack, and as I said in my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review.html">Osprey Levity Review</a>: With Osprey packs hanging in stores around the globe it’s a lot easier to try on a pack and see if it fits you. I still think it is the perfect pack to introduce people to lightweight rucksacks and ultralight backpacking, so I’m really happy that these packs exist.</p>

<p>But there are several features which set these two packs apart (<em>Dear Women: Please excuse that I refer now only to the male packs. The Eja and Exos have all the same features but the Eja has a Women’s Specific Fit. Everything I write about the Exos also applies to the Eja, I’m just lazy writing Exos &amp; Eja the whole time!</em> =). Lets look at them via this easy <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vRD-l0X_-z9A-Ao3t4bmJX9UuATTLncTNQ1BjO4U1ds20nTyc5ZEapuyreha4OZRap3Q3gmqzoV5s2V/pubhtml">Table I made</a>:</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vRD-l0X_-z9A-Ao3t4bmJX9UuATTLncTNQ1BjO4U1ds20nTyc5ZEapuyreha4OZRap3Q3gmqzoV5s2V/pubhtml" title="Osprey Exos vs Levity vs Eja"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4783/40804038981_3683f77cdf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="492" alt="Osprey Exos vs Levity vs Eja" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I think besides the weight and price, which are easy to see in this table, it’s also to remind oneself that the Exos will likely be a tad more durable than the Levity and should carry a few kilogram more in comfort, due to the thicker shoulder straps and the longer &amp; more cushioned hipbelt. The Exos also has a plethora of options to attach and carry gear externally on the pack, something that the Levity is missing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932157207/in/dateposted/" title="Shoulder Straps Eja vs Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4795/25932157207_fdc970e15e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Straps Eja vs Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932158717/in/dateposted/" title="Material Differences"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4781/25932158717_1dab92fe55_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Material Differences" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932159357/in/dateposted/" title="Hipbelts!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4782/25932159357_3b11148591_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hipbelts!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Levity on the other hand has it’s light weight going for it - it’s after all 421 g lighter than an Exos. I also found it a plenty comfortable pack for a week of backpacking, but that’s me. I also really liked the simplicity of the pack - not a lot of extra straps and things, stuff which I generally don’t use and so don’t need.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39894513801" title="On the way to a Loch"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4619/39894513801_6506290024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the way to a Loch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Generally however I think that with the lower price, light weight and rich features of the Exos and Eja the majority of people are better off with these packs than the Levity. With 90€ cheaper than an Levity it’s a much easier investment into a new pack (and lets be honest, it’s nice to buy a high-quality piece of kit and not spend over 200 or 300€ for it!) and gives you some money to go on a weekend trip. If only the lightest Osprey pack will do, however, then it’s obviously the Levity one should go for!</p>

<p><em>Support this blog for no additional costs to you and buy your pack via one of these links.</em> In North America order your <a href="http://bit.ly/2FBmlNX">Exos</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2Gk9tgs">Eja</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/2GjS3R9">Levity</a> at these retailers, while in Europe you can buy your Osprey packs at Bergfreunde: <a href="http://bit.ly/2Dliu5M">Exos</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2FDoJnv">Eja</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/2BrfOml">Levity</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Questions?</strong> Hit me up in the comments underneath or ask on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a>!</p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1704" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731704" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1704"></script>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ski-touring in the Salzburger Lungau]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/skitouring-in-the-salzburger-lungau.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-06T12:08:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/skitouring-in-the-salzburger-lungau</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not far away from the busy streets of Munich you can find Austrian hospitality, empty mountains full of powder snow and warm Saunas to relax in after a day of skiing. After the ISPO I went to the Salzburger Lungau region with my brother and enjoyed a few relaxed days in this hidden gem of Austria, enjoying an untracked experience.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608666222/in/dateposted/" title="Snowy me"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4653/40608666222_60551ec0d7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy me" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Salzburger Lungau Tourism who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.lungau.at">Salzburger Lungau</a> Region is a mere couple of hours away from Munich, and unless you try to drive there on the start of some German holiday you can be in as little as one and half hours by car from Munich in the Lungau - in our case we stayed in the picturesque village of St. Margarethen in the <a href="https://www.grizzly-resort.at">Grizzly Resort Sport Hotel</a>, which is located at the base of the ski slopes. The Hotel staff expected us much later and was surprised when we walked in a bit before 20 o’clock! We checked into our rooms, had a quick shower and then it was down to the restaurant to enjoy some tasty Austrian food.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39754614095/in/dateposted/" title="Grizzly Resort"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4787/39754614095_e0ccd565f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grizzly Resort" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840366340/in/dateposted/" title="Main"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4604/38840366340_c94c6bc14c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Main" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After Dinner I went out to photograph the stars, but soon I was so cold that I wanted to only get back inside and sleep! And as we had a long day in front of us, that’s what I did!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779732717/in/dateposted/" title="Nightfall 2"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4798/25779732717_d9566b7e14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Nightfall 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840229010/in/dateposted/" title="Night on the slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4616/38840229010_932c3308ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night on the slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="ski-touring-to-the-seekpfl">Ski-touring to the Seeköpfl</h2>

<p>The next morning <a href="http://www.geführte-skitouren.at">Albert Essl</a> picked us up at the Hotel. We met Albert already two years ago when we were visiting the Salzburger Lungau in 2016 and enjoyed his guiding and company, so it was great to meet him again and go for a ski tour together.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39940867914/in/dateposted/" title="Skining up"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4781/39940867914_1d45acbd00_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skining up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40650163171/in/dateposted/" title="Albert leading the way"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4650/40650163171_182336eeae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert leading the way" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840247990/in/dateposted/" title="Views!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4801/38840247990_19766187a4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Albert picked for us an easy tour for our first day, to the beautiful Seeköpfl summit. We started at a parking lot where we left the car and after a few hundred meters of walking we were stepping into our bindings and beginning to skin up. Over a narrow road we ascended deep into the forest. I really like the skinning up part of ski-touring, it’s relaxing and enjoyable for me to skin up through the forest, observe how the trees get fewer and fewer and then coming out into the open, with wide, majestic views in all directions. We were very lucky with the weather, too: Sunshine and a blue sky - it was a perfect day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39754694155/in/dateposted/" title="Albert"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4795/39754694155_d7c2bf38f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779169088/in/dateposted/" title="DPS Alchemist + conTour skins"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4613/26779169088_6316d94829_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Alchemist + conTour skins" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225604197/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Happy Seeköpfl Summit Selfie."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4652/25225604197_d3b52ff2a6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happy Seeköpfl Summit Selfie." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a couple of hours we stood at the summit of the Seeköpfl, the sun shining down on us. We were happy, it was a beautiful day, we were outside in nature, and now a nice descent waited for us - or so we thought! The ride down was pretty icy with only a few patches of good snow, and at the end there were the dreaded narrow and icy forest roads back to the car. Ah well, there was snow in the forecast so it will be better soon!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779172888/in/dateposted/" title="Dropping in!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4668/26779172888_41012d8036_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dropping in!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608587112/in/dateposted/" title="On the edge"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4667/40608587112_1417ba3c78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the edge" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39754697965/in/dateposted/" title="Grass Interloop"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4618/39754697965_b17a4e8a38_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grass Interloop" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840312650/in/dateposted/" title="Finding a way"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4606/38840312650_3a96096aed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Finding a way" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840315690/in/dateposted/" title="Shredding"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4752/38840315690_7409dfbf55_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shredding" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the skiing part of the day my brother and me quickly developed a good routine: Chilling on the rooms for a bit‚ then down to the Sauna, then getting dressed and off to Dinner. It was a pretty good Sauna at the Hotel, and it’s nice that in the Southern countries they often have a wee Bar with juices, water, nuts and tea where you can drink &amp; eat a bite during Sauna turns.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779292038/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy sauna"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4740/26779292038_d7a3fd2195_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy sauna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608648372/in/dateposted/" title="Dessert"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4782/40608648372_d0e4b8c929_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dessert" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="skiing-on-the-katschberg-aineck">Skiing on the Katschberg-Aineck</h2>

<p>The next morning I looked out of the window and it was grey and white. The clouds were low and it was snowing a little, but the snow should really start dumping in the afternoon. Hence my brother and me decided to ride the <a href="http://katschi.at/pistenplaene.html">Katschberg-Aineck</a> ski slopes, and with a chair lift in front of the hotel we didn’t have a long way to get there, either! It’s a big ski region with 70 km of slopes and 16 lifts, and you can have days and days of fun here. We enjoyed the A1 slope the most, as it offers some superb views on the valley, as you’ll see from the photos. A benefit of skiing on the slopes is also that you can eat in one of the huts, and it is something I always like to do, with the tasty Germknödel being my lunch of choice! Another benefit of skiing on the slopes is that you just ride down to your hotel and then can be in the Sauna in a matter of minutes 💦🔥👍</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779832427/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Up &amp; down"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4649/25779832427_5dff75e42a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up &amp; down" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40650091891/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Silverjet"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4707/40650091891_4e872d6246_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Silverjet" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779826537/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snow?!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4667/25779826537_25f508f398_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow?!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779234848/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Shredding again"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4740/26779234848_5466e5279a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shredding again" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779244348/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Germknödel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4772/26779244348_5250f1ab28_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Germknödel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="exploring-schnfeld-and-the-nockberge">Exploring Schönfeld and the Nockberge</h2>

<p>The next morning it indeed was still dumping snow, and the forecasted 80 cm of fresh powder seemed very realistic. After a tasty breakfast we went outside to clean the car, and boy was it snowed in! After we almost dug out the car we took off towards the Nockberge, a truly hidden gem of the Salzburger Lungau.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39940945044/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snow!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4708/39940945044_b8f8c91281_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39940953404/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy roads"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4708/39940953404_76daea129a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy roads" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Even when the road was cleared that same morning by the time we were on our way to the Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte another 5 cm of pow ❄️❄️❄️ was on the street and my brother was concerned if we’d actually make it back - there was a rather steep road to get up on the way back. But that was none of my worry right now, I just loved the truly white and snowy surroundings we were in.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40650309221/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy rivver"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4758/40650309221_8dbff37f6f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy rivver" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We made it to the beautiful Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte, parked the car and stepped into our bindings. Our goal was the Matehanshöhe, another easy tour, and given that there was a high Avalanche Danger with the fresh snow we wanted something that was safe and easy. The ascent went for the first part via the closed ski slope and then along a ridge till the summit, though as my brother is not used to so deep powder we decided to cut the tour a bit short, not make for the summit and head back down and enjoy the powder!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608686102/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy huts"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4606/40608686102_81932469c8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy huts" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779877787/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy us"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4795/25779877787_8e2dcafddf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy us" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608683592/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snow till the knee"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4744/40608683592_f04c2c787e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow till the knee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the trip we enjoyed a lunch of Kaiserschmarrn at the hut before safely making it back to the Hotel in the afternoon, with plenty of time to pack, go to the Sauna and enjoy Dinner. Alas, this was our last evening together, and our short trip to the beautiful mountains of Austria were almost over again. I guess we’ll return again, as there’s still so many powdery summits and beautiful views we’d like to see!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39940990614/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy rocks"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4697/39940990614_76782a9f67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy rocks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840407350/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy signs"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4797/38840407350_3b44514677_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy signs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-there-and-where-to-stay">How to get there and where to stay</h2>

<p>You can <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/service/arrival/">travel by train and bus to the Salzburger Lungau</a> to it is the most easiest to arrive by car. A rental car for a week can cost around as little as 120€ and allows you to get around really easy in the region, which is almost mandatory if you want to go ski-touring.</p>

<p>There’s <a href="http://booking.lungau.at/lungau/en/accommodation/list?customHeader=true">over 700 accommodation options</a> in the Salzburger Lungau, with something for every budget level (<em>It makes sense to check out the <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/accommodation/package-offers/">Package Offers</a> where you often can safe quite nicely</em>). We stayed at the <a href="https://www.grizzly-resort.at/hotel/">Grizzly Resort Sport Hotel</a>, a very relaxed and high-quality 4 ⭐️ Hotel right next to the ski slopes. We can completely recommend the hotel with its tasty breakfast buffet, relaxing Spa &amp; Sauna, comfortable and spacious rooms and delicious 3-Course Menus in the evening.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779822147/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Timelapse in motion"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4695/25779822147_1cdc038f5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Timelapse in motion" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you want to go <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/active/your-winter-holiday/ski-touring-and-freeriding/">ski-touring</a> and don’t want to go on your own give <a href="http://www.geführte-skitouren.at">Albert Essl</a> a call and let him show you the best powder stashes and most amazing views. Albert is a superb Guide and skier who also can give you great tips on how to improve your powder skiing. If you prefer the slopes then ski the <a href="http://www.katschi.at">Katschi</a> slopes - with 70 km of slopes you’re busy for a day or seven to explore them all!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3SeI98ZaSRA&amp;t=450s">Watch the Vlog</a>, view <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157663383796697">more photos on Flickr</a>, check out my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/packing-for-ski-touring.html">Ski-Touring Pack List</a> and if you have questions - comment here or on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>!</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3SeI98ZaSRA?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><em>Enjoyed these articles? Then read my summer trip reports from the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/family-adventures-in-vorarlberg.html">Vorarlberg</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/family-adventures-in-the-bregenzerwald.html">Bregenzerwald</a> to get into the mood for hiking!</em></p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1698" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731698" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1698"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 281]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/twir-281.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-02T21:06:49+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/twir-281</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Simplicity is the key to brilliance.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/2EGsKu9">Dieter Rams</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39677552495/in/dateposted/" title="A sign of hope."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4670/39677552495_b77e94ef01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A sign of hope." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-news">Outdoor News</h2>

<p><a href="https://sweepingthegarden.wordpress.com/2018/02/19/sitting-not-doing/">Sitting. Not Doing</a>.</p>

<p>Yama Mountain Gear has launched their first backpack, the <a href="https://www.yamamountaingear.com/sassafras-20/">Sassafras 20</a>. If you want one, be quick as there’s 25% off on the first 25 orders of the pack!</p>

<p>There’s a new Tarptent coming, the <a href="https://www.tarptent.com/notchli.html">Notch Li</a>.</p>

<p>Nine days left to get a <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/557157975/the-rogue-packraft/">Kokopelli Rogue Packraft</a> on Kickstarter.</p>

<p>And Six Moons Designs comes out with a new backpack, <a href="https://www.sixmoondesigns.com/blogs/news/the-minimalist-new-for-2018">The Minimalist</a>.</p>

<p>I’m proud to announce that <a href="http://www.drobo.com/hendrik-morkel/">I am a Drobo Explorer</a>. Stay tuned for a video on why I like the Drobo 5D3. And if you are going to the <a href="https://www.photographyshow.com/registration">Photography Show</a> at NEC in Birmingham you can take £3 off your ticket with the code “DROBTPS18”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/feb/28/britain-national-parks-reclaim-rewild">Britain’s national parks are a farce</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://lighterpacks.com/2018/02/17/the-hypocrisy-of-leave-no-trace/">The hypocrisy of Leave No Trace</a>.</p>

<p>If you rely on Facebook for traffic, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2018/02/28/littlethings">consider this story</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/s/story/are-we-post-lifestyle-699ff6023cb8">Instagram is littered with #sponsored posts</a> and the same photos over and over again. Time to leave?</p>

<p>The <a href="https://climbinggearreviewsuk.wordpress.com/2018/03/01/british-brand-finisterre-attains-b-corp-status/">British Brand Finisterre attains B Corp status</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/news/bikepacker-and-bikepacking/">Bikepacker and BIKEPACKING.com have joined forces</a> - congratulations!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/sj7va8" title="Bergzeit-Gewinnspiel-Orotovox-Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/38823529180_3c431e8d72.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit-Gewinnspiel-Orotovox-Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Ortovox makes some great gear, and some of that you can win in this competition. You <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">just have to answer one question</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0z0ue9" title="Bergzeit-Alpincamp-Edelrid-Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4648/39923537564_6052131396.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit-Alpincamp-Edelrid-Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And here’s a competition for the climbers, where you can win a rope, harness and some more goodies by <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/edelrid-ambassador-line/">sharing a great climbing photo</a>.</p>

<p>If you need a pack for a quick overnighter, peak bagging or a leisurely day hike check out the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=d5c7f197-d13c-4793-943a-b6eda64b8f09&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.ula-equipment.com%2Fproduct%2Ffastpack%2F">ULA Equipment Fastpack</a>.</p>

<p>Spring is coming, and with it the rain. Time to get <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=47cd1998-e608-4548-aa0f-3d33e964ad3a&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.hyperlitemountaingear.com%2Fthe-shell.html">The Shell</a> from Hyperlite Mountain Gear, a 146 g light hardshell.</p>

<p>And lots of garments and gear at <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/outlet/outdoor-clothing/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> are up to 60% off, so check your closet if you need something for the next season.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GwfICDPBYNE&amp;feature=youtu.be">Vlog 002</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3SeI98ZaSRA&amp;t=450s">Vlog 003</a> are online, check them out!</p>

<p>Cam helps you planning your <a href="https://www.thehikinglife.com/2018/02/arthur-range-traverse-planning-guide/">Arthur Range Traverse</a> in Tasmania.</p>

<p>Go to Italy and bikepack on the <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/alta-via-dei-monti-liguri/">Alta Via dei Monti Liguri</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://lesserplaces.com/2018/02/19/max-bites-off-more-than-he-can-chew/">Max bites off more than he can chew</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://live.editiondigital.com/review/e/17cdvpvgq/1448180214#!page80">Ski-touring the Graubünden Haute-Route</a>.</p>

<p>Bikepacking in Colombia, from <a href="http://www.highlux.co.nz/2018/02/mompox-san-antonio/">Mompox to San Antonio</a>.</p>

<p>Stephen hikes the <a href="https://howlingmist.blogspot.com/2018/02/the-coumloughra-horseshoewinter.html">Coumloughra Horseshoe</a> in winter.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_JT1NmtMqPY?rel=0&amp;controls=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/morocco-traverse-south/">Bikepacking through Morocco</a>.</p>

<p>Ben goes <a href="https://bencollinsoutdoors.com/2018/02/25/mountain-climbing-in-tasmania-2018/">Mountain Climbing in Tasmania</a>.</p>

<p>All the info you could need in this <a href="https://mbguiding.ca/lake-ohara-yoho-national-park/">Lake O’Hara Trail Guide</a>.</p>

<p>My friend David tries <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lQeVwW6IUH0">Indian Street Food in in Chandni Chowk</a>.</p>

<p>Henryk goes <a href="https://www.oooyeah.de/skitouring-kitzbueheleralpen-teil2/">skitouring in Tirol</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cedarandsand.blogspot.com/2018/02/the-tushars-crushed.html">Utah’s Tushar Mountains</a>, crushed.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZRTNHDd0gL8?rel=0&amp;controls=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>A first look at the <a href="https://youtu.be/SHlUEBE6f8c">Sigma 16 mm f/ 1.4</a>, me new wide-angle lens.</p>

<p>Magnets in your jacket? <a href="https://www.grough.co.uk/magazine/2018/02/14/flip-experts-warn-new-clothing-trend-could-be-fatal-attraction-for-your-compass">Probably your compass doesn’t like that</a>.</p>

<p>Chris uses <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2018/02/just-one-lens-photography-gear-post.html">just one Lens</a>.</p>

<p>Get to know <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/bikes/peppers-tumbleweed-prospector/">Pepper Cook and her basketpacking Tumbleweed Prospector</a>.</p>

<p>Matthias reviews the <a href="https://quasiout.de/kovea-supalite-titanium-stove-im-test-ein-ultraleichter-gaskocher-nur-fuer-die-kleine-tour/">Kovea Supalite Titanium Stove</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Kathrin reviews the <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/msr-hubba-nx-erfahrungsbericht/">MSR Hubba NX</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Alex shares tips for <a href="http://www.bergreif.de/2018/02/19/naehtipps-fuer-outdoorausruestung/">sewing your first own backpack</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Drew reviews the <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2018/02/27/gear-review-cascade-mountain-tech-carbon-fiber-quick-lock-trekking-poles/">Cascade Mountain Tech Carbon Fiber Quick Lock Trekking Poles</a>.</p>

<p>Kai shares his first insights on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8P5irosYUnA&amp;feature=youtu.be">Sony A7 III</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2018/02/shafted.html">Shafted</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/nordisk-lofoten-2ulw.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-15T12:54:01+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/nordisk-lofoten-2ulw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is light always right? The Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW tent is one of the lightest double-wall two-person tents on the market, but is it really a 2 Person tent and as light as claimed?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36217591645/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Side view"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4301/36217591645_4c05e4c963_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Side view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>I got this tent for free from Nordisk but was under no obligation to review it. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35824649320/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4309/35824649320_f7b76da9fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On paper the Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW sounds great: 575 g packed weight, sleeps two, super-small pack size. From these three claims only one holds true, though: It has a very great small pack size. Going ultralight does for me not only means to pay attention to the weight, but also to the size of the kit I take. And pack size-wise the Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW definitely would be a tent I’d like to take with me, but then there’s a few things which make me think like <strong>STOP</strong>, <em>don’t do it.</em> Have a look at the video to see how the tent is pitched and how it looks on the inside:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CrL9dzXJAT0?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>So my problem with the tent is that it’s pretty small. Even with a better pitch I don’t think the inner would hang much better than it did in my first pitch, and the foot end is so narrow that I definitely would touch the inner with my feet or quilt. As the photos show, it’s also definitely not a tent for 2 persons, which is OK if you go Solo. Going on your own also would solve another problem of this tent: Storage room for gear. The Lofoten 2ULW has no vestibule space so your pack and other gear needs to come inside. With two people that’d be impossible (or barely possible if you’re on a running event?) so going Solo in it at least gives you some space for your kit. Even the optional Tarp pole with which you can put the door up and so create some space for gear would not solve this in my opinion.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36051402742/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Foot space"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4296/36051402742_737f8d8db8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Foot space" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35382518354/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Lying inside"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4300/35382518354_8ed8f8bcb8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Lying inside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36051402072/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="No room for gear"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4301/36051402072_c8a41893db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="No room for gear" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Lets take a look at the weight then:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Main Pole 131 g</li>
  <li>End Pole 18 g</li>
  <li>5 Pegs incl. Pouch 55 g</li>
  <li>Inner &amp; Outer 372 g</li>
  <li>Pack Pouch for the Tent 30 g</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>TOTAL 587 g</strong></p>

<p>Add in another 96 g for the optional extras, like titanium skewer pegs at 2 g each, guylines, the tarp pole, repair stuff and other things. Which means it’s a wee bit over the claimed packed weight of 575 g, and how one could achieve the 490 g weight is a riddle to me as alone the two poles and fly + inner together are over 500 g, and then you don’t have any pegs yet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36051396272/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Poles &amp; pegs"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4326/36051396272_0ed69e4b38_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Poles &amp; pegs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The ventilation also looks not optimal, but as I haven’t yet slept in the tent I can not comment on the condensation in it. Speaking of sleeping in it, I’m actually not at all sure if I want to use the tent: If it is dry &amp; clear I prefer to sleep under the stars, and if it is wet &amp; rainy I do prefer more space - especially to change out of wet clothes and relax in the tent while it is raining outside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35824649620/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Hi there, tiny tent!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4328/35824649620_ffb3bc3c1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hi there, tiny tent!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It could be that the Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW simply isn’t made for ultralight backpacking but for adventure races like the OMM and similar. On these events people need to carry a tent and apparently would even squeeze together into a <em>“2 Person tent”</em> like the Lofoten 2ULW. I, myself, simply am excited about the pack size of the tent, but not really about taking the tent on a trip. But who knows, maybe I give the tent a chance at some fine, dry and warm day where it will mean protection from mosquitos and where I can sleep with all my kit inside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35382495774/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Packsize"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4314/35382495774_3cfbeb288f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packsize" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong> is that while I haven’t slept in the tent the pack size is the only thing which currently has me excited about it. It’s very small on the inside and I’m not sure if it would be any comfortable in pro-longed rain, add in that there’s no space for your gear on the outside (Hello soaking wet shoes, hope you like lying next to my quilt!) and it feels like here a company and it’s designers were only aiming at breaking a record (<em>Lightest tent on the market!</em>) and lost track of what really matters in a good tent. As it is the Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW is just a <em>Meh</em> tent for me, but maybe if I have used it a few times my opinion will change. <strong>Have you used this tent, or would you use it for a backpacking trip? Let me know in the comments!</strong></p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-pricecompare.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=11212" type="text/javascript" id="outtrapricecomparewdgt17311212" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapcwdgt="11212"></script>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 280]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/twir-280.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-11T22:28:09+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/twir-280</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Blue, White, Happiness.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225604977/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="What a view!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4626/25225604977_655d42d5c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="What a view!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p>The first annual <a href="https://kdsoloaward.wordpress.com">Kyle Dempster Solo Adventure Award</a> is open for applications.</p>

<p>There was <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/02/2018-ispo-impressions.html">no new gear at ISPO 2018</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bunterwegs.com/inspirierende-frauen-outdoor/">12 inspiring outdoor women</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Become a <a href="http://eveningsends.com/becoming-a-better-climber-in-2018/">better climber in 2018</a>.</p>

<p>Zack shares his thoughts on <a href="http://dedpxl.com/unsplash-an-interview-with-mikael-cho/">Unsplash</a>.</p>

<p>Dan wants that you <a href="http://danbaileyphoto.com/blog/dont-fall-into-this-trap-with-your-photography/">don’t fall into this Trap with your Photography</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://theconversation.com/is-it-possible-for-everyone-to-live-a-good-life-within-our-planets-limits-91421">Is it possible for everyone to live a good life within our planet’s limits</a>?</p>

<p>While the USA made National Monuments smaller Tompkins Conservation and Chile made history with the <a href="https://youtu.be/0_wedyEllOM">Patagonia and Pumalín Park Donation Ceremony</a>.</p>

<p>Meet the <a href="http://dirtbagdiaries.com/punk-rockers-ski-mountaineering/">Punk Rockers of Ski Mountaineering</a>.</p>

<p>I think I’ll need to go visit the <a href="http://www.agnesdenesstudio.com/works4.html">Tree Mountain</a> here in Finland later this year.</p>

<p>This Land Is Our Land: <a href="http://www.kenilgunas.com/2018/01/this-land-is-our-land-haters-welcome.html">Haters Welcome</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/01/13/opinion/sunday/keep-our-mountains-free-and-dangerous.html">Keep Our Mountains Free. And Dangerous</a>.</p>

<p>The Top <a href="https://www.adventure-journal.com/2018/01/top-10-bad-backcountry-habits-2/">10 Bad Backcountry Skiing Habits</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> has up to 60% off on <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/outlet/outdoor-equipment/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">outdoor equipment</a> and <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/outlet/outdoor-clothing/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">clothing</a>.</p>

<p>At <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=264573&amp;pw=73183">REI’s Winter Clearance Sale</a> you can save up to 50% on Clothing, Outerwear, and Winter Boots.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">The Semiannual Sale at Backcountry.com</a> is on, save up to 50% on Clothing, Gear, and Accessories.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/254570436?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Win a pants and jacket from <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">Black Yak</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/8U3G8p" title="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_Black Yak_Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4669/25350267467_d2050bcee2.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_Black Yak_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Love XC skiing? Take part in <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/bergzeit-frischluft-kick-mit-fischer-zum-langlaufen-livigno/">this competition</a> and win a trip to go skiing in Livigno.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/tSD793" title="Bergzeit_Frischluft Kick_Fischer_Livigno_Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4611/26348538428_bd8d206704.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit_Frischluft Kick_Fischer_Livigno_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A really cool <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/ortovox-safety-package/">Avalanche Security Set</a> from Ortovox you can win in this competition.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/C199PS" title="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Ortovox_Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4668/39323263195_12bb91bcff.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Ortovox_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And if Freeride Skiing is your cup of tea <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/alpincamp/millet-freeride-arlberg/">enter this competition</a> to head to the Arlberg with Millet!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/7o3UUk" title="Bergzeit_Alpincamp_Millet_Google"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4660/26348538808_e37bbc1a78.jpg" width="497" height="279" alt="Bergzeit_Alpincamp_Millet_Google" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="https://emmakarjalainen.com/2018/01/19/the-perfect-winter-warrior-weekend-to-repovesi-national-park/">The Perfect Winter Warrior Weekend to Repovesi National Park</a>.</p>

<p>Some <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau.html">impressions from skitouring and skiing in the Salzburger Lungau</a>.</p>

<p>Agnieszka backpacks on the <a href="http://acrossthewilderness.blogspot.fi/2018/02/finlandia-peuranpolku-i-park-narodowy.html">Peuranpolku</a>! [Polish]</p>

<p>Jill <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2018/02/jump-into-fog.html">jumps into the fog</a> and it looks pretty.</p>

<p>Read Alex’s <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2018/01/in-pursuit-of-perfection-the-lochaber-traverse.html">Lochaber Traverse</a>.</p>

<p>Kathrin goes <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/bergwanderungen-westaustralien/">hiking in the West Australian Mountains</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.johnhayeswalks.com/2018/01/winter-cycling-in-morocco.html">Winter Cycling in Morocco</a> sounds fun.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lxtWMOAHoiI?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.highlux.co.nz/2018/02/bikepacking-cubas-ruta-mala/">Bikepacking Cuba’s La Ruta Mala</a> will have you wanting to go to Cuba.</p>

<p>Stefanie goes <a href="https://www.gipfel-glueck.de/rofanspitze-schneeschuh-erfurter-huette/">snowshoe backpacking</a> in the Rofan Mountains. [German]</p>

<p>Joe sends greetings <a href="https://joecruz.wordpress.com/2018/02/09/tasmania-postcard/">from Tasmania</a>.</p>

<p>Peter spent a night <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2018/02/winter-in-kurjenrahka-national-park.html">in the Kurjenrahka National Park</a>.</p>

<p>Paulina hikes to <a href="https://www.littlegrunts.com/heart-lake-mount-shasta/">Hiking Heart Lake, Mount Shasta</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://smokyscout.blogspot.fi/2018/01/patagonia-2017-french-valley-dia-diaz.html">The French Valley - Día Diaz</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28368278689/in/dateposted/" title="PICTURE"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4652/28368278689_5a190e00fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PICTURE" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>A look at the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hxMWPLzamxY">Marker Alpinist Binding</a>.</p>

<p>Sporks are yesterday, you say? Then check out the small <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=358fd954-c6b8-44a1-9ca9-aaad445d2dfb&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.campsaver.com%2Fsnow-peak-titanium-mini-fork.html">Snow Peak Mini Titanium Fork</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.thehikinglife.com/2018/02/hammocks-for-thru-hiking/">Hammocks for Thru-Hiking</a>.</p>

<p>Philipp shares his impressions of the <a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2018/02/barracuda-r2-pro-first-impression.html">Barracuda R2 Pro</a> packraft. [German]</p>

<p>A look at the <a href="http://www.goout.hk/2018/01/19/ifyouhave-hug-backpack/">ifyouhave ‘hug’ Backpack</a>. [Chinese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/bikes/trek-1120-review/">Trek 1120</a> Review.</p>

<p>Chad takes a first look at the <a href="https://sticksblog.com/2018/01/27/altra-lone-peak-3-5-first-look/">Altra Lone Peak 3.5 shoes</a> while Andrew <a href="https://andrewskurka.com/2018/preview-altra-lone-peak-40-trail-shoe/">previews the Altra Lone Peak 4.0</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergreif.de/2018/01/29/wandern-mit-trail-running-schuhen/">Hiking with trailrunning shoes</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Are you <a href="http://blog.trailcooking.com/2018/02/09/craving-pizza-backpacking/">craving Pizza While Backpacking</a>?</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2018/01/31/winter-or-2018-new-gear-awards/">Winter OR 2018: New Gear Awards</a>.</p>

<p>And have a look at Drew’s <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2018/01/28/11-highlights-from-the-2018-winter-outdoor-retailer/">11 Highlights From The 2018 Winter Outdoor Retailer</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=676921&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/15661/676921/55699/73183/image.png" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2018 ISPO Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/2018-ispo-impressions.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-08T12:06:31+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/2018-ispo-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every year again I make the same mistake: I head to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/02/ispo-2017.html">ISPO</a> in Munich.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115657482/in/dateposted/" title="NEVER STOP EXPLORING"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4611/40115657482_ac715100a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="NEVER STOP EXPLORING" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy this &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors, and your contribution helps keeping the articles coming!</em></p>

<p>Yes, I really do not like the ISPO. It’s a necessary evil one has to attend if you’re in this business, and should the summer OutDoor fair move to Munich I’ll probably just boycott it, there’s just so much big city I can take. Anyway, we don’t need to talk about crappy cities in even worse German states, because there’s of course also upsides to the ISPO. Namely all the people you meet, from the wonderful bloggers like <a href="http://hrxxlight.com">Benjamin</a>, <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de">Kathrin</a>, <a href="http://ulligunde.com">Erika</a>, <a href="https://st-bergweh.de">Björn</a>, <a href="https://bergtouren-im-allgaeu.de">Björn</a> and <a href="https://www.auf-den-berg.de">Uli</a>, to name just a few, to the amazing companies. I scaled down meetings this year and didn’t run around from 9:00 in the morning till 18:00 o’clock in the evening, but was very selective in where I went. This did allow me to see a bit more than in the past of the fair, and one thing which immideately became apparent: A lot of brands were missing from the fair. The Messe Munich tried to cover this up by adding crappy <em>Showcases</em> in the middle of almost every exhibition hall. Imagine these as not very pretty small “exhibitions” where they tried to show you the same stuff you can see in the neighbouring booths. There were also a lot less people at the fair, especially on Sunday and Tuesday the hallways were nice and empty, only on Monday morning it was really busy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115660662/in/dateposted/" title="The Best for the Worst"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4666/40115660662_03a95d095a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Best for the Worst" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the positive side: While in the past years a lot of companies have talked about how environmentally friendly, social and sustainable they are this year was the first time that many of these companies were actually showing off truly good sustainable &amp; socially made products. From down jackets which are made from recycled down (down from old Duvets and pillows, which are cleaned and then re-used) and recycled shell &amp; liner materials, to garments which you can recycle completely at the end of their life-cycle. What keeps on surprising me with these developments is how you’ll visit Company A in the morning and Company B, Company C and Company D will show you during the rest of the day pretty much identical garments with almost identical stories. It does mean what felt like an innovation in the morning already feels old in the afternoon. I reckon it is because the ingredient brands (the ones who make the insulation, liner, shell and other materials - think companies like Polartec, PrimaLoft, Pertex and so on) will offer their new fabrics and technologies to all the companies which make garments out of them, and so you see almost the same thing from one company to the next one.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115659222/in/dateposted/" title="DPS Phantom"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4751/40115659222_78c2872504_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Phantom" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115659892/in/dateposted/" title="SBlocs Cargo Bike"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4720/40115659892_5b5a2abb36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="806" alt="SBlocs Cargo Bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39436790524/in/dateposted/" title="Marker Alpinist"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4698/39436790524_8b860fcba7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marker Alpinist" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115656162/in/dateposted/" title="Long Live the Product"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4748/40115656162_63848cb524_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Long Live the Product" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Happily there are honorable expections. From the <a href="https://www.dpsskis.com/phantom">DPS Phantom</a> permanent, one-time application base-coating to the most awesome and fantastic SBlocs eCargo Bike which I totally want to have (Hashtag #FuckCarsRideBikes), there were some innovations on the fair to be seen. I made a lot of videos of those which I found most interesting so I suggest you <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">subscribe to my Youtube channel</a> to see these, as this article here will likely be the only ISPO post I will make this year.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28368279399/in/dateposted/" title="BD Band"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4703/28368279399_d182ae8aef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="BD Band" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28368278439/in/dateposted/" title="Bar"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4666/28368278439_4ffbcb9acc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25276911507/in/dateposted/" title="Best Coffee was head at Patagonia"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4632/25276911507_37cfbaa082_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Best Coffee was head at Patagonia" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, what else? Reading and talking with fellow content creators and industry partners it becomes clear: The Outdoor Industry is in change, and the question if fairs like the ISPO and OutDoor are still necesary are becoming louder and louder. With costs of 20.000€ for just a small booth you can understand why brands are thinking if they need to be at these shows, because you could do a lot more useful things with such amounts of money. Yes, it’s nice to meet friends, network, and drink some beers toegether, but that are pretty expensive beers indeed. I don’t know if it would help if every brand would make its own event as that would be even more of a time drain, but somehow these fairs need to up their game to stay relevant.</p>

<p>If this all sounds pretty negative - sorry. You just get jaded with these fairs at some point - this was my 5th ISPO - and it starts to feel that there’s just a handful of innovations, and not halls full of them anymore (maybe I didn’t look close enough, though). What does get better is brands and companies realize that we digital content creators are very valuable; as an example, Hiking in Finland has more readers than the two biggest German Outdoor Magazines <em>combined</em>. So you’re no longer seen as someone who might want a free pack or jacket, but as someone who has a very interested and targeted audience (<strong>YOU!</strong>), who talks their language and can show them the cool &amp; interesting stuff he has found on the fair. That’s pretty nice indeed and you can see this becoming better and better at each fair.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25276912267/in/dateposted/" title="10 Years On"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4766/25276912267_611a362990_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="10 Years On" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115658222/in/dateposted/" title="Houdini Shells &amp; Insulation"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4630/40115658222_470125f888_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Houdini Shells &amp; Insulation" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28368277719/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Alpha SK Pack"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4605/28368277719_ab04ce6fe3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Alpha SK Pack" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong> is that after the big-city-business-ISPO I am very much looking forward to the OutDoor in Friedrichshafen in June. The OutDoor has a much better vibe than the ISPO, it’s more relaxed, people are less sick (it’s pretty easy to catch a flu or worse at the ISPO because of the time of the year) and with the mountains and the lake in close proximity it’s just a lot more outdoorsy. And with the Blogger Base and really good programms made especially for us digital content creators (<em>Disclosure: I’m completely biased as with my other company we’re the partner of the Messe Friedrichshafen</em>) it feels just a lot better to be at the OutDoor than at the ISPO. So lets keep our 👍 and hope that the OutDoor will continue to be in Friedrichshafen (or if it moves, that it moves to Hamburg). <em>You can view more photos from the ISPO fair in the accompanying <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157665520832018">Flickr Album</a>.</em></p>

<p><em>You still don’t have enough? Then <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/archives/">browse through the Archive</a>, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions From the Salzburger Lungau]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-05T19:17:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the ISPO I did the only smart thing: Leave the city behind and head to Austria to go ski-touring. These are some first impressions from a too-short trip to the Salzburger Lungau Region.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225607357/in/dateposted/" title="Albert on the way to the summit of the Seeköpfl."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4620/25225607357_aa885b504c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert on the way to the summit of the Seeköpfl." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Salzburger Lungau Tourism who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225608777/in/dateposted/" title="St. Margarethen im Lungau"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4698/25225608777_5329e81066_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="St. Margarethen im Lungau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a very busy fair I met my brother and we made the trip down south to the <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/your-lungau/15-villages/?_wb=en/your-lungau/15-villages/&amp;lang=EN">Salzburger Lungau</a> Region, a place we have visited before and really liked. We arrived at our <a href="https://www.grizzly-resort.at">Hotel</a>, had a tasty dinner and then it was off to bed as early in the morning we would meet Albert again, our <a href="http://www.geführte-skitouren.at">Ski-touring Guide</a> with whom we had the pleasure to go skiing already in the past.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225601117/in/dateposted/" title="Start of the tour."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4770/25225601117_d228306e86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Start of the tour." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225604887/in/dateposted/" title="And what a view again!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4724/25225604887_f11df71d25_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And what a view again!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Albert had two other clients along and our little group was great, we had a lot of fun on the ascent and descent. It was a beautiful sunny day with great views - just the snow could have been a wee bit better.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225603587/in/dateposted/" title="Through the less-than-perfect snow down."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4761/25225603587_f2d6bb985b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Through the less-than-perfect snow down." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225603357/in/dateposted/" title="Albert showing how it&#x27;s done."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/25225603357_6a8f10e645_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert showing how it&#x27;s done." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The view from the Hotel wasn’t bad at all, either. We witnessed the #SuperBlueMoon rising behind the forest as we sat in the Sauna, not a bad place at all!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225606417/in/dateposted/" title="Timelapse."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4673/25225606417_0a106ea3e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Timelapse." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next day we hot the slopes. With a big ski resort right in front of the hotel it was not a long approach, and the skiing was good - though I really prefer soft snow on wild mountains. A good thing that a 80 cm dump of powder was forecast for the next day!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225605937/in/dateposted/" title="Snow? Yeps."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4760/25225605937_fa563906a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow? Yeps." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225610547/in/dateposted/" title="Germknödel, still a favourite meal of mine."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4614/25225610547_fa07863ea4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Germknödel, still a favourite meal of mine." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And so my brother and me headed again to the secluded Thomatal Valley and started from the Dr. Josef-Mehrl Hütte up into the mountains, not to be disappointed by the amount of snow.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225609357/in/dateposted/" title="The fantastic Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4666/25225609357_ef4df5c352_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The fantastic Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Stay tuned for the full trip-report in the next few weeks! In the meanwhile you already can take a look some more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157663383796697">Flickr Album</a> and on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Osprey Levity 45 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-25T20:47:27+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When a major-player in the backpacking market like Osprey decides to make an ultralight backpack you can be sure that there’s going to go a ripple through the scene. I was lucky enough to receive a Osprey Levity 45 backpack in August 2017 for testing and have put the pack through it’s paces in the last six months. <em>Here’s what I liked &amp; didn’t like about the new ultralight backpack from Osprey.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39890791831/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 Review"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4674/39890791831_cc49c75a3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 Review" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from Osprey. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>The Osprey Levity 45 is a great lightweight backpack which carries loads up to 10 kg in comfort. The Airspeed suspension back frame should be especially useful for hikes in hot environments, while the highly water-resistant material of the pack has kept my gear dry while backpacking for a week in Scotland. I would have wished the front and side pockets would have been more stretchy, but other than that this backpack is well made and should be an ideal choice for those who have used heavier backpacks in the past and look to lighten up. For all the details watch the video and read the review.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YhuugW019oI?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received my <a href="https://www.ospreyeurope.com/gb_en/ventilated-pinnacle-coming-soon/">Osprey Levity</a> 45 sample in August 2017 and had it along on a dozen day trips in autumn and winter, as well as a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/10/impressions-from-the-scottish-cairngorms.html">one week backpacking trip through the Cairngorms in Scotland</a>. All in all I have used it over 25 days.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39892290381/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 at Coire Etchachan Shelter, Cairngorms, Scotland"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4694/39892290381_121c47701a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 at Coire Etchachan Shelter, Cairngorms, Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The function of a backpack is to carry your gear in comfort from A to B. The idea behind an ultralight backpack is that it isn’t weighing 2+ kg empty, but significantly less, making the hiking part of a trip more comfortable. The backpack also should protect your gear from the elements and allow fast &amp; easy access to important pieces of gear which you need on the go.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36941189873/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Loch Etchachan"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4497/36941189873_4fe952cbaa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Loch Etchachan" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Straight out of the Levity and Lumina (the Lumina is the female version of this backpack, though it comes out in Europe first in 2019) Owner’s Manual, here’s the features of these pack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A fixed top lid with one zippered pocket</li>
  <li>Two removable side compression cords</li>
  <li>Dual access fabric side pockets</li>
  <li>Bellowed front fabric pocket</li>
  <li>Top lid cord loop attachment points</li>
  <li>Sternum strap with integrated safety whistle</li>
  <li>Internal main compartment compression strap</li>
</ul>

<p>The pack is made from two materials, the Main material is a 30D Silnylon Ripstop while the accents (that’s the lid, bottom, front and side-pockets) are made from a more durable NanoFly™ 100D Nylon x 100D UHMWPE Ripstop. The more durable material is a non-branded version of what other backpack makers sell at a premium as Dyneema or Cordura, and both materials seem to have a DWR coating.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26017236288/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Main Body Material"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4621/26017236288_38c7b5ab15_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Main Body Material" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>I’m hard pressed to give Osprey here any points: Ultralight backpacks have been around for many years, using equally or more advanced materials (like the material still commonly known as Cuben fibre, Silnylon, XPac and mixes thereof). I could say that the Airspeed frame, which allows for air circulation between your back and the main compartment of the pack, is an innovation in such a light pack.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018722777/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Side Pocket Material"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4602/25018722777_77b3c48823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Side Pocket Material" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The pack is well-made as you would expect from a brand like Osprey - they know their trade and how to make backpacks. So expect when you go to the store to get a Levity that it will hold up to many years of backpacking.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180104254/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Front &amp; Side View"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4756/39180104254_dace146f14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Front &amp; Side View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Levity 45 weighs 751 g in Size M. Please keep in mind that this is a pre-production model and the ones hitting the stores are expected to weigh 810 g on average!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018723817/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Shoulder Strap Detail 3"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4756/25018723817_aefa139dcd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Shoulder Strap Detail 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The Levity 45 is with its 45 l volume a good pack for long weekend trips or one week-long backpacking trips without resupplying, as in carrying all the food for one week. It’s going to be a tight fit at the beginning of a trip, even with a UL baseweight, but the more you eat the lighter it gets 😜. The main compartment swallows all my gear - shelter, bivy, mattress, quilt, stove, spare clothes and puffy jacket - with room to spare for food, an extra lens and the Mavic Pro Drone. The shoulder strap is not too wide, which means I can attach my <a href="https://youtu.be/3res6PXJySY">Capture Clip</a> to the pack and have my camera always at the ready.</p>

<p>When packing the backpack it’s important to pack smart, as the main compartment is not a round barrel but has two corners at the bottom which can stay empty if you don’t pack with a system - I stuff my bivy and some socks into these fins, and then come quilt, mattress, etc. If you don’t do that you’ll end up with empty space, and if you go out with a full week worths of food then that empty space might be needed. So pack smart! On the inside you also find a reservoir sleeve for a hydration system if that’s how you roll, I haven’t tried that as I use 1 l Platypus bottles and a Kuksa for water.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018722537/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Content for a weekend"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4626/25018722537_a06b2aa659_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Content for a weekend" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The side pockets as well as the front pocket (which is bellowed, that means it does expand a bit) are not stretchy, which means you’re limited in terms of how much gear you can stuff in them. Of course the pockets on the Levity are more durable than mesh, but if you like to carry some extra stuff on a trip that doesn’t fit into the main compartment then mesh outside pockets were usually there to accommodate that stuff, but not here. For that the Levity has some loops on the lid, to which you could attach some extra gear. I haven’t tried that, and also imagine it’d be difficult to attach some apples or other fruits to these loops 🍎🍉🍒😄.</p>

<p>Back to the pockets, these were fine to carry my water bottles, snacks, a big-ass tripod and extra clothes. The side pockets can be accessed from the top or the side, I can so for example get my Kuksa out of the side pocket when I want to drink and put it back in. As they don’t stretch it can sometimes be a bit difficult to stuff gear in the side pockets when the main compartment is already filled with your gear, so keep that in mind if you carry a tripod. The zippered lid pocket is fantastic, has a keychain hook inside, and swallows an incredible amount of gear - I carried my GR1 pocket with batteries and cables in it, plus some more stuff - all goin’ easily in there.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857991462/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 2"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4697/39857991462_c2f77e4024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Airspeed backpanel does it’s job well, with the aluminium frame keeping the mesh to your back and allowing for airflow. What I really like, though, are the shoulder straps and hipbelt. These have been really well designed and are very comfortable, also if the pack is fully loaded with 10+ kg of gear &amp; food. The foam which is wrapped by a mesh is pretty durable and adapts well to your shoulders and body, making for a comfortable carry all day long. The same goes for the hipbelt, which is pretty minimal but wrapped nicely around my hips and helped transfer the weight to them. I think the carrying frame system of the Levity 45 is very well made, and if you hike in very warm environments then I think this pack should be nice, as with the Airspeed backpanel and the airflow it allows it should possibly make you sweat less.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857989532/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel &amp; Frame"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/39857989532_a3e79958b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel &amp; Frame" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39890792031/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4621/39890792031_77ff9d08e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The side compression cords which are on the pack felt a bit useless to me, I still think that the compression system of the ULA Ohm is one of the best ones out there. The compression strap on the inside is a nice idea, but I tend to forget that the inside strap needs to be connected to the buckle on the inside, so sometimes I just don’t use it. The drawcord works well, though the point where the cord exists the fabric looks a bit weak to me and could be a point of failure.</p>

<p>The material of the Levity seems to have a DWR coating, especially the not transparent material with the white grid (<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180105634/in/dateposted/">see here</a>) kept the rain at bay, while the transparent material started to let some water seep through after a week in the Highlands. To be 100% safe I still would recommend to pack critical gear (quilt, down jacket, dry socks) in a waterproof drybag.</p>

<p><strong>Addition</strong>: Osprey informed me that the stretchy pockets have been fixed for production - these were updated from the sample pack I received. And the point where the drawcord exits the fabric has been reinforced for added durability, so this shouldn’t be an issue either.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39894513801/in/dateposted/" title="On the way to a Loch"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4619/39894513801_6506290024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the way to a Loch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I will repeat myself here, but: I wish Osprey would have made the side and front pockets more stretchy so one can easier get things in &amp; out of them or over-stuff them.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>I have reviewed half a dozen <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">backpacks</a> here and used probably more than triple the amount in the last 10 years, but there’s just a handful of UL packs which have a ventilated backpanel, like some of the ZPacks packs (which are a bit lighter but more expensive), and of course you just could go with the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-exos-46-backpack-2600-3000cu-in">Osprey Exos</a> which also has an Airspeed backpanel.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857991492/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 1"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4674/39857991492_a76aedbd31_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Does the market need another <em>ultralight</em> backpack? If that’s a question which is in your mind after you read this, let me say: Yes. We ultralight backpackers life in our own little UL Bubble, where we don’t see a problem with ordering a pack off the internet from a cottage manufacturer halfway across the globe - but we’re really not the majority. The Osprey Levity brings ultralight backpacks into the big stores and so in front of the eyes of thousands of outdoor enthusiasts who will love this pack - not only because they can choose from three different back lengths, but also because they <em>can try the pack on before they buy it!</em> I remember me ordering my first pack online some eight or nine years ago, it was quite an adventure to find out the right length I’d need, getting it through customs and all that. It’s not a process that many people want to go through, and hence it’s amazing that we have a lightweight backpack like the Osprey Levity now in stores across the globe.</p>

<p>And yes, the Levity backpack itself is also really, really good. It has some things which Osprey can improve upon when the next version of the pack comes around in a couple of years, but overall Osprey has done their homework well and has produced a very good backpack which will satisfy many backpackers. It’s lightweight, made of durable and water-resistant materials, has Osprey’s <a href="https://www.ospreyeurope.com/gb_en/all-mighty-guarantee/">All Mighty Guarantee</a> which lets you send in a damaged pack and get it repaired, and is also very comfortable to carry with a 10 to 12 kg load. It has everything an ultralight backpack needs as well as a backpanel which increases airflow, which should make it perfect for those super-hot summers we are getting these last years across the globe.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>The Levity is AVAILABLE! Get it at <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/osprey-levity-45-walking-backpack/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/osprey-levity-60-walking-backpack/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> in Europe. In North America order it at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-levity-45-backpack%3Fs%3Da">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fproduct%2F126706%2Fosprey-levity-45-pack-mens">REI</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=358fd954-c6b8-44a1-9ca9-aaad445d2dfb&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.campsaver.com%2Fosprey-levity-45-pack.html">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=61fff111-8514-4179-a87e-5da7e9fb1264&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.moosejaw.com%2Fmoosejaw%2Fshop%2Fproduct_Osprey-Men-s-Levity-45-Pack_10364645_10208_10000001_-1_">Moosejaw</a> and <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=258f5de7-8908-4439-9828-304e836d85a8&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.summithut.com%2Flevity-45-3.html">Summit Hut</a>. And yes, please go try the Levity at your local Osprey Shop so you get a feel for what an ultralight backpack feels (I promise, you’ll love it!).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180105634/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4715/39180105634_ce44d6a11a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Family Skiing in Vuokatti]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/skiing-in-vuokatti.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-22T19:37:57+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/skiing-in-vuokatti</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love winter, skiing and my family. So naturally the best thing is to combine all these things into one week of family fun and head to Vuokatti!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27053282929/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="Vuokatti Ski Slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4542/27053282929_903586e363_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Vuokatti Ski Slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Visit Vuokatti who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="off-to-vuokatti">Off to Vuokatti</h2>

<p>For the third time in a row - after a visit to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">Pyhä</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html">Hetta</a> in the previous years - we packed our winter gear, warm socks and skis and travelled North to experience a proper Finnish winter. Though while in the years before we travelled really far we didn’t want to put that stress on us and our kids of then 1 and 5 years, so after some research we found out about Vuokatti, one of the most snow-secure ski resorts in what we still consider Southern Finland (technically it’s probably the South of Lapland, but lets just say it ain’t as far North as Ylläs, Hetta and Saariselkä). To Vuokatti from Vaasa it are only 400 km which you can drive in a day with some proper planning and keeping the kids entertained, which made it the perfect destination for us. Vuokatti actually is also very easy reached by train and bus, and with many accommodation options being within walking distance of the slopes you can also get around without a car.</p>

<p>Vuokatti is a fantastic destinations for families that want to ski together but don’t want to sit 12 or more hours in the car to get far up North. The <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/Vuokatti-Slopes">13 slopes in Vuokatti</a> are wide &amp; easy, there’s a Fun park with a Halfpipe and some nice big kickers, a Snowboard Tunnel and of course you can rent all the equipment right there so don’t need to travel there with all the gear along. Here’s the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/loader.aspx?id=e3625da0-e490-45b2-a45f-508558f77279">slope map</a> to give you an idea; what I missed is some <em>Lähi offarit</em> - lift-accessible backcountry runs through the forests, but that’s really just a case of getting rid of some trees to make that possible 😜!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39836691081/in/dateposted/" title="Sunny Vuokatti slopes!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4675/39836691081_d8917ae008_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunny Vuokatti slopes!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="lets-go-skiing">Lets go skiing!</h2>

<p>Did I mention that I love skiing? Ah yeah, right there at the beginning 😄. Well, my son learned to ski at age 4 in Levi and enjoyed a short refresher with one of the wonderful ski teachers at the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/Vuokatti-Slopes/Vuokatti-Ski-School">Vuokatti Ski School</a> and then hit the slopes on his own. We decided to not push him and let him go at his own speed, which we found was the right way for us because so he gradually wanted to try bigger &amp; bigger slopes and became more confident skiing them. It’s just beautiful to see your child share the same love for an activity you have yourself, and we are very blessed that our kids love to be outdoors and active as much as we.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804532442/in/dateposted/" title="Vuokatti Slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4677/39804532442_8567e515cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Vuokatti Slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It also was the first time for my wife to stand on Downhill skis, and she too enjoyed the great teaching of the Vuokatti Ski School - which is the 2nd Oldest Ski School in Finland! After a couple of days of being taught the principles of skiing she was skiing down the hills on her own, getting more and more confident and loving the experience. The best thing probably was after that week that she told me <em>“I now understand why you love skiing so much!”</em>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127039344/in/dateposted/" title="Ski School 001"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4651/39127039344_9471592108_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski School 001" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25963527478/in/dateposted/" title="Ski School 004"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4661/25963527478_d85395b83b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski School 004" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057808909/in/dateposted/" title="Ski Sirkus"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/28057808909_16189acf99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Sirkus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057800749/in/dateposted/" title="Ski Carousel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4671/28057800749_f25c3c402a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Carousel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And while there were some really small kids skiing we shared the parenting of our one-year old daughter, and I was taking care of her in the morning while my son &amp; wife were skiing, and then when it was lunch time we ate a small snack at the slopes before the rest of the family went home for naps, playing Lego and relaxing I went skiing. The slopes were for me quite a good training, it was after all only the 2nd season that I stood again on skis after a break of around 16 years! Skiing in a resort is excellent for that, ingraining these movements into ones body and mind. I usually started on one side of the resort and then skied every slope till I reached the other side, where I could step out of the skis and walk with the skis on my shoulder in ten minutes back to our accommodation at the Vuokatti Suites. There’s three main lifts which all bring you all up the slope, with some shorter connecting lifts which help you to get from one end to the other one. <a href="http://www.movescount.com/moves/move148262268">This is how a usual day on the slopes looked</a> according to my Suunto Spartan Ultra.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38937896925/in/dateposted/" title="First down!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4610/38937896925_49699d7595_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="First down!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127057454/in/dateposted/" title="Skiing with my son"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4758/39127057454_b7cc181cac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skiing with my son" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="kids-love-vuokatti">Kids Love Vuokatti!</h2>

<p>After skiing in the mornings we enjoyed family activities in the afternoons, it’s how we roll and really like it. The highlight of the trip for our son was most definitely at the Angry Birds themed <a href="https://superpark.fi/park/vuokatti/">SuperPark Vuokatti</a>, it’s a memory he looks with a smile back to and he regularly comes up to me and says <em>“Dad, we need to go back to the Angry Birds Park, it was so fun!”</em>. It’s memories like these that makes travelling with the family so beautiful, I myself have these kinds of memories of travelling with my parents and siblings, and it just gives kids so much more than some tangible thing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127083144/in/dateposted/" title="Welcome to Angry Birds Park Vuokatti!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4751/39127083144_60eb74128e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Welcome to Angry Birds Park Vuokatti!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127074864/in/dateposted/" title="Slides are fun!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4669/39127074864_ede59200f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slides are fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057824409/in/dateposted/" title="Red!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/28057824409_110ee0b823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Red!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38937888245/in/dateposted/" title="Trying bikes at Angry Birds Park Vuokatti"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/38937888245_47a700a3f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trying bikes at Angry Birds Park Vuokatti" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On another day we went to play bowling at <a href="http://www.vuokattibowling.fi/">Vuokatti Bowling</a>, which is again a memory our son recalls with joy - actually just this morning he told us the scores from our visit at Vuokatti Bowling (Him: 148, my wife: 120, me: 84 😄). The bowling alley in Vuokatti was also really child-friendly, they had a playing room for kids which had large windows which allowed our daughter to play inside but always see us. The staff was friendly and helped me figure out the “complicated” bowling computer (you’d think I’d know these things being a geek!), and the best thing is that the bowling allies are child-friendly as when our son bowled rails went up which prevented the bowling ball going into the gutter. All in all this was a great experience and we might just need to have a visit to a bowling alley with the kids again soon!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804546062/in/dateposted/" title="Vuokatti Bowling"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4718/39804546062_52189d6587_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vuokatti Bowling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then we went one afternoon to the Spa and swimming pools at the <a href="https://www.holidayclubresorts.com/fi/kohteet/katinkulta/kylpyla-ja-hoidot/">Holiday Club Katinkulta</a>. Going to the Spa with the kids is all about sharing the time of who watches the kids when, so that both parents can go in piece to the Sauna, Jacuzzi or swimming. Happily our kids love water and there was both a small kids pool and a slide, which made watching the kids easy &amp; fun. So while one of us was relaxing the other one was taking care of the kids, and after a while we high-fived and switched!</p>

<p>But this isn’t everything! We enjoyed some afternoons just exploring Vuokatti on foot (you can for example drive up the slopes from the other side and walk to the Café on the top!) and walking on the frozen lake in front of the hotel and watching the sunset. You also can go on a <a href="http://www.vuokattisafaris.com/en/tour/husky-safaris/">Husky Safari</a> in Vuokatti, enjoy the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/All-year-round/Skiing">massive XC skiing tracks</a> or check out the Vuokatti Ski tunnel. There’s definitely more than enough options for none-skiing activities in Vuokatti, so just have a look at <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/In-winter">what is possible</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127093244/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking in Vuokatti"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4604/39127093244_7125a940c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking in Vuokatti" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804531052/in/dateposted/" title="Ripa&#x27;s Slope Café"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4712/39804531052_91ac5f6820_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ripa&#x27;s Slope Café" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hungry-heres-where-to-eat-in-vuokatti">Hungry? Here’s where to eat in Vuokatti!</h2>

<p>We loved the breakfast at Vuokatti Suites where we stayed (it was hands-down the best breakfast I have eaten at any Hotel) but we were lucky enough to not needing to cook in the evenings as we went to eat out. Vuokatti gathers to many different tastes, from high-class Menus like we enjoyed at <a href="https://www.sokoshotels.fi/en/vuokatti/sokos-hotel-vuokatti/meetings-and-events/meeting-room?id=466583_392858">Restaurant Kippo</a> and really good and tasty food at <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Services/Vuokatti/Restaurants">À la Katti</a> and <a href="https://vuokattisport.fi/en/ravintolapalvelut/">O’las Restaurant</a> to more basic but good food at <a href="https://olearys.fi/holiday-club-katinkulta/">O’Learys</a>, <a href="https://www.ravintolamessi.fi">Ravintola Messi</a> and <a href="https://www.raflaamo.fi/en/sotkamo/amarillo-vuokatti">Amarillo</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804549022/in/dateposted/" title="Restaurant Kippo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4720/39804549022_1db02d4a9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Restaurant Kippo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804547392/in/dateposted/" title="Starter at Kippo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4667/39804547392_d55553a89c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Starter at Kippo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804528872/in/dateposted/" title="Amarillo Menu"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4745/39804528872_bd92bd9f99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Amarillo Menu" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="would-we-go-again">Would we go again?</h2>

<p>We loved our stay in Vuokatti, and so did the kids. The memories we made as a family are more worth to us than a car, TV or other tangible goods - we try to raise our kids and show them that you spending time with the ones you love is the best use of money &amp; time. It’s thus no surprise that family holidays are high on our list, and a perfect family vacation like we experienced in Vuokatti gives you memories for a lifetime. The small town just had it all: Great slopes for beginner skiers, fun and versatile activities for the afternoons, comfortable accommodation and tasty food. Add in that the people we met in Vuokatti - from the Ski instructors over the Café and Restaurant Staff to everyone else - was super-friendly and great with kids! So to answer the question in the heading: YES! We totally would go again to Vuokatti, and when our daughter is four or five we might need to return so she can learn to ski!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39836691701/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="Learning to love skiing!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4649/39836691701_9f7c2691cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to love skiing!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p>As always, you can find more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157689199140311">Vuokatti Flickr Album</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-stay">Where to stay</h2>

<p>We stayed at <a href="http://www.hotellivuokatti.fi/en/suites">Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites</a> and had a gorgeous Suite with lots of space for us four. Our son had his own room and our daughter slept with us in the big bed, which meant in the evenings we parents could have a glass of wine on the comfortable Sofa and watch a movie on TV (which we can’t do at home as we don’t own a TV!). There was a fully-equipped kitchen in which we prepared our afternoon coffee and evening snacks for the kids, and we had our own Sauna in the Suite which was used almost every evening. The Suite had a drying cabinet which we used to dry moist ski boots, gloves and hats, and the view from the balcony over the lake was beautiful. And if the room was an indication for the whole operation, the breakfast we enjoyed each morning at the main Hotel building was just the best ever. Kids can be tricky with new foods, but at Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites they served everything we’d have at home plus some. The delicious fried eggs, Karelian pastries and lots of <em>fresh</em> fruit made for a good start into a new day, and the coffee was good, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057804579/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Living Room"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4703/28057804579_fa56016097_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Living Room" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057805089/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Own Sauna"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4714/28057805089_8849bb91ae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Own Sauna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804540312/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Ski Storage"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4660/39804540312_53040f1343_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Ski Storage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804533732/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites from the top!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4749/39804533732_2c9760f298_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites from the top!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-there">How to get there</h2>

<p>As I said, you can travel by train &amp; bus to Vuokatti and stay close to the slopes and use the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/loader.aspx?id=643138b3-51fb-405a-a15f-d9e7cee95549">free Vuokatti SkiBus</a> so that a car is not needed. That being said, a (rental) car does make things a bit easier if you come with two kids and ski gear or want to eat in the town in the evenings. From Vaasa it is a 400 km drive to Vuokatti, which takes with breaks in winter around six hours. You also can <a href="https://www.finnair.com/fi/gb/offers?OFFER_ID=62287">fly with Finnair to Kajanni</a> via Helsinki and take the <a href="http://www.akyllonen.fi/airbus/?lang=en">Airport shuttle bus</a> and then use the aforementioned free SkiBus around town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38798598622/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="In the middle, a river"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4538/38798598622_90929ef9cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="In the middle, a river" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 279]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/twir-279.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-13T13:02:42+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/twir-279</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Frozen sea/ expectations/ soon it is spring.”</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27870763839" title="Is it packrafting season already?"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4627/27870763839_d2bdbfca65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Is it packrafting season already?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p>I’m Vlogging in 2018! <a href="https://youtu.be/kC764AQjX_M">Vlog 001</a> is out, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">subscribe on Youtube</a> to follow along!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hlMAKpxN8N0&amp;feature=youtu.be">Escape the Rat Race</a>.</p>

<p>New from Enlightened Equipment: The <a href="https://enlightenedequipment.com/hooligan/">Hooligan Cap</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://longreads.com/2017/05/19/my-electric-bike-is-not-cheating/">My Electric Bike is Not ‘Cheating’</a>. And It Could Replace Cars for Millions of People.</p>

<p>A New Year’s Resolution to Commit to <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/2272096/my-new-years-resolution-ride-1-bike-2018">Bike Monogamy</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/planning-climate-change/">Fight Climate Change</a> and it’s deniers.</p>

<p><a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2018/01/plant-tree-sustainable/">#PlantATreeIfYouAreNotSustainable</a>.</p>

<p>Check out Al Humphreys’ <a href="http://www.alastairhumphreys.com/social-media-advice/">Social Media Advice</a>.</p>

<p>Listen in to the <a href="https://besthike.com/2018/01/11/adventure-podcast-episode-2-10-essentials-of-hiking/">Adventure Podcast</a> and the latest <a href="http://mountainpodcast.com/episode/20-the-fall-part-ii/">Mountain Podcast</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.backpackingnorth.com/blog/2018/1/1/southbound">Mark went South</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.hiking-blog.de/aktuelles/biopile-das-neue-biologisch-abbaubare-fleecematerial-aus-tencel/">BIOPILE</a> is a bio-degradable fleece. [German]</p>

<p>Paul helps you <a href="https://pmags.com/quick-tip-estimating-amount-of-daylight-left">estimating the amount of daylight left</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://freieberge.wordpress.com/2018/01/10/wollt-ihr-den-totalen-berg/">Wollt ihr den totalen Berg?</a> [German]</p>

<p>Backcountry.com has a cool new Customer Offer - <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=2267&amp;pw=73183">Get 10% Off Your First Purchase With Code: GET10OFF</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/2r3LmhQ">ULA Equipment Photon is available</a> - get a new pack for your next weekend trip!</p>

<p>Go ultralight in 2018 with a <a href="http://bit.ly/2vSojb9">versatile Flat Tarp</a> from Hyperlite Mountain Gear!</p>

<p>And <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/outlet/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk has a full Outlet full of bargains</a>, take a look if you still need something for your adventure.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=45765&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10083/45765/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="468" height="60" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>The epic bikepacking story though the Americas continues and takes you this time from <a href="http://www.highlux.co.nz/2018/01/punta-arenas-costa-rica-panama-city/">Punta Arenas in Costa Rica to Panama City</a>.</p>

<p>Beautiful images from <a href="http://tarmachan.blogspot.fi/2018/01/an-teallach-winter-photography.html">An Teallach</a>.</p>

<p>Jill enjoys <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2018/01/from-living-out-in-snow.html">living out in the snow</a> again.</p>

<p>A Guide to <a href="https://climbinggearreviewsuk.wordpress.com/2018/01/09/ice-climbing-in-cogne-a-cgr-destination-guide/">Ice climbing in Cogne</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/UmHVoBKLw68">Wild About Argyll</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://filiphaclaeys.wordpress.com/2018/01/11/black-forest-brandenkopf/">Black Forest</a> looks great in the snow.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.wbur.org/onlyagame/2018/01/05/lael-wilcox-endurance-racing">A Story of Ultra Endurance Cycling</a>.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/W43lZPu0IMc?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Drew shares his <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2018/01/12/10-reasons-to-visit-vietnam/">10 Reasons to fall in Love with Vietnam</a>.</p>

<p>Kathrin backpacks on the <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/trekking-joshua-tree-nationalpark/">California Riding and Hiking Trail</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Alex was <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2018/01/walking-1500-miles-in-2017.html">Walking 1,500 miles in 2017</a>.</p>

<p>Emily is <a href="https://brazenbackpacker.com/2018/01/05/slouching-towards-mount-whitney/">slouching towards Mount Whitney</a>.</p>

<p>Tour de Tahoe - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IU1CFHhTE6s">Bikepacking and Fly Fishing in the Sierra Mountains</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38767141165/in/dateposted/" title="RØDE VMP+ Mic with the Sony a6500 and the SIgma 16 mm f/ 1.4 Lens, a sweet combo for Videography!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4627/38767141165_2698677b74_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="RØDE VMP+ Mic with the Sony a6500 and the SIgma 16 mm f/ 1.4 Lens, a sweet combo for Videography!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/01/on-year-on-a-bike.html">One Year on a Bike</a> Book Review.</p>

<p>Make your <a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2018/01/how-to-glowing-in-dark.html">Packraft Glow in the Dark</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://onehundredmountains.blogspot.fi/2018/01/how-to-be-master-climber-in-six-easy.html">How to be a master climber in six easy lessons</a>, I think I need to read this book!</p>

<p>A look at the <a href="http://bikepacker.com/nemo-gogo-elite-minimalist-shelter-tent-bivy/">NEMO Gogo Elite Minimalist Shelter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://blessedoutdoors.blogspot.fi/2018/01/alcohol-vs-canister-stoves.html">Alcohol vs. Canister Stoves</a>.</p>

<p>Matthias tries the <a href="https://quasiout.de/h-a-d-originals-bike-smog-protection-schlauchtuecher-im-test-flexibler-gesichtsschutz-bei-fallenden-temperaturen/">H.A.D. Originals Bike &amp; Smog Protection</a>.</p>

<p>Ken reviews the <a href="https://ultralightandcomfortable.com/2018/01/05/dji-spark-a-video-review-of-the-ultimate-backpacking-drone/">DJI Spark for backpacking</a>.</p>

<p>Peter rides the <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2018/01/bontrager-gnarwhal-275x45-studded.html">Bontrager Gnarwhal 27.5x4.5 studded fatbike tires</a>.</p>

<p>Michael reviews the <a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/msr-freelite-1-tent-review/">MSR Freelite 1</a> and the <a href="http://scottishmountaineer.com/vaude-lizard-gul-tent-review/">Vaude Power Lizard GUL</a>.</p>

<p>Review of the <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/gear/wolf-tooth-master-link-combo-pliers/">Wolf Tooth Master Link Combo Pliers</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Year on a Bike]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/on-year-on-a-bike.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-04T13:15:34+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/on-year-on-a-bike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you have the feeling that you just need to get out of the house, out of the city, out into the world? Then read Martijn Doolaard’s book <em>One Year On A Bike</em> about his journey from Amsterdam to Singapore.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26493855079/in/dateposted/" title="One Year on a Bike"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4584/26493855079_e5da43fa8e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="One Year on a Bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>The book has been provided by the Gestalten Verlag for review. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>It’s 2018, a new year - time for a new adventure? If you’re fed up running every day in the rat race, how about to jump on a bike and just cycle away? This is pretty much what Martijn did. He went from working as a Designer in an Agency to going Freelance, which opened up way more time for adventures small and big. And then, after one trip to Barcelona, he decided to cycle from Amsterdam to China. He researched bikes, gear, roads and then, one day, set off from Amsterdam towards the East.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26493855779/in/dateposted/" title="Great Layout"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4519/26493855779_7e7a237dae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Great Layout" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Equipped with a lightweight setup he starts to cycle - first through the flat Netherlands and the Western Part of Germany, then into the hills, which slowed him down a wee bit. Prague, Bratislava, Budapest and Bucharest, down to Istanbul and across Turkey he cycles. He makes new friends along the way - Nils from Switzerland, who also cycles east - and enjoys the free life of cycle, pitch the tent, eat, sleep and repeat. Sometimes there are worries of bears, the steepness of the mountains, terrible roads &amp; too much traffic, but all in all Martijn has a great adventure.</p>

<p>Like many I also sometimes feel trapped in the rat race - too much work, too little time for fun things. When things get really stressy it is easy to dream of an escape - hiking the PCT, or like Martijn, just jumping on a bike and cycling in one direction until you reach the end. But escaping for such long amounts of time is currently not a possibility, and so reading this book, with it’s beautiful photos and anecdotes, is a good cure to the <em>Fernweh</em> we all sometimes suffer from. But not only that, you could use it as a blue print for your own escape in the future: Start your own company, start planning a route, save money - and then, in 2019, you could jump on your bike and ride away!</p>

<p>You can buy <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/one-year-on-a-bike.html">One Year On A Bike</a> directly at Gestalten or via one of the Affiliate Links at <a href="http://amzn.to/2yLNjz0">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/2hEVytB">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/2hDqomq">Amazone.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38270279911" title="Pretty Photos"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4524/38270279911_e6d40beb45_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Pretty Photos" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 278]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/twir-278.html"/>
    <updated>2017-12-29T13:28:34+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/twir-278</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Brown beans/ fat tires/ Relaxation in the forest.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38490040765/in/dateposted/" title="#CoffeeOutdoors"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4640/38490040765_e4226c7246_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="#CoffeeOutdoors" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles why not <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<h2 id="news">News</h2>

<p>Stop working so much: <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/3067325/after-two-years-of-trying-6-hour-workdays-these-companies-say-it-worked">6 hour work days are most efficient and make you happier &amp; healthier</a>.</p>

<p>Awesome: The <a href="https://news.nationalgeographic.com/2017/12/peel-watershed-yukon-protected-canada-supreme-court-decision-spd/">Peel Watershed is protected from development and mining</a>.</p>

<p>Strange Days: A look back on <a href="http://www.alpinist.com/doc/web17f/wfeature-a-look-back-at-the-bears-ears-saga">the previous 11 months surrounding Bears Ears National Monument and a glance at the future</a>.</p>

<p>And <a href="https://modernhiker.com/lawsuit-filed-to-protect-national-monuments-from-trump/">Trump getting sued over the Bears’ Ears and Grand Staircase-Escalante National Monuments</a> is great News.</p>

<p>The outdoor industry’s opportunity to protect public lands is now, and <a href="https://www.snewsnet.com/people/opinion-jimmy-funkhouser-public-lands">we’re doing it all wrong</a>.</p>

<p>Climate Change is getting Real: <a href="http://grist.org/article/let-it-go-the-arctic-will-never-be-frozen-again/">The Arctic will never be frozen again</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2017/11/25/climate/arctic-climate-change.html">Why Lost Ice Means Lost Hope for an Inuit Village</a>.</p>

<p>Looking for a new lens for your Sony? Check out the <a href="http://amzn.to/2pGnwIr">Sigma 16 mm f/ 1.4</a> - mine should arrive in early January and I’m looking forward to take it out for some Astrophotography.</p>

<p>Need an ultralight phone for backpacking? Have a look at the 13 g light <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1500916193/the-worlds-smallest-phone-introducing-the-zanco-ti">Zanco tiny t1</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.backpacker.com/stories/put-a-filter-on-it">The Outdoors are better without Instagram</a>.</p>

<p>Andrew Skurka is looking for a <a href="https://andrewskurka.com/2017/job-posting-backpacking-guide/">Backpacking guide for 2018 trips</a>!</p>

<p>Watch the <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b09l594s">Roads Less Travelled - The Heart of Scotland</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/77dy57" title="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_ME_Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4688/27726684649_86229be9e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="538" alt="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_ME_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">Win an amazing Mountain Equipment Jacket</a> for your next Mountain Adventure!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/33407z" title="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Rab_blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4599/38794577994_e3c9001e40_b.jpg" width="1024" height="538" alt="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Rab_blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Photographers - how about <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/rab-freeride-outfit/">winning a sweet Rab Jacket &amp; Pants</a> in this photography contest?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/9da446" title="Bergzeit_Alpincamp_Grivel_Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4647/27726684799_1a49a27343_b.jpg" width="1024" height="538" alt="Bergzeit_Alpincamp_Grivel_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Start your ice climbing career with <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/alpincamp/grivel-eisklettern-osttirol/">winning this Grivel Gear</a>!</p>

<p>Need something warm for the cold days? Check out the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/outlet/down-jackets/?pid=10239">Down Jackets on Sale at Alpinetrek.co.uk</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=2267&amp;pw=73183">Get 15% Off Your First Purchase With Code: NEWCUSTOMER15 at Backcountry.com</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=45765&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10083/45765/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="468" height="60" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Chad hiked with many friends on the <a href="https://sticksblog.com/2017/12/20/december-17-florida-trail-hike-ocala-nf-w-zpacks-goosefeet-gear/">Florida Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VQ1vNMaIq-o&amp;feature=youtu.be">Kalkkögel Winter Traverse</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.highlux.co.nz/2017/12/catacamas-honduras-granada-nicaragua/">Bikepacking from Catacamas, Honduras to Granada, Nicaragua</a>.</p>

<p>A hike up <a href="http://www.skadinagrani.pl/2017/12/rysy-2503-m-npm.html">Rysy</a>. [Polish]</p>

<p>Jackie shares her <a href="https://travelingjackie.com/ruined-for-life-musings-from-patagonia/">Musings from Patagonia</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2017/12/halcyon-days.html">Halcyon days</a>.</p>

<p>Paulina shares her <a href="https://www.littlegrunts.com/hiking-backpacking-laugavegur-trail/">101 for Backpacking the Laugavegur Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://talusfield.net/blog/2017/10/29/climbing-in-leonidio-greece">Climbing in Leonidio, Greece</a>.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EoOfiUfCK-w?rel=0" frameborder="0" gesture="media" allow="encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://bikepacker.com/off-piste-pug/">The Off Piste Pug</a>.</p>

<p>2017: <a href="https://chasingmailboxes.com/2017/12/26/2017-a-fine-year-to-ride-bikes-and-the-photos-to-prove-it/">A Fine Year to Ride Bikes</a>.</p>

<p>Peter enjoyed <a href="http://wanderingsupnorths.blogspot.dk/2017/12/so-2017-saw-my-first-wild-camp-on-jan.html">27 Wild Camps in 2017</a>.</p>

<p>A skitour up the <a href="http://biwak.blogspot.dk/2017/12/robispitzen-2410m.html">Röbispitzen</a>. [German]</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/tour-des-combins/">Tour des Combins</a> Loop.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7vZG7FTDM9U">CHINA DOLL</a> - Love, Obsession and Hard Traditional Climbing with Heather Weidner.</p>

<p>And a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TVBMF8LOn8U">3 Months Packrafting Adventure in Greenland</a> to round things out.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28044201296/in/album-72157669978279411/" title="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7797/28044201296_a750b77c3b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/_FYuB9j_9A4">Garment Sizes &amp; Layering for Winter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.thehikinglife.com/2017/12/reveiw-mountain-laurel-designs-solomid-xl/">Mountain Laurel Designs SoloMid XL Review</a>.</p>

<p>Chris Townsend’s <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2017/12/favourite-new-outdoor-gear-2017.html">favourite New Outdoor Gear of 2017</a>.</p>

<p>Carsten tests the <a href="http://www.fastpacking.de/2017/12/20/msr-reactor-test-nicht-ul-ultra-schnell-und-effizient/">MSR Reactor</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Check out these new <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/news/salsa-timberjack-kids-20-24/">Salsa Timberjack Kids bikes</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=5985&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10270/5985/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 24]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-24.html"/>
    <updated>2017-12-24T13:25:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-24</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2017/12/advent-calendar-door-24.html" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Logo"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5675/23371834331_4ee5c10e0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Logo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>it’s the big day once again. Across the globe kids big and small are waiting for you to arrive, and for sure you will not disappoint them. Something that would suit you well is the <a href="https://arcteryx.com/fi/en/shop/mens/Beta-LT-Jacket">Arc’teryx Beta LT Jacket</a>, a lightweight &amp; versatile GORE-TEX Pro hardshell that will keep you dry in the meanest Snowstorms. The Beta LT in the Matador colour is a real Santa 🎅 jacket, and as it durable you can slide down chimneys in it, hide your hat and beard under the fantastic StormHood and the breathable material will keep you dry when the bag with presents is a bit heavier because the kids were so good. The large pockets hold a map of the city or region you are in, and in the inside you can keep some snacks for Rudolph warm. Yes dear Santa, I am sure with the Arc’teryx Beta LT Jacket not only you would be very happy &amp; satisfied!</p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895137/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895137" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_6vyigebu">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/advent-calendar-2017-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prize (<em>you can choose <strong>either</strong> the Arc’teryx Beta LT Jacket in Baja for Women or Matador for Men</em>) is sponsored by Arc’teryx and sent directly from them - <em>possible import fees need to be paid by the winner</em>. <em>This Advent Calendar Door has been supported financially and with gear from Arc’teryx.</em></p>

<p>Read about my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/arcteryx-workshop-tour.html">Tour of the Arc’teryx Factory in Vancouver</a> and the one Duffle to Rule Them All: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/one-duffle-to-rule-them-all-the-arcteryx-carrier-duffle.html">The Arc’teryx Carrier Duffle</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39191888432/in/photostream/" title="HiFAdventCalendar Arc&#x27;teryx Beta LT Jacket"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4684/39191888432_4357f98938_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar Arc&#x27;teryx Beta LT Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
