<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-06-11T15:05:44+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cottage Interview: Tom Gale of Atom Packs]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/06/cottage-interview-tom-gale-of-atom-packs.html"/>
    <updated>2018-06-11T19:08:30+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/06/cottage-interview-tom-gale-of-atom-packs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the 3rd <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">Cottages Interview</a> of 2018 we get to know Tom Gale of Atom Packs 🇬🇧</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/57g3oq" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1740/42680475452_76781e0371_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em><a href="https://www.atompacks.co.uk">Atom Packs</a> I found when Alex Roddie tweeted about the company earlier this year, and like Alex I think the packs which Tom makes are really great looking with smart details. As I was making the list of companies to interview for this series Tom has one of the first ones I contacted, and I am very happy that he agreed to participate (he’s super-busy and hasn’t had a day off in four weeks, so order your pack AFTER you read this interview, OK ;). Without much further ado - here’s Tom’s Interview!</em></p>

<p><strong>Tom, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking, and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>Who am I? Whoa now, this could get deep. I guess I’m a hiker: It is at the core of nearly everything I do.</p>

<p>I started long distance hiking in 2009, setting off on the Appalachian Trail like so many others under a crippling load with as many things strapped to the outside of my bag as were inside. I think I also had maybe 8L of water with me. Urgh. That guy. The longer I hiked, the more content and quiet my busy brain became and I swiftly began to feel that this had to be something that I built my life around. I came home and began working towards becoming a professionally certified Outdoor Guide and, within a few years, was doing what I loved and sharing my passions with others every day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/3w2A25" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1742/42680476092_9b0ecaf815_b.jpg" width="1024" height="846" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</strong></p>

<p>Hahaha, less so now than I would like. I tend to get out on my mountain bike for at least an hour a day. This business expanded much quicker than I’d anticipated but I try and find the time, normally I work until about 7pm and then get out for an hour, chasing the sunset through the trees on one of the mountains near my house. I’m pretty well situated for some incredible riding, even if I’m exhausted it always makes me feel better.</p>

<p><strong>Are you more of a “weekend warrior” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong></p>

<p>I’m a huge fan of micro adventure. I try and get out most weekends but the reality is that currently I don’t get much time off - Hopefully soon things will come back under a little more control. I live surrounded by mountains and lakes and it’s very easy to just grab a pack and go, but I suppose my priorities are currently with growing my business.</p>

<p>I have hiked some 12,000 miles now on the big three trails in the US, the Te Araroa and another few thousand miles around the coast of England. I don’t plan on stopping any time soon, this business might try and stop me but, hey, I’m thirty years old and it’s about time I tried some of this so-called “adulting”. I promised myself I’d give the business three years and see where I am at, only then will I decide if it was a dumb idea.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/623M9Q" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1737/42680476172_c33442b8d2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Hiking in Finland Readers &amp; me, we are gear-nerds! What is your typical baseweight?</strong></p>

<p>That’s a great question. I actually have no idea. Somewhere between 3 - 5 kg. I used to count every gram but after my third major hike I realised it didn’t actually make much difference to me - I’m a big guy, 6ft7 and 100 kg and I eat an absolutely OBSCENE amount of food, at least 2kg a day when on trail so my pack weight is always pretty heinous when leaving town. I also realised it was completely relative – my 3.5kg base weight felt just at terrible the day I left town on the PCT in 2015 as it did leaving town on the AT in 2009 with a 9kg base weight. It doesn’t matter what your baseweight is – your bag will ALWAYS feel like shit the day you leave town. Why worry about a couple of ounces here and there when you are about to hike out an entire rotisserie chicken, three avocados, a bunch of bananas, some beer and whole loaf of bread out of town… It’s good training. I’m not belittling the gram counting approach – for people who have some control over there caloric intake I’m sure it’s very justified – I will just always completely fill my bag with food regardless of how long it is to the next town so the base weight becomes a pretty small percentage of that.</p>

<p>There are a lot of hikers who can starve themselves on trail and come into town with zero calories i.e. without a morsel of food left in their bags. This is the elusive thru hiking “gold star” but, the reality of achieving that largely gives me an anxiety attack, I think I’ve only ever done it twice in 12,000 miles and I nearly fainted. It’s completely out of my control.</p>

<p>I do try to stay under 3.5kg but my process on a thru hike is always the same. I start heavier than I want to, then pare my gear down over the first couple of months, shedding everything I can, and then I realise I’m cold and uncomfortable and in as amazing hiking shape as I’ll ever be and then start adding luxuries items again. I’d say I’m at my most ultra light eight weeks into a hike.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Kn5436" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1727/28856277618_9e24f89dab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “Atom Packs” came from, and what it stands for.</strong></p>

<p>I was trying to think of the smallest, lightest thing that I could. Initially the name was Atomic Ultralight but try typing that into Google and you’ll quickly realise why I changed it, you just can’t compete with the entire spectrum of information on quantum physics. I was stuck on the name for ages and then one day the name <a href="https://www.atompacks.co.uk">Atom Packs</a> came to me. The fact it’s got my name in it as well is just a very happy accident – A-Tom Packs. People give me credit for that. They shouldn’t.</p>

<p><strong>What makes Atom Packs different from other cottages?</strong></p>

<p>I make durable, lightweight gear (Dura-lite if you will!). I build the best packs that I can out of the best materials available to me. Sure, there may be lighter materials available, but that comes at a cost of either durability or comfort. The way I see it, there has to be some sense behind design: A backpack has the hardest job of any piece of gear that you carry, it is responsible for holding onto literally everything else that you take with you into the wilds and an extra few grams in its design can greatly increase both the durability of the pack and the carrying comfort of the user - In my view that is well worth the weight penalty. If you design a pack right, you won’t know that it’s heavier because the weight is working FOR you, not AGAINST you.</p>

<p>I think, in essence, most companies are all in this for the same reason: There isn’t the gear that we desire available to us, so we make our own. Every hiker on the planet has a different way of doing things, so I aim to create the gear that individual people want. Sure, some people will say that another brand/ fabric/ method is better, and they could well be right when it comes to their way of hiking, but I have designed my brand to be flexible to peoples needs so, I’d ask that person to shoot me an email and lets talk. It’s a great learning experience for me as well as people force me to step out of my comfort zone and design something new – quite a few of these requests have actually become part of my daily designs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/D1Ge7D" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1731/42680475722_25128f21b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="890" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Is Atom Packs your full-time job or “just a hobby”?</strong></p>

<p>It’s now full time! Argh! I have some token bits of guiding work over the summer but the reality is that I can’t really afford the time away from the business at present so, yep, I now sew for 70+ hours a week. It’s pretty intense.</p>

<p><strong>Atom Packs makes lightweight and stylish backpacks and backpack accessories. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?</strong></p>

<p>It mostly came from a need to create the gear that I wanted - I’m so tall that any off the shelf backpack/ daypack that I bought ended up with its hipbelt somewhere below my nipples. Combine this with a natural curiosity for the unknown and I found myself sitting at a sewing machine making quite a horrible mess. That is basically the process that is still ongoing today, if not a little more refined!</p>

<p>In the coming weeks I am moving into a proper workshop. Here I will expand my production to cope with demand and begin training up an employee or two. I know that this business cannot possibly expand any more than it currently is with me crouched over a sewing machine for 70+hours a week. The danger is that I eventually have some kind of sewing-induced break down and run bare-assed and screaming into the cold night, never to be seen again. A lot of cottage companies have gone the same way and I’m trying really hard to not make the same mistakes. I’m still slipping and sliding my way along the learning curve but my processes are getting more refined with each day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/71118j" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1727/28856276158_a294c57d60_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Any intentions of starting to branch out into other segments, for example offering shelters and bivys?</strong></p>

<p>Yes… but lets not get ahead of ourselves.</p>

<p><strong>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in the United Kingdom that you work with?</strong></p>

<p>Not at present. Everyone I have spoken with has been very supportive though! I’d love to team up with a few brands in the future, that way we can all benefit.</p>

<p><strong>And are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada, the USA and other places?</strong></p>

<p>Other than a few messages/ comments via Instagram, not currently. There are some great companies making some great kit out there, Instagram gives you a nice peek into what they’re up to.</p>

<p><strong>Your company is a just several months old and already has been getting good reviews and praise from all across Europe. Is business going well?</strong></p>

<p>Haha, yes it blew up pretty quickly didn’t it!? I properly launched the website at the end of February and quickly got far more orders than I knew what to do with. I don’t advertise or spend money on promotion, I’m just trying to let it naturally grow by putting the product out there to be seen. Any product worth its salt will succeed, given the chance, I’m just very wary of outstripping my production capacity. I think that’s always the issue with cottage companies – when you are one guy in a shed it is easy to get overwhelmed and something that started off as creative and fun becomes a great, snarling monster that consumes most of your life. It’s been quite a journey, that’s for sure.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/m55c9N" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1727/28856276218_a3784e81ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of The Atom pack, and where the inspiration came from?</strong></p>

<p>I used to work with Adrian Moore at Aiguille Alpine Equipment and he used to say that “if you take away everything else, a rucksack at its most basic is just a potato sack with straps”. <a href="https://www.atompacks.co.uk/product-page/the-atom">The Atom</a> came from stripping back everything that I knew about backpacks and starting from the ground up. I wanted people to be able to start with a tube and add whatever they wanted to it, The Atom as you see it is exactly the pack that I would want on a thru-hike, it just happens that that has become the standard design.</p>

<p>I have to give some credit to “Dubstep”, my esteemed hiking companion of 5000 miles. I asked her to design her perfect backpack and she, not taking the process particularly seriously, designed a pack with rockets on the side pockets. That’s what inspired some of the Atom’s aesthetic, I was trying to make it look like a rocket.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/1C640E" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1750/28856276118_7a1db6739b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Tom, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! What kind of new products are you working on at the moment?</strong></p>

<p>Removable carbon frames. They’re the future!</p>

<p><strong>And any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong></p>

<p>Liteskin by Dimension Polynant. I bought a bunch of it and have been experimenting with it a little. KS Ultralight have been using it but I’ve not seen any long term reviews yet. It strikes me as a really solid fabric that, for its weight, is pretty incredible. I designed a 35L Atom with a padded hipbelt that came in at under 380g - that’s pretty special! The big test will be how well it holds up. I’ve been working with Andrew Sherry (@thehikingstory on Instagram) – I’m keen to send him one to try and break it just to see how well it holds up as there have been no real long term tests done yet and everyone, myself included, are a little twitchy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/VEnfyk" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1760/28856276628_2eb647b7aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at Atom Packs, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems, which then are adopted in the Atom Packs line-up?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, I think I sort of answered this before. I have already solved the problems that I have encountered, so when people come to you with new issues it can really help to develop the product forwards.</p>

<p><strong>And where do your customer come from, and how do they find you?</strong></p>

<p>I put something on Reddit in February and it sort of went a bit wild from there. I sell a lot of packs to Germany and Scandinavia, I’ve also sent packs to New Zealand, USA, Canada and even Brazil. Basically anywhere. I’ve been amazed at how the Internet has driven this business forward, it has been simultaneously humbling and terrifying – the world is a very small place these days.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last trip?</strong></p>

<p>My last big hike was the Continental Divide Trail, I’ve only just properly gotten over it mentally 🤣. Otherwise I try and get out on day hikes where I can. It’s good for the soul and a great excuse to test backpacks.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/HE3707" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1737/28856276898_7ba145f6aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream trip taking you?</strong></p>

<p>The Te Araroa south island was about as happy as I have ever been. It was also the most amount of times I have ever nearly died in a period of time. I’d hike it again in a heartbeat! I’m aiming to go for the Arizona Trail this October but can not figure out if I can stop this runaway train I’m currently sitting on. I guess the dream trip is the next one you are undertaking or the one you are currently on. And there are so many trails! Argh!</p>

<p><strong>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong></p>

<p>I picked up an <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/msr-blizzard-tent-stakes-tent-stakes/?pid=10239">MSR Blizzard Stake</a> on the CDT and quickly fell in love. They cost $5, weigh 1 oz and I use it for both camping and digging cat holes (because everybody poops). Not only do you feel like you can dig forever but I also put a bit of duct tape on the inside edge and would use it as a water spout to get water out of slow trickling springs, it was amazingly effective!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/5u0449" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1733/28856277268_8c0927d4bc_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the summer in the United Kingdom?</strong></p>

<p>I would like to start a continuous walk around the Wainrwrights, these are 214 fells situated in the Lake District National Park. I doubt I’d be able to do it in one go but I can dream! Otherwise I am determined to hike the AZT in October. There are a load of 200 mile hikes in my vicinity. It’s just having the time!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/3n67QU" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1747/42680475572_e43c10ea46_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Social Media - on which channels is Atom Packs active?</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/atom_packs/">@atom_packs on Instagram</a>. I need to get Facebook and Twitter set up properly so watch this space. It’s very distracting though.</p>

<p><strong>Tom, I thank you very mucho for taking the time to answer my questions =) Is there something you would like to add?</strong></p>

<p>I guess I’d like to encourage those who are seeking out their first UL setup go with their gut and not just the status quo. It takes many hundreds, if not thousands, of miles to truly understand what you need and don’t need. Just because you want a pack with a padded hipbelt does not mean you are no longer qualified to call yourself ultralight, no matter what they say on the forums.</p>

<p>Instead of obsessing over gear lists or whatever everyone else is doing, just throw some stuff in a bag and go hiking. If it works for you, keep it, if it’s cheap, even better. There are many thousands of ways to spend many thousands of dollars on gear. The best way to know what works is to go and actually do it yourself and then slowly, piece by piece, replace items for lighter alternatives. Once you understand an items use and, more importantly how you interact with it, then you can make a truly informed decision. Otherwise the danger is buying every piece of gear three or four times before you get it right – and that doesn’t leave you much money for hamburgers and beer. Thanks for your time, see you down the trail ☺</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/7S5h45" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1744/28856277078_b1251c4c84_b.jpg" width="819" height="1024" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this article <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions From the Causeway Coast Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/06/impressions-from-the-causeway-coast-way.html"/>
    <updated>2018-06-04T19:43:53+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/06/impressions-from-the-causeway-coast-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Northern Ireland, or Ireland in general, is not really a country which you associate with sunshine, 26°C hiking days and long, almost empty beaches and cliff paths. However, to my surprise this was exactly what I encountered on my thru-hike of the Causeway Coast Way!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40750498920/in/dateposted/" title="Cliffs along the Causeway Coast Way"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1732/40750498920_d70abcb72d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cliffs along the Causeway Coast Way" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was supported by <a href="https://www.tourismireland.com">Tourism Ireland</a> and <a href="https://discovernorthernireland.com">Discover Northern Ireland</a>, additionally I also received a fee for my work. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>At home in Vaasa, Finland, I have since six weeks wall-to-wall ☀️ every day, and as I was starting to have an eye on the weather forecasts of Portstweart, Bushmills and Ballycastle, I was happy to see that I will be equally blessed with superb weather during my hike on the Causeway Coast Way in Northern Ireland. So into my carry-on backpack went my Luna Sandals, sunscreen and T-Shirts while the rain pants and jacket stayed at home. I did not regret that decision - maybe the only thing I did regret was that I didn’t apply the sunscreen more often and that I didn’t add a few extra days to explore more of this beautiful part of Ireland.</p>

<p>My detailed trip report will follow in the next weeks, but for now enjoy these B-Roll impressions from the trail and it’s quaint little towns which lay along it. Right now this is still a fairly unknown trail, and while at some points along it you will encounter a lot of people this trail likely will soon be as popular as the Laugavegur Trail in Iceland which is renown for equally stunning scenery.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40750516780/in/dateposted/" title="Grand Day in Portstewart, Northern Ireland"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1742/40750516780_66cea3b94c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grand Day in Portstewart, Northern Ireland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41657578425/in/dateposted/" title="Portstewart Promenade"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1757/41657578425_f59a830f92_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Portstewart Promenade" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41836752974/in/dateposted/" title="Portstewart Strand Sunset"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1723/41836752974_887ac7a0f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Portstewart Strand Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I arrived in Portstewart late in the afternoon, but the weather was so good - I had to go out and hike to the beach. Which was totally worth it!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40750513830/in/dateposted/" title="View out of Portstewart"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1747/40750513830_96ac792006_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="View out of Portstewart" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41836789324/in/dateposted/" title="The Giant&#x27;s Causeway lays behind that hill"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1744/41836789324_8115177b60_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Giant&#x27;s Causeway lays behind that hill" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28685131528/in/dateposted/" title="Giant&#x27;s Causeway, Midday"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1726/28685131528_9c093c4876_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Giant&#x27;s Causeway, Midday" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next day I hiked to the Giant’s Causeway, which is World Heritage site and can be very busy. But go there late in the evening or early in the morning and you’ll likely have it to yourself. It’s a mind-boggling beautiful place, and I didn’t plan for enough time there - I feel a photographer wants at least a full day to spend here!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41657611865/in/dateposted/" title="Sheep"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1745/41657611865_62bb8155fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sheep" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40750564740/in/dateposted/" title="Whitepark House and it&#x27;s beautiful Garden"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1735/40750564740_abdfe2c115_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Whitepark House and it&#x27;s beautiful Garden" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40750501250/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset on White Park Bay"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1728/40750501250_eeddbfc49d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset on White Park Bay" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I hiked onwards in the heat, along cliff paths which had me stop every few hundred meters to soak in the landscape which is just breath-taking.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27689163737/in/dateposted/" title="Carrick-a-Rede"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1731/27689163737_da63861b73_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Carrick-a-Rede" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41836777284/in/dateposted/" title="Local Beer from Portstewart"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1757/41836777284_0e8849bd35_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Local Beer from Portstewart" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On my last day on the trail the drizzle and clouds made an appearance, and also them I found beautiful and serene. And just like that I finished in Ballycastle, sad that this beautiful hike was already over.</p>

<p><em>Stay tuned for the full trip-report in the next couple of weeks, but take a look some more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157669754047208">Flickr Album</a> and on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cottage Interview: Maj and Kajo From GramXpert]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-maj-and-kajo-from-gramxpert.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-28T18:52:19+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-maj-and-kajo-from-gramxpert</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">Cottages Interviews 2018 Series</a> continues with the brothers Maj and Kajo, who together run GramXpert from Slovenia!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/6H528S" title="Interview1"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1724/41618983464_bf13cc332e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="713" alt="Interview1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>I first became aware of <a href="https://www.gramxpert.eu">GramXpert</a> as their Gear popped up in the German Ultraleicht Trekking Forum. Since then their <a href="https://www.trekking-lite-store.com/gramxpert-ultralight-backpack-34-4.html">backpacks</a> and <a href="https://www.trekking-lite-store.com/gramxpert-elite-quilt-apex-267.html">quilts</a> are also sold at the trekking-lite-store.com, and their kit is light and looks good, with some unique solutions. Reason enough to get in touch with the two brothers and hear their story!</em></p>

<p><strong>Maj and Kajo, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking, and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>We are two brothers with a passion for anything active and outdoorsy. Hiking is almost folklore in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/ultralight-summit-daytrippin.html">Slovenia</a> so we’ve been at it from a very young age. The biggest influence was our father. He regularly took us on multi-day hiking and biking trips when we were kids, and those adventures sparked our interest. We still have fond memories of our first bike tour at the age of 8. It was a 4 day, 120km tour and we rode fully loaded 20” bikes with only 6 gears :) Similar adventures on bike &amp; foot were on the menu every summer vacation since. As we got older we started planning our own trips. They became longer and more challenging and with that came better and more elaborate gear.</p>

<p>Kajo: 
I am interested in many outdoor activities, I am not taking anything as a competitive sport but rather as an adventure. I was into rock climbing for a long time, but lately caving and paragliding got my attention. I am responsible for designing new gear and coordinating custom orders, also the main craftsman and tester. I am also finishing my degree in geotechnical engineering so at the moment I can only work part-time.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4XkWCU" title="kajo"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/873/41439554545_c026ff7f65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="kajo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Maj: My approach when it comes to life is holistic. I’m a trained chef and passionate about nutrition. I’m currently also an assistant coach, a Tuina masseur, and a TCM student. I am also an advocate for animal rights and a promoter of sustainable lifestyle. 
I’m the one that takes care of the bureaucratic side of the business, but I enjoy customer service, various daily tasks and of course sewing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/xK1BaZ" title="maj"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1743/41618981894_9a1a92b535_b.jpg" width="760" height="1024" alt="maj" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</strong></p>

<p>As often as we can be. We are very busy these days, but we always make sure to take some time off and go outside in order to recharge our batteries. We take every opportunity we can to go out, test our prototypes and work out the kinks.</p>

<p><strong>Are you two more of “weekend warriors” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong></p>

<p>We regularly go on two or three day hikes and one or two week-long trips per year. Too busy for anything longer at the moment. 
We want to experience thru hikes also, we just weren’t able to do it so far. Hopefully sometime in the near future.</p>

<p><strong>Hiking in Finland Readers &amp; me, we are gear-nerds! What is your typical baseweight?</strong></p>

<p>Kajo: It depends, but generally about 3-3.5kg for a 3 season setup. While I am very selective about each individual piece of gear, I never really weigh the total pack or bother with the LW/UL/SUL tags. I also still have quite a bit of room to optimize the setup.</p>

<p>Maj: I have similar base weight as Kajo, but I usually carry heavier food (fresh if possible). Thankfully it counts as a consumable :)</p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “GramXpert” came from, and what it stands for.</strong></p>

<p>As you might expect Gram comes from grams. As for the Xpert, we would never claim to know everything and are always happy to learn more, but we felt like our experience and almost obsessive research of design and materials justified the Xpert part :)</p>

<p><strong>What makes GramXpert different from other cottages?</strong></p>

<p>We really try to keep up with our short lead times, keeping the products at high quality levels and most importantly providing good customer service. Our products are also highly customizable. Each person has different needs and wants and we are always willing to adjust and adapt to every individual’s wishes.</p>

<p><strong>Is GramXpert your full-time job or “just a hobby”?</strong></p>

<p>Maj: A little bit of both. At the moment we are also busy doing a bunch of other things as we mentioned before, so we are not sure if this will be a full time job for both of us. I would like to keep working halftime at GramXpert so I can simultaneously work on other projects, but Kajo will put more effort into it in the future, after he graduates. European market for UL gear is quite small and most people (at least here in Slovenia) are day hikers and tend to sleep in huts. Despite that the business is on a positive trajectory and steadily growing. Our mantra is: “Find a job you enjoy doing, and you will never have to work a day in your life.”</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/N565Z1" title="hike"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/886/41439556645_15d7ae98ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="hike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>GramXpert makes lightweight and stylish quilts, accessories and a backpack. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?**</p>

<p>It started with us trying to tweak the gear we bought so it would fit our needs. Then we made the first quilts for ourselves and our friends. The key moment was when Kajo’s plan to thru-hike the PCT fell apart due to bureaucratic obstacles. He realized he wouldn’t get the necessary visa in time, so he invested his savings in the company instead.</p>

<p>We’re very enthusiastic and full of ideas and plans for the future. We spend most of our free time thinking about our craft, our mission, and our vision. We’re aware of the areas in which we are lacking, but we always strive to improve. We never want to sacrifice quality in order to get a few extra sales, so while we definitely want to grow and flourish, we plan on doing it strategically.</p>

<p><strong>Any intentions of starting to branch out into other segments, for example offering shelters and bivys?</strong></p>

<p>Yes! Eventually we would like to branch out and offer most items backpackers need. R&amp;D takes a lot of time especially if you want to test the gear thoroughly. Bivys will be available soon. Later we will add some clothing items that are currently in the development phase. Branching out proved to be quite challenging seeing as different gear requires different sewing machine settings, or sometimes an entirely separate machine if you want to do it right. We learned a lot while we were launching our backpacks and we hope we can optimize the process and streamline the workflow in the future. Our workspace is quite limited, we’re currently cramped in a 20 square meter room and this makes some things an impossible task. We would like to produce shelters as well, but first we need to move to a bigger workshop.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/1c0rfr" title="delavnica1"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/889/41618984514_30e1b40594_b.jpg" width="1024" height="585" alt="delavnica1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
 
<strong>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in Slovenia that you work with?</strong></p>

<p>No, we are not aware of any other similar cottage manufacturers nearby, but we do collaborate with a couple of independent local suppliers.</p>

<p><strong>And are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada, the USA and other places?</strong></p>

<p>Not at the moment, but we are open for collaboration. It might be interesting to work on some joint projects.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/f4NA1h" title="machine"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1756/41439561425_9d0d444413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="machine" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Your company is still young and already has been getting good reviews and praise from all across Europe. Is business going well?</strong></p>

<p>We’re slowly but surely increasing the visibility and hopefully building a good reputation. We are very happy with how things are going, but it will take a while before everything will run smooth. We’re planning on expanding our product range so we can reach more people, but like we said, quality over quantity.</p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of eLite quilt, and where the inspiration came from?</strong></p>

<p>Kajo: Our past experiences inspire all of our products. The same thing happened with eLite. I remember winter camping a few years ago. Trying to find those tiny cordlocks to completely close the footbox in the middle of the night drove me crazy. As soon as I came home I designed a new quilt with a handy closure. With eLite you can close the footbox in a breeze, even with your gloves on.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Y99p2E" title="DSC02064new"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1731/41618983844_b022e02cc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="534" alt="DSC02064new" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Kajo and Maj, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! What kind of new products are you working on at the moment?</strong></p>

<p>There are many prototypes of different gear in the works and you can certainly expect new and exciting things in the near future. Insulated balaclava and backpack accessories will be out in the upcoming months. We’re also currently testing two bivy models along with a simple rectangular 1P tarp/ ponchotarp.</p>

<p><strong>And are there any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong></p>

<p>Not really, but we’re looking forward to the day when super light and breathable DCF will be available :) 10g/m² or lighter shell fabric for quilts would be really awesome.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0Q4F5B" title="quilt"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/877/41439559695_e24e189e42_b.jpg" width="963" height="1024" alt="quilt" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at GramXpert, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems, which then are adopted in the GramXpert line-up?</strong></p>

<p>The “base” products are mostly inspired by our own experiences. We design the prototypes, then incorporate any improvements we might feel are needed. Due to our gear being highly customizable, we can always consult each individual customer and figure out a solution for their specific needs.</p>

<p><strong>Where do your customer come from, and how do they find you?</strong></p>

<p>All over the world, but mostly from Europe. Some find us organically, but it seems that most of our customers discover us through word of mouth.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last trip?</strong></p>

<p>We took a two day trip two weeks ago. We hiked through Kamnik-Savinja Alps, mainly because we live nearby, so it was really convenient on top of being gorgeous. Our last week-long trip was last autumn. We did a section hike of Slovenian mountain trail.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Q4791o" title="bivy"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1725/41618985814_014999499c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="bivy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream backpacking trip taking you?</strong></p>

<p>Kajo: My dream backpacking trip is constantly changing. Currently it’s PNT (Pacific-Northwest Trail).</p>

<p>Maj: I enjoy taking short trips all over the world, but if I had to choose, the ultimate backpacking experience would be exploring South America.</p>

<p><strong>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong></p>

<p>Kajo: That would probably be my wind jacket. It’s super convenient if you are always a bit cold like I am. In the colder seasons I always bring a pair of Climashield pants with me to keep me warm and cozy.</p>

<p>Maj: I also never leave home without my wind jacket, but other than that, I always pack my knife so I can prepare fresh meals.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/wTxzZ5" title="triglav"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1739/41618973534_3f9a6d3d06_b.jpg" width="1024" height="654" alt="triglav" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the spring in the Julian Alps?</strong></p>

<p>Our trips are mostly planned a day or two before they actually happen. There is still a lot of snow in the Julian Alps, so we’re focused on other areas at the moment. Our next trip will probably be somewhere in the coastal region. What we really like about Slovenia, and in particular the area near the capital, is that a short 1 hour drive can take you to a sub-mediterranean climate at SW, alpine at NW and continental in the eastern parts of the country. So on a good winter day you can choose between snowshoeing or rock climbing in a T-shirt :)</p>

<p><strong>Social Media - on which channels is GramXpert active?</strong></p>

<p>We’re not very active on social media at the moment, but we plan to change that in the future. We occasionally post on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/GramXpert/">Facebook</a> and you can also find us on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/gramxpert/">Instagram</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/86oZ0X" title="tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/878/41439558095_2c558bdcd5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Maj &amp; Kajo, I thank you very much for taking the time to answer my questions =) Is there something you would like to add?</strong></p>

<p>We’re really happy that the ultralight community is growing and supportive when it comes to smaller manufacturers.  Hvala Hendrik for this opportunity to showcase our work, and all the best to you and your readers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[As Tucas Sestrals Quilt]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/as-tucas-sestrals-quilt.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-23T19:34:43+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/as-tucas-sestrals-quilt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Synthetic quilts have become very light, warm &amp; compact during the last five years - reason enough for me to check out the Sestrals Quilt from As Tucas.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42298562271/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="As Tucas Sestrals Quilt, front view"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/878/42298562271_534ffe1d92_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas Sestrals Quilt, front view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from As Tucas. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://www.astucas.com/en/products/sestrals-quilt/">As Tucas Sestrals Quilt</a> is a very light, comfortable and very well made synthetic quilt. It packs small, has little problems with condensation and other sources of moisture, and keeps you toasty at night. Watch the Video to get the full low-down in moving images:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LobFMfTkPsU?rel=0&amp;controls=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received the As Tucas Sestrals Quilt in time for my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/10/impressions-from-the-scottish-cairngorms.html">Cairngorms Traverse</a> last October and have used the quilt on half a dozen trips in the autumn and spring since. Overall it has been slept under for some 14 nights and been used since nine months.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41397124365/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="Sleeping in the Cairngorms"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/958/41397124365_8491cce6ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sleeping in the Cairngorms" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The function of a quilt, like a sleeping bag, is to keep you warm at night. Ideally it is light and packs compact during the day, and is comfortable, easy to use and warm during the night when you are resting.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42298583301/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="Bivy camp in Sipoonkorpi NP"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/950/42298583301_a946a2896b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bivy camp in Sipoonkorpi NP" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The Sestrals packs a bunch of features, here’s the list straight from the As Tucas Website:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It is <em>Longer than most quilts</em></li>
  <li>It is <em>Wider than most quilts</em></li>
  <li>It has a <em>Closed footbox</em></li>
  <li><em>Very easy to use</em></li>
  <li>Made from <em>schoeller®-ftc fabric with ecorepel® finish</em></li>
  <li>Uses <em>Climashield® APEX</em> synthetic insulation, available in three weights</li>
  <li><em>Handcrafted in the Pyrenees, Spain</em></li>
  <li>Available in four lengths, two widths and three insulation strengths (for a total of 24 different configurations - without the colour options!)</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42298586971/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="As Tucas logo patch"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/886/42298586971_75b6398069_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="As Tucas logo patch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>I have used dozens of (down) quilts and have seen lots of different designs, so it’s hard to see something new. However, I really like that As Tucas uses a schoeller fabric for this quilt, schoeller from Switzerland make some of the best UL fabrics out there, and they’re not just light &amp; functional but also have a solid environmental record.</p>

<p>Oh, and while I’m not 100% sure, I think this quilt qualifies as being Vegan 🌿💚</p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The craftsmanship is top-notch. It is a very well designed and manufactured piece of kit and I found nothing to complain about.</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My As Tucas Sestrals Quilt is a Size M with a Regular Width and an Climashield Apex 200 insulation, and weighs 658 g. That is a wee bit heavier than the claimed weight of 625 g but still acceptable.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41397110345/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="Size comparison"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/976/41397110345_26cbe02531_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Size comparison" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I have used some 18 years ago a light and compact synthetic sleeping bag. It packed about the same size as the Sestrals quilt, but it was nowhere near as warm or easy to use as this quilt. Happily I used it mostly in Central America, where it didn’t get too cold at night! As I started to pay attention to the weight of the gear in my backpack some 10 years ago I quickly switched to a quilt. The advantages for me were just too good to pass up, and it has improved my nights outdoors so much that I would encourage anyone who camps outdoors to try a quilt. The Sestrals Quilt from As Tucas is my first synthetic quilt, and thus far I really enjoy using it.</p>

<p>I love how simple it is constructed and how seams have been kept to a minimum, but at the same time paying attention to useful features like the longer hood. It packs down to a compact package and with some pushing and getting the air out I can pack it down to a size of around 6 l volume (that Helsport drybag it is in on the photos is a 10 l sack). It fluffs out easily when in camp, and condensation and dew do it no harm. I have had in the past some sketchy nights in the mountains when from the really warm day temperatures the thermometer suddenly plummets towards 0°C as soon as the sun sets - in those conditions gear that lays outside immediately starts to accumulate small droplets of water, and I had some uncomfortable nights with down quilts in the past.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28425850028/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="Morning dew on the quilt"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/881/28425850028_0ffdbeace8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Morning dew on the quilt" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With the Sestrals Quilt that is no longer a worry. There’s two fabrics to thank for that: First is the schoeller ftc fabric with the ecorepel finish, which is water repellant and the dew or rain just forms in little drops on the top of the fabric (as seen in the photo above, which I shot during my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/microadventure-sipoonkorpi-national-park.html">Sipoonkorpi Microadventure</a>) and that sweet fabric is also free from fluorocarbons (PFC), so it is not harmful to humans, animals and nature. Secondly, the Climashield APEX insulation is synthetic and does not collapse from moisture, unlike down (Hydrophobic down is another story). I had a down sleeping bag collapse on top of me on a winter trip (I sweated it wet) and that was a very uncomfortable night. Even when the quilt would get wet the insulation would not collapse, so while you still might have an uncomfortable night under a wet synthetic quilt you actually could wring it dry and possibly have a halfway decent sleep (now there’s an idea for a future article!).</p>

<p>But away from such horror scenarios! A quilt for me needs to pack small while I am hiking and be light, and on both accounts the Sestrals quilt convinces. At camp I want to easily unpack it and not need to worry about condensation, where it also scores top marks. And then it obviously needs to be warm, comfortable and easy to use while sleeping. I tuck in the quilt at my sides when I go to sleep, and usually have a leg out to “cool down”. I also turn a lot while sleeping, from my left to my back to my right to my stomach and back, and with a quilt that is no problem. I remember nights in a sleeping bag where I ended up trapped inside because I turned too much, and well, that just ain’t nice. All quilts give you that freedom of movement, and the Sestrals maybe even gives you a little bit more freedom because there’s no drawstrings and straps which can trap you.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42251990132/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="Side view"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/978/42251990132_73498f30bd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Side view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Warmth-wise the Climashield Apex 200 is rated to -5°C Comfort, and I found that a realistic rating. In Scotland we had some cold nights which were around the -2°C mark, and I was toasty under the quilt. I am a very warm sleeper so these kind of ratings are always dependent on the person, your metabolism, and many other factors. If you easily feel cold at night take at minimum the APEX 167 quilt if you want to use it from spring to autumn, or maybe even the APEX 200 if you really, really easily feel cold.</p>

<p>In the morning the quilt dries fast in the sun if some dew collected on it (in black at least), and it is easy to pack up again to a compact package, ready to hike. And while I haven’t washed it yet (it hasn’t seen <em>that</em> much use yet) it should be easy to clean this quilt, just toss it in the washing machine, wash it at 40° and then hang it to dry. No need to send it to a special dry cleaner or throw tennis balls into the dryer, like you have to with a down sleeping bag.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42251988122/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="Back view"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/950/42251988122_a439f03406_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>The quilt itself is for me pretty much perfect, but I would like that it also comes with a stuff sack or dry bag when you buy it. A spacious storage bag is included, so the absence of a stuff sack for hiking was a bit strange - a cuben dry bag would be perfect!</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>In ultralight backpacking you always try to optimize the gear to the conditions of the trip ahead. The As Tucas Sestrals Quilt is my spring, summer and autumn quilt when the temperatures at night are expected to be around 0°C but can go colder, and when I expect a lot of rain and wet ground. For these trips the Sestrals quilt has performed admiringly and I had never any concerns that I might have a cold night - be it hiking in the rain in Scotland and camping out or on the Microadventure near Helsinki earlier this month. It is light, compact and very easy &amp; comfortable in use, and I like to take it along on most trips as it’s just a very well made piece of kit that I know will perform and which I don’t need to worry about. With that it makes my backpacking trips more relaxing, and I have had great nights of sleep under the quilt. I look forward to take it along on a trip with the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/eno-sub6-hammock-review.html">ENO Sub6 Hammock</a> later this summer and see how it works in a hammock 🌳🌲!</p>

<p><em>If you want to find out more about As Tucas, read my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/interview-marco-sanchez-of-as-tucas.html">Interview with Marco Sánchez</a>, the founder of the company!</em> And here are <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157669299782358/">more photos of the Sestrals quilt</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>If you are in the market for a quilt which should keep you toasty from spring to autumn, you can order the Sestrals Quilt directly from <a href="https://www.astucas.com/en/products/sestrals-quilt/">As Tucas</a> in every configuration you want, or from <a href="https://www.trekking-lite-store.com/as-tucas-sestrals-quilt-133.html">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a>.</p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this review &amp; video <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28425851418/in/album-72157669299782358/" title="BTS while filming the video"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/881/28425851418_54c35a102c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="BTS while filming the video" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cottage Interview: Paul Stokes of Tread Lite Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-paul-stokes-of-tread-lite-gear.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-21T20:46:59+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-paul-stokes-of-tread-lite-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">Cottages Interviews 2018 Series</a> is a go and kicking things off is Paul from Tread Lite Gear, who makes amazing kit in the UK 🇬🇧!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4m3931" title="Scotland"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/908/42203328842_b94266a2e6_b.jpg" width="960" height="540" alt="Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>I know Paul and <a href="http://www.treadlitegear.co.uk">Tread Lite Gear</a> since several years and have interacted with him on Twitter on and off. Paul’s gear gets very good reviews from other bloggers and the wallets I bought from him a few weeks ago are very nice indeed. Paul has found a niche and serves it really well. But enough from me, here’s Paul’s answers!</em></p>

<p><strong>Paul, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking, and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>Hello all, Im Paul, im 47 and hail from Coventry in the UK. Its about as central in the UK as you can get and is also about as far as you can get from anywhere interesting to walk. Im married and have a 12 year old daughter. Back in my youth I was in the scouts and my Dad also took me on some hiking trips. I think that’s where my love of all things outdoors started. I suspect like many people life gets busy and you put things on the back burner whilst you chase a career, get married and have a family etc. I started getting back out maybe 10 years ago. At the time Ray Mears was doing his thing and for me it started with bushcraft. I quickly realised that what I really wanted to do was get out in the hills and I started to put away the all the heavy kit and look to ways to lighten my load so I could have a more comfortable journey. I also love to hammock and tend to hang in the winter months. If only there were more forests at altitude.</p>

<p><strong>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</strong></p>

<p>Back when I was in employment I tried to get out at least once a month. After starting the company I was permanently broke and reinvesting everything to get it off the ground so trips were pretty thin on the ground. Last year saw a few health issues that kept me off anything too strenuous but hopefully that’s behind me now and im really looking forward to some proper summit time this year. I have already got two long weekends in the diary for end of May and middle of June. It will be a bit of a shock to my legs im sure!</p>

<p><strong>Are you more of a “weekend warrior” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong></p>

<p>These days I’m mostly out on the weekends but back in the days when I had paid holidays I did a few longer trips in Norway, Estonia and Scotland. I think Norway is a stunning country, its hard in the UK to enjoy my love of a hammock but combine it with walking any great distance. My first time was just a week walking around the Nordmarka. It was cool to walk out of Oslo station and get the metro to the trail head. Easy walking and trees on top of most peaks made for some great hangs. My other Norway trip was very different as I headed off to Karasjok way up in the arctic circle for a winter trip. Pulling a toboggan along frozen rivers was truly fantastic. The Estonia trip was great too. Another winter getaway to Laheema National Park. Living in a temperate climate I’d never seen the sea frozen so that was pretty cool. Im hoping to do something special for my 50th in a few years so need to get my thinking cap on for a destination. I’m never likely to get the time to do anything epic but maybe I could do a few sections of one of the big American trails. I hear the AT is pretty hammocky so that appeals.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/786DoS" title="Estonia"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/973/28376482688_fc04c899d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Estonia" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Hiking in Finland Readers &amp; me, we are gear-nerds! What is your typical baseweight?</strong></p>

<p>It is getting there now. Back in the first year of the business I sold pretty much all my high end kit to keep the lights on. At the time it was painful but looking back it did allow me to start with a clean slate. Like most folks I’d learned a lot of lessons over the years about what worked for me and what didn’t so I was able to assemble my ideal kit list as funds permitted. Im at about 4kg base for 3 season ground camping. I recently got hold of a lightly used DCF Khufu from <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/interview-jotaro-yoshida-from-locus-gear.html">Locus Gear</a> and it’s a really quality bit of kit. The inner I find a little tight on length so I’ve just ordered an EE recon bivy to give a bit more room. My go to pack is an old GG Mariposa, it’s a vintage version in silnylon with acres of external mesh pockets. I don’t like to go into my pack until I hit camp so the mesh works great for stuff I need to access through the day. It’s a bit big for most trips but at just over 500g I’m happy to pack my sleep kit loose to pad it out. I always think its strange when I look at the current model and it weighs nearly double. <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2009/11/interview-glen-van-peski-from-gossamer-gear.html">Gossamer Gear</a>, if you are reading this how about an anniversary special that hits the old weights? A 1.5oz DCF body Mariposa would be my dream pack. I have two so maybe one day I might get busy rebuilding one. My sleep mat is a GG Airbeam XL. Sadly no longer made but I love the extra width over my Neoair. I use a Cumulus 250 quilt from spring through autumn and an EE Enigma 10f for winter. Cooking is a Toaks 850 with titanium cone from Stormin Stove Systems and a Speedster alcohol stove all wrapped up in a Tread Lite bag for 179g total. I own a lot of ti pots but the Toaks is great. I can get a meal and a coffee from one boil and the handles located right at the top means its great in a cone and you don’t get hot handles. I won’t bore you with the whole list, but these are the main ones!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/AG283Y" title="Coffee Caddy"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/823/28376483168_5c86c9ee90_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Coffee Caddy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “Tread Lite Gear” came from, and what it stands for.</strong></p>

<p>Getting a name was a nightmare! You start off thinking of every word associated with being light only for a quick google to reveal someone got there first. I wanted something that reflected the UL sector I was aiming at but that also covered all the bases and didn’t pigeon hole any future product plans. In the end a short list was quickly whittled to Tread Lite Gear on the basis it was the only one I could get the domain for. I like it though, I think it sums up what the company is about and it rolls off the tongue nicely.</p>

<p><strong>What makes Tread Lite Gear different from other cottages?</strong></p>

<p>I think the main thing would be the focus on just hiking accessories. Most cottages offer a full service from the small stuff right up to packs, shelters and sleep systems. I wanted to be able to offer off the shelf products with no long waiting time to a high standard and at a reasonable price point. It’s a very simple ethos. It’s just me, one guy, one product at a time. I’m small enough that I get to interact with my customers on a more personal level and I think people like that connection, I know I do!</p>

<p>I don’t do mailshots or undertake paid marketing. I wanted to take a very organic approach to growing the business at a pace that was comfortable. I get sick of emails asking me to review my purchase so that’s a feature I’ll never implement on the site. Life is too short. I also took the decision not to give away kit for review. It’s not that im tight, it’s just that I believe a review carries more weight if someone has parted with money to get it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Uje400" title="Pot and Stove bags"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/829/42203334392_5d4a238a69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pot and Stove bags" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Is Tread Lite Gear your full-time job or “just a hobby”?</strong></p>

<p>I’m full time. I work long hours but I wouldn’t change it. It’s very rare that it actually feels like work. I get to sit and watch box sets on Prime or Netflix all day while I work. Some people say I’m really a TV critic and sewing is a by-product of the process =) I remember after I finished watching Breaking Bad that I’d love to convert a big camper van into a mobile sewing studio!</p>

<p>I love what I do though. I choose my own hours so there is great flexibility and I find it really rewarding. I think I’m probably unemployable now in the real world and every day I’m thankful that I don’t have to put on a suit, get in a car and drive ridiculous distances at the beck and call of others and tow the line. Its taken me a long time to find what I’m happiest doing and I’d never go back. Paying income tax in one go each year takes some getting used to though!</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>I love what I do. I choose my own hours so there is great flexibility and I find it really rewarding.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Tread Lite Gear makes lightweight lanterns and a massive amount of different pockets and bags accessories. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?</strong></p>

<p>In my old life I was a surveyor. I worked in the public sector for a large funding body providing capital funding for education. I left that to go into private practice on the other side of the table preparing property strategies and funding bids for clients. It was a great job and provided a comfortable life but it was stressful and involved a huge amount of travel and staying away from home. When the credit crunch hit, government funding collapsed. I managed to stay in employment and even started my own consultancy company. Eventually there were too many people chasing too little money and work started to be hard to come by. I kept it going a little too long. Usual story of flogging a dead horse when I should have cut and run. So one day I woke up with a pile of debt and no clue about where I wanted to go next but I knew I needed a change. With little cash to fund my gear I started playing at making my own. I bought a singer 201k sewing machine on ebay for £50 and a knackered MSR Hubba Bubba. I cut up the tent and made some awful looking monstrosities haha! I found I really enjoyed it though and after a few weeks of practice stuff started to look good. I thought the UK market was under represented and had potential so I shut the surveying business, flogged my car to release some funds and started the company. My wife went back to work full time to support us while I slowly set about building the business. Year 1 was really tough and I considered chucking it in more than once but deep down I thought it had the legs to go somewhere. Year 2 was much better and Year 3 finally saw the point where it seemed to start to gather some momentum.</p>

<p>In my mind I thought that summers would be really busy and winters would be quiet allowing me to hike more but it didn’t work like that and I seem to be busy year round. December is probably the only time I get to take a proper rest over Christmas and we usually rent a cottage in Norfolk. Long dog walks on huge beaches with big skies are a family favourite and it’s nice to switch off and relax.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4e61e4" title="Tryfan Summit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/952/28376483398_90f46dd160_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Tryfan Summit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I still use the same sewing machine for the majority of my work. It was built in the 1950s and it is still perfect. I like the juxtaposition of sewing space age fabrics on an old machine. I do have a bit of a habit of picking up more Singer 201s. There are 8 in the loft as we speak. A good investment though as prices are going through the roof.</p>

<p>The future is something im thinking about now a lot. Im about at the limit of what one guy can do in a small workshop. I think I’ll tough it out this year but next year I’m going to need some bigger premises and maybe some staff if growth continues. I have a largish garden and would have loved to construct a workshop but alas it’s a big investment so I’ll end up leasing I think. Expansion brings all sorts of extra hassle and more risk but we’ll cross that bridge when we get there.</p>

<p><strong>Any intentions of starting to branch out into other segments, for example offering backpacks or stoves?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t see it but I never say never. There are a few barriers that make it difficult. The UK has lost much of its fabric manufacturing base over the years and the type of materials customers want need to be imported. Packs, and shelters in particular use huge swathes of fabric and I’m not in a position to import tons of fabric at costs that make the economics work. My workshop is pretty compact too which means I don’t have the space for a huge cutting table. Watch the Workshop tour Video to get an idea:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BhC3Rm9cAd0?rel=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>In the short time I’ve been doing this I’ve seen many cottages go to the wall or have huge problems. The online communities are full of stories of people folding and still taking money from people for gear that doesn’t arrive. They always seem to be big ticket items where payment is taken up front and lead times can be huge. There are some very sad stories behind some of these situations and whilst you can empathise, I never want to be in the position of needing to take up front payment or suddenly having a workload that is out of control. Life throws things at you that you have to deal with and always at a time that is inconvenient. Although people cut cottages a lot of slack, when all said and done it’s a business and, you need to act accordingly and fulfil your obligations. For that reason if I ever did branch out into big ticket stuff I would only sell what I could put on the shelf.</p>

<p><strong>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in the United Kingdom that you work with?</strong></p>

<p>Not at this time.</p>

<p><strong>And are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada, the USA and other places?</strong></p>

<p>Not really although there are often interactions on social media.</p>

<p><strong>Your company is now three years old has been getting good reviews and praise from all across Europe. Is business going well?</strong></p>

<p>Yes it’s good. Cash is always tight but each year gets a little easier. I launched the website this year so that’s brought a new dimension to things. I kind of thought that ebay sales would subside as the web became more popular but ebay seems to continue to grow as does the website. In time I hope to get off ebay as it’s a terribly expensive platform to sell on and they are making it more and more admin intensive and bureaucratic for businesses. Im already introducing lines that won’t go on ebay.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/M5E9UJ" title="Packing Cells"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/967/42203326782_192201d601_b.jpg" width="1024" height="961" alt="Packing Cells" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of Chest Pack / Front Pouch, and where the inspiration came from?</strong></p>

<p>The chest pack in itself is very simple in its construction. I’d always liked the idea of a chest pouch and it’s something that customers asked for a lot. Reaching for side pockets can be a pain so it is nice to have somewhere easy to get to. The problem was always attachment to the pack. I’d tried some commercial versions in the past like the OMM trio and a Salomon one and always found them hard to mount to my pack and the weights were poor. I tried a few prototypes of my own but never quite got something that I thought would be a universal fit. The current model seems to tick those boxes and feedback has been great.</p>

<p><strong>Paul, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! What kind of new products are you working on at the moment?</strong></p>

<p>As I mentioned in another question im about at the limit of my time so I don’t have anything major planned. As I write this I’ve finally added cuben packing cells in a few sizes to the website which I’d only ever done previously on a custom basis. My focus over the summer will be weeding out the stuff that’s not really cutting it on the rosta, improving some of the photography and getting more pictures of gear in use whilst expanding some of the options on stuff that’s already there. My time outdoors is precious to me and I hate taking work out with me but I do appreciate studio photos are not as nice as stuff pictured on the hill. I seldom take a camera out with me. It’s too easy to live trips looking through a lens so I tend to just drink it in. I am also a little camera shy.</p>

<p>I’d also like to get a budget range of gear up on the website too as I’m always conscious that we don’t all have unlimited funds to splash out with. It is hard though as the labour costs and overhead are the same no matter what the fabric cost.</p>

<p><strong>Any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong></p>

<p>Not really, DCF (I still prefer the <em>cuben</em> name) is still really the benchmark and I don’t see anything to challenge it in the near future. I see lots of new, heavier weight fabrics that I like though, particularly from the racing sail side of the industry, but obviously their UL appeal is limited. I’m not a huge fan of the recreational lite skin for instance but some of the racing sail lite skin laminates are beautiful.</p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at Tread Lite Gear, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems?</strong></p>

<p>I think it’s a mixture. UL hikers are very knowledgeable. I mean we all spend hours on end looking for solutions and looking at Gucci kit to shave a few more g’s and for sure customers are your biggest asset when it comes to product development. You can’t make every customer suggestion work due to practicalities or economics but you can often implement small changes that make gear more useable. A good exampIe would be the roll top camera strap pocket which came into being after it was requested by Ed and Robin on the trek lite forum. Took me a while to get something I was happy with but they are very popular now.</p>

<p>I’m always kicking around ideas with the guys I walk with too. On my last trip to the Lakes I was testing a new UL rechargeable cuben lantern. Rich and Chiseller quickly made a few suggestions to improve the design and it was on sale the following week. Cheers chaps!</p>

<p>I do love doing something new as it breaks up the routine. I have a list of stuff that I’d like to make or develop when time permits. Some of that is customer driven and some are my own musings on gaps in my lineup.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/CfGa2r" title="Haweswater"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/28376482518_d2d96d62a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haweswater" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Where do your customer come from, and how do they find you?</strong></p>

<p>Last financial year 66% of sales were in the UK and 34% overseas. USA and Germany are about equal as the biggest overseas markets but I ship pretty much everywhere there is a reliable postal service. The UK decision to leave the EU has had a big impact on the strength of Sterling and it has been good for exports. It’s a double edged sword though with most of my input costs being in Dollars or Euros. I’m nervous about the deal that will be put in place post Brexit. It all seems a bit of a mess currently but hopefully it will get hashed out. Whatever happens I guess you just have to adapt. Filling in customs paperwork is already the bane of my life so I hope there isn’t a need for more of it. Politics eh? Its enough to make you go hiking =)</p>

<p>I’m on social media and forums so that is a big pathway to my door. I’ve been lucky to have some exposure from other areas which I’ll mention later if I may. Ebay and Google are probably a big route too.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last trip?</strong></p>

<p>Ennerdale in the Lake District late March for a couple of nights in the hammock. It was dry too. That’s probably my last low level camp this year. It is time to get some high level stuff in, get my fitness back and escape the midge season!</p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream backpacking trip taking you?</strong></p>

<p>I was recently chatting to a Norwegian customer who is about to embark on a trip from the far SW of Norway right up to North Cape (3000km). It’s not a recognised trail but of all the backpacking I’ve done in Norway just makes me glow inside. I think some of that has to do with the great company of people I went with, the warm welcome from local people we met as well as the great beauty of the place. So yea I reckon something similar.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/47Kg3J" title="At the Summit!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/28376483258_412a7231e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="At the Summit!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong></p>

<p>Too many! I love my little cuben lanterns and there is one clipped to all my shelters and hammocks. They weigh very little and its nice not to burn the battery on my head torch in camp and it saves the need to carry a spare cell. I’m a coffee fuelled entity too so my little cuben coffee caddy bag is something that sees a lot of use. Other stuff I’m never without is my Zebralight head torch. It has never let me down. My swing lite flex brolly, my old school Mariposa pack and a Fenix 5 watch for route tracking and data. I never thought an Umbrella would be something I’d take but it’s surprisingly useful and hey it is orange! I do like bright colours and own very little stuff in earthy tones. Top of my wish list is the new Garmin Inreach Mini. I seldom have a phone signal when hiking so it would be nice to text the wife to tell her I’m alive once in a while. I’ll wait a while and see what people think of it in use.</p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the spring in the United Kingdom?</strong></p>

<p>Yes indeed. Lake District end of May and middle of June. May to meet up with a few mates and June to meet some of the friends I’ve never met from the excellent <a href="http://trek-lite.com/index.php">Trek-Lite.com forum</a>. After that I’d like to get over to Snowdonia for a few trips. I like my mountains craggy and gnarly. Tryfan and the Glyders are a favourite.</p>

<p><strong>Social Media - on which channels is Tread Lite Gear active?</strong></p>

<p>I am on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/treadlitegear/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Treadlitegear/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/@treadlitegear">Twitter</a> for work and active on the Trek-Lite.com forum which I try to keep for more personal enjoyment although work does creep in as you’d expect. I recently culled a lot of the Facebook groups I’m active on a personal level as my feed was just solid hiking related and sometimes it’s nice to see what my family and friends are up to. I read BPL from time to time but I prefer smaller more close knit places. Hammock forums is somewhere I visit too and Reddit occasionally as I’m not mad on the interface although the content is good. I probably spend too much time online but most of the people I hike with I met through online community meetups. I don’t think I’ve ever met anyone I didn’t get on with and it’s always nice to put a face to a name.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/RvuFDD" title="Morning glory"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/946/28376483348_5c858970fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Morning glory" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Paul, I thank you very much for taking the time to answer my questions =) Is there something you would like to add?</strong></p>

<p>Well firstly thanks for reaching out to do the interview Hendrik. I’ve been lucky to have a lot of other people help in getting my name out there too so I would like to also offer them some thanks if that’s OK.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theoutdoorsstation.co.uk/2017/01/no-424-tread-lite-gear/">Bob Cartwright at the Outdoor Station</a> interviewed me last year which I really enjoyed and definitely had a positive impact on the business. To <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com">Chris Townsend</a> and the <a href="https://www.tgomagazine.co.uk">TGO Magazine</a> team who recently did a feature which has again given a boost to things and rather impressed my daughter at the same time. She took great delight in going to buy a copy and then texting pictures to everyone.</p>

<p>Thanks also to all the people on Facebook, Twitter, Insta, blog writers and Youtubers who share my posts and mention my products - many of whom have become friends!</p>

<p>My wife deserves special praise for her support, allowing me to steal away time working when I should be spending it with the family and yet still encouraging me to get out and hike.</p>

<p>Last but no means least, my customers. I get tons of messages offering thanks and encouragement. You keep the dream alive! It is deeply appreciated!</p>

<p>Happy Trails,</p>

<p>Paul</p>

<hr />

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this interview &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hanging Between Trees 🌳🌲🌴 - a Look at the ENO Sub6 Hammock]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/eno-sub6-hammock-review.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-18T21:20:54+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/eno-sub6-hammock-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In Finland, Sweden and Norway we have plenty of 🌳🌲🌲🌳🌲🌲🌳🌳🌲🌲🌲, a logical conclusion is thus to carry a hammock when you want to relax in the forest! In the past hammocks have been bulky, heavy and difficult to set up - that is not the case if you carry the ultralight ENO Sub6 Hammock and the amazing ENO Helios Suspension System. They let you lay in your hammock in less than two minutes on your next backpacking trip or day hike - reason enough for me to check them out!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175363991/in/dateposted/" title="Chilling"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/910/42175363991_ba6803793f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from Eagle Nest Outfitters and Partioaitta. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5s5Kj85_nfM?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I have tried several hammocks over the last years, but never really fell in love with them. Either they were too bulky, too uncomfortable or just too troublesome to set up. That changed as the <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/shop/eagle-nest-outfitters-sub6-hammock-1005617-charcoal/">Sub6 Hammock</a> and the <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/shop/eagle-nest-outfitters-helios-suspension-system-1005620-grey/">Helios Suspension System</a> from <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/tuotemerkit/eagle-nest-outfitters/">Eagle Nest Outfitters</a> arrived at Hiking in Finland HQ. At first I couldn’t believe how tiny and light the hammock and tree straps were, so I went out in the garden to see if they really work.</p>

<p>Well, they do! I came back in, showed them to my wife (who loves hammocks!) and told her that I got a nice hammock in which she can relax the next time we go on a day hike or visit the beach. She too couldn’t believe how light and compact they were, but after another demonstration in the garden she was convinced! <em>“So how light are they?”</em> you might be wondering. Well, according to my scale the Sub6 Hammock is 163 g including the Stuff Sack, and the Helios Suspension System is 123 g total, that’s 5 g for the stuff sack and 58 g per strap. Together they are 286 g, which is pretty amazing in my books!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28302880728/in/dateposted/" title="An Ultralight Hammock Combo!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/911/28302880728_bd3f35f69d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="An Ultralight Hammock Combo!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175361661/in/dateposted/" title="Helios Suspension System"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/976/42175361661_79b1b45aff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Helios Suspension System" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41274731205/in/dateposted/" title="Connect Hammock Here -&gt;"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/909/41274731205_e66969f801_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Connect Hammock Here -&gt;" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28302883568/in/dateposted/" title="It&#x27;s Sandals &amp; Shorts weather!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/903/28302883568_dd2029d670_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="It&#x27;s Sandals &amp; Shorts weather!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Since then I had the hammock along on some bike rides and day hikes and was always again amazed at how light and how easy to set up this combo is. That alone means it’s almost a no-brainer to take these two along instead of a sit pad, as they are smaller than a 500 ml water bottle (in Fact they are so small that I sometimes need to rummage through my backpack to find them =). It now takes me less than two minutes to put up the hammock to the trees and lay down in it, and after some practicing I also have it down to operate the stove from the hammock and prepare the coffee while chilling! It adds a whole new layer of relaxation in nature to my hikes, and I have found myself napping in the shade of the trees while the wind plays with the leafs far above me.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175346741/in/dateposted/" title="Boiling water from the hammock"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/968/42175346741_2d7f8f5f84_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boiling water from the hammock" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40368021030/in/dateposted/" title="Underbelly Gear Sling"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/911/40368021030_3c5e2acdb2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Underbelly Gear Sling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175359321/in/dateposted/" title="Lots of awesome ENO kit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/910/42175359321_4cc61b34fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lots of awesome ENO kit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But that ain’t all: ENO makes everything you would need for hammocking, including an underquilt so you don’t get cold, the Underbelly Gear Sling which is a Mini-Hammock for your backpack &amp; gear, a bug net to keep the Mosquitos out and a Tarp which keeps you dry. That means if you fall in love with hammocking after you’ve had the Sub6 along on some day hikes and feel like you want to sleep in it, you now can add the gear you need and are ready for sleeping elevated in the forest! I have a bunch of ENO hammocking gear here and plan to try hammock camping again this summer, and I have a feeling that I will like it much better this time around.</p>

<p><strong>In conclusion</strong> it is safe to say that for day trips in the forest and afternoons at the beach we have a tiny &amp; light addition to the backpack with the ENO Helios Suspension System and the Sub6 Hammock. They are easy to put up, so very comfortable to chill in and don’t need a lot of space in the backpack. And with all the 🌲🌲🌳🌲🌲🌲🌳🌲 we have here in Finland it’s about time we elevate ourselves from the ground! If you’d like to try the Sub6 Hammock and Helios Suspension System yourselves, head over to <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/tuotemerkit/eagle-nest-outfitters/">Partioaitta</a> who carry the gear here in Finland!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42175348611/in/dateposted/" title="Chilling under the Underbelly"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/950/42175348611_9d1bb1992b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling under the Underbelly" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this trip report &amp; video <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[24 Hours in Sipoonkorpi National Park (a Microadventure)]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/microadventure-sipoonkorpi-national-park.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-16T10:34:01+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/microadventure-sipoonkorpi-national-park</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you prefer the Outdoors over Cities but need to go to Helsinki - squeeze in a Microadventure to Sipoonkorpi National Park the next time you are in the Capital of Finland!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337489450/in/dateposted/" title="Chilling at Sunset"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/976/40337489450_c4f9faa8f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling at Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Last week I was going to Helsinki for <a href="https://pingfestival.fi">PING Festival 2018</a> and I decided to sneak in a wee Microadventure in <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/sipoonkorpinp">Sipoonkorpi National Park</a> before the event. Sipoonkorpi is a new-ish National Park and less than an hour by bus away from the centre of Helsinki, so it makes for an excellent place to escape the city for a while and enjoy this unique park with its forests, hills and beautiful nature. If you prefer Video over photos and want to see some enchanting Drone Footage, relaxed hiking and me brushing my teeth just hit play:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZXMh_jyu2es?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I took the train to Helsinki, a great way to do some work and watch the latest Episode of Neo Magazine Royale, and then jumped on the Tram to the Clarion Helsinki to drop of the stuff I needed for the following few days in Helsinki and Ruka. Then it was off with the Bus to Sipoonkorpi National Park, which lays on the outskirts of Vantaa, one of the three cities which makes up the Helsinki Metropolitan area. I got off in the middle of nowhere at a scenic road. I followed the sign to the Tractor Museum and then just walked down the road where I saw the blue “Sipoonkorpi National Park” sign. Shortly after I saw the Luontopolku sign, this trail can be walked in either direction but as it was early in the day and I had an idea where I wanted to sleep and what I wanted to see when I followed the trail first north.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144268101/in/dateposted/" title="Entering the National Park"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/830/42144268101_25ab3fb891_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Entering the National Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337492750/in/dateposted/" title="And there&#x27;s the Nature Path!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/907/40337492750_bcf8920e3b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And there&#x27;s the Nature Path!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337484140/in/dateposted/" title="Wood Anemone"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/40337484140_6437bfc456_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wood Anemone" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Right away I loved the little trail - Wood Anemone were everywhere along the narrow trail which went through a very young forest which was beautiful, and then one got a first taste of the granite slick rocks which I later see a lot in the Högberget section of the trail. This section was short and after a short while I was out on the forest road again, before entering a more shaded pine forest on the other side. This section ended also again in that same forest road, and then the trail went on the road further till a parking lot where quite a few cars were parked and a few boulderers where just shouldering their crashpads to go hug some pebbles in the National Park’s surroundings. I followed the trail towards the Kalkkiruukki Laavu, which was very busy with day hikers grilling sausages and enjoying the fantastic warm weather.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144269461/in/dateposted/" title="Kalkkiruukki Laavu"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/980/42144269461_56fc976e99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kalkkiruukki Laavu" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337485940/in/dateposted/" title="Signs &amp; Portents"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/824/40337485940_d2cae06a34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Signs &amp; Portents" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144265471/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking too fast"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/970/42144265471_a7323be439_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking too fast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I sat down for an hour or so, drunk a coffee and shot some video scenes, and complained on Instagram that my NEW Katadyn BeFree 1l bottle was apparently already broken as I got it (<a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel/status/996281448062705664">see it here on Twitter</a>). I packed up and then the trail continued for a few kilometres through dark pine forests, past rocks, climbing up and down and over streams. The path was wide and great condition, and here and there one could see where the winter XC trail goes. I had a chat with two women who where hiking with their dog and inquired about Ticks, and according to them these little pests are not a problem here (I didn’t encounter any).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423898904/in/dateposted/" title="Only a short stroll to Högberget"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/825/41423898904_bcb18926b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Only a short stroll to Högberget" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423901054/in/dateposted/" title="Högberget from above!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/828/41423901054_08a0cfefe6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Högberget from above!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144265851/in/dateposted/" title="Högberget!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/954/42144265851_4e53c82b72_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Högberget!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then I arrived at Högberget! These are probably the most popular spot of the National Park, I saw a lot of people here, enjoying the view from the higher rocks towards the city and sea beyond (I didn’t see the Baltic, but it should be possible to see it on a clear day). These slick granite rocks are really nice and I decided that I wanted to sleep under the stars somewhere over there, though as there was no water close by I first needed to find a water source - and I wanted to finish the trail before looking for a place to sleep. As the days are long in Finland now - the sun sets somewhere around 22:30 - I had enough time to do everything, and still could find a nice spot to roll out my mat &amp; quilt and have something to eat.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144266671/in/dateposted/" title="Trails"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/905/42144266671_660cc89c18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trails" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423898614/in/dateposted/" title="Death &amp; Young"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/969/41423898614_ac932c684f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Death &amp; Young" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41423900404/in/dateposted/" title="Dessert &#x3D;)"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/972/41423900404_48864e2a62_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dessert &#x3D;)" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41243046955/in/dateposted/" title="Goes on"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/963/41243046955_841eb20bc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Goes on" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144267591/in/dateposted/" title="I go to bed"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/42144267591_5618124f3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I go to bed" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I slept shortly that night - because I got up at 1:00 o’clock to photograph the stars, and low-and-behold, I got very lucky as I even captured some Northern Lights! In May! The next morning I slept in as long as I could before the sun was just too warm, made breakfast, shot a video about the As Tucas Sestrals quilt and then ran back to the Bus stop to catch the Bus back to Helsinki - I had a Design Tour to attend and didn’t want to meet that!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144264151/in/dateposted/" title="Barefoot Breakfast"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/909/42144264151_c1f8fe7e5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Barefoot Breakfast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144277081/in/dateposted/" title="After-hike Burger"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/907/42144277081_2cf23f1d17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="After-hike Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All in all it was a fantastic little trip: Beautiful warm T-Shirt weather, stars and Northern Lights, beautiful nature and lots of fresh green on the ground and trees! If you come to Helsinki, Espoo or Vantaa (or life there!) and have an extra day, do it like me: Take along your Ultralight backpack, some food and hop on the Bus to Sipoonkorpi National Park!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144269981/in/dateposted/" title="Calazo Sipoo Map!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/976/42144269981_6e86295399_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Calazo Sipoo Map!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-there--what-you-need">How to get there &amp; what you need</h2>

<p>I took Bus 717A from next to the Helsinki Railway Station to Sotunki, Google Maps or the Reittiopas Website are recommended to find the times when the bus goes and see where you have to get off (which is <em>Kalkkiuunintie</em> and should be displayed in the Bus, too). From there follow the sign which says <em>Trollberga</em> and <em>Traktori- ja Konemuseo</em> and after around 250 m you’ll see the blue Sipoonkorven Kansallispuito sign above. From the bus stop the complete nature path is around 8 km in length, and you can hike it either direction. A water bottle and some snacks are recommended for a day trip, if you want stay for the night bring a mattress, quilt and bivy which are appropriate for the season, and possibly a tarp or tent if you do not want to stay in one of the lean-to shelters. <strong>Questions?</strong> Ask me on Twitter of Facebook!</p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1746" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731746" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1746"></script>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this trip report &amp; video <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 283]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/twir-283.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-11T23:53:45+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/twir-283</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Flickering green/ a hint of orange/ the night is gone.”</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41367965264/in/dateposted/" title="Northern Lights in May!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/944/41367965264_33b1cefbd1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Northern Lights in May!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-news">Outdoor News</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/apr/17/poland-violated-eu-laws-by-logging-in-biaowieza-forest-says-ecj">Poland violated EU laws by logging in Białowieża forest</a>, court rules.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/40548564/better-technology-isnt-the-solution-to-ecological-collapse">Better Technology isn’t the Solution</a> to Ecological Collapse.</p>

<p>Great news for nature: The <a href="https://www.mnn.com/earth-matters/animals/blogs/eu-passes-total-ban-neonicotinoids-bee-harming-pesticides">EU passes a total ban on bee-harming pesticides</a>.</p>

<p>Yay, I <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">announced the Cottages Interviews 2018 Series</a>! If you like ultralight gear makers you definitely should <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">subscribe via RSS</a> to not miss these!</p>

<p>The <a href="https://blog.outdoor-spirit.de/outdoor-spirit-podcast-38-was-ist-eigentlich-dieses-glamping/">Outdoor-Spirit Podcast #38</a> is out and talks about Glamping. [German]</p>

<p>Should we be <a href="http://eveningsends.com/crowdfunding-rescues/">crowdfunding resuces</a>?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.gipfel-glueck.de/fit-fuer-die-berge-7-yoga/">Yoga for hikers</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Something to look forward to: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2018/may/05/happiness-curve-life-gets-better-after-50-jonathan-rauch">Life gets better after 50</a> (Why age tends to work in favour of happiness).</p>

<p>How to <a href="https://youtu.be/A9BgTdQ0AzM">Lightpaint with Steel Wool</a>.</p>

<p>An <a href="https://brazenbackpacker.com/2018/05/03/ode-to-the-instagram-hiker/">Ode to the Instagram Backpacker</a>.</p>

<p>Learn to understand the <a href="https://www.photopills.com/articles/understanding-golden-hour-blue-hour-and-twilights">Golden Hour, Blue Hour and Twilights</a>.</p>

<p>SmugMug <a href="https://www.smugmug.com/together/">bought Flickr</a>.</p>

<p>Revelate Designs launched a new seat pack, the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fproduct%2F131608%2Frevelate-designs-terrapin-system-saddle-pack-8-liters">Terrapin System 8L</a>.</p>

<p>Garmin unveiled the new <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fproduct%2F140110%2Fgarmin-inreach-mini-2-way-satellite-communicator">inReach Mini</a>.</p>

<p>Impressions from the <a href="http://www.goout.hk/2018/05/10/dlgm-ii/">DLGM II</a>.</p>

<p>Check out the new <a href="https://katabaticgear.com/shop/knik-liteskin-40l-backpack/">LiteSkin</a> backpacks from Katabatic Gear.</p>

<p>Buy a <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=47cd1998-e608-4548-aa0f-3d33e964ad3a&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.hyperlitemountaingear.com%2Fallproducts.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Backpack</a> and get a free Pod to organize your gear!</p>

<p>You want to vote with your £$€ when you buy gear and buy from companies which think about social and environmental matters? You can now shop by sustainability attributes on the REI website, for example by searching for “<a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fsearch.html%3Fq%3DMade%2Bin%2BUSA%26origin%3Dweb%26ir%3Dq%253AMade%2Bin%2BUSA%26page%3D1">Made in USA</a>” “<a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fsearch.html%3Fq%3Dfair%2Btrade%26origin%3Dweb%26ir%3Dq%253Afair%2Btrade%26page%3D1">fair trade</a>” or “<a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fsearch.html%3Fq%3Dorganic%2Bcotton%26origin%3Dweb%26ir%3Dq%253Aorganic%2Bcotton%26page%3D1">Organic Cotton</a>”.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/337979" title="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Salomon_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/825/28162269868_393289209f_z.jpg" width="640" height="336" alt="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Salomon_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Win a <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/salomon-hike-plus-outfit/">Salomon Multisport Outfit</a> in this Photo Contest.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/kNCR8Y" title="Bergzeit_Frischluftkick-adidas_terrex_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/903/28162269538_6fbf8b56d2_z.jpg" width="640" height="336" alt="Bergzeit_Frischluftkick-adidas_terrex_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Stay at the Explorer Hotel Kitzbühel and get a sweet adidas terrex apparel outfit in this <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/bergzeit-frischluft-kick-adidas-terrex-explorer-kitzbuehel/">contest</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4v74D4" title="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Deuter_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/951/41990925382_e1e4f900c9_z.jpg" width="640" height="336" alt="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Deuter_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Win a trip to the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/alpincamp/deuter-klettern-wilder-kaiser/">Wilder Kaiser Region</a> and Deuter kit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/3yiyy3" title="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel-Icebreaker_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/826/41990925062_c0741b94dd_z.jpg" width="640" height="336" alt="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel-Icebreaker_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And finally, win 500€ worth of <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">Icebreaker Cool-Lite garments</a> for your next adventure!</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fnew-arrivals%3Ffl%3Dtrue">new arrivals at Backcountry</a>.</p>

<p>Summer is here, and so are the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/walking-trousers/?listorderby=oxinsert&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">new hiking trousers</a> for this season.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=706625&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/706625/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Agnieszka is hitting the trail again! This year she will be <a href="https://acrossthewilderness.blogspot.fi/2018/05/continental-divide-trail-crazy-cook.html">hiking the Continental Divide Trail</a>. [Polish]</p>

<p>Drew hikes to <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2018/05/07/hiking-to-el-montanon-peak-santa-cruz-island/">El Montanon Peak</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://freedirtmonger.blogspot.fi/2018/05/desert-trail-death-valley.html">Desert Trail: Death Valley</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://photomomlinda.blogspot.fi/2018/04/sedona-hiking-hiline-trail.html">Hiking the Hiline Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Backpacking on <a href="https://ultralightpedestrian.com/2018/04/24/bornholm-rundt-langs-kyststien/">Bornholm</a>. [Danish]</p>

<p>It was a <a href="https://coastkid.blogspot.fi/2018/05/saturdays-big-sky-day.html">Big Sky Saturday</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://steviehaston.blogspot.fi/2018/05/the-dalliance-of-eagles-by-stevie.html">The Dalliance of Eagles</a>.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/264661267?color=ffffff" width="640" height="338" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://urbanflyfisher.com/how-time-flies/">How time flies</a>.</p>

<p>A hike up <a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/hiking/mt-tenmoku/">Mt. Tenmoku 天目山</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fsc%2Fthru-hiking-the-oregon-coast-trail%3FINT_ID%3DIB23734">Thru-Hiking the Oregon Coast Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2018/04/7-auf-einen-streich-revierbeschreibung.html">7 Packrafting trips in Croatia</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.planetapackraft.com/2018/05/packrafting-en-rusia-ii-los-urales.html">Packrafting in Russia</a>. [Spanish]</p>

<p>Read the <a href="http://ladyonarock.com/2018/04/30/john-muir-trail-northbound-guide/">John Muir Trail Northbound Guide</a> before hiking it!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plog/bombtrack-romagna-bike-trail/">Bombtrack on the Romagna Bike Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/stories/roadside-intervention/">Bikepacking with Keith Richards</a>.</p>

<p>And some beautiful impressions from <a href="https://willemvandoorne.wordpress.com/2018/05/13/greenland-2017-part-ii-disko-island/">Willem’s 2017 Greenland adventures</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28214430548/in/dateposted/" title="Lunch with a View"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/946/28214430548_d6e7bd5625_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lunch with a View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>Matthias embarked on an epic bikepacking tour across Europe - <a href="https://quasiout.de/dracula-skischanzen-und-juetlands-brise-packliste-fuer-mein-far-packing-2018/">here’s the gear he has along</a>. [German]</p>

<p>The Great Outdoors <a href="https://www.tgomagazine.co.uk/review/review-ordnance-survey-aventura-gps/">reviews the OS Aventura GPS</a>.</p>

<p>Read Kat’s <a href="http://attitude-over-ability.com/te-araroa-gear-debrief/">Te Araroa Gear Debrief</a> before heading to New Zealand.</p>

<p>Chris reflects on <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2018/05/40-years-on-gear-for-long-distance.html">Gear for Long-Distance Walks Then &amp; Now</a>.</p>

<p>Martin’s gear list for his <a href="https://www.gehlebt.at/hoamatroas-packliste/">1370 km Hoamatroas hike</a>. [German]</p>

<p>First impressions of the <a href="https://pig-monkey.com/2018/05/kojin/">Kojin Stove</a>.</p>

<p>Alex helps you sew a <a href="https://www.bergreif.de/2018/04/11/ultraleichten-myog-biwaksack-naehen/">breathable bivy bag</a> and a <a href="https://www.bergreif.de/2018/05/02/ultraleicht-1-personen-silnylon-tarp-naehen/">1P Tarp</a>. [German]</p>

<p>First impressions of the <a href="https://theultralightguru.wordpress.com/2018/03/23/first-impressions-on-the-atom-from-atompacks/">Atom backpack</a> from Atom Packs.</p>

<p>Ken reviews the <a href="https://ultralightandcomfortable.com/2018/04/26/gear-review-gossamer-gear-the-one-tent/">Gossamer Gear The One</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/plan/five-bikepacking-tool-kits/">What’s in your tool kit</a>?</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing the Cottages Interviews 2018 Series]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-02T18:47:06+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Be prepared for more than a dozen of fresh cottage interviews coming this spring and summer to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com">Hiking in Finland</a> =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40943661375/in/dateposted/" title="Announcing the Cottages Interviews 2018"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/832/40943661375_1cb2a9403e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Announcing the Cottages Interviews 2018" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Almost ten years after I started the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/interviews/">Cottage Interview Series</a> they are back! I always really enjoyed conducting these interviews and getting to know the people behind the gear, and what drives them. It’s just - around eight years ago I slowly ran out of companies to interview 😊 But during the last years more &amp; more new cottages came into existence, and many of them have a unique solution or design on how to make our bacpacking trips more fun - and lighter! Thus over the next several months I will be interviewing some of the newest Ultralight cottages across the globe to find out what drives them, but I also will be re-visiting some of the cottages I interviewed way back in the day and find out how they are doing in 2018!</p>

<p>If you are interested in what drives ultralight gear makers, what goes into designing and making an ultralight hammock, backpack, quilt or hoody - you will want to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">subscribe via RSS</a> to the blog or become a Fan &amp; Follower on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> where I also will announce the new articles. Excited? Better be - the first interview will go up in two weeks!</p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy reading Hiking in Finland <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">get me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on this blog to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 282]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/04/twir-282.html"/>
    <updated>2018-04-09T13:53:45+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/04/twir-282</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>A goal/ blue sky/ into the mist</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39218815430/in/dateposted/" title="Getting there"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/815/39218815430_7d2e395259_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Getting there" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-news">Outdoor News</h2>

<p>Marc-André Leclerc and Ryan Johnson have <a href="https://gripped.com/news/canadian-marc-andre-leclerc-has-passed-away-in-alaska/">passed away while on a climb in Alaska</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.gq.com/story/patagonia-versus-donald-trump">Patagonia vs. Donald Trump</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/G40ooKzI664">Climate Change is Killing this Alaskan Village</a>.</p>

<p>Take a minute to <a href="https://actions.sumofus.org/a/stop-hydroelectric-power-plants-on-albania-s-wild-rivers">Stop Hydroelectric Power Plants on Albania’s Wild Rivers</a>.</p>

<p>Join the <a href="https://swiftcampout.com">Swift Campout</a> on June 23rd and 24th - mark it in your calendars!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.atompacks.co.uk">Atom Packs</a> is a new cottage out of the United Kingdom.</p>

<p>NEW: The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/04/trailblazers-locus-gear-djedi-dome-tent.html">LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent</a>.</p>

<p>Are you a content creator that loves the outdoors? Then meet like-minded people at the <a href="http://www.outdoor-show.com/od-en/press/blogger.php">Outdoor Show in Friedrichshafen</a>.</p>

<p>Support the <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/gnarbox/gnarbox-20-ssd-rugged-backup-device-for-your-camer?ref=hendrikmorkel">GNARBOX 2.0 SSD</a> – Rugged backup device for your camera</p>

<p>Need something to read for the next weeks? Buy <a href="https://amzn.to/2GDDCKS">Bothy Tales: Footsteps in the Scottish hills</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/2uQkWCf">High and Low: How I Hiked Away From Depression Across Scotland</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tgomagazine.co.uk/skills/navigation-skills/digital-feature-the-future-of-mountain-navigation-and-mapping/">The future of Mountain Navigation and Mapping</a>.</p>

<p>Awesome use of Tax Money: <a href="https://www.citylab.com/life/2018/03/european-union-interrail-travel-ticket-for-teenagers/554978/">The EU is giving Teens a Month of Free Train Travel Across Europe</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/environmentalisms-racist-history">Environmentalism’s Racist History</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/03/02/climate/bears-ears-national-monument.html">Oil Was Central in Decision to Shrink Bears Ears Monument</a></p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/aIYtuqLs030">Astrophotography with the Sony A7 III</a>.</p>

<p>Andrew interviews the <a href="https://andrewskurka.com/2018/ultralight-jerk-instagram/">Ultralight Jerk</a>.</p>

<p>Martin joins the <a href="https://www.gehlebt.at/rother-neuheiten-2019/">Bergverlag Rother</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=beEcJ7toodo">Drawn To High Places</a>.</p>

<p>There’s <a href="https://swisspowder.wordpress.com/2018/04/03/april-2018-still-meters-of-snow-in-the-swiss-alps/">still Meters of Snow in the Swiss Alps</a> so ski-touring season isn’t over yet.</p>

<p>Agnes shares her tips on <a href="https://acrossthewilderness.blogspot.fi/2018/04/sposoby-na-urazy-jak-uniknac-kontuzji.html">how to prevent injuries</a>. [Polish]</p>

<p>Spring. A new Season means new Gear - check out the latest <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/new/category--outdoor-clothing/?pid=10239">outdoor apparel</a> and <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/trail-running-shoes/?pid=10239">trailrunning shoes</a> for your next hike!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=49341&amp;pw=73183">ULA Equipment Backpacks</a> have FREE US Shipping on ALL Orders!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/23D0Va" title="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_Buff_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/894/39530188810_8f6d929cb3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="538" alt="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_Buff_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Win tickets for the <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">Salomon Trails 4 Germany</a> and a full BUFF package.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/59zL6k" title="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Dynafit_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/872/26467825887_a8d9e9af96_b.jpg" width="1024" height="538" alt="Bergzeit_Alpincamp-Dynafit_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Hike with <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/alpincamp/dynafit-watzmann-drei-zinnen/">Dynafit from the Großer Watzman to the Tre Cime</a> and get the full kit, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/X07m34" title="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Bergans_Blog"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/822/41296653012_50a7867236_b.jpg" width="1024" height="538" alt="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Bergans_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Photographers can <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/bergans-floyen-outfit/">win an outfit from Bergans</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=706625&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/706625/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p>Benjamin and family hike the <a href="http://hrxxlight.com/2018/03/muggestutz-dwarf-adventure-trail/">Dwarf Adventure Trail</a>.</p>

<p>Paulina shares her <a href="https://www.littlegrunts.com/5-favorite-bay-area-hikes/">5 Favorite Bay Area Hikes</a>.</p>

<p>How about skiing <a href="https://walkingwomad.com/2018/03/08/winter-ski-tour-sarek-lapland/">11 days along the Padjelantaleden, through Sarek National Park and along the Kungsleden</a>?</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/VW77mXpkQQ0">Never coming home</a>.</p>

<p>Kelly heads <a href="https://kellycordes.com/2018/03/22/into-the-whiteout/">into the Whiteout</a> to go winter climbing in Scotland.</p>

<p>Geoff headed out to <a href="https://farnotfast.blogspot.fi/2018/04/march-backpack-bleaklow-and-kinder.html">Bleaklow and Kinder</a>.</p>

<p>Kathrin hiked through the <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/suedafrika-trekking-amatola-trail-erfahrungsbericht/">Amatola Mountains</a> in South Africa. [German]</p>

<p>Jill shares <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2018/03/photos-from-iditarod-trail.html">photos from the Iditarod Trail</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://ridgelineimages.com/hiking/shikinejima-coastal-hike/">Shikinejima Coastal Hike</a>.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/10uM6IU8S6U?rel=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>A <a href="https://www.thehikinglife.com/2018/03/a-quick-dirty-guide-to-the-sierra-high-route/">Quick &amp; Dirty Guide to the Sierra High Route</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2018/03/a-night-in-ben-alder-cottage.html">A night in Ben Alder Cottage</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://consequencesofmindfulness.com/2018/02/27/cigarettes-silhouettes-running-the-cancelled-lovit-100-mile-trail-run/">Running the Cancelled LOViT 100 Mile Trail Run</a>.</p>

<p>James hikes from <a href="https://backpackingbongos.wordpress.com/2018/04/02/the-arctic-trail-kautokeino-to-kilpisjarvi-pt4-mountains-and-waterfalls/">Kautokeino to Kilpisjärvi</a> in the 4th part of his Arctic Trail adventure.</p>

<p>Looks like a fun hike in Germany, the <a href="http://awesomatik.de/der-schluchtensteig-etappen-1-bis-3/">Schluchtensteig</a>. [German]</p>

<p>And <a href="http://www.highlux.co.nz/2018/03/colombia-salento-valle-de-cocora-bogota/">bikepacking in Colombia</a> looks amazing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37562880556/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Morning Glory"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4490/37562880556_2086b79487_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Morning Glory" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/E5LP_YFXJIM">f-stop gear Tilopa Review</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity.html">Osprey Exos or Osprey Levity</a> - Which Backpack to Get?</p>

<p>Quasi builds his <a href="https://quasiout.de/salsa-vaya-custom-bike-3-0-umbau-zum-bikepacking-tourer/">Salsa Vaya Custom Bike 3.0</a>.</p>

<p>Drew reviews the <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2018/03/31/gear-review-five-ten-access-knit-hiking-shoes/">Five Ten Access Knit Hiking Shoes</a>.</p>

<p>Sandra reviews the <a href="http://www.fastpacking.de/2018/03/21/gastbeitrag-testbericht-dd-superlight-pyramid-tent-und-pyramid-mesh-tent/">DD Superlight Pyramid Tent and Pyramid Mesh Tent</a>. [Germany]</p>

<p>Chris Townsend writes about the <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2018/04/tents-and-tarps-ive-used-for-long.html">tents and tarps I’ve used for long-distance walking over the decades</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/news/nordest-sardinha/">Nordest Sardinha Bikepacking Rig</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trailblazers: LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/04/trailblazers-locus-gear-djedi-dome-tent.html"/>
    <updated>2018-04-05T19:30:23+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/04/trailblazers-locus-gear-djedi-dome-tent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent is finally available for Sale - it is the first Dome tent made from the new waterproof-breathable Dyneema® Composite Fabric and tips the scales at a sweet 980 g!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/C55727" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/866/39440149990_460ed33c86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I have followed Jotaro’s development of the LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent over the last four years, being very interested in this amazing little tent. I find free-standing dome tents a great and useful design, and the lighter the package the better. During the past winter Jotaro hinted that the tent might soon be ready for production - and that moment has now arrived!</p>

<p>Watch the Video to get some insights on how the Djedi became a reality.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BMl0DWL6JCI?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Quite a great story, and also interesting to see a little bit into the LOCUS GEAR workshop! I caught up with Jotaro and here’s a wee background on the design and production process:</p>

<p>“Most people think it’s a Star Wars thing,” says Jotaro, “But originally ‘Djedi’ is an Egyptian God’s name. ‘Djedi’ starts with the letter D, and D is also the shape of the dome.” Jotaro needed almost four years to be happy with what he considered the ultimate dome tent: The strong, lightweight, waterproof and breathable Djedi Dome – the first Dome tent made with Dyneema® Composite Fabric with eVent. This fabric combines the advantages of two very popular fabrics in the ultralight niche - Dyneema Composite Fabric and eVent. The result is a lightweight fabric which is waterproof and exceptionally breathable.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0t67Fj" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/876/39439981060_0c69470051_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/22WjTt" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/900/39439979840_2dd51bf08c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>“I made eight different prototypes using different fabrics but was never satisfied,” says Jotaro. “Condensation is a major problem for anyone who camps. And if your inside walls and then possibly your down sleeping bag and other gear gets wet, the situation can even become life threatening at worst or less fun at best. So, for a dome tent it goes beyond being strong and extremely light. Breathability is the true ‘dream’ property.”</p>

<p>As Jotaro has being producing functional &amp; beautiful Dyneema Composite Fabric shelters for many years, it was a logical move to also use this fabric for the Djedi. Dyneema is the world’s strongest, lightest fiber that is fifteen times stronger than steel but floats on water. It has been used since many years by most key players in the ultralight outdoor industry to create lighter and more functional gear while driving innovation and performance levels of shelters and tents – to make them both stronger for protection and lighter for packing. The new breathability factor of the DCF-eVent fabric can now inspire the tent industry to yet newer heights.</p>

<p><em>You can order the <a href="http://locusgear.com/items/djedi-dcf-event-dome/?lang=en">LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent</a> directly from LOCUS GEAR in Japan and support an innovative ultralight cottage manufacturer.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/76Y394" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/874/41205932612_d9a30b3705_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/9g6aW1" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent in Kings Canyon National Park."><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/786/41249683601_4f56909c32_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent in Kings Canyon National Park." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0C51wA" title="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/789/26376608687_a68bcff755_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="LOCUS GEAR Djedi DCF-eVent Dome Tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions From the MDV Transalp]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/impressions-from-the-mdv-transalp.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-26T12:54:01+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/impressions-from-the-mdv-transalp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mid March: Italy, Switzerland, Austria, sunshine AND great powder snow - sounds impossible? Think again, as that’s exactly what we experienced on the Marker Dalbello Völkl Transalp tour!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40134314135/in/dateposted/" title="Almost at the summit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/802/40134314135_44eee10380_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Almost at the summit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Marker Dalbello Völkl who invited me on this trip. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40319033954/in/dateposted/" title="The kit for the TransAlp"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/790/40319033954_31a9831c1f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="The kit for the TransAlp" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Last Monday was a travel day. Last Tuesday was a powder day. Life is good, right until when it is not good anymore.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39218813480/in/dateposted/" title="A long slog up"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/797/39218813480_96e1030f3d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="A long slog up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The TransAlp sounded like an Event that was made for me: A traverse of three countries on ski, from Livigno in Italy to the Kleinwalsertal in Austria via Switzerland. It’s exactly the kind of trips I enjoy and look for, so the invitation to the adventure from <a href="https://www.marker.net/de/">Marker</a>, <a href="https://www.dalbello.it/">Dalbello</a> and <a href="https://www.voelkl.com/">Völkl</a> was after a bit of pondering and some questions quickly decided upon.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40985738652/in/dateposted/" title="Michi enjoying the POW"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/818/40985738652_d099fe5537_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Michi enjoying the POW" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>What I couldn’t be aware of was that a flu I had decided to trouble me up at almost 3.000 m up in the Alps, and slow me down quite a bit in comparison with my more skilled tour partners.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27156585138/in/dateposted/" title="Talabfahrt Bliss"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/806/27156585138_8bbe55094b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Talabfahrt Bliss" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The full story will follow before the season ends, if you can’t wait you should head over to <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and read between the lines on how the trip went.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39218886610/in/dateposted/" title="The Road to AWESOMENESS"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/815/39218886610_93968eef1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="The Road to AWESOMENESS" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this trip report &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1721" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731721" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1721"></script>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39218825560/in/dateposted/" title="Wettersteinspitze"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/786/39218825560_c8ac835702_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Wettersteinspitze" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Osprey Exos or Osprey Levity - Which Backpack to Get?]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-14T12:24:50+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With Osprey offering two (four if you include the female models!) lightweight backpacks which share a similar construction the Question arises: Which backpack should I get? With this wee article I’ll try to help you answer that question!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932158287/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos vs Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4785/25932158287_9162e6ac1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Exos vs Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from Osprey. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>If you’re a fan of lots of details and video, just go take a cup of ☕️ and maybe even some 🍫 and then watch this video:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rt6pKmvtGXA?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The Exos and Eja (the Eja being the Women’s Model) have been for many years super popular lightweight backpacks from Osprey. As the original Exos came out some six or seven years ago a big Roar went through the Ultralight community (it was more Niche back then =) and there were those that liked them &amp; used them and those who thought they’re too heavy. In 2018 the Exos is a well-established and liked pack, and as I said in my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review.html">Osprey Levity Review</a>: With Osprey packs hanging in stores around the globe it’s a lot easier to try on a pack and see if it fits you. I still think it is the perfect pack to introduce people to lightweight rucksacks and ultralight backpacking, so I’m really happy that these packs exist.</p>

<p>But there are several features which set these two packs apart (<em>Dear Women: Please excuse that I refer now only to the male packs. The Eja and Exos have all the same features but the Eja has a Women’s Specific Fit. Everything I write about the Exos also applies to the Eja, I’m just lazy writing Exos &amp; Eja the whole time!</em> =). Lets look at them via this easy <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vRD-l0X_-z9A-Ao3t4bmJX9UuATTLncTNQ1BjO4U1ds20nTyc5ZEapuyreha4OZRap3Q3gmqzoV5s2V/pubhtml">Table I made</a>:</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vRD-l0X_-z9A-Ao3t4bmJX9UuATTLncTNQ1BjO4U1ds20nTyc5ZEapuyreha4OZRap3Q3gmqzoV5s2V/pubhtml" title="Osprey Exos vs Levity vs Eja"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4783/40804038981_3683f77cdf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="492" alt="Osprey Exos vs Levity vs Eja" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I think besides the weight and price, which are easy to see in this table, it’s also to remind oneself that the Exos will likely be a tad more durable than the Levity and should carry a few kilogram more in comfort, due to the thicker shoulder straps and the longer &amp; more cushioned hipbelt. The Exos also has a plethora of options to attach and carry gear externally on the pack, something that the Levity is missing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932157207/in/dateposted/" title="Shoulder Straps Eja vs Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4795/25932157207_fdc970e15e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Straps Eja vs Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932158717/in/dateposted/" title="Material Differences"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4781/25932158717_1dab92fe55_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Material Differences" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932159357/in/dateposted/" title="Hipbelts!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4782/25932159357_3b11148591_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hipbelts!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Levity on the other hand has it’s light weight going for it - it’s after all 421 g lighter than an Exos. I also found it a plenty comfortable pack for a week of backpacking, but that’s me. I also really liked the simplicity of the pack - not a lot of extra straps and things, stuff which I generally don’t use and so don’t need.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39894513801" title="On the way to a Loch"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4619/39894513801_6506290024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the way to a Loch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Generally however I think that with the lower price, light weight and rich features of the Exos and Eja the majority of people are better off with these packs than the Levity. With 90€ cheaper than an Levity it’s a much easier investment into a new pack (and lets be honest, it’s nice to buy a high-quality piece of kit and not spend over 200 or 300€ for it!) and gives you some money to go on a weekend trip. If only the lightest Osprey pack will do, however, then it’s obviously the Levity one should go for!</p>

<p><em>Support this blog for no additional costs to you and buy your pack via one of these links.</em> In North America order your <a href="http://bit.ly/2FBmlNX">Exos</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2Gk9tgs">Eja</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/2GjS3R9">Levity</a> at these retailers, while in Europe you can buy your Osprey packs at Bergfreunde: <a href="http://bit.ly/2Dliu5M">Exos</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2FDoJnv">Eja</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/2BrfOml">Levity</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Questions?</strong> Hit me up in the comments underneath or ask on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a>!</p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1704" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731704" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1704"></script>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ski-touring in the Salzburger Lungau]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/skitouring-in-the-salzburger-lungau.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-06T12:08:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/skitouring-in-the-salzburger-lungau</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not far away from the busy streets of Munich you can find Austrian hospitality, empty mountains full of powder snow and warm Saunas to relax in after a day of skiing. After the ISPO I went to the Salzburger Lungau region with my brother and enjoyed a few relaxed days in this hidden gem of Austria, enjoying an untracked experience.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608666222/in/dateposted/" title="Snowy me"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4653/40608666222_60551ec0d7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy me" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Salzburger Lungau Tourism who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.lungau.at">Salzburger Lungau</a> Region is a mere couple of hours away from Munich, and unless you try to drive there on the start of some German holiday you can be in as little as one and half hours by car from Munich in the Lungau - in our case we stayed in the picturesque village of St. Margarethen in the <a href="https://www.grizzly-resort.at">Grizzly Resort Sport Hotel</a>, which is located at the base of the ski slopes. The Hotel staff expected us much later and was surprised when we walked in a bit before 20 o’clock! We checked into our rooms, had a quick shower and then it was down to the restaurant to enjoy some tasty Austrian food.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39754614095/in/dateposted/" title="Grizzly Resort"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4787/39754614095_e0ccd565f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grizzly Resort" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840366340/in/dateposted/" title="Main"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4604/38840366340_c94c6bc14c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Main" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After Dinner I went out to photograph the stars, but soon I was so cold that I wanted to only get back inside and sleep! And as we had a long day in front of us, that’s what I did!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779732717/in/dateposted/" title="Nightfall 2"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4798/25779732717_d9566b7e14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Nightfall 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840229010/in/dateposted/" title="Night on the slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4616/38840229010_932c3308ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night on the slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="ski-touring-to-the-seekpfl">Ski-touring to the Seeköpfl</h2>

<p>The next morning <a href="http://www.geführte-skitouren.at">Albert Essl</a> picked us up at the Hotel. We met Albert already two years ago when we were visiting the Salzburger Lungau in 2016 and enjoyed his guiding and company, so it was great to meet him again and go for a ski tour together.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39940867914/in/dateposted/" title="Skining up"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4781/39940867914_1d45acbd00_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skining up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40650163171/in/dateposted/" title="Albert leading the way"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4650/40650163171_182336eeae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert leading the way" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840247990/in/dateposted/" title="Views!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4801/38840247990_19766187a4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Albert picked for us an easy tour for our first day, to the beautiful Seeköpfl summit. We started at a parking lot where we left the car and after a few hundred meters of walking we were stepping into our bindings and beginning to skin up. Over a narrow road we ascended deep into the forest. I really like the skinning up part of ski-touring, it’s relaxing and enjoyable for me to skin up through the forest, observe how the trees get fewer and fewer and then coming out into the open, with wide, majestic views in all directions. We were very lucky with the weather, too: Sunshine and a blue sky - it was a perfect day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840242450/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="ORTOVOX Avabag S28"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4697/38840242450_88fac6e739_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ORTOVOX Avabag S28" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39754694155/in/dateposted/" title="Albert"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4795/39754694155_d7c2bf38f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779169088/in/dateposted/" title="DPS Alchemist + conTour skins"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4613/26779169088_6316d94829_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Alchemist + conTour skins" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225604197/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Happy Seeköpfl Summit Selfie."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4652/25225604197_d3b52ff2a6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happy Seeköpfl Summit Selfie." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a couple of hours we stood at the summit of the Seeköpfl, the sun shining down on us. We were happy, it was a beautiful day, we were outside in nature, and now a nice descent waited for us - or so we thought! The ride down was pretty icy with only a few patches of good snow, and at the end there were the dreaded narrow and icy forest roads back to the car. Ah well, there was snow in the forecast so it will be better soon!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779172888/in/dateposted/" title="Dropping in!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4668/26779172888_41012d8036_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dropping in!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608587112/in/dateposted/" title="On the edge"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4667/40608587112_1417ba3c78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the edge" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39754697965/in/dateposted/" title="Grass Interloop"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4618/39754697965_b17a4e8a38_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Grass Interloop" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840312650/in/dateposted/" title="Finding a way"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4606/38840312650_3a96096aed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Finding a way" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840315690/in/dateposted/" title="Shredding"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4752/38840315690_7409dfbf55_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shredding" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the skiing part of the day my brother and me quickly developed a good routine: Chilling on the rooms for a bit‚ then down to the Sauna, then getting dressed and off to Dinner. It was a pretty good Sauna at the Hotel, and it’s nice that in the Southern countries they often have a wee Bar with juices, water, nuts and tea where you can drink &amp; eat a bite during Sauna turns.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779292038/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy sauna"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4740/26779292038_d7a3fd2195_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy sauna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608648372/in/dateposted/" title="Dessert"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4782/40608648372_d0e4b8c929_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dessert" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="skiing-on-the-katschberg-aineck">Skiing on the Katschberg-Aineck</h2>

<p>The next morning I looked out of the window and it was grey and white. The clouds were low and it was snowing a little, but the snow should really start dumping in the afternoon. Hence my brother and me decided to ride the <a href="http://katschi.at/pistenplaene.html">Katschberg-Aineck</a> ski slopes, and with a chair lift in front of the hotel we didn’t have a long way to get there, either! It’s a big ski region with 70 km of slopes and 16 lifts, and you can have days and days of fun here. We enjoyed the A1 slope the most, as it offers some superb views on the valley, as you’ll see from the photos. A benefit of skiing on the slopes is also that you can eat in one of the huts, and it is something I always like to do, with the tasty Germknödel being my lunch of choice! Another benefit of skiing on the slopes is that you just ride down to your hotel and then can be in the Sauna in a matter of minutes 💦🔥👍</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779832427/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Up &amp; down"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4649/25779832427_5dff75e42a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up &amp; down" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40650091891/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Silverjet"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4707/40650091891_4e872d6246_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Silverjet" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779826537/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snow?!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4667/25779826537_25f508f398_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow?!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779234848/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Shredding again"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4740/26779234848_5466e5279a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shredding again" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26779244348/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Germknödel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4772/26779244348_5250f1ab28_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Germknödel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="exploring-schnfeld-and-the-nockberge">Exploring Schönfeld and the Nockberge</h2>

<p>The next morning it indeed was still dumping snow, and the forecasted 80 cm of fresh powder seemed very realistic. After a tasty breakfast we went outside to clean the car, and boy was it snowed in! After we almost dug out the car we took off towards the Nockberge, a truly hidden gem of the Salzburger Lungau.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39940945044/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snow!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4708/39940945044_b8f8c91281_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39940953404/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy roads"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4708/39940953404_76daea129a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy roads" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Even when the road was cleared that same morning by the time we were on our way to the Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte another 5 cm of pow ❄️❄️❄️ was on the street and my brother was concerned if we’d actually make it back - there was a rather steep road to get up on the way back. But that was none of my worry right now, I just loved the truly white and snowy surroundings we were in.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40650309221/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy rivver"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4758/40650309221_8dbff37f6f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy rivver" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We made it to the beautiful Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte, parked the car and stepped into our bindings. Our goal was the Matehanshöhe, another easy tour, and given that there was a high Avalanche Danger with the fresh snow we wanted something that was safe and easy. The ascent went for the first part via the closed ski slope and then along a ridge till the summit, though as my brother is not used to so deep powder we decided to cut the tour a bit short, not make for the summit and head back down and enjoy the powder!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608686102/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy huts"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4606/40608686102_81932469c8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy huts" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779877787/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy us"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4795/25779877787_8e2dcafddf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy us" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40608683592/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snow till the knee"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4744/40608683592_f04c2c787e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow till the knee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the trip we enjoyed a lunch of Kaiserschmarrn at the hut before safely making it back to the Hotel in the afternoon, with plenty of time to pack, go to the Sauna and enjoy Dinner. Alas, this was our last evening together, and our short trip to the beautiful mountains of Austria were almost over again. I guess we’ll return again, as there’s still so many powdery summits and beautiful views we’d like to see!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39940990614/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy rocks"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4697/39940990614_76782a9f67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy rocks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38840407350/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Snowy signs"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4797/38840407350_3b44514677_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowy signs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-there-and-where-to-stay">How to get there and where to stay</h2>

<p>You can <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/service/arrival/">travel by train and bus to the Salzburger Lungau</a> to it is the most easiest to arrive by car. A rental car for a week can cost around as little as 120€ and allows you to get around really easy in the region, which is almost mandatory if you want to go ski-touring.</p>

<p>There’s <a href="http://booking.lungau.at/lungau/en/accommodation/list?customHeader=true">over 700 accommodation options</a> in the Salzburger Lungau, with something for every budget level (<em>It makes sense to check out the <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/accommodation/package-offers/">Package Offers</a> where you often can safe quite nicely</em>). We stayed at the <a href="https://www.grizzly-resort.at/hotel/">Grizzly Resort Sport Hotel</a>, a very relaxed and high-quality 4 ⭐️ Hotel right next to the ski slopes. We can completely recommend the hotel with its tasty breakfast buffet, relaxing Spa &amp; Sauna, comfortable and spacious rooms and delicious 3-Course Menus in the evening.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25779822147/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="Timelapse in motion"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4695/25779822147_1cdc038f5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Timelapse in motion" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you want to go <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/active/your-winter-holiday/ski-touring-and-freeriding/">ski-touring</a> and don’t want to go on your own give <a href="http://www.geführte-skitouren.at">Albert Essl</a> a call and let him show you the best powder stashes and most amazing views. Albert is a superb Guide and skier who also can give you great tips on how to improve your powder skiing. If you prefer the slopes then ski the <a href="http://www.katschi.at">Katschi</a> slopes - with 70 km of slopes you’re busy for a day or seven to explore them all!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3SeI98ZaSRA&amp;t=450s">Watch the Vlog</a>, view <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157663383796697">more photos on Flickr</a>, check out my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/packing-for-ski-touring.html">Ski-Touring Pack List</a> and if you have questions - comment here or on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>!</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3SeI98ZaSRA?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><em>Enjoyed these articles? Then read my summer trip reports from the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/family-adventures-in-vorarlberg.html">Vorarlberg</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/family-adventures-in-the-bregenzerwald.html">Bregenzerwald</a> to get into the mood for hiking!</em></p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1698" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731698" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1698"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 281]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/twir-281.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-02T21:06:49+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/twir-281</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Simplicity is the key to brilliance.”</em> - <a href="http://amzn.to/2EGsKu9">Dieter Rams</a></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39677552495/in/dateposted/" title="A sign of hope."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4670/39677552495_b77e94ef01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A sign of hope." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-news">Outdoor News</h2>

<p><a href="https://sweepingthegarden.wordpress.com/2018/02/19/sitting-not-doing/">Sitting. Not Doing</a>.</p>

<p>Yama Mountain Gear has launched their first backpack, the <a href="https://www.yamamountaingear.com/sassafras-20/">Sassafras 20</a>. If you want one, be quick as there’s 25% off on the first 25 orders of the pack!</p>

<p>There’s a new Tarptent coming, the <a href="https://www.tarptent.com/notchli.html">Notch Li</a>.</p>

<p>Nine days left to get a <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/557157975/the-rogue-packraft/">Kokopelli Rogue Packraft</a> on Kickstarter.</p>

<p>And Six Moons Designs comes out with a new backpack, <a href="https://www.sixmoondesigns.com/blogs/news/the-minimalist-new-for-2018">The Minimalist</a>.</p>

<p>I’m proud to announce that <a href="http://www.drobo.com/hendrik-morkel/">I am a Drobo Explorer</a>. Stay tuned for a video on why I like the Drobo 5D3. And if you are going to the <a href="https://www.photographyshow.com/registration">Photography Show</a> at NEC in Birmingham you can take £3 off your ticket with the code “DROBTPS18”.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2018/feb/28/britain-national-parks-reclaim-rewild">Britain’s national parks are a farce</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://lighterpacks.com/2018/02/17/the-hypocrisy-of-leave-no-trace/">The hypocrisy of Leave No Trace</a>.</p>

<p>If you rely on Facebook for traffic, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2018/02/28/littlethings">consider this story</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://medium.com/s/story/are-we-post-lifestyle-699ff6023cb8">Instagram is littered with #sponsored posts</a> and the same photos over and over again. Time to leave?</p>

<p>The <a href="https://climbinggearreviewsuk.wordpress.com/2018/03/01/british-brand-finisterre-attains-b-corp-status/">British Brand Finisterre attains B Corp status</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/news/bikepacker-and-bikepacking/">Bikepacker and BIKEPACKING.com have joined forces</a> - congratulations!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/sj7va8" title="Bergzeit-Gewinnspiel-Orotovox-Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/38823529180_3c431e8d72.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit-Gewinnspiel-Orotovox-Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Ortovox makes some great gear, and some of that you can win in this competition. You <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">just have to answer one question</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0z0ue9" title="Bergzeit-Alpincamp-Edelrid-Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4648/39923537564_6052131396.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit-Alpincamp-Edelrid-Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And here’s a competition for the climbers, where you can win a rope, harness and some more goodies by <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/edelrid-ambassador-line/">sharing a great climbing photo</a>.</p>

<p>If you need a pack for a quick overnighter, peak bagging or a leisurely day hike check out the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=d5c7f197-d13c-4793-943a-b6eda64b8f09&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.ula-equipment.com%2Fproduct%2Ffastpack%2F">ULA Equipment Fastpack</a>.</p>

<p>Spring is coming, and with it the rain. Time to get <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=47cd1998-e608-4548-aa0f-3d33e964ad3a&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.hyperlitemountaingear.com%2Fthe-shell.html">The Shell</a> from Hyperlite Mountain Gear, a 146 g light hardshell.</p>

<p>And lots of garments and gear at <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/outlet/outdoor-clothing/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> are up to 60% off, so check your closet if you need something for the next season.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=196169&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10248/196169/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GwfICDPBYNE&amp;feature=youtu.be">Vlog 002</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3SeI98ZaSRA&amp;t=450s">Vlog 003</a> are online, check them out!</p>

<p>Cam helps you planning your <a href="https://www.thehikinglife.com/2018/02/arthur-range-traverse-planning-guide/">Arthur Range Traverse</a> in Tasmania.</p>

<p>Go to Italy and bikepack on the <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/alta-via-dei-monti-liguri/">Alta Via dei Monti Liguri</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://lesserplaces.com/2018/02/19/max-bites-off-more-than-he-can-chew/">Max bites off more than he can chew</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://live.editiondigital.com/review/e/17cdvpvgq/1448180214#!page80">Ski-touring the Graubünden Haute-Route</a>.</p>

<p>Bikepacking in Colombia, from <a href="http://www.highlux.co.nz/2018/02/mompox-san-antonio/">Mompox to San Antonio</a>.</p>

<p>Stephen hikes the <a href="https://howlingmist.blogspot.com/2018/02/the-coumloughra-horseshoewinter.html">Coumloughra Horseshoe</a> in winter.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_JT1NmtMqPY?rel=0&amp;controls=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/routes/morocco-traverse-south/">Bikepacking through Morocco</a>.</p>

<p>Ben goes <a href="https://bencollinsoutdoors.com/2018/02/25/mountain-climbing-in-tasmania-2018/">Mountain Climbing in Tasmania</a>.</p>

<p>All the info you could need in this <a href="https://mbguiding.ca/lake-ohara-yoho-national-park/">Lake O’Hara Trail Guide</a>.</p>

<p>My friend David tries <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lQeVwW6IUH0">Indian Street Food in in Chandni Chowk</a>.</p>

<p>Henryk goes <a href="https://www.oooyeah.de/skitouring-kitzbueheleralpen-teil2/">skitouring in Tirol</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://cedarandsand.blogspot.com/2018/02/the-tushars-crushed.html">Utah’s Tushar Mountains</a>, crushed.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZRTNHDd0gL8?rel=0&amp;controls=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>A first look at the <a href="https://youtu.be/SHlUEBE6f8c">Sigma 16 mm f/ 1.4</a>, me new wide-angle lens.</p>

<p>Magnets in your jacket? <a href="https://www.grough.co.uk/magazine/2018/02/14/flip-experts-warn-new-clothing-trend-could-be-fatal-attraction-for-your-compass">Probably your compass doesn’t like that</a>.</p>

<p>Chris uses <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com/2018/02/just-one-lens-photography-gear-post.html">just one Lens</a>.</p>

<p>Get to know <a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/bikes/peppers-tumbleweed-prospector/">Pepper Cook and her basketpacking Tumbleweed Prospector</a>.</p>

<p>Matthias reviews the <a href="https://quasiout.de/kovea-supalite-titanium-stove-im-test-ein-ultraleichter-gaskocher-nur-fuer-die-kleine-tour/">Kovea Supalite Titanium Stove</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Kathrin reviews the <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/msr-hubba-nx-erfahrungsbericht/">MSR Hubba NX</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Alex shares tips for <a href="http://www.bergreif.de/2018/02/19/naehtipps-fuer-outdoorausruestung/">sewing your first own backpack</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Drew reviews the <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2018/02/27/gear-review-cascade-mountain-tech-carbon-fiber-quick-lock-trekking-poles/">Cascade Mountain Tech Carbon Fiber Quick Lock Trekking Poles</a>.</p>

<p>Kai shares his first insights on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8P5irosYUnA&amp;feature=youtu.be">Sony A7 III</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://lacemine29.blogspot.fi/2018/02/shafted.html">Shafted</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=1430&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/10060/1430/55699/73183/image.jpg" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/nordisk-lofoten-2ulw.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-15T12:54:01+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/nordisk-lofoten-2ulw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is light always right? The Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW tent is one of the lightest double-wall two-person tents on the market, but is it really a 2 Person tent and as light as claimed?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36217591645/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Side view"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4301/36217591645_4c05e4c963_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Side view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>I got this tent for free from Nordisk but was under no obligation to review it. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35824649320/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4309/35824649320_f7b76da9fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On paper the Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW sounds great: 575 g packed weight, sleeps two, super-small pack size. From these three claims only one holds true, though: It has a very great small pack size. Going ultralight does for me not only means to pay attention to the weight, but also to the size of the kit I take. And pack size-wise the Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW definitely would be a tent I’d like to take with me, but then there’s a few things which make me think like <strong>STOP</strong>, <em>don’t do it.</em> Have a look at the video to see how the tent is pitched and how it looks on the inside:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CrL9dzXJAT0?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>So my problem with the tent is that it’s pretty small. Even with a better pitch I don’t think the inner would hang much better than it did in my first pitch, and the foot end is so narrow that I definitely would touch the inner with my feet or quilt. As the photos show, it’s also definitely not a tent for 2 persons, which is OK if you go Solo. Going on your own also would solve another problem of this tent: Storage room for gear. The Lofoten 2ULW has no vestibule space so your pack and other gear needs to come inside. With two people that’d be impossible (or barely possible if you’re on a running event?) so going Solo in it at least gives you some space for your kit. Even the optional Tarp pole with which you can put the door up and so create some space for gear would not solve this in my opinion.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36051402742/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Foot space"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4296/36051402742_737f8d8db8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Foot space" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35382518354/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Lying inside"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4300/35382518354_8ed8f8bcb8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Lying inside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36051402072/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="No room for gear"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4301/36051402072_c8a41893db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="No room for gear" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Lets take a look at the weight then:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Main Pole 131 g</li>
  <li>End Pole 18 g</li>
  <li>5 Pegs incl. Pouch 55 g</li>
  <li>Inner &amp; Outer 372 g</li>
  <li>Pack Pouch for the Tent 30 g</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>TOTAL 587 g</strong></p>

<p>Add in another 96 g for the optional extras, like titanium skewer pegs at 2 g each, guylines, the tarp pole, repair stuff and other things. Which means it’s a wee bit over the claimed packed weight of 575 g, and how one could achieve the 490 g weight is a riddle to me as alone the two poles and fly + inner together are over 500 g, and then you don’t have any pegs yet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36051396272/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Poles &amp; pegs"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4326/36051396272_0ed69e4b38_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Poles &amp; pegs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The ventilation also looks not optimal, but as I haven’t yet slept in the tent I can not comment on the condensation in it. Speaking of sleeping in it, I’m actually not at all sure if I want to use the tent: If it is dry &amp; clear I prefer to sleep under the stars, and if it is wet &amp; rainy I do prefer more space - especially to change out of wet clothes and relax in the tent while it is raining outside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35824649620/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Hi there, tiny tent!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4328/35824649620_ffb3bc3c1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hi there, tiny tent!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It could be that the Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW simply isn’t made for ultralight backpacking but for adventure races like the OMM and similar. On these events people need to carry a tent and apparently would even squeeze together into a <em>“2 Person tent”</em> like the Lofoten 2ULW. I, myself, simply am excited about the pack size of the tent, but not really about taking the tent on a trip. But who knows, maybe I give the tent a chance at some fine, dry and warm day where it will mean protection from mosquitos and where I can sleep with all my kit inside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35382495774/in/album-72157684142567894/" title="Packsize"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4314/35382495774_3cfbeb288f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packsize" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong> is that while I haven’t slept in the tent the pack size is the only thing which currently has me excited about it. It’s very small on the inside and I’m not sure if it would be any comfortable in pro-longed rain, add in that there’s no space for your gear on the outside (Hello soaking wet shoes, hope you like lying next to my quilt!) and it feels like here a company and it’s designers were only aiming at breaking a record (<em>Lightest tent on the market!</em>) and lost track of what really matters in a good tent. As it is the Nordisk Lofoten 2ULW is just a <em>Meh</em> tent for me, but maybe if I have used it a few times my opinion will change. <strong>Have you used this tent, or would you use it for a backpacking trip? Let me know in the comments!</strong></p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-pricecompare.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=11212" type="text/javascript" id="outtrapricecomparewdgt17311212" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapcwdgt="11212"></script>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Week in Review 280]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/twir-280.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-11T22:28:09+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/twir-280</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Blue, White, Happiness.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225604977/in/album-72157663383796697/" title="What a view!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4626/25225604977_655d42d5c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="What a view!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p>The first annual <a href="https://kdsoloaward.wordpress.com">Kyle Dempster Solo Adventure Award</a> is open for applications.</p>

<p>There was <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/02/2018-ispo-impressions.html">no new gear at ISPO 2018</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://bunterwegs.com/inspirierende-frauen-outdoor/">12 inspiring outdoor women</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Become a <a href="http://eveningsends.com/becoming-a-better-climber-in-2018/">better climber in 2018</a>.</p>

<p>Zack shares his thoughts on <a href="http://dedpxl.com/unsplash-an-interview-with-mikael-cho/">Unsplash</a>.</p>

<p>Dan wants that you <a href="http://danbaileyphoto.com/blog/dont-fall-into-this-trap-with-your-photography/">don’t fall into this Trap with your Photography</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://theconversation.com/is-it-possible-for-everyone-to-live-a-good-life-within-our-planets-limits-91421">Is it possible for everyone to live a good life within our planet’s limits</a>?</p>

<p>While the USA made National Monuments smaller Tompkins Conservation and Chile made history with the <a href="https://youtu.be/0_wedyEllOM">Patagonia and Pumalín Park Donation Ceremony</a>.</p>

<p>Meet the <a href="http://dirtbagdiaries.com/punk-rockers-ski-mountaineering/">Punk Rockers of Ski Mountaineering</a>.</p>

<p>I think I’ll need to go visit the <a href="http://www.agnesdenesstudio.com/works4.html">Tree Mountain</a> here in Finland later this year.</p>

<p>This Land Is Our Land: <a href="http://www.kenilgunas.com/2018/01/this-land-is-our-land-haters-welcome.html">Haters Welcome</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/01/13/opinion/sunday/keep-our-mountains-free-and-dangerous.html">Keep Our Mountains Free. And Dangerous</a>.</p>

<p>The Top <a href="https://www.adventure-journal.com/2018/01/top-10-bad-backcountry-habits-2/">10 Bad Backcountry Skiing Habits</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> has up to 60% off on <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/outlet/outdoor-equipment/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">outdoor equipment</a> and <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/outlet/outdoor-clothing/?listorderby=bfdiscountpercent&amp;listorder=desc/?pid=10239">clothing</a>.</p>

<p>At <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=264573&amp;pw=73183">REI’s Winter Clearance Sale</a> you can save up to 50% on Clothing, Outerwear, and Winter Boots.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=3483&amp;pw=73183">The Semiannual Sale at Backcountry.com</a> is on, save up to 50% on Clothing, Gear, and Accessories.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/254570436?title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Win a pants and jacket from <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/glueckspilz/gewinnspiel/">Black Yak</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/8U3G8p" title="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_Black Yak_Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4669/25350267467_d2050bcee2.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit_Gewinnspiel_Black Yak_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Love XC skiing? Take part in <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/bergzeit-frischluft-kick-mit-fischer-zum-langlaufen-livigno/">this competition</a> and win a trip to go skiing in Livigno.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/tSD793" title="Bergzeit_Frischluft Kick_Fischer_Livigno_Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4611/26348538428_bd8d206704.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit_Frischluft Kick_Fischer_Livigno_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A really cool <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/fotocontest/ortovox-safety-package/">Avalanche Security Set</a> from Ortovox you can win in this competition.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/C199PS" title="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Ortovox_Blog"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4668/39323263195_12bb91bcff.jpg" width="500" height="263" alt="Bergzeit_Fotocontest_Ortovox_Blog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And if Freeride Skiing is your cup of tea <a href="https://www.bergzeit.de/magazin/alpincamp/millet-freeride-arlberg/">enter this competition</a> to head to the Arlberg with Millet!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/7o3UUk" title="Bergzeit_Alpincamp_Millet_Google"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4660/26348538808_e37bbc1a78.jpg" width="497" height="279" alt="Bergzeit_Alpincamp_Millet_Google" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="trip-reports">Trip Reports</h2>

<p><a href="https://emmakarjalainen.com/2018/01/19/the-perfect-winter-warrior-weekend-to-repovesi-national-park/">The Perfect Winter Warrior Weekend to Repovesi National Park</a>.</p>

<p>Some <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau.html">impressions from skitouring and skiing in the Salzburger Lungau</a>.</p>

<p>Agnieszka backpacks on the <a href="http://acrossthewilderness.blogspot.fi/2018/02/finlandia-peuranpolku-i-park-narodowy.html">Peuranpolku</a>! [Polish]</p>

<p>Jill <a href="http://www.jilloutside.com/2018/02/jump-into-fog.html">jumps into the fog</a> and it looks pretty.</p>

<p>Read Alex’s <a href="http://www.alexroddie.com/2018/01/in-pursuit-of-perfection-the-lochaber-traverse.html">Lochaber Traverse</a>.</p>

<p>Kathrin goes <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de/bergwanderungen-westaustralien/">hiking in the West Australian Mountains</a>. [German]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.johnhayeswalks.com/2018/01/winter-cycling-in-morocco.html">Winter Cycling in Morocco</a> sounds fun.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lxtWMOAHoiI?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.highlux.co.nz/2018/02/bikepacking-cubas-ruta-mala/">Bikepacking Cuba’s La Ruta Mala</a> will have you wanting to go to Cuba.</p>

<p>Stefanie goes <a href="https://www.gipfel-glueck.de/rofanspitze-schneeschuh-erfurter-huette/">snowshoe backpacking</a> in the Rofan Mountains. [German]</p>

<p>Joe sends greetings <a href="https://joecruz.wordpress.com/2018/02/09/tasmania-postcard/">from Tasmania</a>.</p>

<p>Peter spent a night <a href="http://www.yetirides.com/2018/02/winter-in-kurjenrahka-national-park.html">in the Kurjenrahka National Park</a>.</p>

<p>Paulina hikes to <a href="https://www.littlegrunts.com/heart-lake-mount-shasta/">Hiking Heart Lake, Mount Shasta</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://smokyscout.blogspot.fi/2018/01/patagonia-2017-french-valley-dia-diaz.html">The French Valley - Día Diaz</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28368278689/in/dateposted/" title="PICTURE"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4652/28368278689_5a190e00fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="PICTURE" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gear-reviews">Gear Reviews</h2>

<p>A look at the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hxMWPLzamxY">Marker Alpinist Binding</a>.</p>

<p>Sporks are yesterday, you say? Then check out the small <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=358fd954-c6b8-44a1-9ca9-aaad445d2dfb&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.campsaver.com%2Fsnow-peak-titanium-mini-fork.html">Snow Peak Mini Titanium Fork</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.thehikinglife.com/2018/02/hammocks-for-thru-hiking/">Hammocks for Thru-Hiking</a>.</p>

<p>Philipp shares his impressions of the <a href="http://www.packrafting.de/2018/02/barracuda-r2-pro-first-impression.html">Barracuda R2 Pro</a> packraft. [German]</p>

<p>A look at the <a href="http://www.goout.hk/2018/01/19/ifyouhave-hug-backpack/">ifyouhave ‘hug’ Backpack</a>. [Chinese]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bikepacking.com/bikes/trek-1120-review/">Trek 1120</a> Review.</p>

<p>Chad takes a first look at the <a href="https://sticksblog.com/2018/01/27/altra-lone-peak-3-5-first-look/">Altra Lone Peak 3.5 shoes</a> while Andrew <a href="https://andrewskurka.com/2018/preview-altra-lone-peak-40-trail-shoe/">previews the Altra Lone Peak 4.0</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bergreif.de/2018/01/29/wandern-mit-trail-running-schuhen/">Hiking with trailrunning shoes</a>. [German]</p>

<p>Are you <a href="http://blog.trailcooking.com/2018/02/09/craving-pizza-backpacking/">craving Pizza While Backpacking</a>?</p>

<p>Check out the <a href="http://www.thealpinestart.com/2018/01/31/winter-or-2018-new-gear-awards/">Winter OR 2018: New Gear Awards</a>.</p>

<p>And have a look at Drew’s <a href="https://trailtopeak.com/2018/01/28/11-highlights-from-the-2018-winter-outdoor-retailer/">11 Highlights From The 2018 Winter Outdoor Retailer</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=676921&amp;pw=73183"><img src="//www.avantlink.com/gbi/15661/676921/55699/73183/image.png" width="728" height="90" style="border: 0px;" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2018 ISPO Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/2018-ispo-impressions.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-08T12:06:31+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/2018-ispo-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every year again I make the same mistake: I head to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/02/ispo-2017.html">ISPO</a> in Munich.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115657482/in/dateposted/" title="NEVER STOP EXPLORING"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4611/40115657482_ac715100a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="NEVER STOP EXPLORING" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy this &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors, and your contribution helps keeping the articles coming!</em></p>

<p>Yes, I really do not like the ISPO. It’s a necessary evil one has to attend if you’re in this business, and should the summer OutDoor fair move to Munich I’ll probably just boycott it, there’s just so much big city I can take. Anyway, we don’t need to talk about crappy cities in even worse German states, because there’s of course also upsides to the ISPO. Namely all the people you meet, from the wonderful bloggers like <a href="http://hrxxlight.com">Benjamin</a>, <a href="http://fraeulein-draussen.de">Kathrin</a>, <a href="http://ulligunde.com">Erika</a>, <a href="https://st-bergweh.de">Björn</a>, <a href="https://bergtouren-im-allgaeu.de">Björn</a> and <a href="https://www.auf-den-berg.de">Uli</a>, to name just a few, to the amazing companies. I scaled down meetings this year and didn’t run around from 9:00 in the morning till 18:00 o’clock in the evening, but was very selective in where I went. This did allow me to see a bit more than in the past of the fair, and one thing which immideately became apparent: A lot of brands were missing from the fair. The Messe Munich tried to cover this up by adding crappy <em>Showcases</em> in the middle of almost every exhibition hall. Imagine these as not very pretty small “exhibitions” where they tried to show you the same stuff you can see in the neighbouring booths. There were also a lot less people at the fair, especially on Sunday and Tuesday the hallways were nice and empty, only on Monday morning it was really busy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115660662/in/dateposted/" title="The Best for the Worst"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4666/40115660662_03a95d095a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Best for the Worst" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the positive side: While in the past years a lot of companies have talked about how environmentally friendly, social and sustainable they are this year was the first time that many of these companies were actually showing off truly good sustainable &amp; socially made products. From down jackets which are made from recycled down (down from old Duvets and pillows, which are cleaned and then re-used) and recycled shell &amp; liner materials, to garments which you can recycle completely at the end of their life-cycle. What keeps on surprising me with these developments is how you’ll visit Company A in the morning and Company B, Company C and Company D will show you during the rest of the day pretty much identical garments with almost identical stories. It does mean what felt like an innovation in the morning already feels old in the afternoon. I reckon it is because the ingredient brands (the ones who make the insulation, liner, shell and other materials - think companies like Polartec, PrimaLoft, Pertex and so on) will offer their new fabrics and technologies to all the companies which make garments out of them, and so you see almost the same thing from one company to the next one.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115659222/in/dateposted/" title="DPS Phantom"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4751/40115659222_78c2872504_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Phantom" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115659892/in/dateposted/" title="SBlocs Cargo Bike"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4720/40115659892_5b5a2abb36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="806" alt="SBlocs Cargo Bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39436790524/in/dateposted/" title="Marker Alpinist"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4698/39436790524_8b860fcba7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Marker Alpinist" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115656162/in/dateposted/" title="Long Live the Product"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4748/40115656162_63848cb524_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Long Live the Product" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Happily there are honorable expections. From the <a href="https://www.dpsskis.com/phantom">DPS Phantom</a> permanent, one-time application base-coating to the most awesome and fantastic SBlocs eCargo Bike which I totally want to have (Hashtag #FuckCarsRideBikes), there were some innovations on the fair to be seen. I made a lot of videos of those which I found most interesting so I suggest you <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">subscribe to my Youtube channel</a> to see these, as this article here will likely be the only ISPO post I will make this year.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28368279399/in/dateposted/" title="BD Band"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4703/28368279399_d182ae8aef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="BD Band" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28368278439/in/dateposted/" title="Bar"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4666/28368278439_4ffbcb9acc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25276911507/in/dateposted/" title="Best Coffee was head at Patagonia"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4632/25276911507_37cfbaa082_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Best Coffee was head at Patagonia" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, what else? Reading and talking with fellow content creators and industry partners it becomes clear: The Outdoor Industry is in change, and the question if fairs like the ISPO and OutDoor are still necesary are becoming louder and louder. With costs of 20.000€ for just a small booth you can understand why brands are thinking if they need to be at these shows, because you could do a lot more useful things with such amounts of money. Yes, it’s nice to meet friends, network, and drink some beers toegether, but that are pretty expensive beers indeed. I don’t know if it would help if every brand would make its own event as that would be even more of a time drain, but somehow these fairs need to up their game to stay relevant.</p>

<p>If this all sounds pretty negative - sorry. You just get jaded with these fairs at some point - this was my 5th ISPO - and it starts to feel that there’s just a handful of innovations, and not halls full of them anymore (maybe I didn’t look close enough, though). What does get better is brands and companies realize that we digital content creators are very valuable; as an example, Hiking in Finland has more readers than the two biggest German Outdoor Magazines <em>combined</em>. So you’re no longer seen as someone who might want a free pack or jacket, but as someone who has a very interested and targeted audience (<strong>YOU!</strong>), who talks their language and can show them the cool &amp; interesting stuff he has found on the fair. That’s pretty nice indeed and you can see this becoming better and better at each fair.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25276912267/in/dateposted/" title="10 Years On"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4766/25276912267_611a362990_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="10 Years On" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115658222/in/dateposted/" title="Houdini Shells &amp; Insulation"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4630/40115658222_470125f888_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Houdini Shells &amp; Insulation" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28368277719/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Alpha SK Pack"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4605/28368277719_ab04ce6fe3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Alpha SK Pack" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>The Bottomline</strong> is that after the big-city-business-ISPO I am very much looking forward to the OutDoor in Friedrichshafen in June. The OutDoor has a much better vibe than the ISPO, it’s more relaxed, people are less sick (it’s pretty easy to catch a flu or worse at the ISPO because of the time of the year) and with the mountains and the lake in close proximity it’s just a lot more outdoorsy. And with the Blogger Base and really good programms made especially for us digital content creators (<em>Disclosure: I’m completely biased as with my other company we’re the partner of the Messe Friedrichshafen</em>) it feels just a lot better to be at the OutDoor than at the ISPO. So lets keep our 👍 and hope that the OutDoor will continue to be in Friedrichshafen (or if it moves, that it moves to Hamburg). <em>You can view more photos from the ISPO fair in the accompanying <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157665520832018">Flickr Album</a>.</em></p>

<p><em>You still don’t have enough? Then <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/archives/">browse through the Archive</a>, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions From the Salzburger Lungau]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-05T19:17:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the ISPO I did the only smart thing: Leave the city behind and head to Austria to go ski-touring. These are some first impressions from a too-short trip to the Salzburger Lungau Region.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225607357/in/dateposted/" title="Albert on the way to the summit of the Seeköpfl."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4620/25225607357_aa885b504c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert on the way to the summit of the Seeköpfl." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Salzburger Lungau Tourism who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225608777/in/dateposted/" title="St. Margarethen im Lungau"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4698/25225608777_5329e81066_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="St. Margarethen im Lungau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a very busy fair I met my brother and we made the trip down south to the <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/your-lungau/15-villages/?_wb=en/your-lungau/15-villages/&amp;lang=EN">Salzburger Lungau</a> Region, a place we have visited before and really liked. We arrived at our <a href="https://www.grizzly-resort.at">Hotel</a>, had a tasty dinner and then it was off to bed as early in the morning we would meet Albert again, our <a href="http://www.geführte-skitouren.at">Ski-touring Guide</a> with whom we had the pleasure to go skiing already in the past.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225601117/in/dateposted/" title="Start of the tour."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4770/25225601117_d228306e86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Start of the tour." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225604887/in/dateposted/" title="And what a view again!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4724/25225604887_f11df71d25_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And what a view again!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Albert had two other clients along and our little group was great, we had a lot of fun on the ascent and descent. It was a beautiful sunny day with great views - just the snow could have been a wee bit better.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225603587/in/dateposted/" title="Through the less-than-perfect snow down."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4761/25225603587_f2d6bb985b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Through the less-than-perfect snow down." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225603357/in/dateposted/" title="Albert showing how it&#x27;s done."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/25225603357_6a8f10e645_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert showing how it&#x27;s done." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The view from the Hotel wasn’t bad at all, either. We witnessed the #SuperBlueMoon rising behind the forest as we sat in the Sauna, not a bad place at all!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225606417/in/dateposted/" title="Timelapse."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4673/25225606417_0a106ea3e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Timelapse." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next day we hot the slopes. With a big ski resort right in front of the hotel it was not a long approach, and the skiing was good - though I really prefer soft snow on wild mountains. A good thing that a 80 cm dump of powder was forecast for the next day!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225605937/in/dateposted/" title="Snow? Yeps."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4760/25225605937_fa563906a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow? Yeps." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225610547/in/dateposted/" title="Germknödel, still a favourite meal of mine."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4614/25225610547_fa07863ea4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Germknödel, still a favourite meal of mine." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And so my brother and me headed again to the secluded Thomatal Valley and started from the Dr. Josef-Mehrl Hütte up into the mountains, not to be disappointed by the amount of snow.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225609357/in/dateposted/" title="The fantastic Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4666/25225609357_ef4df5c352_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The fantastic Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Stay tuned for the full trip-report in the next few weeks! In the meanwhile you already can take a look some more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157663383796697">Flickr Album</a> and on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Osprey Levity 45 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-25T20:47:27+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When a major-player in the backpacking market like Osprey decides to make an ultralight backpack you can be sure that there’s going to go a ripple through the scene. I was lucky enough to receive a Osprey Levity 45 backpack in August 2017 for testing and have put the pack through it’s paces in the last six months. <em>Here’s what I liked &amp; didn’t like about the new ultralight backpack from Osprey.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39890791831/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 Review"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4674/39890791831_cc49c75a3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 Review" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from Osprey. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>The Osprey Levity 45 is a great lightweight backpack which carries loads up to 10 kg in comfort. The Airspeed suspension back frame should be especially useful for hikes in hot environments, while the highly water-resistant material of the pack has kept my gear dry while backpacking for a week in Scotland. I would have wished the front and side pockets would have been more stretchy, but other than that this backpack is well made and should be an ideal choice for those who have used heavier backpacks in the past and look to lighten up. For all the details watch the video and read the review.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YhuugW019oI?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received my <a href="https://www.ospreyeurope.com/gb_en/ventilated-pinnacle-coming-soon/">Osprey Levity</a> 45 sample in August 2017 and had it along on a dozen day trips in autumn and winter, as well as a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/10/impressions-from-the-scottish-cairngorms.html">one week backpacking trip through the Cairngorms in Scotland</a>. All in all I have used it over 25 days.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39892290381/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 at Coire Etchachan Shelter, Cairngorms, Scotland"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4694/39892290381_121c47701a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 at Coire Etchachan Shelter, Cairngorms, Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The function of a backpack is to carry your gear in comfort from A to B. The idea behind an ultralight backpack is that it isn’t weighing 2+ kg empty, but significantly less, making the hiking part of a trip more comfortable. The backpack also should protect your gear from the elements and allow fast &amp; easy access to important pieces of gear which you need on the go.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36941189873/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Loch Etchachan"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4497/36941189873_4fe952cbaa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Loch Etchachan" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Straight out of the Levity and Lumina (the Lumina is the female version of this backpack, though it comes out in Europe first in 2019) Owner’s Manual, here’s the features of these pack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A fixed top lid with one zippered pocket</li>
  <li>Two removable side compression cords</li>
  <li>Dual access fabric side pockets</li>
  <li>Bellowed front fabric pocket</li>
  <li>Top lid cord loop attachment points</li>
  <li>Sternum strap with integrated safety whistle</li>
  <li>Internal main compartment compression strap</li>
</ul>

<p>The pack is made from two materials, the Main material is a 30D Silnylon Ripstop while the accents (that’s the lid, bottom, front and side-pockets) are made from a more durable NanoFly™ 100D Nylon x 100D UHMWPE Ripstop. The more durable material is a non-branded version of what other backpack makers sell at a premium as Dyneema or Cordura, and both materials seem to have a DWR coating.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26017236288/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Main Body Material"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4621/26017236288_38c7b5ab15_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Main Body Material" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>I’m hard pressed to give Osprey here any points: Ultralight backpacks have been around for many years, using equally or more advanced materials (like the material still commonly known as Cuben fibre, Silnylon, XPac and mixes thereof). I could say that the Airspeed frame, which allows for air circulation between your back and the main compartment of the pack, is an innovation in such a light pack.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018722777/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Side Pocket Material"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4602/25018722777_77b3c48823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Side Pocket Material" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The pack is well-made as you would expect from a brand like Osprey - they know their trade and how to make backpacks. So expect when you go to the store to get a Levity that it will hold up to many years of backpacking.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180104254/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Front &amp; Side View"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4756/39180104254_dace146f14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Front &amp; Side View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Levity 45 weighs 751 g in Size M. Please keep in mind that this is a pre-production model and the ones hitting the stores are expected to weigh 810 g on average!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018723817/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Shoulder Strap Detail 3"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4756/25018723817_aefa139dcd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Shoulder Strap Detail 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The Levity 45 is with its 45 l volume a good pack for long weekend trips or one week-long backpacking trips without resupplying, as in carrying all the food for one week. It’s going to be a tight fit at the beginning of a trip, even with a UL baseweight, but the more you eat the lighter it gets 😜. The main compartment swallows all my gear - shelter, bivy, mattress, quilt, stove, spare clothes and puffy jacket - with room to spare for food, an extra lens and the Mavic Pro Drone. The shoulder strap is not too wide, which means I can attach my <a href="https://youtu.be/3res6PXJySY">Capture Clip</a> to the pack and have my camera always at the ready.</p>

<p>When packing the backpack it’s important to pack smart, as the main compartment is not a round barrel but has two corners at the bottom which can stay empty if you don’t pack with a system - I stuff my bivy and some socks into these fins, and then come quilt, mattress, etc. If you don’t do that you’ll end up with empty space, and if you go out with a full week worths of food then that empty space might be needed. So pack smart! On the inside you also find a reservoir sleeve for a hydration system if that’s how you roll, I haven’t tried that as I use 1 l Platypus bottles and a Kuksa for water.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018722537/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Content for a weekend"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4626/25018722537_a06b2aa659_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Content for a weekend" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The side pockets as well as the front pocket (which is bellowed, that means it does expand a bit) are not stretchy, which means you’re limited in terms of how much gear you can stuff in them. Of course the pockets on the Levity are more durable than mesh, but if you like to carry some extra stuff on a trip that doesn’t fit into the main compartment then mesh outside pockets were usually there to accommodate that stuff, but not here. For that the Levity has some loops on the lid, to which you could attach some extra gear. I haven’t tried that, and also imagine it’d be difficult to attach some apples or other fruits to these loops 🍎🍉🍒😄.</p>

<p>Back to the pockets, these were fine to carry my water bottles, snacks, a big-ass tripod and extra clothes. The side pockets can be accessed from the top or the side, I can so for example get my Kuksa out of the side pocket when I want to drink and put it back in. As they don’t stretch it can sometimes be a bit difficult to stuff gear in the side pockets when the main compartment is already filled with your gear, so keep that in mind if you carry a tripod. The zippered lid pocket is fantastic, has a keychain hook inside, and swallows an incredible amount of gear - I carried my GR1 pocket with batteries and cables in it, plus some more stuff - all goin’ easily in there.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857991462/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 2"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4697/39857991462_c2f77e4024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Airspeed backpanel does it’s job well, with the aluminium frame keeping the mesh to your back and allowing for airflow. What I really like, though, are the shoulder straps and hipbelt. These have been really well designed and are very comfortable, also if the pack is fully loaded with 10+ kg of gear &amp; food. The foam which is wrapped by a mesh is pretty durable and adapts well to your shoulders and body, making for a comfortable carry all day long. The same goes for the hipbelt, which is pretty minimal but wrapped nicely around my hips and helped transfer the weight to them. I think the carrying frame system of the Levity 45 is very well made, and if you hike in very warm environments then I think this pack should be nice, as with the Airspeed backpanel and the airflow it allows it should possibly make you sweat less.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857989532/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel &amp; Frame"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/39857989532_a3e79958b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel &amp; Frame" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39890792031/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4621/39890792031_77ff9d08e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The side compression cords which are on the pack felt a bit useless to me, I still think that the compression system of the ULA Ohm is one of the best ones out there. The compression strap on the inside is a nice idea, but I tend to forget that the inside strap needs to be connected to the buckle on the inside, so sometimes I just don’t use it. The drawcord works well, though the point where the cord exists the fabric looks a bit weak to me and could be a point of failure.</p>

<p>The material of the Levity seems to have a DWR coating, especially the not transparent material with the white grid (<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180105634/in/dateposted/">see here</a>) kept the rain at bay, while the transparent material started to let some water seep through after a week in the Highlands. To be 100% safe I still would recommend to pack critical gear (quilt, down jacket, dry socks) in a waterproof drybag.</p>

<p><strong>Addition</strong>: Osprey informed me that the stretchy pockets have been fixed for production - these were updated from the sample pack I received. And the point where the drawcord exits the fabric has been reinforced for added durability, so this shouldn’t be an issue either.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39894513801/in/dateposted/" title="On the way to a Loch"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4619/39894513801_6506290024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the way to a Loch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I will repeat myself here, but: I wish Osprey would have made the side and front pockets more stretchy so one can easier get things in &amp; out of them or over-stuff them.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>I have reviewed half a dozen <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">backpacks</a> here and used probably more than triple the amount in the last 10 years, but there’s just a handful of UL packs which have a ventilated backpanel, like some of the ZPacks packs (which are a bit lighter but more expensive), and of course you just could go with the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-exos-46-backpack-2600-3000cu-in">Osprey Exos</a> which also has an Airspeed backpanel.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857991492/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 1"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4674/39857991492_a76aedbd31_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Does the market need another <em>ultralight</em> backpack? If that’s a question which is in your mind after you read this, let me say: Yes. We ultralight backpackers life in our own little UL Bubble, where we don’t see a problem with ordering a pack off the internet from a cottage manufacturer halfway across the globe - but we’re really not the majority. The Osprey Levity brings ultralight backpacks into the big stores and so in front of the eyes of thousands of outdoor enthusiasts who will love this pack - not only because they can choose from three different back lengths, but also because they <em>can try the pack on before they buy it!</em> I remember me ordering my first pack online some eight or nine years ago, it was quite an adventure to find out the right length I’d need, getting it through customs and all that. It’s not a process that many people want to go through, and hence it’s amazing that we have a lightweight backpack like the Osprey Levity now in stores across the globe.</p>

<p>And yes, the Levity backpack itself is also really, really good. It has some things which Osprey can improve upon when the next version of the pack comes around in a couple of years, but overall Osprey has done their homework well and has produced a very good backpack which will satisfy many backpackers. It’s lightweight, made of durable and water-resistant materials, has Osprey’s <a href="https://www.ospreyeurope.com/gb_en/all-mighty-guarantee/">All Mighty Guarantee</a> which lets you send in a damaged pack and get it repaired, and is also very comfortable to carry with a 10 to 12 kg load. It has everything an ultralight backpack needs as well as a backpanel which increases airflow, which should make it perfect for those super-hot summers we are getting these last years across the globe.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>The Levity is AVAILABLE! Get it at <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/osprey-levity-45-walking-backpack/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/osprey-levity-60-walking-backpack/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> in Europe. In North America order it at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-levity-45-backpack%3Fs%3Da">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fproduct%2F126706%2Fosprey-levity-45-pack-mens">REI</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=358fd954-c6b8-44a1-9ca9-aaad445d2dfb&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.campsaver.com%2Fosprey-levity-45-pack.html">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=61fff111-8514-4179-a87e-5da7e9fb1264&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.moosejaw.com%2Fmoosejaw%2Fshop%2Fproduct_Osprey-Men-s-Levity-45-Pack_10364645_10208_10000001_-1_">Moosejaw</a> and <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=258f5de7-8908-4439-9828-304e836d85a8&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.summithut.com%2Flevity-45-3.html">Summit Hut</a>. And yes, please go try the Levity at your local Osprey Shop so you get a feel for what an ultralight backpack feels (I promise, you’ll love it!).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180105634/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4715/39180105634_ce44d6a11a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
