<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: laufbursche | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/laufbursche/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-09-29T11:20:53+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Visit to HUCKEPACKS]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/10/a-visit-to-huckepacks.html"/>
    <updated>2019-10-29T10:11:16+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/10/a-visit-to-huckepacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Accompany me on a visit to the ultralight candy shop that is the HUCKEPACKS Workshop in Cologne, Germany!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48979283501/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Packs"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48979283501_fbe2f3bebf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="HUCKEPACKS Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Mateusz is a long-time friend, but I paid this trip myself and was not paid to write this article or produce the videos. I received a PHOENIX Lite for testing and giving feedback. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978727288/in/dateposted/" title="Handmade in Cologne"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978727288_7f77d42166_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Handmade in Cologne" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I remember the first call from Mateusz about the new company. I was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLqEBC4yj3FagZCjz9vfwc7r8iiwZaz63R">backpacking in Vålådalen</a> in September 2018, and was just at the beautiful turquoise lakes having a short break when my phone rang. I answered, and as usual Mateusz talked and talked and talked, until I had to tell him that I was about to continue hiking again and would like to know what it’s about. <em>“Well, I plan to open LAUFBURSCHE Gear again. But it won’t be called LAUFBURSCHE anymore. What do you think about the name HUCKEPACKS?”</em> I like it, I answered, it connects well to the old brand. From then on forward my phone would regularly ring and I’d chat for an half hour or longer with Mateusz about the new company and the new products.</p>

<p>Fast forward to the summer of 2019 and the family and me are on a train to Cologne. We have been travelling for two weeks around Germany, visiting <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B3ZtJIgDl6G/">Berlin</a>, my home town and other places, and now we arrived in the city with the cathedral. We stayed at a nice Hostel in Ehrenfeld, and one morning I was able to steal away from parental duties and visit Mateusz at his Workshop.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978725668/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Workshop"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978725668_918d68c526_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="HUCKEPACKS Workshop" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now I have seen photos of the workshop before when friends were visiting him, and it was with much anticipation that I entered these “holy halls”. And amazing they were indeed. I was welcomed by the four new packs - the PACKL and PHOENIX - in their DxG and Cuben versions, and Mateusz walked towards me with a coffee in hand. I gave him a big hug and was happy that he was still with us. He made me a coffee, and then we sat down to chat.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/7oWBgnSEBMY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>It is always enlightening to sit and talk with Mateusz, and realize how much thought he puts into the smallest of details. Case in point: The new roll-top closure of the PHOENIX backpack. Where other companies are happy to use a tried &amp; tested roll-top, Mateusz found it neither practical nor aesthetically pleasing. When he showed me the new roll-top closure, which folds and opens like an accordion, my jaw dropped. So easy, so beautiful, so practical, and such a smart continuation of the old HUCKEpack closure. And what is most amazing: He had this design already in 2015, and tested it on his HRP thru-hike that year!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978724333/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS PHOENIX"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978724333_ab1833e7de_h.jpg" width="1600" height="900" alt="HUCKEPACKS PHOENIX" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978725273/in/dateposted/" title="Mateusz and the PACKLs"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978725273_3a1074fdab_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Mateusz and the PACKLs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48979465772/in/photostream/" title="DXg x DCF"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48979465772_917b913280_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="DXg x DCF" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48979462612/in/dateposted/" title="Cutting"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48979462612_9e85d5eb8a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Cutting" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We shot two more videos after the Interview above, about the <a href="https://youtu.be/EKFC7FB76LA">PHOENIX</a> and the <a href="https://youtu.be/x32RhEvdhqw">PACKL</a>, drank another coffee and talked about the launch of the company, backpacking, and much more. Sadly, and you likely see this coming, parental duties called and so, after several hours, it was time to say good bye to Mateusz and head back to the city, so I could play with the kids and we could go have some lunch with the family =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/6q39eY" title="Cologne Playgrounds"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48979621342_b28a5f2f59_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Cologne Playgrounds" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I am so excited that my friend Mateusz not only won his battle with cancer, but that he decided to return to sewing the finest ultralight backpacks which he is well-known and loved for! A few weeks later I was fortunate enough that a PHOENIX Lite pack arrived here, which I used on a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/09/impressions-from-the-far-north.html">backpacking trip in Lapland</a>, and I still am <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/09/solo-hike-to-the-zugspitze.html">using my old PACKsack regularly</a>. If you are in the market for a pack for everyday use and Overnighters, or need a pack for long backpacking trips, give the new <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/">HUCKEPACKS packs</a> a good look! I for one am really loving these packs, and wish Mateusz all the best with the new business!</p>

<p>If you enjoyed this article and video <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978725948/in/dateposted/" title="LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978725948_61238ce76d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Leg for LAUFBURSCHE]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/a-leg-for-laufbursche.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-23T23:26:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/a-leg-for-laufbursche</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mateusz, backpacker and manufacturer of the ultralight <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">LAUFBURSCHE</a> backpacks, lost a leg in his battle against cancer. With this fundraiser I want to help him pay his medical bills and hopefully get a prosthesis that allows him to go hiking again. [<strong>Updated with winner!</strong>]</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/" title="ILoveLAUFBURSCHE.com"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7176/26188616394_48ddfab21e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="615" alt="ILoveLAUFBURSCHE.com" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Mateusz and I met the first time six years ago when he joined a group of ultralight backpackers who followed my invite for an <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/02/tufwt-1-0-trip-report.html">Ultralight Winter trip</a>. We hiked, laughed, camped in the snow, went to Sauna and jumped into the ice hole together, and have been in contact ever since. I was lucky enough to get one of the very first 40D black Silnylon huckePACKs, a design which was back then and still today is revolutionary. As an Architect Mateusz has a great eye for functional design, and his backpacks are considered far and wide works of art. My “Packing your framless backpack - LAUFBURSCHE huckePACK” video is probably my most-watched video on Youtube, and it is that backpack which I today will to raffle off in support of Mateusz.</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MDF26eJ2sqU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>As a fellow entrepreneuer I know that should sickness strike then shit hits the fan, and it’s sadly not different for Mateusz. Many other’s have written about his condition so I do not want to concentrate on it here, but instead send good vibes and support his way and a one-of-a-kind LAUFBURSCHE huckePACK your way. The pack is in great condition without any damage, is made of black 40d Silynlon with an XPAC floor, is Size L (which fits me at 175 cm very well) and weighs with all the straps attached 343 g. I guesstimate the volume at around 35 to 45 l, so it’s a great size for a week long trip in the mountains or woods.</p>

<p><em>So, how do you get a chance on winning this backpack AND help Mateusz?</em></p>

<ul>
  <li>One lottery ticket costs 5€, and you can buy as many as you’d like. More tickets obviously increase your chances to win this unique pack and help Mateusz more!</li>
  <li>You Donate for each lottery ticket you’d like to buy 5€ to Mateusz via <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">this website</a> (<em>you can donate via PayPal or bank transfer, please follow the simple instructions given over there for your donation</em>)</li>
  <li>You send an Email with a screenshot of the confirmed donation to <em>laufbursche[ät]hikinginfinland.com</em> with your name and the amount of lottery tickets you purchased</li>
  <li>If you like, comment underneath to let others know how many tickets you have bought =)</li>
  <li>You can buy lottery tickets till the 22nd of May, Midnight Finnish time</li>
  <li>On the 23rd of May I will put all tickets in a hat and my son will pull out one lucky winner who gets the backpack!</li>
</ul>

<p>If you just like to help and have already enough huckePACKs, just head over to <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">I Love LAUFBURSCHE</a> and donate. Every donation is appreciated and helps Mateusz on the long trail of rehabilitation and getting back outdoors. <em>To read more about Mateusz condition head over to <a href="http://www.outdoormaedchen.de/2016/04/crowdfunding-laufbursche.html">Outdoormädchen</a>, <a href="https://limitcamper.wordpress.com/2016/04/27/i-love-laufbursche/">Limitcamper</a> or the <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3737-ein-laufbursche-für-den-laufburschen/">various</a> <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3626-die-gute-tat-für-laufbursche-frühling/">threads</a> on <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3495-laufbursche-genesungswünsche/">Ultraleicht</a> <a href="http://www.ultraleicht-trekking.com/forum/topic/3504-schulterschluss-für-mateusz/">Trekking</a>.</em></p>

<h2 id="update-23052016">Update 23.05.2016</h2>

<p>Wow, what a great effort! There were donations for a total of 201 lottery tickets, with some donations which didn’t want to enter, which raised a grand total of 1.295 € for Mateusz! I imagine that helps him with getting a ultralight carbon or titanium part for his prosthesis! The winner of the huckePACK has already been contacted and I hope she will enjoy hiking with the pack =)</p>

<p>Of course we don’t need to stop now - Mateusz is still battling with the complications of his sickness, and you can still <a href="http://www.ilovelaufbursche.de/english/">donate</a> to support him. Every small donation helps, so just drink one less fancy coffee and donate that sum instead =)</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I have no financial benefit in this campaign. Mateusz is a friend of mine and I want to help him pay his medical bills &amp; hike again in the future.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
