<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: backpacks | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/backpacks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-09-19T14:54:28+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Osprey Exos or Osprey Levity - Which backpack to get?]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity.html"/>
    <updated>2018-03-14T12:24:50+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/03/osprey-exos-vs-osprey-levity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With Osprey offering two (four if you include the female models!) lightweight backpacks which share a similar construction the Question arises: Which backpack should I get? With this wee article I’ll try to help you answer that question!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932158287/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Exos vs Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4785/25932158287_9162e6ac1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Exos vs Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from Osprey. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>If you’re a fan of lots of details and video, just go take a cup of ☕️ and maybe even some 🍫 and then watch this video:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rt6pKmvtGXA?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The Exos and Eja (the Eja being the Women’s Model) have been for many years super popular lightweight backpacks from Osprey. As the original Exos came out some six or seven years ago a big Roar went through the Ultralight community (it was more Niche back then =) and there were those that liked them &amp; used them and those who thought they’re too heavy. In 2018 the Exos is a well-established and liked pack, and as I said in my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review.html">Osprey Levity Review</a>: With Osprey packs hanging in stores around the globe it’s a lot easier to try on a pack and see if it fits you. I still think it is the perfect pack to introduce people to lightweight rucksacks and ultralight backpacking, so I’m really happy that these packs exist.</p>

<p>But there are several features which set these two packs apart (<em>Dear Women: Please excuse that I refer now only to the male packs. The Eja and Exos have all the same features but the Eja has a Women’s Specific Fit. Everything I write about the Exos also applies to the Eja, I’m just lazy writing Exos &amp; Eja the whole time!</em> =). Lets look at them via this easy <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vRD-l0X_-z9A-Ao3t4bmJX9UuATTLncTNQ1BjO4U1ds20nTyc5ZEapuyreha4OZRap3Q3gmqzoV5s2V/pubhtml">Table I made</a>:</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vRD-l0X_-z9A-Ao3t4bmJX9UuATTLncTNQ1BjO4U1ds20nTyc5ZEapuyreha4OZRap3Q3gmqzoV5s2V/pubhtml" title="Osprey Exos vs Levity vs Eja"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4783/40804038981_3683f77cdf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="492" alt="Osprey Exos vs Levity vs Eja" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I think besides the weight and price, which are easy to see in this table, it’s also to remind oneself that the Exos will likely be a tad more durable than the Levity and should carry a few kilogram more in comfort, due to the thicker shoulder straps and the longer &amp; more cushioned hipbelt. The Exos also has a plethora of options to attach and carry gear externally on the pack, something that the Levity is missing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932157207/in/dateposted/" title="Shoulder Straps Eja vs Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4795/25932157207_fdc970e15e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Straps Eja vs Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932158717/in/dateposted/" title="Material Differences"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4781/25932158717_1dab92fe55_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Material Differences" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25932159357/in/dateposted/" title="Hipbelts!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4782/25932159357_3b11148591_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hipbelts!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Levity on the other hand has it’s light weight going for it - it’s after all 421 g lighter than an Exos. I also found it a plenty comfortable pack for a week of backpacking, but that’s me. I also really liked the simplicity of the pack - not a lot of extra straps and things, stuff which I generally don’t use and so don’t need.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39894513801" title="On the way to a Loch"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4619/39894513801_6506290024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the way to a Loch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Generally however I think that with the lower price, light weight and rich features of the Exos and Eja the majority of people are better off with these packs than the Levity. With 90€ cheaper than an Levity it’s a much easier investment into a new pack (and lets be honest, it’s nice to buy a high-quality piece of kit and not spend over 200 or 300€ for it!) and gives you some money to go on a weekend trip. If only the lightest Osprey pack will do, however, then it’s obviously the Levity one should go for!</p>

<p><em>Support this blog for no additional costs to you and buy your pack via one of these links.</em> In North America order your <a href="http://bit.ly/2FBmlNX">Exos</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2Gk9tgs">Eja</a> or <a href="http://bit.ly/2GjS3R9">Levity</a> at these retailers, while in Europe you can buy your Osprey packs at Bergfreunde: <a href="http://bit.ly/2Dliu5M">Exos</a>, <a href="http://bit.ly/2FDoJnv">Eja</a> and <a href="http://bit.ly/2BrfOml">Levity</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Questions?</strong> Hit me up in the comments underneath or ask on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a>!</p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1704" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731704" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1704"></script>

<p><em>Disclaimer: There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Osprey Levity 45 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-25T20:47:27+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/osprey-levity-45-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When a major-player in the backpacking market like Osprey decides to make an ultralight backpack you can be sure that there’s going to go a ripple through the scene. I was lucky enough to receive a Osprey Levity 45 backpack in August 2017 for testing and have put the pack through it’s paces in the last six months. <em>Here’s what I liked &amp; didn’t like about the new ultralight backpack from Osprey.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39890791831/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 Review"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4674/39890791831_cc49c75a3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 Review" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from Osprey. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>The Osprey Levity 45 is a great lightweight backpack which carries loads up to 10 kg in comfort. The Airspeed suspension back frame should be especially useful for hikes in hot environments, while the highly water-resistant material of the pack has kept my gear dry while backpacking for a week in Scotland. I would have wished the front and side pockets would have been more stretchy, but other than that this backpack is well made and should be an ideal choice for those who have used heavier backpacks in the past and look to lighten up. For all the details watch the video and read the review.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YhuugW019oI?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received my <a href="https://www.ospreyeurope.com/gb_en/ventilated-pinnacle-coming-soon/">Osprey Levity</a> 45 sample in August 2017 and had it along on a dozen day trips in autumn and winter, as well as a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/10/impressions-from-the-scottish-cairngorms.html">one week backpacking trip through the Cairngorms in Scotland</a>. All in all I have used it over 25 days.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39892290381/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 at Coire Etchachan Shelter, Cairngorms, Scotland"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4694/39892290381_121c47701a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 at Coire Etchachan Shelter, Cairngorms, Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The function of a backpack is to carry your gear in comfort from A to B. The idea behind an ultralight backpack is that it isn’t weighing 2+ kg empty, but significantly less, making the hiking part of a trip more comfortable. The backpack also should protect your gear from the elements and allow fast &amp; easy access to important pieces of gear which you need on the go.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36941189873/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Loch Etchachan"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4497/36941189873_4fe952cbaa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Loch Etchachan" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>Straight out of the Levity and Lumina (the Lumina is the female version of this backpack, though it comes out in Europe first in 2019) Owner’s Manual, here’s the features of these pack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A fixed top lid with one zippered pocket</li>
  <li>Two removable side compression cords</li>
  <li>Dual access fabric side pockets</li>
  <li>Bellowed front fabric pocket</li>
  <li>Top lid cord loop attachment points</li>
  <li>Sternum strap with integrated safety whistle</li>
  <li>Internal main compartment compression strap</li>
</ul>

<p>The pack is made from two materials, the Main material is a 30D Silnylon Ripstop while the accents (that’s the lid, bottom, front and side-pockets) are made from a more durable NanoFly™ 100D Nylon x 100D UHMWPE Ripstop. The more durable material is a non-branded version of what other backpack makers sell at a premium as Dyneema or Cordura, and both materials seem to have a DWR coating.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26017236288/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Main Body Material"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4621/26017236288_38c7b5ab15_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Main Body Material" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>I’m hard pressed to give Osprey here any points: Ultralight backpacks have been around for many years, using equally or more advanced materials (like the material still commonly known as Cuben fibre, Silnylon, XPac and mixes thereof). I could say that the Airspeed frame, which allows for air circulation between your back and the main compartment of the pack, is an innovation in such a light pack.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018722777/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Side Pocket Material"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4602/25018722777_77b3c48823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Side Pocket Material" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The pack is well-made as you would expect from a brand like Osprey - they know their trade and how to make backpacks. So expect when you go to the store to get a Levity that it will hold up to many years of backpacking.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180104254/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Front &amp; Side View"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4756/39180104254_dace146f14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Front &amp; Side View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Levity 45 weighs 751 g in Size M. Please keep in mind that this is a pre-production model and the ones hitting the stores are expected to weigh 810 g on average!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018723817/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Shoulder Strap Detail 3"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4756/25018723817_aefa139dcd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Shoulder Strap Detail 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The Levity 45 is with its 45 l volume a good pack for long weekend trips or one week-long backpacking trips without resupplying, as in carrying all the food for one week. It’s going to be a tight fit at the beginning of a trip, even with a UL baseweight, but the more you eat the lighter it gets 😜. The main compartment swallows all my gear - shelter, bivy, mattress, quilt, stove, spare clothes and puffy jacket - with room to spare for food, an extra lens and the Mavic Pro Drone. The shoulder strap is not too wide, which means I can attach my <a href="https://youtu.be/3res6PXJySY">Capture Clip</a> to the pack and have my camera always at the ready.</p>

<p>When packing the backpack it’s important to pack smart, as the main compartment is not a round barrel but has two corners at the bottom which can stay empty if you don’t pack with a system - I stuff my bivy and some socks into these fins, and then come quilt, mattress, etc. If you don’t do that you’ll end up with empty space, and if you go out with a full week worths of food then that empty space might be needed. So pack smart! On the inside you also find a reservoir sleeve for a hydration system if that’s how you roll, I haven’t tried that as I use 1 l Platypus bottles and a Kuksa for water.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25018722537/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Content for a weekend"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4626/25018722537_a06b2aa659_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Content for a weekend" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The side pockets as well as the front pocket (which is bellowed, that means it does expand a bit) are not stretchy, which means you’re limited in terms of how much gear you can stuff in them. Of course the pockets on the Levity are more durable than mesh, but if you like to carry some extra stuff on a trip that doesn’t fit into the main compartment then mesh outside pockets were usually there to accommodate that stuff, but not here. For that the Levity has some loops on the lid, to which you could attach some extra gear. I haven’t tried that, and also imagine it’d be difficult to attach some apples or other fruits to these loops 🍎🍉🍒😄.</p>

<p>Back to the pockets, these were fine to carry my water bottles, snacks, a big-ass tripod and extra clothes. The side pockets can be accessed from the top or the side, I can so for example get my Kuksa out of the side pocket when I want to drink and put it back in. As they don’t stretch it can sometimes be a bit difficult to stuff gear in the side pockets when the main compartment is already filled with your gear, so keep that in mind if you carry a tripod. The zippered lid pocket is fantastic, has a keychain hook inside, and swallows an incredible amount of gear - I carried my GR1 pocket with batteries and cables in it, plus some more stuff - all goin’ easily in there.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857991462/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 2"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4697/39857991462_c2f77e4024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Airspeed backpanel does it’s job well, with the aluminium frame keeping the mesh to your back and allowing for airflow. What I really like, though, are the shoulder straps and hipbelt. These have been really well designed and are very comfortable, also if the pack is fully loaded with 10+ kg of gear &amp; food. The foam which is wrapped by a mesh is pretty durable and adapts well to your shoulders and body, making for a comfortable carry all day long. The same goes for the hipbelt, which is pretty minimal but wrapped nicely around my hips and helped transfer the weight to them. I think the carrying frame system of the Levity 45 is very well made, and if you hike in very warm environments then I think this pack should be nice, as with the Airspeed backpanel and the airflow it allows it should possibly make you sweat less.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857989532/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel &amp; Frame"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/39857989532_a3e79958b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel &amp; Frame" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39890792031/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4621/39890792031_77ff9d08e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Airspeed Backpanel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The side compression cords which are on the pack felt a bit useless to me, I still think that the compression system of the ULA Ohm is one of the best ones out there. The compression strap on the inside is a nice idea, but I tend to forget that the inside strap needs to be connected to the buckle on the inside, so sometimes I just don’t use it. The drawcord works well, though the point where the cord exists the fabric looks a bit weak to me and could be a point of failure.</p>

<p>The material of the Levity seems to have a DWR coating, especially the not transparent material with the white grid (<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180105634/in/dateposted/">see here</a>) kept the rain at bay, while the transparent material started to let some water seep through after a week in the Highlands. To be 100% safe I still would recommend to pack critical gear (quilt, down jacket, dry socks) in a waterproof drybag.</p>

<p><strong>Addition</strong>: Osprey informed me that the stretchy pockets have been fixed for production - these were updated from the sample pack I received. And the point where the drawcord exits the fabric has been reinforced for added durability, so this shouldn’t be an issue either.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39894513801/in/dateposted/" title="On the way to a Loch"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4619/39894513801_6506290024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the way to a Loch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I will repeat myself here, but: I wish Osprey would have made the side and front pockets more stretchy so one can easier get things in &amp; out of them or over-stuff them.</p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>I have reviewed half a dozen <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/gear-reviews/">backpacks</a> here and used probably more than triple the amount in the last 10 years, but there’s just a handful of UL packs which have a ventilated backpanel, like some of the ZPacks packs (which are a bit lighter but more expensive), and of course you just could go with the <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-exos-46-backpack-2600-3000cu-in">Osprey Exos</a> which also has an Airspeed backpanel.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39857991492/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 1"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4674/39857991492_a76aedbd31_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45 - Sidepocket 1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Does the market need another <em>ultralight</em> backpack? If that’s a question which is in your mind after you read this, let me say: Yes. We ultralight backpackers life in our own little UL Bubble, where we don’t see a problem with ordering a pack off the internet from a cottage manufacturer halfway across the globe - but we’re really not the majority. The Osprey Levity brings ultralight backpacks into the big stores and so in front of the eyes of thousands of outdoor enthusiasts who will love this pack - not only because they can choose from three different back lengths, but also because they <em>can try the pack on before they buy it!</em> I remember me ordering my first pack online some eight or nine years ago, it was quite an adventure to find out the right length I’d need, getting it through customs and all that. It’s not a process that many people want to go through, and hence it’s amazing that we have a lightweight backpack like the Osprey Levity now in stores across the globe.</p>

<p>And yes, the Levity backpack itself is also really, really good. It has some things which Osprey can improve upon when the next version of the pack comes around in a couple of years, but overall Osprey has done their homework well and has produced a very good backpack which will satisfy many backpackers. It’s lightweight, made of durable and water-resistant materials, has Osprey’s <a href="https://www.ospreyeurope.com/gb_en/all-mighty-guarantee/">All Mighty Guarantee</a> which lets you send in a damaged pack and get it repaired, and is also very comfortable to carry with a 10 to 12 kg load. It has everything an ultralight backpack needs as well as a backpanel which increases airflow, which should make it perfect for those super-hot summers we are getting these last years across the globe.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>The Levity is AVAILABLE! Get it at <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/osprey-levity-45-walking-backpack/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> and <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/osprey-levity-60-walking-backpack/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> in Europe. In North America order it at <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=b5770911-39dc-46ac-ba0f-b49dbb30c5c7&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.backcountry.com%2Fosprey-packs-levity-45-backpack%3Fs%3Da">Backcountry.com</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=e295c418-295a-447c-b265-734e25f82503&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.rei.com%2Fproduct%2F126706%2Fosprey-levity-45-pack-mens">REI</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=358fd954-c6b8-44a1-9ca9-aaad445d2dfb&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.campsaver.com%2Fosprey-levity-45-pack.html">CampSaver.com</a>, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=61fff111-8514-4179-a87e-5da7e9fb1264&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.moosejaw.com%2Fmoosejaw%2Fshop%2Fproduct_Osprey-Men-s-Levity-45-Pack_10364645_10208_10000001_-1_">Moosejaw</a> and <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=cl&amp;merchant_id=258f5de7-8908-4439-9828-304e836d85a8&amp;website_id=a037a589-aec6-4e81-920c-77b10ab91eff&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.summithut.com%2Flevity-45-3.html">Summit Hut</a>. And yes, please go try the Levity at your local Osprey Shop so you get a feel for what an ultralight backpack feels (I promise, you’ll love it!).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39180105634/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4715/39180105634_ce44d6a11a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Osprey Levity 45" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>There are affiliate links in this article to help finance the website. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc'teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/12/arcteryx-voltair-avalanche-airbag.html"/>
    <updated>2015-12-16T23:18:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/12/arcteryx-voltair-avalanche-airbag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The second big news from last weeks <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> media event in Vancouver was the launch of the Voltair Avalanche Airbag. As I was able to use and deploy it over three days in the Canadian backcountry what follows are more insights on this game-changing avalanche airbag.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23716165196/in/dateposted/" title="Arc’teryx Designer Gord Rose skiing with his creation, the Voltair Avalanche Airbag"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5734/23716165196_6633e02f0d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Designer Gord Rose skiing with his creation, the Voltair Avalanche Airbag" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-tech">The Tech</h2>

<p>No, it has no similarities with the JetForce Technology. Both are powered by a battery, but that’s already what these two technologies have in common. And the Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag battery allows the bag to be deployed up to 8 times on a fully charged battery, which is two times as often as the Jetforce lets you deploy the ballon. It’s even more at warmer temperatures, and less at -30°C - but then again, not many will be out skiing at -30°C.</p>

<p>Gordon Rose started to dabble in Avalanche packs around ten years ago, but the Voltair project started in February 2010 for real. Since then Gordon and his colleague Peter Hill, who is responsible for the backpack part of the Voltair, have been working on this avalanche pack. The inspiration for Gordon came from RC Models - he and a colleague where talking about how fast model planes can go, the short comings of compressed gas airbag, and saw possibilities of RC Technology for avalanche bags. Gordon went through many tests of propellor and centrifugal blowers until he settled on a mixed flow centrifugal blower. Advanced Design Technology in London, UK, helped him and Arc’teryx design the optimal propellor and after 21 designs and tests they had the perfect one for their pack.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23447243040/in/dateposted/" title="Gordon Rose with the tech guts of the Voltair Avalanche Airbag"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5798/23447243040_c612e0e1b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gordon Rose with the tech guts of the Voltair Avalanche Airbag" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next step was to get the battery right. Gordon settled on a Lithium Polymer battery design as these work well at cold temperatures and are the most efficient. Powertraveller helped design and manufacture the battery, and the one in the Voltair now allows you to deploy the ballon up to 8 times at -15°C - more at warmer temperatures, less at -30°C. The benefit of this should be obvious: It allows you to practice to deploy the airbag. If you know how it behaves, you’re less likely to hesitate to pull the trigger and deploy the ballon. Each of us popped the ballon a couple of times in a test environment, and then up in the mountains again. In the case of an avalanche this means you don’t wait and pull the trigger and deploy the ballon. The battery is charged via a cable and goes from empty to full in 2,5 hours, and weighs 800 g - a weight that Arc’teryx hopes to improve in the future.</p>

<p>For the release trigger Arc’teryx decided to use a mechanical system - while the possibility to use an electronic system is tempting, they decided in harsh conditions there’s just too much which can go wrong with a electronic release, and a reliable pull trigger is the best way to go. The Trigger is easy to unlock, but even in a locked position it is easy to release the ballon with just a small twist. The trigger is custom-molded and easy to grip with mitts and gloves, and connects via a steel cable to the ballon compartment. A pull on the trigger pops the closure open, this in turn connects to an electronic trigger which starts up the centrifugal blower which inflates the ballon in less than five seconds.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23716201286/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Release Trigger Locked"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/675/23716201286_fc4b267027_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Release Trigger Locked" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next design hurdle was the Brushless DC Motor, which are difficult to make reliable at cold weather. After tracking down many designers across the globe Gord found the right guy just five minutes from the Arc’teryx Design HQ, and he helped him design a reliable engine which also performs at -30°C. 90% of the other technology in the pack is also custom-made, from flexible wires to the circuit board and release notch, Arc’teryx spent nearly six years to make this backpack the best in its category. To learn more, please watch this exclusive video where Gordon Rose and Peter Hill talk about the Voltair Avalanche Airbag:</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xjq-NAQUK-k" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>(<em>Interview video coming soon!</em>)</p>

<h2 id="the-pack">The Pack</h2>

<p>The goal of Peter Hill was to make a classic, timeless Arc’teryx backpack which still looks great in five years. Constructed from the AC² material with taped seams and glued-in Sidewinder zippers, the pack is waterproof and keeps your gear dry. As it rained &amp; snowed all the time as we were up in the mountains it was a good test for the pack, and it performed great: Everything stayed dry inside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23633782422/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag - Side"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5797/23633782422_324efe2db1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag - Side" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Voltair has three compartments: A ballon compartment, an avalanche Kit compartment and a main compartment. Available in two sizes these pack are real 20 l and 30 l packs, unlike some packs of competitors which barely let you pack a puffy jacket and thermos bottle in their claimed volumes. I carried in my 30 l test pack two extra pairs of gloves, my <a href="http://bit.ly/1P2NxEx">Arc’teryx Cerium SV Jacket</a>, my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/norroena-lyngen-alpha100-vest-kunstfaserweste/?pid=10239">Norrona Lyngen Alpha100 Vest</a>, a water bottle, sandwiches and snacks, my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/contour-hybrid-mix-130-skifelle/?pid=10239">countour Hybrid skins</a>, a tripod, two cameras and I had plenty of room to spare. If I compare that to my <a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/black-diamond-dawn-patrol-25-ski-rucksack-deep-torch-black-m-l/?pid=81">Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 25 pack</a> that’s a massive difference, where it gets pretty hard to get so much gear in.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23716247456/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Avalanche Kit Pocket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/738/23716247456_a1a40505f3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Avalanche Kit Pocket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The carrying system of the Voltair is very comfortable and is fully adjustable. The hipbelt has some freedom of movement so you can turn those hips for your turns, and if you want to save weight you can remove the stays. The hipbelt also can be turned around for transport, and the chest strap can be removed if you feel you don’t need it. The leg loop strap is very easy to use which is very important: It’s the piece of gear that ensures you stay connected to the backpack and ballon if you get into an avalanche. It is super easy to clip in and out - also with mitts on - and the design is inspired by ice clippers as you might know them from ice climbing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23742317785/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Leg loop clip-in point"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5829/23742317785_aa47814a51_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Leg loop clip-in point" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The pack isn’t ultralight, even if Arc’teryx tried to use the lightest &amp; most durable materials and technology in the pack. The 20 l pack is 3.235 g and the 30 l pack is 3.465 g - the tech inside is a big part of that, with the battery itself already being a wee bit over 800 g. Arc’teryx hopes that this weight will be decreased in the not-too-distant future, especially since major players are heavily infesting into energy storage solutions.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In Use</h2>

<p>I was able to use the pack for three days out at <a href="http://www.callaghancountry.com">Callaghan Country</a>, which gave me a good understanding how this pack carries and deploys. The first thing you realize is the comfortable carrying system, which carries also (for an ultralight backpacker) very well, even with a pretty full pack. Also the leg loop is wonderfully intuitive and unobtrusive: It clips in and out super easy even with thick gloves on, and you don’t realize it is there while skinning and skiing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23633780212/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag at Callaghan Country"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5702/23633780212_2243ce5e36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag at Callaghan Country" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As I haven’t used Avalanche Airbags before I have nothing to compare the Voltair to, but chatting with Lou of <a href="http://wildsnow.com">Wildsnow</a> and my other colleagues at the event it became evident that the Voltair is a well-designed Avalanche backpack which compares very good with other packs in the market. The advantages of battery-powered packs in comparison to compressed air backpacks are evident: You can practice and test the release of the ballon at home, it is much easier to travel with as you don’t need to find a place to fill up the air cartridge before you hit the slopes at your destination, and being able to release the ballon in the Voltair up to eight times means using this pack on long outings adds a lot of safety.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23659988171/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Packing the Ballon 1"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5703/23659988171_0fef0d05d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packing the Ballon 1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Packing the ballon is a thing of two to five minutes, depending on your level of practice. The ballon deflates via a valve which you slide in. Happily the ballon does not need to be folded in a special way - just stuff it back into the ballon compartment, close the zipper, pop the hatch back in and you’re ready. I discussed at length with Peter and Gordon about the use of zippers for the ballon compartment as it’s most certainly the thing I like least, but as every other avalanche pack on the market uses zippers (they work!) and in a pinch you can use the ballon even if the zipper is broken, I am convinced that it is OK.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23115555973/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Ballon compartment"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/579/23115555973_03b5921fd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ballon compartment" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Putting the system on and releasing the ballon is also easy. You put the battery on and get a re-assuring short whirr which means the system is on and ready to go. The green LED lamp at the outside will blink green indicating that all is good to go, then you just turn the handle to the green dot side and you’re ready to skin up and ski down. In the case of an avalanche you pull the trigger and <em>POP!</em> the ballon deploys, helping you to hopefully stay on top thanks to the inverse segregation principle, which sorts larger particles to the top of the avalanche. The handle of the Voltair is also always accessible and can not be stowed away, this again minimizes the risk of user error and is different from other avalanche packs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23742279705/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="POW Turns"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5814/23742279705_0876730dd4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="POW Turns" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>You can carry skis/ snowboard and an ice axe at the front of the pack, just make sure to put the ice axe with the tip down (ballons and steel tips don’t work well together). The side compression straps help to minimize volume if you are out with a small load, and the front hipbelt is comfortable and carries well. All buckles are easy to open in cold weather with gloves, and the zippers have tabs which makes them easy to operate with gloves on.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23374347639/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Crossing streams"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/654/23374347639_0df435ac5f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Crossing streams" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, the battery and control unit of the circuit collect data of the pack in use, with the aim to further the knowledge base of avalanche airbags in use. This data can be downloaded - should the user agree - when the pack is sent in for inspection. Arc’teryx works close together with Pascal Haegeli of the Simon Fraser University in Vancouver, one of the premier avalanche researchers on the planet.</p>

<h2 id="the-bottomline">The Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Voltair is a beautifully designed avalanche pack which is spacious and easy to use. The tech inside is all custom-made and designed to the highest standards, so that it can operate at -30°C and for many years in the harsh conditions of the backcountry. It is easy to learn how to deploy the ballon, pack it back in and then carry all your gear on your backcountry ski-tours. Fully waterproof it keeps your kit inside dry, and the possibilities for human error minimized it hopefully helps you to survive an avalanche if you should ever get into one. The packs will retail for 1650€ for the 30 l pack and 1550€ for the 20 l and will be available in autumn 2016. <em>Of course using the pack for just three days is not enough for a long-term review, but I am confident that with a sample pack showing up hopefully soon I can put it through its paces during the many ski-touring trips I have planned for this winter and then can get a more detailed review up by spring.</em></p>

<p>A lot more <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157662401963745">high resolution photos are in the Flickr Album</a>, and if you enjoyed this article <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">buy me a coffee</a></strong>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23115487673/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Skinning up"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/758/23115487673_22ec0ed64b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skinning up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l.html"/>
    <updated>2014-07-08T11:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/07/patagonia-ascensionist-pack-45l</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>What if <a href="http://bit.ly/1vVr6Wj">Patagonia</a> would go and build an alpine climbing pack that is minimalistic, comfortable, highly water-resistant and durable? Would it work also for backpacking?</em> These and other questions I answer in this review.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193953927" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3877/14193953927_5201bcbb49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia/rucksack.html">Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L</a> landed here in March 2014 and has been used various times at the local crag and in Chamonix, a week backpacking in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/lake-district/">Lake District</a> and a week climbing &amp; hiking in the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/poland/">Polish Tatras</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193760149" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2916/14193760149_8ba4f829a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>This is a streamlined alpine climbing backpack with more space than it’s litte brothers (there’s a <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia/rucksack.html">25 l</a> and <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia/rucksack.html">35 l</a> version available), made to carry more climbing gear for big ascents and/ or an overnight kit. It carries very well thanks to the Aluminium frame and easily can be used for week-long ultralight backpacking strips.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14378961872" title="Patagonia Ascensionist 45 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2926/14378961872_aeec0f6d90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist 45" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>This is what Patagonia says about their pack:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Light and durable nylon ripstop with excellent tear and abrasion resistance</li>
  <li>The spindrift collar opens wide for easy packing; drawcord simultaneously cinches collar and closes lid for a secure seal; additional spindrift collar deploys to protect your gear when you have overstuffed your pack</li>
  <li>Aluminium stay frame with tensioned mesh center gives the pack structure and helps to support heavy loads and can be removed for Fast &amp; Light adventures</li>
  <li>Padded hip belt can be removed to create a simple webbing hip belt</li>
  <li>Center sheath ice axe carry system accommodates a wide assortment of axes</li>
  <li>Daisy chains on front and side panels provide lashing options; compression straps on sides help manage different size loads; zippered pocket on lid provides easy access to small items</li>
</ul>

<p>What they fail to mention is that this pack is the brain-child of Steve House, one of the world’s top alpinists. This pack won’t make you climb like him, but at least you can carry your gear like him =)</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/FnWap_pZ3YU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Something I haven’t seen before is the internal frame system that Patagonia uses in this pack. It’s an aluminium frame that’s covered by mesh and that’s super flexible - you can twist it 180° so it gives the pack great freedom of movement. The DWR on the material is also very good and kept my gear inside dry during hikes in sustained, heavy rain from all angles. Also the inside rain-cover is a nice way to not need an external one when you carry more gear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624434903" title="Patagonia Ascensionist internal frame by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5530/14624434903_5969025411_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist internal frame" /></a></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>After over two weeks of backpacking, climbing and scrambling with it it still shows no tears or signs of weakness. The DWR also still holds up very well, and all seams - despite some heavier loads and being fully packed - are still perfect like on day one. I think this pack will be with me for many hikes and climbs to come.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14624459203" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3918/14624459203_a9bd18b0f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The Patagonia Ascensionist is available in two lengths and I have the S/ M length of the pack.</p>

<p>Stripped Pack: 847
Frame: 151 g
Hipbelt: 140 g</p>

<p>TOTAL: 1138g</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417796848" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3838/14417796848_c8389e3d6c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="770" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>It’s Patagonia who made this pack so you know it has top-notch environmental credentials. ‘Nuff said!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602382524" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2939/14602382524_dd6979ab34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>There’s a wide variety of <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/kletterrucksack.html">climbing backpacks</a>, very good ones are the <a href="http://bit.ly/1qR0yaH">Crux AK-47</a> and the <a href="http://www.campsaver.com/speed-22-pack">Black Diamond Speed</a> packs. <a href="http://www.cilogear.com/">Cilogear</a> also makes top-notch climbing packs, as does <a href="http://www.mchalepacks.com/ultralight/index.htm">McHale</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14581386756" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3904/14581386756_39bdddd491_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>The closure of the pack is really nice. It is easy to open and close, even if it seems like an old-fashioned closure it is a smart system in my opinion. You can close it with one hand, opening with both. You pull the cord to close it, and then put the aluminium hook through the webbing loop. Even when fully packed it’s easy to open and close and most important - it stays closed. The front aluminium hook can be moved up if it’s really fully loaded.</p>

<p>The elastic loops to tie down straps are a very nice detail. This way webbing does not dangle around when the straps are pulled tight - if you’re anal-retentive about straps and stuff dangling around on your pack and like things to be orderly you will really like this small addition to all the straps.</p>

<p>Your ice axes or <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/petzl-nomic-ice-tools.html">ice tools</a> are connected to the pack via a small and durable ice axe pocket with a buckle at the front pocket and the shafts are held in place by the side compression straps. It’s a safe, good system for transport to the mountain and when you really won’t need it. For in between sections where you won’t need the tools you can store the ice axe He-Man style between your shoulder blade and strap.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14581388176" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2903/14581388176_f817a9ed5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<p>The top pocket is surprisingly spacious and I can fit a large amount of stuff in there. Map, compass, sunscreen, lip balm, snacks, shades, extra camera lens - and still room to spare. It’s fairly weatherproof too, so in case you forgot your phone’s rain cover it’s safe in there (but even safer inside the pack!).</p>

<p>For a 45 l pack the Ascensionist is super spacious. Food and UL kit for six days + 2 l water were no problem for it, and there would have been even more space - that large opening + inside rainflap makes it a very large backpack. But also a full trad kit, helmet, harness, crampons and rope + UL sleeping gear and snacks fit in there with some room left. I really like the form of the pack with the narrow bottom and the wider top - it makes for easy packing. Food or climbing gear go in the bottom, followed by down garments and rain clothes, kitchen, quilt, bivy, shelter and helmet. Water bottles I store on the top of everything for easy access.</p>

<p>So is the Ascensionist better with the frame or without? That’s a difficult question to answer. In the Lake District I had the frame in the pack and found it worked superb. In the Polish Tatras I left the frame at home and also found it excellent. Subjectively I feel with the frame it carries slightly better and transfers weight more effectively to the hipbelt. The pack has what feels like a closed cell foam pad in the back which does a good job of keeping the shape of the pack when the frame is removed and also gives a bit of extra cushioning against your back.</p>

<p>Moving with it - climbing, hiking, scrambling - is wonderful. It rides high on the waist and does not limit movement at all. As it is a streamlined pack it you also have no stuff at the sides in your way, and low chances of the pack snagging something along the route or trail. As the pack is narrow and not very deep it’s close to the body so you can squeeze through tight passages, and your centre of gravity is close to where it’s supposed to be. The thickly cushioned shoulder straps are comfy also on long days, as is the hip belt. The gear loops on the hip belt are solid and a welcome addition to rack gear on long routes.</p>

<p>Oh, and you also can attach the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/01/peak-design-capture-pro-camera-clip.html">Peak Designs Capture PRO</a> wonderfully to the shoulder straps!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417878278" title="Hiking in the Polish Tatras by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5507/14417878278_ff97606b7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking in the Polish Tatras" /></a></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>When climbing with the frame in the pack I often would hit my head on it when looking up, which is not good. Removing the frame solves this, but it’s better with the frame inside for carrying heavier loads. If it’s possible I’d imagine making the internal frame shorter would solve this, as would a gap for the helmet when climbing/ looking up.</p>

<p>You can remove the padded hipbelt (and save 140 gram weight) but it’s too complicated - mainly because the wide webbing belt is sewn to the pack and can’t be removed. So you need to thread the webbing through the padding loops to take it off. I’d wish that everything could have been removed easily - I don’t see much sense in using the webbing as a hipbelt.</p>

<p>Water Management is not as straight forward as I’d like it to be. There’s no hydration system exit and no side pockets, so you need to take the pack off to drink. When climbing this is fine as you likely take the pack off at the belay and then can drink, but when hiking it’s not convenient to stop every 30 minutes to take the pack off to access your water bottle. You could attach your water bottle with a carabiner to the gear loop on the hipbelt, though I think that would be annoying if you have a bottle dangling in front of your legs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14417828779" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3924/14417828779_643901874a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>At the moment the Patagonia Ascensionist Pack 45L is my favourite backpack. It carries very well, is large enough for week-long trips - be it climbing or backpacking - and can take a lot of abuse. It’s weatherproof, easy to pack, the big haul loop makes it easy to grab the pack &amp; put on, and the cushioned shoulder straps and hip belt make it comfortable to carry also on 30 km days with 2000+ m of ascent. Most importantly it does not bother me when climbing or scrambling and gives me freedom of movement to go to those high places I enjoy so much! If you’re in the market for a large-volume alpine climbing backpack I can really recommend the Ascensionist 45L from <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia.html">Patagonia</a>.</p>

<p>Oh, in orange it also looks great - Hup Holland Hup!</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-it">Where to buy it</h2>

<p>Get your Ascensionist pack at <a href="http://www.unterwegs.biz/patagonia/rucksack.html">Unterwegs.biz</a> if you are in Europe, from <a href="http://bit.ly/1qG5cXo">CampSaver</a> if you’re in the USA or directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1lPYO9Z">Patagonia</a> everywhere else.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14602411384" title="Patagonia Ascensionist by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3917/14602411384_f4f4f02911_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Patagonia Ascensionist" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Packing your raft]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/10/packing-your-raft.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-17T10:15:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/10/packing-your-raft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I really like the <a href="http://bit.ly/WUaRuk">ULA EPIC</a> for packrafting, though I never liked how they suggested to pack your packraft on it. Until I figured out a much better way to carry it.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/packing-your-raft.html" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2820/10324096124_daec431087_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/WUaRuk">ULA Equipment EPIC</a> was made for packrafting, and I have been using it for over three years. It’s a great pack for that activity, the possibility to use it with dry sacks of different volumes is excellent. However, I did not like how the packraft was supposed to be carried in the pack: Rolled together at the bottom of the pack, even strapped underneath it. Even when packrafts are light, 2,5 kg at the bottom of a pack isn’t comfortable for me. So I started to experiment to find a better way to carry the packraft, with the weight further up.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9534961449/" title="Wet packraft &amp; paddle"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7432/9534961449_d2ae90436e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Wet packraft &amp; paddle" /></a></p>

<p>My first tries saw me using a mat (a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-z-lite-sol-isomatte/">Z-Lite</a> or <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/therm-a-rest-ridgerest-solite-isomatte/">RidgeRest</a> usually) at the bottom to push the rolled packraft further up. That worked OK, but wasn’t perfect. Then, on a packrafting trip it hit me: Why roll the raft at all - it could just as well be laid out double against the backpanel of the EPIC, and the dry sack goes in front of it. The thought was implemented, and I was surprised about how much better the whole pack carried in an instant! With hindsight this isn’t surprising - traditional packing of a backpack suggests you pack heavy items in the centre of the pack, close to the back.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10324280143/" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3706/10324280143_ce55d2e92d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10324123586/" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2830/10324123586_04e4a399b2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10324133366/" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3733/10324133366_eb1368e674_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a></p>

<p>So how to pack it? After the raft is dry, I fold my packraft twice - the two sides are folded into the middle (the seat area). This makes for a more compact package than folding it just once in the middle and makes it only slightly wider than the backpanel of the EPIC. I then open the EPIC completely up, fold the packraft twice and lay it down. Dry sack on top, close the side and top buckles, slide in the paddle and pull the straps tight, and you’re done! With longer rafts - I got the small Alpaca - you might need to fold it maybe four times, but it still should result in a fairly flat package.</p>

<p>This works especially well with the <a href="http://www.alpackaraft.com/">Alpacka packrafts</a>, but also should work just fine with rafts from <a href="http://bit.ly/ZDiyFO">Klymit</a>, <a href="http://flyweightdesigns.com/">FlyWeight Designs</a>, <a href="http://www.supaiadventuregear.com/">Supai Adventure Gear</a> and others, even if these packrafts are lighter and more compact to pack. You could employ this technique also with another backpack, as long as the pack has enough volume and is wide enough. You also can pack it inside a dry sack this way, though both of these options are a bit more fiddly.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10324127325/" title="ULA Equipment EPIC"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2888/10324127325_ee111960fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="ULA Equipment EPIC" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
