<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: advent calendar 2017 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/advent-calendar-2017/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-11-29T12:33:33+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off-2017.html"/>
    <updated>2017-11-29T09:53:34+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <em>“Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off 2017”</em> is a go!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24846027678/in/dateposted/" title="HiFAdventCalendar Kickoff Logos"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4544/24846027678_19603d3465_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar Kickoff Logos" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>really, 12 months passed and we’re talking again? How are you? Did your pack get lighter this year? How’s the snow up North, and are the reindeers alright? I did miss our conversations, and am looking forward to catch up with you over the next 24 days. But I also need to tell you that this is likely the last time we’ll be having our chats - rumor has it that this is the final #HiFAdventCalendar - that could be just a rumor, or then it’s a fact - I guess we’ll have to wait till November 2018 to find out. Anyway.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2017/">2017 Hiking in Finland Advent Calendar</a> looks like it will be the best yet again, with great prizes that will make quite a few people happy. Also, Hiking in Finland is <a href="https://mossy.earth/collections/carbon-offsetting-travel/products/plant-a-tree">planting one tree for each door that goes open</a>, so once the 24th of December comes around there will be 25 trees planted, already a wee forest! That’s not just great for the environment, but also for future generations of outdoor enthusiasts! Well, lets have a look at the prizes this year, shall we?</p>

<p>The ADZHiFACKO Door has some sweet kit from GSI with the <a href="http://www.gsioutdoors.com/halulite-microdualist-complete.html">Halulite Microdualist Complete Set</a> and the <a href="http://www.gsioutdoors.com/ultralight-java-drip.html">Ultralight Java Drip</a>. The Halulite Microdualist is an excellent choice to boil water and cook food when outdoors, and best of all: It’s made for two people and packs up in itself. But even when outdoors on my own the Halulite is a solid choice and with the Ultralight Java Drip a good cup of real coffee is never far away. And who can resist good coffee - especially outdoors?!</p>

<p>The <a href="https://kupilka.fi/en/products/kupilka-37">Kupilka 37</a> goes very well with the stove and coffee dripper, and the 370 ml volume of this new, larger Kuksa is a real benefit: Large cups of coffee in the morning, warm soups in the afternoon, refreshingly cold cups of water while hiking and hot chocolate in the evening can be consumed from it in style.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://mountainlaureldesigns.com/product/event-rain-mitts/">eVent Rain Mitts</a> from Mountain Laurel Design on the other hand are a good weather charm - carry these 30 g mitts and it’s bound not to rain! I can not imagine a better way to influence the weather, and if one’s luck runs out then one can always wear them to keep the hands dry!</p>

<p>The <a href="https://goosefeetgear.com/products/down-socks/">Down Socks</a> from GooseFeet Gear on the other hand are a sure guarantor to toasty toes and feet. They also pack down next to nothing, are ultralight and nowadays come in a variety of colours from Black to Red, Pink and Blue. The Mitts and Socks even pack so small, you could stuff them into your Kuksa!</p>

<p>As you see Dear Santa, this kick-off Door is already filled to the brim with sweet kit - and all potential winners need to do is enter via the Rafflecopter Widget below!</p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895114/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895114" data-theme="classic" data-template="" id="rcwidget_ape2q5iu">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/advent-calendar-2017-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prizes are sent directly from GSI, Kupilka, GooseFeet Gear and Mountain Laurel Designs, <em>possible import duty fees need to be paid by the winner</em>. You can pick the size of the Mitts and the Size and Colour of the Down Socks. Want to stay warm when going outdoors? Read my Layering Guide and learn <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">How to Dress for Winter</a>!*</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37831610115/in/dateposted/" title="HiFAdventCalendar Kick-off Prizes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4542/37831610115_5aaf672e5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar Kick-off Prizes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar 2017 - The Rules]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/11/advent-calendar-2017-the-rules.html"/>
    <updated>2017-11-29T09:37:19+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/11/advent-calendar-2017-the-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some Rules can be broken, but the #HiFAdventCalendar Rules can not.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8230998731/" title="HiF Advent Calendar"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8350/8230998731_e265161b94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="HiF Advent Calendar Logo" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Welcome to the seventh and final Hiking in Finland Advent Calendar! Like in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2014/">years</a> <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2016/">before</a>, a good set of rules makes running the Advent Calendar a lot easier for all of us. Read them carefully and everything will be clear, and for some added benefit check out the <strong>tips</strong> at the end!</p>

<p>This years calendar will run 25 days (= 25 Doors), and behind each door you will find a fine piece of equipment which should make your next outdoor adventure fun and ultralight. Some information on the prizes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>All prizes are sent directly from the company providing them (<strong>which can mean that you might need to pay import duties when it comes from abroad</strong>!).</li>
  <li>Sometimes it is possible that you can choose size, colour and other variables. Where this is the case, it will be mentioned in the text of the Door.</li>
  <li>This means garments can be either female or male, backpacks can be different torso sizes and meals can be vegetarian or with meat.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-rules">The Rules</h2>

<p>To win something you should check in each day here and enter the raffle. There are a couple of points to keep in mind:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>You only can win once.</strong> If you don’t win on one day, you can try your luck the next day - you got 25 chances!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I am using a paid-for version of <a href="https://www.rafflecopter.com/">Rafflecopter</a> for the Give-Aways. With Rafflecopter you can get multiple entries by following someone on Instagram, Twitter, visit a page on Facebook, follow a Pinterest page or susbscribe to a Mailing List. This increases your chances to win, but is not mandatory.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Rafflecopter Widget is integrated with <a href="http://www.random.org/">Random.org</a> and it choses the winner.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>If you are the lucky winner</strong> I contact you via the provided Email address and <strong>you have 24 hours to reply</strong>. If I don’t hear from you, I imagine you don’t want the item and will let Random.org chose a new winner.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Posts go online around midnight and the raffles close at midnight - Finnish time. Rafflecopter then will show the name of the winner after I pushed that button, this keeps posts to a minimum.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>It is open to everyone. As in from Amsterdam to Zanzibar, from Canada to South Africa, prices are send everywhere (unless noted otherwise).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Possible Import Duty taxes and fees are paid by the winner. If you’re not willing to pay these, don’t compete.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can’t bribe me or anyone involved to win. You use the item(s) on your own responsibility. Use common sense.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37735067715/in/dateposted/" title="Impressions from Koli. Read https://hikinginfinland.com &#x3D;)"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4556/37735067715_708060f582_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Impressions from Koli. Read https://hikinginfinland.com &#x3D;)" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="tips">Tips</h2>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You can participate via the Rafflecopter widget by registering with your Email or your Facebook accoount. Please make sure for either option that it’s an Email address you regularly check, so when I contact you you get the email.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>There is usually one mandatory option to answer to participate. This can be something fun or a question about the price in question. You should be easily able to answer the question by reading the text or visiting the manufacturer website.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You can get additional entries which improve your chances of winning. This could be visiting a Facebook page or following someone on Youtube, Twitter, Instagram and the like. It’s a good thing to do, and also allows you stay up-to-date with news about the HiF Advent Calendar and the company sponsoring the prize.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If you think your friends and fans would like to participate - spread the word! Use the #HiFAdventCalendar hashtag on Instagram, Twitter &amp; Facebook when you spread the word =)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Some prizes could incur you import duties. You will need to pay these and there’s no way around them, so please don’t ask me or the sponsor for a way to avoid them. If you’re not willing to pay them, please don’t enter for that price.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>That’s it. The Advent Calendar starts today, the 29th of November. Subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://plus.google.com/105082905705272949032">Google+</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to get an update every time a new door opens.</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>All gear is sponsored. Sponsors pay a fee to participate. Part of the income is donated to <a href="https://mossy.earth/collections/carbon-offsetting-travel/products/plant-a-tree">plant trees</a>. I try to not spend all time in front of a screen so relax if a post goes up a tad late or I don’t reply an email asap.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
