<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: advent calendar 2017 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/advent-calendar-2017/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-12-03T22:38:34+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-4.html"/>
    <updated>2017-12-04T23:25:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38098141954/in/dateposted/" title="HiFAdventCalendar Peak Design Logo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4553/38098141954_0613ed9ec5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar Peak Design Logo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>you know what is more exciting than skiing, hiking and climbing? Right, documenting these pursuits when you are outdoors! Sadly storing and transporting your gear with the leashes and pockets which come with cameras aren’t always the best - if you want those, you will need to stop by at Peak Design. This company from San Fransisco has been designing and manufacturing some of the best accessories for photographers out there, and with their new <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/bags/everyday-sling-5/?acc=97">Everyday Sling 5L</a> they now also offer such a compact pouch that it fits my a6500 and some equipment just perfectly! I also prefer to use the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/straps/leash/?acc=97">Leash</a> instead of the camera straps which come with my cameras, as the Leash is easy to take off when not needed (when e.g. using a slider) - or you can add the <a href="https://www.peakdesign.com/product/straps/cuff/?acc=97">Cuff</a> if you want to secure your camera to just your hand. This lightweight trio of Everyday Sling, Leash and Cuff is the ideal companion to any small DSLR or M43 Camera, and hence I’d love to add it to my camera kit!</p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895118/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895118" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_s9a3y6xe">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/advent-calendar-2017-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prizes are sponsored by Peak Design and sent directly from them - <em>possible import duty fees still need to be paid by the winner</em>. The winner can pick the colour of the items - depending on availability =) <em>This Advent Calendar Door has been supported financially and with gear from Peak Design.</em></p>

<p><em>If you want know which camera I love, read my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/sony-rx100-iv-field-report.html">Sony RX 100 IV Field Report</a>.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38783342782/in/dateposted/" title="HiFAdventCalenda Peak Design Prizes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4519/38783342782_af2043151a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalenda Peak Design Prizes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-3.html"/>
    <updated>2017-12-03T23:25:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38066001184/in/dateposted/" title="HiFAdventCalendar As Tucas Logo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4527/38066001184_1dec722286_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar As Tucas Logo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>picture this: You arrive up North for your trip and you realize your quilt isn’t up to the task of keeping you toasty. Staying warm in subzero temperatures isn’t easy, but happily the <a href="https://www.astucas.com/en/products/foratata-quilt/">Foratata Quilt</a> from the Spanish Cottage As Tucas would do just that! Available in three styles and made with the high craftsmanship you know from them, the Foratata uses 900 cuin down to keep one warm when stationary but also packs small when one is moving. It’s a great piece of gear and brand-new - so new, indeed, that it ain’t available until later in December and this is the best chance to get the first Foratata quilt ever!</p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895117/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895117" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_7g3nl5oj">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/advent-calendar-2017-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prize is sponsored by As Tucas and is sent directly from them (<em>possible import duty fees still need to be paid by the winner</em>). The winner can pick the size and colour of her quilt =) <em>This Advent Calendar Door has been supported financially and with gear from As Tucas.</em></p>

<p><em>Prefer autumn? Come <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/backpacking-on-the-orealvsleden-trail.html">backpacking on the Öreälvsleden Trail</a> with me!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38782690421/in/dateposted/" title="HiFAdventCalendar Foratata Quilt"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4574/38782690421_d53ac00aa2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar Foratata Quilt" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-2.html"/>
    <updated>2017-12-02T23:25:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31652260101" title="Advent Calendar Mountain Equipment"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/416/31652260101_85d55cacb3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Advent Calendar Mountain Equipment" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>picture this: I was just yesterday in Slushy Helsinki, but travelling back north it got colder and whiter the further north we went. As I arrived in Vaasa and walked to my bicycle it was covered under a white blanket and I wished I would have had a warmer jacket with me - something like the <a href="http://www.mountain-equipment.de/moreno-jacket">Moreno Jacket</a> from Mountain Equipment. The Polartec Thermal Pro Fleece has this cuddly look and is just as at home on a trip to the office as it is ice-climbing in Korouoma. Two zippered pockets store the essentials when on the go in town or some snacks when climbing up a frozen waterfall. It’s so versatile in use that I’m even pondering getting the <a href="http://www.mountain-equipment.de/womens-moreno-jacket">female version</a> for my wife because she most certainly would love this warm fleece jacket!</p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895116/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895116" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_1n051ncr">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/advent-calendar-2017-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prize is sponsored by Mountain Equipment and sent directly from them - it will only be shipped within Europe, though (<em>possible import duty fees still need to be paid by the winner</em>). The winner can pick the sex, size and colour - depending on availability =) <em>This Advent Calendar Door has been supported financially and with gear from Mountain Equipment.</em></p>

<p>If you want more snow, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/winter-fun-in-ruka.html">come to Wintery Ruka with me</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24894343788/in/dateposted/" title="HiFAdventCalendar ME Moreno Jacket"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4517/24894343788_f1f110376a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar ME Moreno Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-1.html"/>
    <updated>2017-12-01T13:25:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/12/advent-calendar-door-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/DF7j41" title="HiFAdventCalendar Alpinetrek.co.uk Logo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4554/38688037092_8b9dfc9b36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar Alpinetrek.co.uk Logo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>December is here! What better way to kick things of for the next 24 days than with a backpack? <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> was so kind to provide one lucky hiker with the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/berghaus-freeflow-30-trekking-backpack/?pid=10239">Berghaus Freeflow 30</a>. At 30 l it packs a lot of gear for a day out in the hills, and the ultralight backpacker will even take the pack outdoor a weekend trip or longer. The back panel is increasing airflow and should be great for sweaty summer hikes, while the included rain cover keeps the contents dry when the weather turns. Stretchy side pockets carry a water bottle while the stretchy front pocket takes in a jacket or other gear. All in all a sweet pack which is great for hillwalking and dayhikes!</p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895115/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895115" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_jlbl6t6l">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/advent-calendar-2017-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prize is sponsored by Alpinetrek.co.uk and sent directly from them - it will only be shipped within Europe, though (<em>possible import duty fees still need to be paid by the winner</em>). <em>This Advent Calendar Door has been supported financially and with gear from Alpinetrek.co.uk.</em></p>

<p>And if you wish it’d still be autumn, escape with me to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho Kekkonen National Park in Autumn</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/8N8BQY" title="HiFAdventCalendar Alpinetrek Price"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4531/38002920224_8b5db8e58a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar Alpinetrek Price" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off 2017]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off-2017.html"/>
    <updated>2017-11-29T09:53:34+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/11/annual-day-zero-hif-advent-calendar-kick-off-2017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <em>“Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off 2017”</em> is a go!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24846027678/in/dateposted/" title="HiFAdventCalendar Kickoff Logos"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4544/24846027678_19603d3465_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar Kickoff Logos" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>really, 12 months passed and we’re talking again? How are you? Did your pack get lighter this year? How’s the snow up North, and are the reindeers alright? I did miss our conversations, and am looking forward to catch up with you over the next 24 days. But I also need to tell you that this is likely the last time we’ll be having our chats - rumor has it that this is the final #HiFAdventCalendar - that could be just a rumor, or then it’s a fact - I guess we’ll have to wait till November 2018 to find out. Anyway.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2017/">2017 Hiking in Finland Advent Calendar</a> looks like it will be the best yet again, with great prizes that will make quite a few people happy. Also, Hiking in Finland is <a href="https://mossy.earth/collections/carbon-offsetting-travel/products/plant-a-tree">planting one tree for each door that goes open</a>, so once the 24th of December comes around there will be 25 trees planted, already a wee forest! That’s not just great for the environment, but also for future generations of outdoor enthusiasts! Well, lets have a look at the prizes this year, shall we?</p>

<p>The ADZHiFACKO Door has some sweet kit from GSI with the <a href="http://www.gsioutdoors.com/halulite-microdualist-complete.html">Halulite Microdualist Complete Set</a> and the <a href="http://www.gsioutdoors.com/ultralight-java-drip.html">Ultralight Java Drip</a>. The Halulite Microdualist is an excellent choice to boil water and cook food when outdoors, and best of all: It’s made for two people and packs up in itself. But even when outdoors on my own the Halulite is a solid choice and with the Ultralight Java Drip a good cup of real coffee is never far away. And who can resist good coffee - especially outdoors?!</p>

<p>The <a href="https://kupilka.fi/en/products/kupilka-37">Kupilka 37</a> goes very well with the stove and coffee dripper, and the 370 ml volume of this new, larger Kuksa is a real benefit: Large cups of coffee in the morning, warm soups in the afternoon, refreshingly cold cups of water while hiking and hot chocolate in the evening can be consumed from it in style.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://mountainlaureldesigns.com/product/event-rain-mitts/">eVent Rain Mitts</a> from Mountain Laurel Design on the other hand are a good weather charm - carry these 30 g mitts and it’s bound not to rain! I can not imagine a better way to influence the weather, and if one’s luck runs out then one can always wear them to keep the hands dry!</p>

<p>The <a href="https://goosefeetgear.com/products/down-socks/">Down Socks</a> from GooseFeet Gear on the other hand are a sure guarantor to toasty toes and feet. They also pack down next to nothing, are ultralight and nowadays come in a variety of colours from Black to Red, Pink and Blue. The Mitts and Socks even pack so small, you could stuff them into your Kuksa!</p>

<p>As you see Dear Santa, this kick-off Door is already filled to the brim with sweet kit - and all potential winners need to do is enter via the Rafflecopter Widget below!</p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895114/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895114" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_3g95bdwm">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/advent-calendar-2017-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prizes are sent directly from GSI, Kupilka, GooseFeet Gear and Mountain Laurel Designs, <em>possible import duty fees need to be paid by the winner</em>. You can pick the size of the Mitts and the Size and Colour of the Down Socks. Want to stay warm when going outdoors? Read my Layering Guide and learn <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">How to Dress for Winter</a>!*</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37831610115/in/dateposted/" title="HiFAdventCalendar Kick-off Prizes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4542/37831610115_5aaf672e5b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="614" alt="HiFAdventCalendar Kick-off Prizes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
