<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: trip reports | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/trip-reports/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-02-15T13:47:14+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions from the Salzburger Lungau]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-05T19:17:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the ISPO I did the only smart thing: Leave the city behind and head to Austria to go ski-touring. These are some first impressions from a too-short trip to the Salzburger Lungau Region.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225607357/in/dateposted/" title="Albert on the way to the summit of the Seeköpfl."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4620/25225607357_aa885b504c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert on the way to the summit of the Seeköpfl." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Salzburger Lungau Tourism who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225608777/in/dateposted/" title="St. Margarethen im Lungau"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4698/25225608777_5329e81066_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="St. Margarethen im Lungau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a very busy fair I met my brother and we made the trip down south to the <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/your-lungau/15-villages/?_wb=en/your-lungau/15-villages/&amp;lang=EN">Salzburger Lungau</a> Region, a place we have visited before and really liked. We arrived at our <a href="https://www.grizzly-resort.at">Hotel</a>, had a tasty dinner and then it was off to bed as early in the morning we would meet Albert again, our <a href="http://www.geführte-skitouren.at">Ski-touring Guide</a> with whom we had the pleasure to go skiing already in the past.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225601117/in/dateposted/" title="Start of the tour."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4770/25225601117_d228306e86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Start of the tour." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225604887/in/dateposted/" title="And what a view again!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4724/25225604887_f11df71d25_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And what a view again!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Albert had two other clients along and our little group was great, we had a lot of fun on the ascent and descent. It was a beautiful sunny day with great views - just the snow could have been a wee bit better.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225603587/in/dateposted/" title="Through the less-than-perfect snow down."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4761/25225603587_f2d6bb985b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Through the less-than-perfect snow down." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225603357/in/dateposted/" title="Albert showing how it&#x27;s done."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/25225603357_6a8f10e645_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert showing how it&#x27;s done." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The view from the Hotel wasn’t bad at all, either. We witnessed the #SuperBlueMoon rising behind the forest as we sat in the Sauna, not a bad place at all!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225606417/in/dateposted/" title="Timelapse."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4673/25225606417_0a106ea3e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Timelapse." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next day we hot the slopes. With a big ski resort right in front of the hotel it was not a long approach, and the skiing was good - though I really prefer soft snow on wild mountains. A good thing that a 80 cm dump of powder was forecast for the next day!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225605937/in/dateposted/" title="Snow? Yeps."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4760/25225605937_fa563906a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow? Yeps." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225610547/in/dateposted/" title="Germknödel, still a favourite meal of mine."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4614/25225610547_fa07863ea4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Germknödel, still a favourite meal of mine." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And so my brother and me headed again to the secluded Thomatal Valley and started from the Dr. Josef-Mehrl Hütte up into the mountains, not to be disappointed by the amount of snow.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225609357/in/dateposted/" title="The fantastic Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4666/25225609357_ef4df5c352_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The fantastic Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Stay tuned for the full trip-report in the next few weeks! In the meanwhile you already can take a look some more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157663383796697">Flickr Album</a> and on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Family Skiing in Vuokatti]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/skiing-in-vuokatti.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-22T19:37:57+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/skiing-in-vuokatti</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love winter, skiing and my family. So naturally the best thing is to combine all these things into one week of family fun and head to Vuokatti!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27053282929/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="Vuokatti Ski Slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4542/27053282929_903586e363_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Vuokatti Ski Slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Visit Vuokatti who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="off-to-vuokatti">Off to Vuokatti</h2>

<p>For the third time in a row - after a visit to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">Pyhä</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html">Hetta</a> in the previous years - we packed our winter gear, warm socks and skis and travelled North to experience a proper Finnish winter. Though while in the years before we travelled really far we didn’t want to put that stress on us and our kids of then 1 and 5 years, so after some research we found out about Vuokatti, one of the most snow-secure ski resorts in what we still consider Southern Finland (technically it’s probably the South of Lapland, but lets just say it ain’t as far North as Ylläs, Hetta and Saariselkä). To Vuokatti from Vaasa it are only 400 km which you can drive in a day with some proper planning and keeping the kids entertained, which made it the perfect destination for us. Vuokatti actually is also very easy reached by train and bus, and with many accommodation options being within walking distance of the slopes you can also get around without a car.</p>

<p>Vuokatti is a fantastic destinations for families that want to ski together but don’t want to sit 12 or more hours in the car to get far up North. The <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/Vuokatti-Slopes">13 slopes in Vuokatti</a> are wide &amp; easy, there’s a Fun park with a Halfpipe and some nice big kickers, a Snowboard Tunnel and of course you can rent all the equipment right there so don’t need to travel there with all the gear along. Here’s the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/loader.aspx?id=e3625da0-e490-45b2-a45f-508558f77279">slope map</a> to give you an idea; what I missed is some <em>Lähi offarit</em> - lift-accessible backcountry runs through the forests, but that’s really just a case of getting rid of some trees to make that possible 😜!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39836691081/in/dateposted/" title="Sunny Vuokatti slopes!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4675/39836691081_d8917ae008_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunny Vuokatti slopes!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="lets-go-skiing">Lets go skiing!</h2>

<p>Did I mention that I love skiing? Ah yeah, right there at the beginning 😄. Well, my son learned to ski at age 4 in Levi and enjoyed a short refresher with one of the wonderful ski teachers at the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/Vuokatti-Slopes/Vuokatti-Ski-School">Vuokatti Ski School</a> and then hit the slopes on his own. We decided to not push him and let him go at his own speed, which we found was the right way for us because so he gradually wanted to try bigger &amp; bigger slopes and became more confident skiing them. It’s just beautiful to see your child share the same love for an activity you have yourself, and we are very blessed that our kids love to be outdoors and active as much as we.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804532442/in/dateposted/" title="Vuokatti Slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4677/39804532442_8567e515cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Vuokatti Slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It also was the first time for my wife to stand on Downhill skis, and she too enjoyed the great teaching of the Vuokatti Ski School - which is the 2nd Oldest Ski School in Finland! After a couple of days of being taught the principles of skiing she was skiing down the hills on her own, getting more and more confident and loving the experience. The best thing probably was after that week that she told me <em>“I now understand why you love skiing so much!”</em>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127039344/in/dateposted/" title="Ski School 001"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4651/39127039344_9471592108_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski School 001" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25963527478/in/dateposted/" title="Ski School 004"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4661/25963527478_d85395b83b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski School 004" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057808909/in/dateposted/" title="Ski Sirkus"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/28057808909_16189acf99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Sirkus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057800749/in/dateposted/" title="Ski Carousel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4671/28057800749_f25c3c402a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Carousel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And while there were some really small kids skiing we shared the parenting of our one-year old daughter, and I was taking care of her in the morning while my son &amp; wife were skiing, and then when it was lunch time we ate a small snack at the slopes before the rest of the family went home for naps, playing Lego and relaxing I went skiing. The slopes were for me quite a good training, it was after all only the 2nd season that I stood again on skis after a break of around 16 years! Skiing in a resort is excellent for that, ingraining these movements into ones body and mind. I usually started on one side of the resort and then skied every slope till I reached the other side, where I could step out of the skis and walk with the skis on my shoulder in ten minutes back to our accommodation at the Vuokatti Suites. There’s three main lifts which all bring you all up the slope, with some shorter connecting lifts which help you to get from one end to the other one. <a href="http://www.movescount.com/moves/move148262268">This is how a usual day on the slopes looked</a> according to my Suunto Spartan Ultra.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38937896925/in/dateposted/" title="First down!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4610/38937896925_49699d7595_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="First down!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127057454/in/dateposted/" title="Skiing with my son"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4758/39127057454_b7cc181cac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skiing with my son" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="kids-love-vuokatti">Kids Love Vuokatti!</h2>

<p>After skiing in the mornings we enjoyed family activities in the afternoons, it’s how we roll and really like it. The highlight of the trip for our son was most definitely at the Angry Birds themed <a href="https://superpark.fi/park/vuokatti/">SuperPark Vuokatti</a>, it’s a memory he looks with a smile back to and he regularly comes up to me and says <em>“Dad, we need to go back to the Angry Birds Park, it was so fun!”</em>. It’s memories like these that makes travelling with the family so beautiful, I myself have these kinds of memories of travelling with my parents and siblings, and it just gives kids so much more than some tangible thing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127083144/in/dateposted/" title="Welcome to Angry Birds Park Vuokatti!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4751/39127083144_60eb74128e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Welcome to Angry Birds Park Vuokatti!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127074864/in/dateposted/" title="Slides are fun!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4669/39127074864_ede59200f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slides are fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057824409/in/dateposted/" title="Red!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/28057824409_110ee0b823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Red!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38937888245/in/dateposted/" title="Trying bikes at Angry Birds Park Vuokatti"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/38937888245_47a700a3f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trying bikes at Angry Birds Park Vuokatti" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On another day we went to play bowling at <a href="http://www.vuokattibowling.fi/">Vuokatti Bowling</a>, which is again a memory our son recalls with joy - actually just this morning he told us the scores from our visit at Vuokatti Bowling (Him: 148, my wife: 120, me: 84 😄). The bowling alley in Vuokatti was also really child-friendly, they had a playing room for kids which had large windows which allowed our daughter to play inside but always see us. The staff was friendly and helped me figure out the “complicated” bowling computer (you’d think I’d know these things being a geek!), and the best thing is that the bowling allies are child-friendly as when our son bowled rails went up which prevented the bowling ball going into the gutter. All in all this was a great experience and we might just need to have a visit to a bowling alley with the kids again soon!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804546062/in/dateposted/" title="Vuokatti Bowling"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4718/39804546062_52189d6587_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vuokatti Bowling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then we went one afternoon to the Spa and swimming pools at the <a href="https://www.holidayclubresorts.com/fi/kohteet/katinkulta/kylpyla-ja-hoidot/">Holiday Club Katinkulta</a>. Going to the Spa with the kids is all about sharing the time of who watches the kids when, so that both parents can go in piece to the Sauna, Jacuzzi or swimming. Happily our kids love water and there was both a small kids pool and a slide, which made watching the kids easy &amp; fun. So while one of us was relaxing the other one was taking care of the kids, and after a while we high-fived and switched!</p>

<p>But this isn’t everything! We enjoyed some afternoons just exploring Vuokatti on foot (you can for example drive up the slopes from the other side and walk to the Café on the top!) and walking on the frozen lake in front of the hotel and watching the sunset. You also can go on a <a href="http://www.vuokattisafaris.com/en/tour/husky-safaris/">Husky Safari</a> in Vuokatti, enjoy the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/All-year-round/Skiing">massive XC skiing tracks</a> or check out the Vuokatti Ski tunnel. There’s definitely more than enough options for none-skiing activities in Vuokatti, so just have a look at <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/In-winter">what is possible</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127093244/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking in Vuokatti"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4604/39127093244_7125a940c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking in Vuokatti" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804531052/in/dateposted/" title="Ripa&#x27;s Slope Café"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4712/39804531052_91ac5f6820_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ripa&#x27;s Slope Café" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hungry-heres-where-to-eat-in-vuokatti">Hungry? Here’s where to eat in Vuokatti!</h2>

<p>We loved the breakfast at Vuokatti Suites where we stayed (it was hands-down the best breakfast I have eaten at any Hotel) but we were lucky enough to not needing to cook in the evenings as we went to eat out. Vuokatti gathers to many different tastes, from high-class Menus like we enjoyed at <a href="https://www.sokoshotels.fi/en/vuokatti/sokos-hotel-vuokatti/meetings-and-events/meeting-room?id=466583_392858">Restaurant Kippo</a> and really good and tasty food at <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Services/Vuokatti/Restaurants">À la Katti</a> and <a href="https://vuokattisport.fi/en/ravintolapalvelut/">O’las Restaurant</a> to more basic but good food at <a href="https://olearys.fi/holiday-club-katinkulta/">O’Learys</a>, <a href="https://www.ravintolamessi.fi">Ravintola Messi</a> and <a href="https://www.raflaamo.fi/en/sotkamo/amarillo-vuokatti">Amarillo</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804549022/in/dateposted/" title="Restaurant Kippo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4720/39804549022_1db02d4a9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Restaurant Kippo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804547392/in/dateposted/" title="Starter at Kippo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4667/39804547392_d55553a89c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Starter at Kippo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804528872/in/dateposted/" title="Amarillo Menu"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4745/39804528872_bd92bd9f99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Amarillo Menu" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="would-we-go-again">Would we go again?</h2>

<p>We loved our stay in Vuokatti, and so did the kids. The memories we made as a family are more worth to us than a car, TV or other tangible goods - we try to raise our kids and show them that you spending time with the ones you love is the best use of money &amp; time. It’s thus no surprise that family holidays are high on our list, and a perfect family vacation like we experienced in Vuokatti gives you memories for a lifetime. The small town just had it all: Great slopes for beginner skiers, fun and versatile activities for the afternoons, comfortable accommodation and tasty food. Add in that the people we met in Vuokatti - from the Ski instructors over the Café and Restaurant Staff to everyone else - was super-friendly and great with kids! So to answer the question in the heading: YES! We totally would go again to Vuokatti, and when our daughter is four or five we might need to return so she can learn to ski!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39836691701/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="Learning to love skiing!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4649/39836691701_9f7c2691cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to love skiing!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p>As always, you can find more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157689199140311">Vuokatti Flickr Album</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-stay">Where to stay</h2>

<p>We stayed at <a href="http://www.hotellivuokatti.fi/en/suites">Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites</a> and had a gorgeous Suite with lots of space for us four. Our son had his own room and our daughter slept with us in the big bed, which meant in the evenings we parents could have a glass of wine on the comfortable Sofa and watch a movie on TV (which we can’t do at home as we don’t own a TV!). There was a fully-equipped kitchen in which we prepared our afternoon coffee and evening snacks for the kids, and we had our own Sauna in the Suite which was used almost every evening. The Suite had a drying cabinet which we used to dry moist ski boots, gloves and hats, and the view from the balcony over the lake was beautiful. And if the room was an indication for the whole operation, the breakfast we enjoyed each morning at the main Hotel building was just the best ever. Kids can be tricky with new foods, but at Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites they served everything we’d have at home plus some. The delicious fried eggs, Karelian pastries and lots of <em>fresh</em> fruit made for a good start into a new day, and the coffee was good, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057804579/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Living Room"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4703/28057804579_fa56016097_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Living Room" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057805089/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Own Sauna"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4714/28057805089_8849bb91ae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Own Sauna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804540312/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Ski Storage"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4660/39804540312_53040f1343_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Ski Storage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804533732/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites from the top!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4749/39804533732_2c9760f298_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites from the top!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-there">How to get there</h2>

<p>As I said, you can travel by train &amp; bus to Vuokatti and stay close to the slopes and use the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/loader.aspx?id=643138b3-51fb-405a-a15f-d9e7cee95549">free Vuokatti SkiBus</a> so that a car is not needed. That being said, a (rental) car does make things a bit easier if you come with two kids and ski gear or want to eat in the town in the evenings. From Vaasa it is a 400 km drive to Vuokatti, which takes with breaks in winter around six hours. You also can <a href="https://www.finnair.com/fi/gb/offers?OFFER_ID=62287">fly with Finnair to Kajanni</a> via Helsinki and take the <a href="http://www.akyllonen.fi/airbus/?lang=en">Airport shuttle bus</a> and then use the aforementioned free SkiBus around town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38798598622/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="In the middle, a river"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4538/38798598622_90929ef9cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="In the middle, a river" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Autumn Backpacking in the Dolomites]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/10/autumn-backpacking-in-the-dolomites.html"/>
    <updated>2016-10-18T23:30:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/10/autumn-backpacking-in-the-dolomites</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Impressions from a six day backpacking trip into the Sextner Dolomites in South Tyrol.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30287292142/in/dateposted/" title="Into the Fanes-Sennes-Prags Nature Park"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7771/30287292142_62106525cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Into the Fanes-Sennes-Prags Nature Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Weather. It can change - in a matter of minutes. Thus experienced on my last backpacking trip into the Tre Cime and Fanes-Sennes-Prags Nature Parks. What should have been a warm autumn hike in a great surrounding turned out to be an early winter/ autumn hike in an even prettier surrounding, just a tad colder as expected. Good thing we had enough warm clothes with us, some fine Whiskey from Scotland and plenty of good mood. This is just a teaser, a detailed trip report should follow in the next three weeks or so. Here’s a few photos to make you curious for the full article =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30403910045/in/dateposted/" title="Things start out sunny"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5762/30403910045_e2080693d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Things start out sunny" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30317862781/in/dateposted/" title="Then turn to cloudy"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5673/30317862781_4138a8feaa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Then turn to cloudy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30403910445/in/dateposted/" title="Until you stand in the clouds at the summit"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5708/30403910445_a4f40a09ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Until you stand in the clouds at the summit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Day one went from sunny and warm to white-out. Good thing we found an open winter room!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30287291392/in/dateposted/" title="Descent through snowy switchbacks"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8127/30287291392_1bd6230774_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Descent through snowy switchbacks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30287286302/in/dateposted/" title="Along the river to the valley"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8277/30287286302_b73ac2e551_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Along the river to the valley" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Day two was snow, snow, going down and rain.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30317861721/in/dateposted/" title="La Sportiva TX2"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8550/30317861721_e7048769ff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="La Sportiva TX2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the third day we again had rain, snow and then some spectacular sunshine on the way up through an enchanted forest. Sublime.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30287286992/in/dateposted/" title="Camp on the fourth morning"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5680/30287286992_aeb90feb6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Camp on the fourth morning" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30317857621/in/dateposted/" title="Hello there cloudy sky!"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8597/30317857621_5fcabbdd7d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hello there cloudy sky!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the fourth day we visited the gorgeous Rossalm where I had some tasty Kaiserschmarrn before setting off into the cold hail &amp; snow again.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30317858291/in/dateposted/" title="Dinner!"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8271/30317858291_7810df26a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dinner!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Dinner was always something to look forward too, and that Curry Chicken from Real Turmat was so good, we could have eaten two (or three)!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30404195455/in/dateposted/" title="Where does the trail lead?"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5544/30404195455_b2ca9ae254_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Where does the trail lead?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And as most trips, also this adventure needed to end some day.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ar2UYIDe6oU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>I thank Südtirol for the invitation to their region. They helped with getting there but as always this does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2016: Six months in]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/07/2016-six-months-in.html"/>
    <updated>2016-07-04T23:46:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/07/2016-six-months-in</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2016 is six months old, time to reflect on the past outdoor months and reveal what lays ahead!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27976948552/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking towards the sunset"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7417/27976948552_cefcfdeaf0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking towards the sunset" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="january">January</h2>

<p>In January I was again on <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/aland-in-winter.html">Åland</a>, this time as a Hostblogger with NBE Finland. It was a superb trip and I loved showing our beautiful country to my fellow blogger friends.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24766179696/in/album-72157663594014166/" title="Bloggers at work"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/2/1514/24766179696_3ccdf7c9fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bloggers at work" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24699056571/in/album-72157663594014166/" title="Kick!"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/2/1461/24699056571_3f05252121_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kick!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="february">February</h2>

<p>In February I went <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/ski-touring-south-tyrol-and-salzburger-lungau.html">ski-touring in South Tyrol</a> with my brother, and then we continued to Austria and the Salzburger Lungau. It was a great trip with some good, and some not so good snow.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/24460363514/in/album-72157664166747400/" title="I love me a nice cabin!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1466/24460363514_7edaab5590_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I love me a nice cabin!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I love cabins! And my DPS Skis like them too =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25736343534/in/album-72157664672954972/" title="Albert ripping it!"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1584/25736343534_f07a20c1bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert ripping it!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Our ski guide Albert traded his ski school to backcountry touring. With views like this, who wouldn’t?</p>

<h2 id="march">March</h2>

<p>March started off in Switzerland, where my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/03/teaser-graubunden-haute-route.html">Graubünden Haute-Route Tour</a> didn’t go according to plan. But we had a great time nevertheless, and that’s what counts.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25455047716/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Going down."><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/2/1445/25455047716_5a5b16aa20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Going down." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>March was also the month of skiing and winter activities with the family. First we were in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html">Hetta</a> and had a lot of fun with Huskies, XC skiing and winter hiking, followed by a few nights in Ylläs and then Levi.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148429495/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/2/1490/26148429495_885653ee53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A husky Tour in Hetta is a must in our opinion. It’s so relaxing and fun!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25333253494/in/album-72157665518007610/" title="Powder turns on Kesänki"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1649/25333253494_d679a86349_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Powder turns on Kesänki" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>While Ylläs is known as the XC Ski Mekka of Finland I loved the ski-touring, too. Imagine finding perfect snow and you can make the first turns!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28044201296/in/dateposted/" title="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7797/28044201296_a750b77c3b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Santa&#x27;s Cabin in Levi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Santa’s Cabin on Levi is a wee bit off-piste and was built for the Finnish Santa movie from a few years back. It’s a beautiful cabin with a great view.</p>

<h2 id="april">April</h2>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/lyngen.html">Lyngen</a> with Henryk scores high as the most memorable ski-touring trip of the year.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25455047716/in/album-72157665020355632/" title="Going down."><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/2/1445/25455047716_5a5b16aa20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Going down." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With sunsets like these it is easy to understand why Northern Norway is a photographers paradise, and equally popular amongst climbers &amp; skiers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148754883/in/album-72157665452784994/" title="What a view!"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/2/1694/26148754883_8441890563_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="What a view!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And also the skiing is pretty awesome, as Henryk here shows.</p>

<h2 id="may">May</h2>

<p>In may I was on the AdventureNEXT Conference in Macedonia, and went afterwards to Meteora in Greece. The Balkans are a gorgeous region with untapped potential for hiking, climbing, packrafting, bikepacking and will enchant you with the lovely people, tasty food and the pristine mountains and nature.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26965428300/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Climbing"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7295/26965428300_4a48114bb5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Climbing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The climbing in Macedonia was great, and I am looking forward to sample more of it in the future.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26505575123/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Hiking in Meteora"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7060/26505575123_422cb17f12_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Hiking in Meteora" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The same I can say about Meteora in Greece. What an outstandingly beautiful place!</p>

<h2 id="june">June</h2>

<p>In June we went on summer holidays with the family to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/impressions-from-the-bregenzerwald-in-vorarlberg-austria.html">Vorarlberg</a> in Austria.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27700551721/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Sunrise on the Kanisfluh"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7180/27700551721_12abb83624_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunrise on the Kanisfluh" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That one morning where the sun shone, everything came together on the sunrise hike on the Kanisfluh.</p>

<h2 id="onwards">Onwards</h2>

<p>The next six months look pretty good too. Next week I am off to my annual <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/outdoorfn-2016-is-a-go.html">OutDoor pilgrimage</a>, then it is likely to Ireland and Wales, a visit to the south in November, dozens of research trips in Finland and in December I hope to be hunting some snow again. So, <strong>how has your outdoor year been thus far?</strong> What was the most memorable trip, and which trip in the second half of 2016 are you most looking forward to! <strong>Let us know in the comments!</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hetta: Winter Adventures in Finnish Lapland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-04T23:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friendly, calm and lots to do: Hetta in Finnish Lapland is an ideal place if you want to enjoy winter holidays without hustle &amp; bustle. <em>A Winter Trip Report.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26057151772/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Pyhäkero in blue &amp; white 2"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1528/26057151772_de1f89e375_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pyhäkero in blue &amp; white 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="hetta">Hetta</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi">Hetta</a> is in the far, far north of Finland and that means: Lots of snow, crispy cold temperatures, Northern Lights and beautiful sunny days in spring. Last year we spent our winter holiday in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">Pyhä</a> and this year we decided to visit another small and family-friendly town: Hetta. Right in the heart of Lapland it is located at the top of the <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/pallas-yllastunturinp">Pallas-Yllästunturi National Park</a> and the starting point of the <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/hettapallashikingtrail">Hetta-Pallas Trail</a> which you can ski in winter or hike in the summer. <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/poyrisjarvi">Pöyrisjärvi Wilderness Area</a> and <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/tarvantovaara">Tarvantovaara Wilderness Area</a> are right around the corner, and it isn’t far to Norway, either - which makes it an ideal base camp for outdoor and nature lovers in summer &amp; winter.</p>

<p>It has all that a winter enthusiast needs: Cafés &amp; <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/services/restaurants/">Restaurants</a>, various <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/accommodation/">accommodation options</a>, a supermarket and various other shops, the <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/felllaplandvisitorcentre">Fell Lapland Visitor Centre</a> and lots of stuff to do, from skiing on the local hill to enjoying the silence on a Husky Sled ride. With six days in Hetta we had plenty of time to try various <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/things-to-do/winter/">activities</a> and experience what the town has to offer.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546943983/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Sunshine!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1646/25546943983_f5b7a882b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunshine!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outside-with-hetta-huskies">Outside with Hetta Huskies</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.hettahuskies.com/en">Hetta Huskies</a> are probably one of the most well-known companies from Hetta, and if you meet the dogs, owners and Guides it is clear why: The dogs are lovely and will make your trip unforgettable, while the owners Pasi &amp; Anna with their friendly, international staff of Guides will ensure you have a great experience - be it just a few hours or a week!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26122490546/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Hetta Huskies"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1550/26122490546_2d432ac709_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hetta Huskies" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We were with the whole family - my four year old son, baby, wife and me - on the <a href="http://www.hettahuskies.com/en/activities/single-day-safaris">Silent Landscapes</a> Safari, in which you get a tour of the Farm, meet the dogs, get instructed on how to ride the sleigh and then are off into the winter wonderland for around 45 minutes. It’s was a great and interesting experience that we all enjoyed, especially our son thought it was a lot of fun (the baby slept!). We were accompanied by a guide who stayed mostly away but helped when the need arose - we had a small change in the configuration of dogs, for example. After I got instructed in riding the sleigh the family sat down and then we were off to the mires. I always love to explore swamps in winter, their vast area and wide views are beautiful to behold and in winter you can explore them without mosquitos and wet feet. We could see the distant fjells of the National Park, rode through the forest and loved the silence of nature. We could have gone much longer - and the dogs, too! - but after 45 minutes we were back at the farm where we helped bringing the dogs back to their compounds and said thanks for their great service!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25545774183/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Hi there!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1624/25545774183_6423523d01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hi there!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148429495/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1490/26148429495_885653ee53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25875556930/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Through the forest"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1490/25875556930_ccd9bde31b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Through the forest" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25875557260/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Hi there again!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1646/25875557260_aa5aa4d111_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hi there again!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="a-visit-to-the-hetta-snow-castle">A visit to the Hetta Snow Castle</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nakkala.com">Näkkälä Eräpalvelut</a> offers visits to their Snow Castle which is a short 20 minute snowmobile ride over the frozen lake away from Hetta. The castle is open from the end of November and still stands there in the end of June and with walls several meters thick that’s no surprise! The kids loved it and it is easy to understand why they were fascinated by the ice castle: Consisting of three domed rooms they were adorned with ice sculptures, an ice bar and tables as well as a frozen bed! You can sleep in the ice castle, too! After exploring the snow castle for a while we had hot juice and then it was again back to Hetta in the sleigh. A great activity for the morning or afternoon after which you might find yourself again outside trying to build your own snow igloo!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26082084491/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Entering the Hetta Ice Castle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1588/26082084491_3c4f638e8e_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Entering the Hetta Ice Castle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26082084791/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="At the Bar in the Hetta Ice Castle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1466/26082084791_1836e001fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the Bar in the Hetta Ice Castle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25543654324/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Cold as ice!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1512/25543654324_9b04cb2c86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cold as ice!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26082086091/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="The Hetta Ice Castle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1539/26082086091_c298c5a23f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Hetta Ice Castle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25875554680/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Back to Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1566/25875554680_fbdf050119_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back to Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="skiing-at-hetta-hiihtomaa">Skiing at Hetta Hiihtomaa</h2>

<p>If you <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">follow me on Instagram</a> you probably have realized that I have been ski-touring a lot this winter. <a href="http://www.hettahiihtomaa.fi">Hetta Hiihtomaa</a> is the local skiing hill and we took the chance for our son to learn a bit of skiing and I too took a ride in the lift up to go down through the snow-covered forest. The service at Hetta Hiihtomaa was superb, the two Gentlemen were super-friendly and helpful with <a href="http://www.hettahiihtomaa.fi/p/valinevuokraus.html">loaning the gear</a> and sharing local knowledge. Besides the lift and ski-rental there’s also a Café, a big sledding hill and a illuminated XC Loipe. The prizes are very affordable when compared to the large ski areas, and the people and kids all had a lot of fun on the slopes or off-piste. Hetta Hiihtomaa has also a small beginner’s hill which is excellent for learning to ski, and I can totally recommend the sledding hill, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25486428803/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Learning to ski at Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1654/25486428803_d47754d6f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to ski at Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25816133670/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Backcountry fun on Jyppyrä, Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1675/25816133670_564e5094cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Backcountry fun on Jyppyrä, Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26022665581/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Sledding fun at Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1526/26022665581_f882f141b8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Sledding fun at Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="ski-touring-into-the-white--out-at-nkklvaara">Ski-touring into the White (-Out) at Näkkälävaara</h2>

<p>What I like more than skiing at a resort is going into the backcountry, and I was fortunate enough to go out for a morning with Riikka from <a href="http://www.wildriver.fi">Wild River Nature Adventures</a>. We decided it’d be a good idea to go to Näkkälä, a tiny village some 30 minutes from Hetta, where we’d tour up to the local fjell, Näkkälävaara. It’s an easy tour with a really cool descent through a birch forest and I had a huge smile on my face after the cool run down!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546895203/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Yay!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1464/25546895203_30c25d623d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yay!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25544790224/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Snowhare vs Skis"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1593/25544790224_06566ed3f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowhare vs Skis" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546918523/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Never trust the weather forecast"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1605/25546918523_63fb03b0c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Never trust the weather forecast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We started next to one of the few houses and then toured over a narrow lake to the foot of the fjell. It was a cold day and a mist was hanging in the air, which would before long engulf us as we started the climb up the hill. The visibility was soon just a couple dozen metre, and first as we were starting the descent the weather cleared a bit to give a few views price. Nevertheless it was beautiful to tour through the white landscape, with trees hidden under thick covers of snow &amp; ice, arctic hare tracks running across the hill and the wind being the only sound wide &amp; far. At the summit we waited for half an hour for the weather to clear, as you could see till Pyhäkero to the south and the mountains in Norway to the north, as well as the large Pöyrisjärvi lake. Alas, they stayed all hidden!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546929473/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Winter birch forest"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1520/25546929473_13dc3a1b94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Winter birch forest" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26057122202/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Fun, fun, fun!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1564/26057122202_1e546f6369_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Fun, fun, fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the superb descent we skied along the lake, past the rental cabins of <a href="http://www.nakkala.com/kampat/">Näkkälä Eräpalvelut</a> and to a sacred rock of the Sami, which showed ancient reindeer paintings. Too soon we were back at the car and on our way back to Hetta, where we encountered many reindeer next to the road - and the sun also came out! There’s plenty of great ski-touring around Hetta, from the majestic Pyhäkero to smaller fjells in the area. Grab a map and go out explore!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26083255541/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Drawings"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1601/26083255541_e5e4bc0b53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Drawings" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26123653876/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Reindeers"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1482/26123653876_3da37f61cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reindeers" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="tasty-lappish-food">Tasty Lappish food</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.hetan-majatalo.fi/en">Hotel Hetan Majatalo</a> has every Friday a Lappish Buffet which is super-tasty. Reindeer, salmon, mashed potatoes and a tasty dessert along with a great home-brewed beer it is something you should treat yourself to.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26205517916/in/dateposted/" title="Lappish Buffet at Hetan Majatalo"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1535/26205517916_286bf7a114_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lappish Buffet at Hetan Majatalo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25626691604/in/dateposted/" title="Dessert at Hetan Majatalo"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1460/25626691604_e84413b6a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dessert at Hetan Majatalo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Also the buffet at the Lapland Hotel Hetta was very tasty, with a wide variety of salads for startes, wish and meat mains and several sweet desserts. Add in a good selection of wines and beers with great service and you have a great evening!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26063083516/in/dateposted/" title="Salad buffet at Lapland Hotel Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1497/26063083516_065d21ef59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salad buffet at Lapland Hotel Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484255534/in/photostream/" title="Main course at Lapland Hotel Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1609/25484255534_00e25051e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Main course at Lapland Hotel Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="enjoying-the-silence-of-xc-skiing">Enjoying the silence of XC skiing</h2>

<p>As we stayed in a cottage next to the lake and there’s around 100 km of skiing tracks (here’s the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/wp-content/uploads/Hetan-alueen-latukartta.pdf">map</a>) going XC skiing is something that you can do any time of the day - even at night, as there’s illuminated tracks, too! I took my son in a Pulka for a few hours of skiing along, which is a great way to be outdoors. XC skiing is relatively easy, you go at a low speed and thus still can experience the nature around you but it’s fast enough to feel good after a few hours outside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26165151521/in/dateposted/" title="XC Skiing with kids"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1570/26165151521_0a3b0f0504_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="XC Skiing with kids" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25628771613/in/dateposted/" title="Skiing to Hetta across the lake"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1493/25628771613_48dbeaf9c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skiing to Hetta across the lake" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="learning-about-sami-culture-at-the-fell-lapland-visitor-centre">Learning about Sami Culture at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre</h2>

<p>If the weather is so bad that you don’t want to be outside, head to the wonderful <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/felllaplandvisitorcentre">Fell Lapland Visitor Centre</a>. It’s open every day of the week, has also a Café with tasty cakes and pastries and the exhibitions are free of charge - hence an ideal way to spend an afternoon. There’s even a very nice children’s corner which our son enjoyed playing at! The main exhibition shows the eight seasons of the Sámi and how their life has changed over the time. To take it all in a couple of hours would be needed I reckon, though it is easy to spend even more time there to also explore the small library and the two other exhibitions.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25996473812/in/dateposted/" title="Tunturi-Lappi Luontokeskus"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1709/25996473812_9c603c6ec6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tunturi-Lappi Luontokeskus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26089003635/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1704/26089003635_69d533bf44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484241564/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 2"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1540/25484241564_7906a223df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484242434/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 3"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1552/25484242434_6eaf72deff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26063074576/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 7"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1624/26063074576_635461a3cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 7" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="more-things-to-see--do">More things to see &amp; do</h2>

<p>Hetta has many other things to offer, from festivals like the Nordic Ice &amp; Snow Sculpture competition at the end of February over regular Nature evenings in the Museum to the <a href="http://saamiskirace.fi">Saami Ski Race</a> in April. You can view the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/events/">events</a> here. There’s also two silver smiths in Hetta which are worth checking out and a church which is architecturally interesting. It’s not far to Kilpisjärvi, either, or you could go for a day trip over to Alta in Norway. If you’re looking for a few days in nature you could ski from Pallas to Hetta through the fjells (or vice versa) and you even can ski onwards to Näkkälä.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25816138370/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Swan snow sculpture in Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1582/25816138370_0439531fd8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Swan snow sculpture in Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p>More photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157665518007630">Hetta Photo Album</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Where to stay?</strong></p>

<p>We stayed at the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/ounistieva-en/">Ounistieva Cottage</a> which is a nice cottage a bit out of town right next to the lake. It’s a self-service cottage with a nice wood-heated sauna, a warm wood stove and you can go XC skiing from the doorstep, which is awesome. Cottages are great for families as you can be as loud as you want, the kids can play safely outside in the snow and there’s plenty of space inside. If you prefer something more central then we can recommend the <a href="http://www.hetan-majatalo.fi">Hotel Hetan Majatalo</a> and the <a href="https://www.laplandhotels.com/EN/hotels-in-lapland/hetta/lapland-hotel-hetta.html">Lapland Hotel Hetta</a> which are close to the centre of town and also have their own Restaurants with great food. Their rooms, especially in the Hetan Majatalo, are very cozy and it’s nice to have breakfast &amp; dinner served each evening. There’s several more <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/accommodation/">accommodation options in Hetta</a> for every budget, so have a look around and find what suits you!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26205520136/in/dateposted/" title="Ounistieva Cottage"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1617/26205520136_1638186cfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ounistieva Cottage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How to get there?</strong></p>

<p>We travelled with a combination of <a href="https://www.vr.fi/cs/vr/fi/etusivu">train</a> and <a href="https://www.sixt.fi">car</a> instead of driving all the way up north, with a night in Rovaniemi on the way up and down - if you have small kids it is more comfortable this way, for everyone really. In the train the kids can play, nap and go easily to the toilet, and the ride from Rovaniemi to Hetta takes only around four hours by car - much better than the 12+ hours of driving it would take from Vaasa! And if you come from abroad - just fly straight to <a href="https://www.finavia.fi/en/enontekio/">Enontekiö Airport</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26063067296/in/dateposted/" title="Rush-hour in Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1467/26063067296_97c0b28cc2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rush-hour in Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: Thanks to the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi">Enontekiö Region</a> who invited us up north. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
