<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: kids | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/kids/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2022-10-03T13:17:40+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[woom OFF AIR Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/07/woom-off-off-review.html"/>
    <updated>2021-07-22T09:26:39+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/07/woom-off-off-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After many years of riding very happily on his <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/woom-bikes/">woom Bikes</a> it was once again to size up to the next one - but this time we decided to for the woom OFF AIR as it will allow us to go explore the local Mountain Bike trails! It of course also works great for riding to school and to the beach, as we have seen during the past three months, but it really shines on trails!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327790178/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 in its natural habitat"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327790178_7dcd01ab76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 in its natural habitat" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>The woom Bike was provided for free to us for this review. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>The <a href="https://woom.com/de_DE/fahrraeder/off-air-6">woom AIR OFF 6</a> is my son’s third woom Bike in four years - we started with the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">woom 4</a> in 2018, a great bike which our smallest is starting to ride now. In 2019 we got the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/07/woom-bikes-because-also-kids-deserve-great-bikes.html">woom 5</a> which he rode very happily in all seasons for nearly two years, before now in 2021 getting the woom OFF AIR 6. The numbers in Sizing of the woom Bikes is brilliant, it makes it very easy to know which bike to get next - and the Bikes themselves also grow nicely with the kids, and often can be used over a year or two as you can adjust the seat and handlebar. That just as a side note - now onwards to the woom OFF AIR 6.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51326855692/in/dateposted/" title="Downhill with the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51326855692_e19283d706_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Downhill with the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The first question probably is: Why the woom OFF AIR 6 and not a regular <a href="https://woom.com/de_DE/fahrraeder/woom-6">woom 6</a> or the <a href="https://woom.com/en_INT/bikes/off-6">woom OFF</a>? The answer is easy: The woom OFF AIR 6 gives us more possibilities. The possibility to go ride MTB Trails and some easier Downhill Trails - things the regular woom 6 also can do, but which are more comfortable, fun and safe with the woom OFF AIR. If you want your kids to go outdoors instead of sitting inside and playing video games all day, then good equipment is key in our experience. And getting the kids to want to go outside means they spend all that energy on something useful - in this case riding their bikes in nature - instead of fighting, nagging and other unproductive stuff. So, good gear gets the kids outside where they exhaust their power, and everyone in the family benefits 😊</p>

<p>The Specs of the OFF AIR are made for trail riding, with hydraulic disc brakes, an hydraulic air suspension fork with 80 mm travel, SRAM X5 gears and Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires for maximum grip on the trails. My son finds the woom saddles very comfortable and also long or rocky rides are no problem. Equally the handlebar grips are comfortable, with the brake and shifting levers in easy reach of smaller children hands. The bike also comes with flat pedals which is nice, so you don’t need to go hunt for some pedals when the bike arrives. Finally, the geometry of the bike is good for pedalling and not too aggressive, which means the bike also can be used for riding to school and the beach. You can check out the full specs on the woom website and be delighted about the high-quality components woom used on this kid’s bike - they are great!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327790363/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 backside"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327790363_8ce1ee8e68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 backside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327589981/in/dateposted/" title="Brakes on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327589981_0a2edcdf0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Brakes on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328581330/in/dateposted/" title="SRAM X5 Gears on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328581330_4bb6796112_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SRAM X5 Gears on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This being a woom bike obviously also means it is light, something which is SO IMPORTANT for a kids bike that I can not stress it enough. The woom OFF AIR 6 weighs just 11 kg as it is made from high-quality 6061 T6 aluminum (with butted and hydroformed tubes), which makes this a nimble bike on the trails and despite “only” nine gears my son was racing up the hills and it was a joy to watch - if you ever had your child complain about not wanting to ride an uphill, you know what I mean! On the downhill and the singletrack trails the bike reacts fast and gets through tight corners with ease - even if these corners are full of roots and rocks. And even without much training it was easy for my son to lift the fork over obstacles like trees on the trail, which is another benefit of the light build and the good geometry.</p>

<p>Something I liked was that the bike has high-quality 6 x 2.35″ Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires with the addition of the ADDIX SPEED rubber compound, which makes the tires more durable. It’s great to see woom giving their bikes high-quality tires instead of cutting corners and saving some €£$ and go with cheaper non-branded ones. These Schwalbe tires have a low rolling resistance and great grip on trails and gravel roads alike. The tires are high-volume which means they helps absorb some vibration and provide a plusher ride compared to skinnier tires. I didn’t really care for the Car-type valves for easy filling at any gas station, but happily our tire pump has an adapter for these so it’s just a small issue =) You probably have noticed on the photos that the woom OFF AIR has thru-axles on both the front and rear wheel. These provide superior stability in comparison to the quick-release skewers you’ll find on most kids bikes, and shows once more the bike’s trail credentials.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328580575/in/dateposted/" title="Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328580575_6522da691e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328580935/in/dateposted/" title="Top View of the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328580935_d091b96cb7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Top View of the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now the Suspension fork is made my RST, it is an AIR fork as the name suggests which means you’re easily able to adjust the pressure to the weight of your child. The Suspension fork works great (and also gets a lot of use, even on normal non-trail rides 😊), with the stanchions sliding effortlessly through the lowers with a super smooth feel, without any noticeable friction. The rebound is smooth, even with the lower pressure we put on it as our son is lightweight. The 80 mm of the AIR fork provide plenty of travel for most types of riding, and it has a lockout switch which is useful on longer climbs. Once I explained what it’s for and how to use it, it was also easy to operate by my son himself. If you feel your child doesn’t need a suspension fork - there’s the <a href="https://woom.com/en_INT/bikes/off-6">woom OFF</a> which comes with a rigid, light carbon fork and which is only 9,3 kg heavy in Size 6. It’s also cheaper than the AIR version, but otherwise nearly identical to the OFF AIR 6 in this review.</p>

<p>The handlebars on the woom OFF AIR 6 are 680 mm wide, which is a good size for our son. Sure, you could have a wider handlebar but he feels this is fine at the moment and does not need to be changed. In the beginning my son had some problems with the SRAM trigger shifter on the OFF AIR, as he was used to the grip-shifter found on his old woom bikes. After I explained how to use them (something you always should do, it’s too easy to think “<em>They will know!</em>” as an adult!) he is now easily shifting gears - though still sometimes forget on an uphill climb that he can shift in a lower gear 😆</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327590491/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327590491_2a09b25115_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327791083/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork Lock Switch"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327791083_5130204c03_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork Lock Switch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327590156/in/dateposted/" title="Suspension fork on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327590156_77d094afc7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Suspension fork on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327790878/in/dateposted/" title="Handlebars on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327790878_1a17220902_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Handlebars on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328581185/in/dateposted/" title="Brakes and SRAM Trigger Shifter on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328581185_da53bd1644_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Brakes and SRAM Trigger Shifter on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We have not rode on very technical trails (as in, very rocky and full of roots) yet, but on the “normal” trails here in Vaasa with a normal amount of roots and rocks the fork has absorb everything well. But it’s still a hard tail, so make sure your kid knows to have a good riding posture so it doesn’t get thrown around. I imagine my son should be fine to ride green and blue Trails in most Bike Parks with his woom OFF AIR 6, which means if you as a parent enjoy going to the Bike Park then with this Bike you can take your child along and don’t need to rent a bike!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327589291/in/dateposted/" title="Über STock &amp; Stein"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327589291_1b0e1f8d7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Über STock &amp; Stein" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328581430/in/dateposted/" title="Roll them planks!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328581430_e316cf547b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Roll them planks!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>In the end the <a href="https://woom.com/de_DE/fahrraeder/off-air-6">woom OFF AIR 6</a> is a great addition to our bike shed, and allows us to spend more time together in nature on our local trails. If your child is completely new to riding singletrack trails and easy downhill runs at the Bike Park, then this bike is a solid choice - also because with its light weight and child-friendly geometry it works well as a everyday bike for riding around town. But it’s obviously made for riding mountain bike trails, and that it does superbly - even with a beginner rider in the saddle. The suspension fork works great for our lightweight child, the hydraulic brakes make stopping a breeze, the SRAM X5 gears make climbing uphills fun and the Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires give the rider good grip and confidence on even the most loose surfaces. Overall we are very happy with the OFF AIR 6, and while we wish the bike would come with a quick-release seatpost collar to easier change the height of the seat, and internal cable routing, for more protection of the cables on trails, our son and us parents are very happy with this bike. I see us riding many trails in Finland and hopefully also Norway and Sweden in the future with this superb kid’s bike!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328580125/in/dateposted/" title="Going for the ramp!?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328580125_6694375297_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Going for the ramp!?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> (and you get great discount codes from partners - you could save 20% on your next purchase!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[woom Bikes - because also kids deserve great Bikes!]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/07/woom-bikes-because-also-kids-deserve-great-bikes.html"/>
    <updated>2019-07-31T14:03:31+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/07/woom-bikes-because-also-kids-deserve-great-bikes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How do you ensure that your child likes to ride its bike, come rain, sunshine or snow? In our opinion it’s by giving it a bike which it likes and which works well throughout the seasons!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421710247/in/photostream/" title="Speeding up on the woom 5"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421710247_34bc7ced8a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Speeding up on the woom 5" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>The woom Bike was provided for free to us for this review. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>That we are a family which ride their bikes year-round I <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">wrote earlier this year</a>, and now I want to shed a bit of light on the latest addition to our bike shed: The <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/5?ls=en">woom 5</a>. woom makes bikes exclusively for kids, and that you can see in their products: They are made for the needs of kids, and not just some fancy, miniaturised version of an adult bike. The woom bikes are light, safe for the rider and safe in traffic, and there’s a host of functional and pretty accessories available for the bike. That they do it for kids you can see for yourself when you have a woom bike in front of you, as around 85% of their bike parts are individually designed and produced exclusively for woom, customized to fit the needs of small anatomies.</p>

<p>Now we have owned several non-woom bikes for our kids before we made the switch, and I have done plenty of research on the topic, too. One thing you’ll read in review after review is that the lighter a kids bike is, the better it is for the child. From our own experience with some very cheap kids bikes which were heavy as two bags of cement we can confirm: The lighter the bike, the more fun the rider has. woom bikes are around 40% lighter than comparable kids bikes, so as an ultralight backpacker this is obvious very positive, too. But enough about facts and stats, lets dive in to our subjective observations of riding the bike for almost three months.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421564311/in/dateposted/" title="Riding is fun!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421564311_d2e930696c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Riding is fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421736537/in/dateposted/" title="At the Beach"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421736537_691a52b43b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="At the Beach" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now our son was already riding a woom 4 which he and we loved, but the one thing which became obvious as time went on was that the bike got too small for him. The <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/4?ls=en#section-product">woom 4</a> is made for kids between a height of 115 and 130 cm, though realistically I’d say that after 125 cm one should switch to the bigger bike. The woom 5 is made for kids between a height of 125 and 145 cm, and for our son it’s right now the perfect bike. Where in the past I had to say several times on a trip “Please cycle faster!” nowadays, since he’s on the woom 5, I have to ask him to slow down. He’s soooo fast on the new bike that he really likes to challenge us to races, and often enough wins! Thanks to the adjustable seat post and the vario stem the bike grows with him, and we hope that he’ll be able to ride this bike for a year or two (and that simply depends on how fast he grows!).</p>

<p>Going fast also means he needs to brake, and the the V-Brakes on the bike are so good that it takes little effort for him to stop safely. The SRAM X4 8-speed derailleur and the easy grip shift make switching gears easy as pie when we go up hills or ride into the wind, and the tires it comes with have a low rolling resistance and great grip from asphalt to single track trails and gravel roads. The Geometry also is great, because he can easily get on and off the bike and if he wants to stand on his feet, for example when taking in a view or waiting at a stop light, the top tube is at a friendly height.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421563356/in/dateposted/" title="Exploring"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421563356_53ecf3db20_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Exploring" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421564006/in/dateposted/" title="Should we stop for coffee and waffles?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421564006_82cd350310_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Should we stop for coffee and waffles?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421712272/in/dateposted/" title="Taking in the view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421712272_7780173572_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Taking in the view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Just a few words on assembling the bike before we wrap up this review. The bike is delivered in a 120 x 62 x 22 cm box and weighs around 10 kg (the bike itself is 8,2 kg light), and it comes with all the tools you need to assemble the bike. You can add a host of useful accessories to the bike, from the mandatory <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/schutzbleche?ls=en">Fenders</a> (which I yet have to install!) over the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-kickstand-2018?ls=en">Kickstand</a> to the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/vienna-bell?ls=en">bell</a>. We also got a Size L <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-helmet?ls=en">woom Helmet</a> in the same colour as his bike, and while the previous helmet had some shortcomings we hope this one will survive the next Finnish winter. It is, other than the problem with the extreme cold, a great helmet which is well ventilated, easy to adjust and our son can open and close it easily thanks to the magnetic buckle closure.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421712507/in/dateposted/" title="woom Helmet &#x3D; Safe Head"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421712507_3d2e6f5f6f_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="woom Helmet &#x3D; Safe Head" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421711987/in/dateposted/" title="Single Trail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421711987_d9a7b32f9b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Single Trail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All in all our son and us are very happy with the latest addition to our bike shed. He enjoys cycling now even more (as he can go so fast) and a lot of his friends have come up to him and wanted to ride his cool bike. I keep on repeating myself, but he cycles fast thanks to the bigger tires and the correct size for his height, and I think we’ll try to squeeze in some bike trips before winter is coming as he seems to be able to easily ride 40 km a day with some ice cream and Pulla breaks in-between. I also intend to go ride some easy single trails with him here in Vaasa, as he has enjoyed the short bits where we were riding in the forests a lot.</p>

<p>So to sum things up, if you want that your child enjoys cycling then the best thing you can do is get them a bike which makes them want to ride. The <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/5?ls=en">woom 5</a> definitely is such a bike for our son, as he loves to ride (fast!) on it, be it to school, to the beach or the ice cream parlour. The bike is safe, handles really well, is specially made for kids with great attention to details and easy to maintain for me. We are looking forward to many more rides together, both in town and on trails!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421562801/in/dateposted/" title="A small break"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421562801_629c19ca1e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="A small break" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Climbing Gear for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/08/climbing-gear-for-kids.html"/>
    <updated>2014-08-09T13:39:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/08/climbing-gear-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Climbing is fun, and it’s even more fun to have your children along. In this article I share some thoughts on climbing with litte kids &amp; highlight some kids climbing gear that has worked well for us.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14863252951" title="Kids Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3865/14863252951_76a691f99f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kids Climbing" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Our son always has climbed: First on chairs and the sofa, up stairs and even on top of the table when no-one was looking. Taking him along to the climbing gym and outside bouldering and rock climbing, he quickly also wanted to climb like dad. As normal shoes are fairly inadequate for climbing and I want to encourage him to climb &amp; have fun, I did quite a bit on research on kids climbing gear: Interviewing friends who go climbing with their little ones, comparing at online shops and reading the handful of reviews on blogs. So that you have an easier time picking good gear for your little one to come along and climb safely &amp; have fun, here’s our gear recommendations.</p>

<h2 id="shoes">Shoes</h2>

<p>As children grow fast almost all <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/kletterschuhe/fuer--kinder/">kids climbing shoes</a> are available in adjustable sizes. It hurts in the wallet if you need to buy a new pair each four to six months and at a regular price of around 50€ <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/kletterschuhe-kinder/">climbing shoes for kids</a> ain’t cheap. We bought the <a href="http://bit.ly/1A2essj">Climb X Monkey</a> in EU Size 29 (16 cm inside length). The Monkey print on them is a nice touch for kids, and parents will appreciate the large Velcro closure which makes it super easy to put on. In the heel there is a 2nd Velcro strap which lets you adjust the size. It has a flat, grippy rubber sole, a rubber toe bumper and the rubber goes up in the heel, too - ideal for heel hooks. The toe box is wide if I compare them to my shoes so you won’t damage your kids feet. The rubber sole is thick but still lets the little ones climb very precise - I’m often surprised by how well he can stand on narrow ledges with the shoes.</p>

<p>I usually buy his shoes a number larger and adjust the size then via the Velcro strap, that way we get more usage out of them. As it’s now summer sale in most shops it’s a good decision to check out what they have on offer - at least at <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/kletterschuhe/fuer--kinder/">Bergfreunde</a> all kids climbing shoes are almost 15 or more % reduced in price right now, so a good opportunity to pick up a pair. If you only go bouldering then a pair of shoes is pretty much all you’ll need for the start, but if you also do a lot of rock climbing you also might want to pick up a kids harness.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14864052894" title="Climb X Monkey Kids climbing shoe by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5568/14864052894_5cfb04c66a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Climb X Monkey Kids climbing shoe" /></a></p>

<h2 id="harness">Harness</h2>

<p>Our son started climbing before he was two years old and since then has been climbing indoors &amp; outdoors and often comes along bouldering with me. As I really like rock climbing I decided to buy him a <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/klettergurte/fuer--kinder/">Kids harness</a> so he can come along to the gym and crag once and a while. After some research I quickly settled on the <a href="http://bit.ly/1h4WCge">Edelrid Fraggle</a> - it’s a full-body harness, affordable and easy to use. We use the XXS Size since January 2014 and I expect we’ll get another year or one and half out of this harness. The XXS size goes from a Torso length of 50 to 70 cm and the leg loops go till 37 cm in diameter and can carry a child up to 40 kg.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://bit.ly/1olaR65">Edelrid Fraggle</a> is easy to put on: Two leg loops and two arm loops with two buckles to adjust the size - one in the front, one on the backside. A Buckle closes the harness below the tie-in loop. It’s padded &amp; comfy and my son wears it often the whole time we’re at the crag until we go home. What’s special about it is that in the back it has a 2nd loop, which is ideal for kids that already can climb on their own but are too light and tend to get stuck when you lower them. In this back loop you can tie in a 2nd rope, wicht which you can gently pull the child down when it is stuck again. If your child is already a bit older and can already sit upright in a harness by itself then a normal harness like the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/edelrid-finn-kinderklettergurt/">Edelrid Finn</a> would be a good solution. For more safety you can add the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/edelrid-kermit-brustgurt/">Edelrid Kermit Chest Harness</a> which is compatible with any (normal) harness.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14679865078" title="Edelrid Fraggle - Back by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5571/14679865078_e58cf79c49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Edelrid Fraggle - Back" /></a></p>

<h2 id="helmet">Helmet</h2>

<p>There are dedicated kids climbing helmets, like the <a href="http://bit.ly/1A2eFM4">Petzl Picchu</a>. While safety is of the utmost importance for us if we go climbing with our son we thus far have used my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/petzl-sirocco-helmet.html">Petzl Sirocco</a> for my son as with a thin beanie underneath it can be cinched down to a good fit for him. When he will be older &amp; we’ll be more regularly rock climbing he will get his own helmet (maybe the new <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-1.html">Edelrid Kids helmet</a>) but for now we use the Sirocco. If you’re child already has a bicycle helmet, that’d be an option that could work in a pinch, too.</p>

<h2 id="clothes">Clothes</h2>

<p>Clothes for climbing should be durable and give freedom of movement. It’s astounding how fast kids learn just by seeing what mom and dad do: We once were bouldering and I heel hooked, and the next time it was my sons turn to climb he started to also heel hook - without me having told him so! It’s a case of monkey see, monkey do =) So pants and shirts should not inhibite movement and should be robust: The little ones will often lean against the rock to take a break or slide down on it, so unless you want to buy new clothes after each climbing trip it’s well worth it to buy durable garments that have reinforcements in the seat and knees.</p>

<p>We like <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/">Isbjörn of Sweden</a> and so does our son, too. The <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.13.841/trapper-pant-cordura">Trapper Pant Cordura</a> has the afore-mentined reinfocements in the knee and seat area, made of Cordura these pants take any abuse my son throws at them. To keep mosquitos and UV rays at bay he wears the very cool <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.13.1339/mountain-longsleeve">MOUNTAIN Longsleeve</a> which has a topographic print of the Kebnekaise on it. Made from Tencel it’s soft on the skin and his favourite piece to wear when we go outdoors. If there’s a chance of rain then the <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.16.776/light-weight-jacket">Light Weight Jacket</a> comes into the <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/fjaellraeven-kanken-mini-daypack/">backpack</a>. Made from a wind- and waterproof fabric with a high collar and removable hood, it’s a nice jacket that keeps him dry &amp; warm in bad weather. Finally, to keep the ears warm and make the helmet fit better we have the soft merino wool <a href="http://www.isbjornofsweden.com/en/articles/2.18.878/beanie-extended">Isbjörn Beanie</a> along.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14680213960" title="Isbjörn of Sweden Kids clothing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5562/14680213960_fab69a0d94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="760" alt="Isbjörn of Sweden Kids clothing" /></a></p>

<h2 id="good-mood-snacks-and-toys">Good mood, snacks and toys</h2>

<p>Probably most important when we go to the crag is that there’s a good atmosphere and setting no objectives &amp; high expectations. When my son doesn’t want to climb but rather play with his toys or eat some fruit - that’s a decision I happily accept. Forcing kids likely will result in the opposite so he only climbs when he likes to do it. So one, two toys and snacks (We carry apples, water melon, sandwiches and nuts along &amp; go pick raspberries &amp; blueberries where available) are important to have along so he can be entertained. Often he likes to sit and watch what mom &amp; dad are doing and cheers us on. A couple more things are important to have along:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A full <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/klean-kanteen/">water bottle</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/mawaii/">Sunscreen</a></li>
  <li>A sun hat</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/julbo-looping-ii-spectron-4-baby-sonnenbrille/">Sunglasses</a></li>
  <li>The rain jacket in case the weather turns</li>
  <li>Something comfy to sit on (I use some segments of a <a href="http://bit.ly/1yguVGx">ZLite</a>)</li>
</ul>

<p>The last time we were at the crag I walked up to the top of the cliff with my son and we wanted to try to rappel down, so he can see how to “<em>walk down</em>”. We were almost over the lip as I realized that he didn’t seem to like it, so we made the two steps back up to the cliff and saved the rappel experience for another time. I think as a parent it is important in these situations to be <strong>a)</strong> Aware if the little one is doing fine and <strong>b)</strong> If one’s owns plans are feasible &amp; safe. If either of these questions is answered with “No” it’s a smart solution to just walk back down.</p>

<p><strong>That’s it. A pair of shoes, a harness and helmet along with comfy clothes, snacks and some toys and you’re ready to take you daughter or son along for a safe, fun climbing trip =)</strong></p>

<p><em>Here’s the small print: Climbing is dangerous and as a responsible adult you should know what you’re doing. Don’t do dangerous stuff when the health of your child is at risk, don’t force them to do things, and most of all, have fun. You’re a hero for them already, no matter if you manage to top out or not. Be wise &amp; be a good example.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14121989044" title="Kids Bouldering &amp; Climbing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5221/14121989044_4ed8072ff0_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Kids Bouldering &amp; Climbing" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
