<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ultralight backpacking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/blog/categories/ultralight-backpacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-21T08:58:44+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker's Gear Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/2015/09/andrew-skurka-the-ultimate-hikers-gear-guide.html"/>
    <updated>2015-09-04T23:54:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/2015/09/andrew-skurka-the-ultimate-hikers-gear-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>New to (ultralight) backpacking, hiking and camping? Then read Andrew Skurka’s book “The Ultimate Hiker’s Gear Guide” before you spend a lot of money on your outdoor gear and avoid a lot of mistakes!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20944339600/in/dateposted-public/" title="Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker&#x27;s Gear Guide"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5806/20944339600_aab8b5cb74_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker&#x27;s Gear Guide" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Andrew Skurka is an Outside “Adventurer of the Year” and has hiked over 30.000 miles on long-distance trails and off the beaten path - to say he knows a thing or two about hiking &amp; backpacking is a small understatement. I bought Andrew’s Manuscript for this book in 2011 and as the book hit the shelves in 2012 I also ordered a copy. That’s one thing to keep in mind, as the book is from 2012 some gear recommendations will be outdated by now - GoLite for example is bankrupt and doesn’t trade anymore - but you’ll still find similar recommended kit that is likely even lighter! Plus there are several classics in there that are still available, from <a href="http://bit.ly/1PPeQS5">ULA Equipment</a> to <a href="http://bit.ly/1JGgXpL">Granite Gear</a>. The gear recommendations are solid &amp; lightweight, and you’ll not find heavy, traditional recommendations in this book - which is great.</p>

<p>Besides gear recommendations the best reason to get this book are the skills and knowledge articles. From tips on pitching a tarp, how to make a fancy feast alcohol stove to minimizing drafts when you sleep under a quilt, there’s hundreds of tried &amp; tested tricks in the book which will help you to pick up knowledge and skills without making the mistakes to learn them. For me these were the most interesting sections of the book, and it’s easy to pick up some new idea to try out on a future hike.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21106252506/in/dateposted-public/" title="Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker&#x27;s Gear Guide"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/704/21106252506_582d709224_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Andrew Skurka: The Ultimate Hiker&#x27;s Gear Guide" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As someone who likes logic I found it disappointing that the illogical imperial units where used in the book and not the Metric system. The gear lists in the end are all focussed on the United States of America which can be adapted to European, Asian and Australian needs in a pinch. Also, as mentioned before, some gear has evolved since Andrew wrote the book, and so it makes sense to check out for example breathable insulation garments and consider hydrophobic down when buying a quilt or jacket.</p>

<p>The book proclaims that this book is for novices, occasional backpackers and seasoned hikers alike, and I have to concur with that statement. The book packs a ton of knowledge into its 224 pages and is very much worth the ~ $20 it costs - because the result will be that you will save money on future (lightweight) gear purchases and have more fun &amp; comfort right from the start of your hiking career. The book has a good layout, is easy to read &amp; understand and has great photos of Andrew’s adventures in it which will get you in the mood to go outdoors. The book is a smaller size so it even could come along on a weekend trip or on your commute - a great way to learn about ultralight backpacking on the way to the office!</p>

<p>You can order a <a href="http://andrewskurka.com/product/ultimate-hikers-gear-guide/">signed copy from Andrew</a> or buy it online at <a href="http://amzn.to/1UqVZTS">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1JSjr5y">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1NedN0d">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Justin Lichter: Trail Tested]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/2014/03/justin-lichter-trail-tested.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-27T15:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/2014/03/justin-lichter-trail-tested</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you looking for a book which helps you choose trail tested gear and has a gear list for any occasion? Then Trail Tested by Justin Lichter is for you!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7801519412" title="Trail Tested: A Thru-Hiker&#x27;s Insights Into Hiking and Backpacking by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8431/7801519412_3ea1547a14_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Trail Tested: A Thru-Hiker&#x27;s Insights Into Hiking and Backpacking" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="http://www.justinlichter.com/sample-page/shop/trail-tested-revised-ed/">Trail Tested: A Thru-Hiker’s Insights Into Hiking and Backpacking</a> is a useful book for every backpacker who has set his sights on thru-hiking a long-distance trail - although also hikers and backpackers who go out for only “short” trips will benefit from the accumulated experience of the author. Justin has hiked over 35.000 miles - he is a Triple Crowner, has hiked in Nepal, Africa, and many other countries, and over the duration of that time in the outdoors he has learned a lot, and helps us to not make some costly mistakes.</p>

<p>The book has three distinct sections:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>For Starters</em>, which looks at gear</li>
  <li><em>Getting The Grove</em>, which gives useful tips for the trail</li>
  <li><em>Stepping It Up</em>, which gives advanced tips</li>
</ul>

<p>All three sections will help you to make smart decisions - first at home and at the gear shop, then on the trail. Justin is a lightweight backpacking proponent and lists several reasons to go for lightweight gear - and if someone who puts thousands of kilometers on a shelter, sleeping bag and backpack thinks it’s durable &amp; smart, be ensured that it is! He runs you through the details when choosing the Big Three, gives tips on footwear and socks, stoves, clothes and everything else. Always along are small anecdotes and tips, which highlight the item in question.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7880235432" title="Trail Tested by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8429/7880235432_bdfdfca6ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Trail Tested" /></a></p>

<p>After the gear is sorted, Justin takes us out on the trail, and again small anecdotes and tips give insightful advice on the topic. As Justin often hikes with his dog, there’s several pages of useful infos on taking your best friend into the outdoors, choosing a backpack for him, and how to ensure he stays healthy and fit. If you’re planning to hike abroad, especially in less developed countries, he has some useful tips on making it a beautiful trip, and also if you’re setting out to thru-hike a long trail the book has a few good tips for you.</p>

<p>This book might feel like it is aimed at hiking and backpacking beginners, but even seasoned backpackers will find a few nuggets of wisdom and tips in it. Every page is accompanied by beautiful photos from across the globe which alone will make you want to hit the trail, and with the extensive knowledge dispersed over 217 pages this book really is for everyone who likes to spend time hiking &amp; backpacking in the outdoors.</p>

<p>Get the book <a href="http://www.justinlichter.com/sample-page/shop/trail-tested-revised-ed/">directly from the author</a> (autographed versions available!) or from <a href="http://amzn.to/1g72bpY">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1dzHM26">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1g72jWz">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
