<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: one stop shop 2019 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/one-stop-shop-2019/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2019-04-16T16:29:43+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Stop Shop: Alpinetrek.co.uk]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/one-stop-shop-alpinetrek-dot-co-dot-uk.html"/>
    <updated>2019-04-16T19:45:59+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/one-stop-shop-alpinetrek-dot-co-dot-uk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/one-stop-shop/">One Stop Shop</a> Series kicks off with a list from Alpinetrek.co.uk!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47620292771/in/dateposted/" title="One Stop Shop 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/47620292771_3484cc310f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="One Stop Shop 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially from Bergfreunde. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://alpinetrek.co.uk/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> is the British site of the well-established German online shop <a href="http://bergfreunde.de/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a>. I have been working together since many years with Alpinetrek and was very happy that they agreed to come on board for this series. Alpinetrek carries a wide assortment of brands, from Houdini to Patagonia, Salomon, Ortovox and Rab and also smaller brands which aren’t that well known yet. Their benefit definitely is that wide assortment, and while you won’t find many cottage brands in their shop, you still can put together a solid ultralight list. Another of their benefits is in my opinion that they carry such a large range of garments - this is great and allows you to get your hiking socks and boxershorts at the same time that you are ordering your shelter and sleeping bag! But without much further ado, here is the list which they sent us:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th><strong>Item</strong></th>
      <th style="text-align: left"><strong>Name</strong></th>
      <th style="text-align: center"><strong>Weight</strong></th>
      <th style="text-align: right"><strong>Price</strong></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Backpack</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Dwt4I1">Osprey Levity 60</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">850 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£237.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Sleeping bag</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Ujdjvs">Rab Neutrino 400 Sleeping Bag</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">795 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£331.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Mattress</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2V5rskJ">Therm-A-Rest NeoAir Uberlite Regular</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">227 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£179.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Shelter</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Pdmlt9">Nordisk Voss PU Tarp Green</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">850 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£63.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stove</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2P84T9x">Esbit CS985 Set</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">417 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£40.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pot</td>
      <td style="text-align: left">-</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">-</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">-</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Cutlery</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Zd7bso">Sea To Summit Alpha Light Cutlery Long Spork</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">12 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£6.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Knife</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2v1L8aq">Morakniv Eldris</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">177 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£29.50</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Cup</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2UhIKqj">Kupilka 21</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">80 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£15.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Waterfilter</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2ZbCBiX">Katadyn BeFree 1l</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">63 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£43.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>T-Shirt</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2UiYjh9">Patagonia Cap Cool Trail Shirt</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">130 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£34.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Longsleeve</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Xffmm6">Ortovox 150 Cool Logo L/S</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">176 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£83.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trekking pants</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2D8LeS3">Arc’teryx Palisade Pants</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">310 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£113.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Fleece</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2UXxpQl">Houdini Outright Houdi</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">291 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£142.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Insulation</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Dekpf3">Haglöfs L.I.M Essens Jacket</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">165 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£182.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Wind jacket</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Umop2N">Rab Vital Windshell Hoody</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">160 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£49.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Rain pants</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Gnxll2">Montane Minimus Pants</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">150 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£98.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Rain jacket</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Ikm1YV">Marmot PreCip Eco Plus Jacket</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">292 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£116.06</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Shoes</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2ZcUjCx">Inov-8 X-Talon 210</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">420 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£118.95</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Lamp</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2Da3GcL">Petzl e+LITE Headlamp</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">25 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£21.56</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Trekking Poles</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2UTwNLK">Swix Sonic Pro Trail Carbon</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">335 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£107.55</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Navigation</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><a href="http://bit.ly/2VHleVa">Suunto Spartan Ultra Black</a></td>
      <td style="text-align: center">77 g</td>
      <td style="text-align: right">£414.71</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><br /><strong>Total Weight</strong>: 6.002 g
<br /><strong>Total Price</strong>: £2.437,58 (in today’s exchange rate that’s 2.822,26 €)
<br /><strong>Price per g</strong>: £0,40 (0,46 €)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47620204541/in/dateposted/" title="One Stop Shop: Alpinetrek.co.uk"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/47620204541_843467533a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="560" alt="One Stop Shop: Alpinetrek.co.uk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>My thoughts on the list:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Very nice mix of brands for the Big 3. The Levity is a solid pack for beginners and experienced hikers alike, as is the sleeping setup (I expect we will see the <a href="https://youtu.be/5oXFCJi0TII">Uberlite</a> in a lot of lists this time around!). It’s nice to see the choice of a tarp for sleeping, it’s still one of my favourite ways to sleep outside. With a weight of 2.722 g for these four items the Big 3 are also well under 3 kg.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A very nice lightweight stove and kitchen Setup. The Esbit CS985 Set can use both solid fuel and alcohol to boil water, with the StS Long Spork you can eat directly from the bag, the Eldris is a solid knife which is good for all camp tasks and while the <a href="https://youtu.be/CneJY3F6zuY">BeFree Waterfilter</a> has some issues with the flask it’s a solid waterfilter which is really easy to use.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The whole clothing setup is 2.094 g, if you subtract the rain garments which are hopefully most of the time in your pack, and some of the insulation pieces you get a worn weight of 1.311 g including the shoes! That’s really good, and as I have used some of these garments myself I can tell you also that they are really durable!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The eLite is still a good choice for summer, though I personally would like something slightly heavier and with more Lumen for spring and autumn. The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/swix-pro-trail-carbon-120-trekking-pole.html">trekking poles are good</a> and as I myself also use the Spartan Ultra I can not find a fault in having it in this list - except it really is quite pricey.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Overall a very good lightweight list with a nice choice of gear. Maybe a bit pricey because of the inclusion of the Spartan Ultra, but other than that I find that a very good list which gets you lightweight on the trail in one go!</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><em>Keep in mind that these lists are suggestions!</em> If you for example rather spend a bit less and get a bit more heavy backpack like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/11/osprey-exos-48-review.html">Osprey Exos</a> or <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/10/gregory-optic-48.html">Gregory Optic</a> - then it is easy to get those packs at Alpinetrek. Similarly, if you feel that you are happy with your hiking shoes or headlamp - just leave these out.</p>

<p>At the end of the series I will compare all lists which each other, so definitely make sure you <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">subscribe</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">follow along</a> to not miss out.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337489450" title="Chilling at Sunset"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/976/40337489450_c4f9faa8f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling at Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/one-stop-shop/">One Stop Shop Series</a> was <a href="http://fastpacking.de">Carsten</a>’s idea back in the day. The 2019 Series we have created together and you can read his take on the different lists in German on his blog, and you can read my take over here in English. Furthermore, we have been remunerated for our time by the individual shops.</em></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Stop Shop 2019]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/one-stop-shop-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2019-04-15T10:18:02+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/one-stop-shop-2019</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you remember the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/one-stop-shop/">One Stop Shop</a> Series from 2014 where Carsten and me reached out to a bunch of Shops and asked if they’d like to participate in creating a complete ultralight kit list from their assortment? Yes? Great! Then you’d be delighted to know that the series is back this year and we look forward to share some exciting lists with you!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40645873863/in/dateposted/" title="One Stop Shop 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/40645873863_2ce6a50d47_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="One Stop Shop 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Five years have passed since <a href="http://fastpacking.de">Carsten</a> and me did our <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/one-stop-shop/">One Stop Shop Series</a>, and much has changed since then. Ultralight gear has become mainstream and pretty much every manufacturer offers now lightweight and ultralight alternatives of their equipment. This is great for consumers - where previously you needed to buy your quilt here, the sleeping mat there, and the backpack elsewhere nowadays you can even walk into a brick &amp; mortar store and find the lightweight gear you are searching for. This has the benefit that with some critical items like backpacks and garments you’re able to try them on before buying them, which makes returns much less likely.</p>

<p>But also the ultralight cottages haven’t been sleeping and resting on their UL Laurels - they have realized that people like to purchase their gear from a few sources instead of a dozen or more shops, and so especially we Europeans are quite lucky to have a handful of Shops which sell ultralight cottage gear all under one roof. It are these, but also more broad shops with more widely known brands, which we will showcase in this series, and I at least am very curious to see which new items will be on these lists, and which classic items we will meet again.</p>

<p>The reason for trying to purchase from one shop instead of six or more different ones is simple: You minimize shipping costs and the possibility for things to go wrong, like lost packages, long waiting times and different currencies + paying methods are all adding up to frustration when you want to buy ultralight gear in one go. Imagine you’d be able to buy all of the lightweight trekking gear you want from just one shop - <em>actually</em>, don’t imagine it - just read our articles to see that it is possible! What we do in this series is to challenge a dozen or so outdoor stores (online, brick &amp; mortar and online shops with a brick &amp; mortar shop) to send us their ideal and functional UL gear list of lightweight &amp; ultralight gear, which one can buy normally (no special orders) in their store. To make these lists easy to compare with each other and that they stay within the same boundaries, these are our Guidelines:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Creat a 3-Season gear list (Day temperature of 10 to 20°C, Night temperature of 0 to 5°C)</li>
  <li>Rain is possible every day and night</li>
  <li>Mosquitos and other insects are not an issue</li>
  <li>Tours are 5 to 7 days long</li>
</ol>

<p>These are the outlines of many classic 3-season backpacking trips, and with this one list you should be able to go hiking from spring till autumn, in Scotland, Scandinavia, China, Colorado or elsewhere. The resulting list should give you the possibility to go backpacking in warmer or colder regions with just a few little adaptations, and we are asking for suggestions for the following items:</p>

<p><strong>The Big 3</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Backpack</li>
  <li>Sleeping bag or quilt</li>
  <li>Mattress</li>
  <li>Shelter</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>The Ultralight Kitchen</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Stove</li>
  <li>Pot (if not included with Stove)</li>
  <li>Cutlery</li>
  <li>Knife</li>
  <li>Cup</li>
  <li>Waterfilter</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Getting Dressed</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Baselayer T-Shirt</li>
  <li>Longsleeve</li>
  <li>Trekking pants</li>
  <li>Fleece jacket</li>
  <li>Insulation jacket</li>
  <li>Wind jacket</li>
  <li>Rain pants</li>
  <li>Rain jacket</li>
  <li>Shoes</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Accessories</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>(Head-) Lamp</li>
  <li>Trekking poles</li>
  <li>Navigation/ Electronics</li>
</ul>

<p>The first four items are the big three (sleep system, backpack and shelter) which weigh the most and where one can save the most weight when lightening up. The kitchen is something many of us like to thinker with and everyone has their preference - the speed and efficiency of a gas stove, the super ultra light weight of an alcohol stove, or the relaxing fire of a woodstove. As most of us do not hike naked it’s good to get dressed, and finally we also need some accessories for our trips. The first article goes online tomorrow, and then we will publish them as be get them throughout the following weeks. Make sure to Like and follow along on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> to not miss updates from this series, and check out <a href="https://www.fastpacking.de/2019/04/15/one-stop-shop-2019-die-komplette-ultraleicht-ausruestung-in-einem-laden-kaufen/">Carsten’s article in German</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337489450/in/album-72157695044886921/" title="Chilling at Sunset"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/976/40337489450_c4f9faa8f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling at Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>The <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/one-stop-shop/">One Stop Shop Series</a> was <a href="http://fastpacking.de">Carsten</a>’s idea back in the day. The 2019 Series we have created together in order to bring you this series, and you can read his take on the different lists in German on his blog, and you can read my take over here in English. Furthermore, we have been remunerated for our time by the individual shops, though as you know - that had no influence on the articles as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em> *</p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
