<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: family | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/family/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2021-08-24T09:54:15+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Car in 2021: Still the Exception, and sometimes a Problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/06/no-car-in-2021-still-the-exception.html"/>
    <updated>2021-06-01T19:07:38+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/06/no-car-in-2021-still-the-exception</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We still don’t own a car, we still don’t want to own a car, and there’s still no alternatives to owning a car available in Vaasa (or any other small town in Finland/ Scandinavia) in 2021. It’s frustrating if you want to go to a hiking trail a bit further away with the family or if you have to pick up stuff you can not transport with a bike. And it makes me wonder: Will we still have to own a car in 2030 or will there soon come Mobility As A Service options also to smaller cities and towns?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51217433153/in/dateposted/" title="Find Your Car"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51217433153_5622a0eb81_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Find Your Car" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>In March 2019 I blogged that not owning a car isn’t a problem for us, as <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">we can do everything with the bike</a>. This still holds true 95% of the time today, but then there’s those 5%. Much of these 5% involve kid’s hobbies, especially during winter (so the time between November and April here in Vaasa), where it’s not easy to motivate kids (and adults) to ride at -15°C on badly ploughed roads to a swimming lesson in the evening - and back home. You might think: <em>“Don’t complain, just cycle there!”</em> and it’s definitely the attitude I also have - but forcing a child to go cycle in such weather is a sure way to make them hate the hobby as they don’t want to bother with the cycling there and back in such weather. So this past winter we cheated a bit, as we had a car loaned to us (I’m calling it “The Coffin” as it’s 30+ years old and has a lot of problems).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/872x51" title="Herbie"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51216467167_9417f69dee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Herbie" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hours">168 hours</h2>

<p>One Day has 24 hours and thus a week has 168 hours. We moved with the car around 3 hours a week, which means it sat 165 hours in the driveway - or 98,21% of the time. Is it worth it to own a car so that it can sit 98% of the time in your driveway? I think not. Sure, we are again an exception to this situation, as our neighbours have one, two, three, four or more cars sitting in their driveways and seem to move around with them a bit more than us (because we still cycle almost everywhere), but even they probably don’t move their cars for more than 20 hours a week - which would be 12% of the weekly hours and means a car is sitting idly on a parking spot for 78% of the week.</p>

<p>Do you see where I go with this? The majority of <strong>cars only stand around</strong>. Yes, it’s nice to jump in a heated car in winter and drive the 10 minutes to the swim lesson if there’s a snow storm raging outside. If you want to support a local restaurant it’s nice to go pick-up tasty Take-Away Food. Have to transport four bags of cement? That’s one easy ride with the car. But it still means the car stands around, in our case, 98% of the time. Which for me means it’s a waste of space (I don’t like that it blocks the bigger part of the driveway) and also resources, as even this loaned car has costs - gasoline for use, insurance, Parking fees in the city and electricity costs for pre-heating it in winter.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/AJDft6" title="Yellow"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51216467097_67c70c4755_b.jpg" width="766" height="1024" alt="Yellow" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="a-new-car">A New Car</h2>

<p>So over the past months we have had many discussions about if we should buy a car once <em>“The Coffin”</em> leaves us in a few weeks. There are happily many good Electric Car Alternatives available today, which at least make the driving part more environmentally friendly - I want to avoid buying a gasoline powered car for many reasons. Thus we looked at many small EVs or electric car alternatives - from the Arcimoto FUV over the Citroën Ami and Next e.Go to the BMW i3 and “bigger” cars like a Skoda Enyaq, Volkswagen ID.3/ ID.4 and even a Tesla. But we always came back to the same conclusion: We don’t want to buy a car. We don’t want to own a car. But for these two to three hours a week where a car is useful, it would be AMAZING to have easy access to a car without needing to travel (by bike or Taxi) to a pick-up point to get a loan car for an hour or less.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/n2706N" title="Tesla Model 3"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51217390878_a95a2d6368_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tesla Model 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="mobility-as-a-service">Mobility As A Service</h2>

<p>As we don’t want to own a car, we looked at Mobility as a Service Options. It would be great to have a MaaS Provider like <a href="https://www.greenmobility.com/fi/en/greenmobilitys-cities/">GreenMobility</a> in Vaasa, alas they are at the moment only in Helsinki (and Copenhagen, Gothenborg, Ghent and more). It’s a modern System that works with an App and the thing I like the most is that it are all Electric Vehicles and that it’s a Pay as you need System - so if you only need a car for driving 10 Minutes to the Swimming Hall, you pay for 10 minutes - all within the App. And something which is very convenient too is that Insurance is also included, and it should be very easy to find a Parking Spot thanks to the App and the VIP Parking Spots of GreenMobility in the cities they are. The single best thing is that you can unlock the car with the App, so if you see the car in on the street you simply can walk there, unlock it, and drive away. It’s super easy and really how I envision MaaS to work 🚙😊 And no, sadly this article isn’t sponsored by them!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51216485507/in/photostream/" title="GreenMobility App"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51216485507_de58f011c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="GreenMobility App" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="https://whimapp.com/helsinki/en/">Whim</a> is another MaaS Provider in Helsinki (and Turku, Vienna, and more) which is including even more options: You can easily buy a (seasonal) ticket for Public Transportation, rent a car, drive a Citybike, E-Scooter or a Taxi. It also works with an App and makes it very convenient to e.g. ride a Citybike to a Metro Stop, ride the Metro to your destination and then there walk (or use a E-Scooter) to your final destination. This has a lot more mobility options which makes it a great All-In-One Place to book transportation of any means.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Here’s an <a href="http://www.shapehelsinki.com/project/whimapp">interesting case study</a> on the creation of the Whim App.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In Helsinki you also have the <a href="https://citycarclub.fi/en">City Car Club</a>, a real innovator in the Car Sharing area as they exist since 1999. If you join you can use their cars to do your driving, from one hour to several days. There are many benefits to car sharing, like one car sharing car replaces between 8 - 10 private cars and there are less cars standing around (remember that in my example above our car would be standing around 165 hours a week!). Sharing a car with multiple neighbours or people from our neighbourhood could work great, as long as not everyone needs the car at the same time. There’s things like working out the insurance stuff and such, but generally car sharing would be a great way for us to have access to a car, but not owning a car. Sadly, such an option is currently not available in Vaasa, so we might need to bring up this idea with the neighbourhood.</p>

<p>A MaaS Provider which is available in Vaasa is 24Rent. Sadly they only have Vans available for renting, otherwise this would be a good opportunity to rent a car for short amounts of time. But if I need to transport large amounts of stuff, this will come in useful in the future!</p>

<p><em>Update 02.06.2021</em>: Matti from 24Rent reached out to me to inform me that they soon also will offer passenger cars in Vaasa for rent. And even better, they also have a service called <a href="https://24go.fi">24Go</a> which is already available in the Capital Region, Tampere, Lahti and Oulu and they also are planning on launching it to Vaasa at some point - which would another perfect solution for us as it works easy with an App and would allow us to loan a car for simply 15 minutes when needed!</p>

<h2 id="so-what-now">So what now?</h2>

<p>Yeah, that is a good question. If you don’t want to have a car standing around in your driveway for 98% of the time you are sadly in a minority, as most people seem to be happy to have one or more cars standing in front of their house. There’s no good MaaS Provider available in Vaasa (yet!) so currently the only option is to either start a Car Sharing Initiative in the neighbourhood/ city or get an own car. Happily right now it is summer, our daughter &amp; son are very enthusiastic about cycling, so for the next three months we won’t need to think too much about a car. But once November rolls around with lots of rain, darkness and then winter with snow and cold temperatures, the discussion of how to get to the Hobbies will come up again, and till then we’d like to have a viable solution on the table. Of course being able to drive to hiking trails which are a bit further away during the summer is nice, too! If you have an idea, feel free to reach out on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a>! And if you are living in Vaasa and want to start a car sharing initiative - get in touch, too 😎</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/1HNh1E" title="Defender"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51217184231_8eb5b9299b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Defender" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> (and you get great discount codes from partners - you could save 20% on your next purchase!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Car, No Problem: Urban Family Transportation]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html"/>
    <updated>2019-03-29T21:05:38+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/urban-family-transportation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Riding bikes is fun and healthy. Too bad too many people drive cars in our cities. <strong>Cars don’t belong in cities</strong> is a thought which we share in our family. Cars have their place, but for both humans and the environment, and also the aesthetics of our towns, it would be best if most of us would cycle to the grocery store, work and the cinema. That that is possible I want to show you in this article.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47434099322/in/dateposted/" title="Family cycling"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7888/47434099322_30dc75ef70_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Family cycling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>Some of the products in this article have been provided to us by the manufacturers. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>

<p>I admit that <strong>#FuckCarsRideBikes</strong> is probably the best Hashtag I have invented. I dislike cars as they illustrate what is wrong with our cities &amp; towns: Everywhere we have multi-lane streets so that thousands of people who sit <em>alone</em> in their car can drive from A to B. What’s wrong about this is that the distances these people drive <strong>ALONE</strong> in their cars is statistically less than 5 km, or the distance which most of the readers of this blog hike in an hour in the hills or would be able to ride on a bike in 20 to 30 minutes. Add in that nowadays seemingly every other car driver is distracted while checking his or her phone, our ageing societies mean that there are more people who are physically less able to drive <strong>safely</strong>, and the emissions from cars which are bad for our health and you start to realize that we need to get rid of the majority of cars in cities and towns. That that is possible and that one can thrive without a car and <strong>get everything done</strong> is what I want to show today, and hopefully encourage you to ride more on your bike and drive less in your car.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610376678/in/dateposted/" title="Jkl Uni"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7915/33610376678_b349aec085_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jkl Uni" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-from-a-to-b">How to get from A to B</h2>

<p>The kids have hobbies, need to be brought to school and kindergarden, there’s the occasional thing to pick up at the post office and groceries for cooking at home also need to be bought and brought home. Add in a visit to the cinema, going for lunch with colleagues, <a href="https://youtu.be/v0ae-3BQzFM">playing games with friends</a>, swimming at the beach and oh, yeah, showing up at the office for work is also smart. <strong>Can one <em>REALLY</em> do all that by bike?</strong> Well, yes 😊</p>

<p>Statistically most people use their cars for journeys of three to five kilometre in length, which if you think about it, is insane. I ride with my kids, with the trailer behind me and my son on his own bike, in 15 minutes to the centre of Vaasa, which is about three kilometre away from our house. Pretty much all of it is on cycling lanes, and in the centre there’s dozens of parking places for bikes so one never needs to ponder “Where do I park?”. It’s also free! If the weather is poor hardshells come on - living in a coastal town (= lots of wind, 🌬💨 all the time) means we are used to wearing a <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/windproof-jackets/?pid=10239">wind jacket</a> when we go outside - and when you arrive at the Café, Restaurant or school you take it off. No problem!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571687275/in/dateposted/" title="Parking for bikes"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7865/46571687275_0d5cbf2101_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Parking for bikes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This is not some kind of magic that only we can achieve. Most people have very short commutes and can do all of it by riding a bike, and did I mention that being on a bike is healthy and fun? I at least always feel very happy when I can ride my bike. I think the biggest hurdle to those who drive with a car everywhere is that they think that they can not cycle. The truth is - if you have learned to ride a bike, and own a bike, then you can bicycle. No one is expecting you to win the <a href="https://www.transcontinental.cc">Transcontinental Race</a> or going <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/10/active-holidays-in-are-sweden.html">Downhill mountain biking</a> but you likely just want go to the Café or to the beach. You also don’t need to sell your car and go all in, but gradually try what you all can do by bike. Cycle to work two days a week, instead of taking the car to the gym take the bike to go grocery shopping, and if you want to go out and meet friends why not go cycle to that lovely Café instead of taking the car? If you slowly phase out the use of a car you’ll see that going by bike everywhere is easy - and not just for adults, also kids love to ride their bike. The smile my 3 year old daughter gives me when we cycle together is amazing, and while this obviously only are short distances like going to the Kindergarden, the playground and the library bus, it still allows her to get used to cycling. For longer distances she sits in the Thule Chariot, which is also great to transport stuff. And if it doesn’t fit on the bike or in the trailer I take the bus or use a Taxi. By not owning a car we save a minimum of 400€ per month on car-related expenses, and that are even in Finland quite a few Taxi rides.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614273578/in/dateposted/" title="Happy Cycler"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7926/33614273578_e6c06abdf3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happy Cycler" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bikes">The Bikes</h2>

<p>Now I have been talking so much about our bikes - time to take a look at them! I have written before about my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Pelago Stavanger</a> which I am now riding since five years. I bought for my wife some years ago a <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com/bicycles/airisto-commuter.html">Pelago Airisto</a> which she loves, and with both of these bikes we can pull the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/thule-chariot-cross2-kinderanhaenger/?pid=10239">Thule Chariot 2</a> where our daughter sits and rides with us. The Airisto is a fantastic bike and I got my wife the front basket as it makes transporting things so much easier. The Airisto also performs well for bike tours - we cycled for a week on Åland with these bikes and had a lot of fun.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40520962753/in/dateposted/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7922/40520962753_23798cdaea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571688285/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7917/46571688285_5aa533fa0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Our son is on his fourth bike, and since about a year he is riding the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/4?ls=en">woom 4 children’s bike</a> which has been his best bike to date. It’s not just light and grew with him, it also has 8 gears which made cycling up hills and in winter a lot easier. The bike handles very well (especially if compared to his older bikes) and it’s a pleasure to see him ride his bike proudly and having fun. A good bike which is the right size and easy to use makes all the difference in getting a child being willing to ride a bike year-around, from spring till winter, and the woom 4 certainly has made it easier for us parents to go cycling together - because the bike works flawlessly. We also have cycled some longer rides around Vaasa with him, and thanks to his woom bike he’s able to cycle up to 20 km without a problem.</p>

<p>Our son is wearing the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-helmet?ls=en">woom Helmet</a> which is good, though it’s not really made for the cold weather of Finland and the width adjustment knob broke in the middle of winter - we have been using the Helmet now in the max. size, which is either way what we needed. It’s a light and well-ventilated helmet and stands up to daily use. Similarly the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-radlicht">woom bike lights</a> had a battery which had problems coping with the Finnish winter, it only worked on a charge for a day or two max and then needed recharging, though I imagine this is not a problem in warmer climates. And we also got the easy to use <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-radschloss?ls=en">woom chain lock</a>. You can put in your own code (and can change it easily, too) so that way the bike can always be securely locked when at school or in town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571691295/in/dateposted/" title="woom 4"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7865/46571691295_12bb9d92f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom 4" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571691555/in/dateposted/" title="Summer cycling in Vaasa"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7814/46571691555_271e76e918_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Summer cycling in Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47434095572/in/dateposted/" title="woom 4 + woom Helmet"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7916/47434095572_a59a09ed9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="woom 4 + woom Helmet" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Thule Chariot 2 is an amazing trailer and honestly the most important piece of cycling gear for a family with small kids which wants to rely less on the car. The <a href="http://bit.ly/2FxaMIU">Chariot 2</a> has allowed us to transport both kids at the same time when they were younger, we can use it to transport large packages and it makes grocery shopping a breeze as you can fit a child and the groceries for a week in it with room to spare. We also have travelled with the bikes and the trailer on <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/cycling-and-bouldering-on-aland.html">Åland</a> which was an amazing trip which combined the bikes, train and ferry for a lovely week of cycling in the Archipelago. The Thule Chariot also has flown with us when the kids were smaller, as it can be converted into a pram in one minute (or a sled if there’s enough snow!). This really is an amazing piece of equipment which is integral to our family not having a car, and I can foresee that even when our 3-year old daughter is old enough to cycle herself that we might keep the trailer for a while as it is so damn easy to transport large things with it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47434099002/in/dateposted/" title="Thule Chariot 2 Transporter"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7863/47434099002_f54316e494_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Thule Chariot 2 Transporter" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571689175/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7800/46571689175_b8ac2a62d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610375218/in/dateposted/" title="Family cycling in Vaasa"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7896/33610375218_358a20220e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Family cycling in Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614272628/in/dateposted/" title="Cycle Touring on Åland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7828/33614272628_29bff33595_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cycle Touring on Åland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46768405674/in/dateposted/" title="Thule Chariot 2 in the rain"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7857/46768405674_b0f7f378fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Thule Chariot 2 in the rain" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Speaking of transporting, my <a href="https://www.trekbikes.com/us/en_US/bikes/adventure-touring-bikes/920/920/p/21996/">Trek 920 Disc</a> has been an amazing bike for both transporting, urban commutes, fun rides and adventures. I can transport an unreasonable amount of stuff on it thanks to the two racks, and especially the front rack is one of the best things on a bike, ever (<em>Seriously, if there’s one thing you should get for your bike it is a front rack!</em>). I love this bike and even more after I made it <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/08/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit.html">tubeless</a> two years ago. If it would allow me to pull the Thule Chariot I probably would own only this one bike.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40524987693/in/dateposted/" title="Trek 920 All loaded up"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7886/40524987693_3f0f1a2faa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trek 920 All loaded up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571686395/in/dateposted/" title="Cockpit view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7897/46571686395_eb521756db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cockpit view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As we are a family and we have to transport kids, groceries and parcels every now and then, I think you understand why we are dreaming of a Cargobike. <a href="https://www.bakfiets.nl">There’s</a> <a href="http://www.larryvsharry.com">just</a> <a href="https://yubabikes.com">too</a> <a href="https://sblocs.bike">many</a> <a href="http://www.workcycles.com">options</a> and they’re also all a bit pricey, but maybe in the future we will change from the Thule Chariot to a Cargobike for transporting…</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115659892/in/album-72157665520832018/" title="SBlocs Cargo Bike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4720/40115659892_5b5a2abb36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="806" alt="SBlocs Cargo Bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s the kick bike which our kids used when they were small. We had a <a href="https://www.puky.de/en/home">Puky</a> kick bike for both kids, and our daughter has been riding it since she was 1,5 years old. It’s something she really enjoys a lot and she is pretty good at it, and when we go to the playground, for a walk or to the library bus she takes the kick bike as that way the longer distances are no problem for her.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610373888/in/photostream/" title="Loving to bike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7836/33610373888_00e0ca4350_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Loving to bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610374408/in/dateposted/" title="Learning to bike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7892/33610374408_d270d6610c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="come-rain-come-sunshine-we-ride">Come Rain, come Sunshine, we Ride</h2>

<p>Riding our bikes in any weather - from damn slippery roads to the rain and hot 30°C days - needs a little planning garment-wise, though as you’re likely a backpacker or skier you have everything you need to ride in any climate. We just use our hiking garments for cycling, the most important thing is that they have a good freedom of movement. A wind or rain jacket and a rain pants are needed in foul weather, while in the summer we cycle in shorts and T-shirts. My wife and kids use a Helmet while I only use one on long bike rides - because <a href="https://www.bicycling.com/news/a24110027/bike-helmet-safety/">it’s OK to not wear a helmet</a>, as bicycle lanes make cycling safe and not a helmet. <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/gloves/recommended-use--cycling/?pid=10239">Windproof gloves</a> make sure your hands don’t freeze solid (they’re also recommended in windy summers as warm hands make cycling a lot more fun).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614272908/in/dateposted/" title="Rocking the Puky Kickbike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7856/33614272908_075dbb2416_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rocking the Puky Kickbike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That’s really it what ones need to transporting oneself from A to B by bicycle - yes there’s lots of fancy things one can add to the bike but a basic bike, some gloves, maybe a helmet and depending on the weather a wind or rain jacket are all that is needed. In the future I’ll write more about useful accessories for cycling, but that’s not the focus of this post!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40524988183/in/dateposted/" title="Cycling to go skiing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7863/40524988183_1c28c90e01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cycling to go skiing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614273378/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Stavanger Cockpit"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7862/33614273378_ebbb6f6882_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Stavanger Cockpit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="cant-do-without-car">Can’t do without car?</h2>

<p>If you can not be without a car - because you actually life far away from civilization - I would encourage you to at least not drive alone. Share a car with a neighbour or two, drive together, make less trips and if your car is old get a car which is fuel-efficient or is an electric car. Generally, sharing the car and driving together makes the use of a motorized vehicle more acceptable. Alternatively you could try a e-Bike as these allow you to go a bit faster and further without too much of your own muscle power, or have a look at something like the <a href="https://www.arcimoto.com">Arcimoto</a> if it needs to be a vehicle.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23170406440/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Cabo da Roca"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/5701/23170406440_011dc7899e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cabo da Roca" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="go-ride-your-bike">Go Ride Your Bike!</h2>

<p>I hope you see it is easy, fun and healthy to not drive everywhere in a car and that using the bike for transportation in an urban environment makes a lot of sense. There’s no searching for a parking spot, you don’t need to go to the gym, you’re outside at the fresh air and are having fun. Having good bikes for the kids and getting them used from an early age to cycling helps to instil a happiness to bicycle everywhere in them, and also makes them more independent as you as a parent don’t need to drive them everywhere. So in conclusion I hope that you now, with the beginning of spring, try to cycle more! After all - it’s fun, healthy and allows you to be more outside, and isn’t that what we all enjoy the most?!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40524987853/in/dateposted/" title="Spring Races"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7902/40524987853_2430810228_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Spring Races" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614272478/in/dateposted/" title="Åland scenary"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7877/33614272478_4dbe015350_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Åland scenary" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Family Adventures in the Bregenzerwald]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/09/family-adventures-in-the-bregenzerwald.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-21T23:40:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/09/family-adventures-in-the-bregenzerwald</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The family adventure-mountain-holiday saga from the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/bregenzerwald/">Bregenzerwald</a> continues with a lot of hikes and some fine views!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29204080844/in/dateposted/" title="Along the ridge"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8281/29204080844_8238aac4da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Along the ridge" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="a-panorama-hike-in-the-brandnertal">A Panorama Hike in the Brandnertal</h2>

<p>Where did I leave off? Ah yeah, that I just came back to our apartment after my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/family-adventures-in-vorarlberg.html">Sunrise hike up the Kanisfluh</a>, ready for a day full of family adventures. With such a good weather forecast - the first really sunny day during our stay - we decided to head to the neighbouring Brandnertal¹ and hike on the family-friendly <a href="https://www.vorarlberg-alpenregion.at/brandnertal/bergbahnen/angebot-am-berg/naturspruengeweg/">Natursprünge-Weg Brandnertal</a>. After a drive of a bit over an hour we arrived in Studa and took the Dorfbahn up the mountain. There we switched into the Panoramabahn which brought us over to the start of the nature experience trail, which has been created in cooperation with the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/family-adventures-in-vorarlberg.html">inatura museum</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29538786880/in/dateposted/" title="Up with the cable car"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7569/29538786880_53f3da0611_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up with the cable car" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But first it was already again lunch time, and so we sat down at <a href="http://www.frööd.at">Frööd</a> and ate to strengthen us for the stroll through the mountains. The food was tasty, as were their home-made lemonades, and the playground keeps kids active for a long time! Add in great views and you might just be inclined to sit on the terrace and sip cold drinks!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748738131/in/dateposted/" title="Tasty lemonade!"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8022/29748738131_bef1f283f0_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Tasty lemonade!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29831378735/in/dateposted/" title="Inside Frööd"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8163/29831378735_7839bb3640_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inside Frööd" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29831378565/in/photostream/" title="Terrace at Frööd"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8775/29831378565_9b705853bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Terrace at Frööd" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But we weren’t there to sit out a sunny day on a terrace and so we soon started to hike on the interactive Natursprünge Weg. In regular distances you find information stations which explain a certain topic - from the views over geology to respect for nature, it’s a wide array of topics which you can find out about.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748736891/in/dateposted/" title="Natursprünge-Weg Brandnertal"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8033/29748736891_dcb20ae59d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Natursprünge-Weg Brandnertal" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29796036516/in/dateposted/" title="Filtering water on the Natursprünge-Weg Brandnertal"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8090/29796036516_5b995791e8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Filtering water on the Natursprünge-Weg Brandnertal" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29538775480/in/dateposted/" title="German, English, Dutch"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8176/29538775480_f2db5f157b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="German, English, Dutch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It was a wide, hard path which was OK to walk - the views were spectacular, though on a sunny day the lack of shadow could be causing trouble when on the trail with little kids, so always bring enough water, a longsleeved shirt and pants and a sun hat to protect the little hikers. Also the relative long distance (it’s around 90 minutes walking time with kids, so maybe close to 6 km) could be a problem, as there’s no shortcut. However, you can loan a handcart from the second station which would allow you to pull your kids down the trail, making it easier!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748739211/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Eagle"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8547/29748739211_5daac6f772_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Eagle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748740181/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Barefoot trail at the end of the Natursprünge-Weg Brandnertal"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/8/7523/29748740181_ab82290f79_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Barefoot trail at the end of the Natursprünge-Weg Brandnertal" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>At the end we passed another Restaurant and the start of a Barefoot Trail which looked pretty nice, but we just went straight for the cable car as our little one was getting pretty tired and needed to get into bed soon! All in all the Natursprünge Trail was a good experience, but we did like the Panorama Trail in Bezau (read about it underneath) more as it was a lot prettier.</p>

<h2 id="a-barefoot-hike-in-bizau">A Barefoot Hike in Bizau</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bizau-bregenzerwald.com/sommer/sport-freizeit/wandern/barfussweg/">Barfußweg Bizauer Moos</a> is a great little hike for friends of barefoot walking! It was also very close to our <a href="http://www.appartements-wuestner.at">apartment in Mellau</a> - a short bus ride from Mellau to Bizau and we could start! We followed the trail markers over narrow paths and wider streets to the start of the barefoot trail, which runs all the time along the short (or through) the little Ulve creek which finds its way through the highmoor.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29538800070/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Kanisfluh"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8208/29538800070_9ceeae31bd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kanisfluh" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29796151196/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Start of the Barfuss Weg Bizau"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8383/29796151196_305b390584_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Start of the Barfuss Weg Bizau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Once we reached it we told our four year old son that we will now continue without shoes. He was highly sceptical and needed some serious convincing, but after he saw that mom and dad were walking through the muddy puddles he was all in favour of barefoot hiking! The barefoot trail runs mostly on grassy trails, with a few crossings of the ice-cold creek.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688676552/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Ice-cold on the Barefoot Trail in Bizau"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7188/27688676552_38b75b524b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ice-cold on the Barefoot Trail in Bizau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29718474512/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Barefoot!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8179/29718474512_816cdfccf3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Barefoot!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Our son really liked the ice-cold crossings, and loved it even more if he could make dad cross the creek twice =) The highmoor is beautiful, with colourful wildflowers all around and great views on the surrounding mountains.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29718476562/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Colourful"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8284/29718476562_d1def7a701_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Colourful" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29831355175/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Dirty feet"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8060/29831355175_748b8ec898_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dirty feet" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>At the end the trail runs in tight curves there and back, but always along the little creek, sometimes now also on duckboards (which can be very slippery with wet, muddy feet!) but mostly on grassy trails. Once you see the yellow-green bench you know that you’ve made it to the end of the trail! Now it’s time to wash your feet a final time in the cold creek - hopefully you brought a towel! - and get back into your shoes (unless you’re a monkey like me and have your <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a> along!) and continue - for example towards <a href="http://www.jagdgasthaus-egender.at">Jagdgasthaus Egender</a> in Schönenbach, where you can taste the best Kässpätzle of the whole region!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29831389995/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="End of the Barefoot Trail Bizau"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8323/29831389995_9e2b137e96_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="End of the Barefoot Trail Bizau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29831356145/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Jagdgasthaus Egender"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8439/29831356145_48093fb836_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jagdgasthaus Egender" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688675722/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Kässpätzle at Jadggasthaus Egender, Schönenbach"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7469/27688675722_96b71c5617_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kässpätzle at Jadggasthaus Egender, Schönenbach" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hiking-on-the-panaoramaweg-bezau">Hiking on the Panaoramaweg Bezau</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://touren.vorarlberg.travel/de/tour/wanderung/bezau-panoramaweg-baumgarten/2952601/">Panaoramaweg Bezau</a> was our absolute highlight of the trip to the Bregenzerwald in Vorarlberg. It was again very close to where we stayed in Mellau - a mere 10 minute Bus ride! - and the scenery, the lovely little path, the great Restaurant and the amazing views really made this hike stand out.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29204076584/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Up into the fog"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8016/29204076584_3ae5ea3718_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up into the fog" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29204074304/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Incoming!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7536/29204074304_3125daa3a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Incoming!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29204075504/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Lunch with a view"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8252/29204075504_3d4b5fa5e8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lunch with a view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It started with a cable car ride up into the clouds for us four, and we took the pram along - which we then left at the Restaurant as the trail didn’t accommodate a pram (it was very washed out and there were some gates where you would have to lift it over it). We had a quick lunch - tasty soups and bread - while the clouds were racing around us. As the weather cleared up we made our first start at hiking the Panorama Trail.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29796027006/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="What&#x27;s that mountain there?"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7507/29796027006_3e75cd3a26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="What&#x27;s that mountain there?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688676802/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="There I was the other day!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7735/27688676802_c1c71fc283_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="There I was the other day!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29796022696/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Back in the mist"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8402/29796022696_f80bf30fe4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back in the mist" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But then the clouds and rain came back, and so we turned around to sit it out. Good thing the restaurant has a very nice playing corner where the kids could entertain themselves =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29205364873/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Playground"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8348/29205364873_a68dd68e37_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Playground" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Then the weather cleared up again and we made our second try. With rain jackets on we left the Restaurant and hiked up the narrow, washed-out trail while a little creek was flowing down. Blue sky started to gain the upper hand and the grey rain clouds moved on to other places.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29831354255/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Clearing up"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8528/29831354255_4688f96fa0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Clearing up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748741131/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Bodensee"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8007/29748741131_a681170dde_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bodensee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748741611/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Helping Hand"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8296/29748741611_ef606a7083_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Helping Hand" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The views on the trail are simply outstanding: Even on this cloudy day you could see the Alps in Switzerland, the commanding Kanisfluh which is the landmark peak of the Bregenzerwald, to the north over the low, lovely foothills of the Alps, the Allgäu and Lake Constance, and then to imposing mountains to the south. 
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748743091/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Bodensee views"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8491/29748743091_0b35ede8a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bodensee views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The trail was great for kids, always interesting - from Paragliders that were taking off to sheep - and kept our son in high spirits throughout the hike.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748743501/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Inside the Chapel"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8549/29748743501_de015822f1_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Inside the Chapel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We had a look into the pretty Alpe Niedere chapel which was relatively new before we made the climb back towards the Restaurant and the cable car station. After an ice cream and Germknödel walked over to the cable car station and made the last cable car back to Bezau. This is a great and easy afternoon or morning out for a family with kids, even in moody weather. We felt it had all you need for a family hike: Easy access, good food for kids, a spacious changing room, an interesting trail which isn’t too long and stunning scenery.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27700552731/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Germknödel"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7284/27700552731_b3d1ded089_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Germknödel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="one-more">One more!</h2>

<p>Yes, there was even more on this holiday and I hope to have the final instalment about food and accommodation out next week. In the meanwhile you can take a sneak peek at the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157667276500013">Vorarlberg Flickr Album</a> where you can see a lot more photos from these adventures. And if you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748752301/in/dateposted/" title="Fahrtende"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8067/29748752301_175a35a8f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fahrtende" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>¹ The Brandnertal does not belong to the Bregenzerwald region, but to the <a href="https://www.vorarlberg-alpenregion.at/en/">Alpenregion Bludenz</a> which is also part of Vorarlber.</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>I thank Tourism Vorarlberg for the invitation to their region. They helped with getting there, accommodation and activities, but as always this does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Family Adventures in Vorarlberg]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/09/family-adventures-in-vorarlberg.html"/>
    <updated>2016-09-13T23:45:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/09/family-adventures-in-vorarlberg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hiking to see the sun rise in the mountains, petting lovely goats, driving on a narrow gauge train and visiting the superb inatura museum - there’s plenty of adventures to be had for old &amp; young in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/06/impressions-from-the-bregenzerwald-in-vorarlberg-austria.html">Bregenzerwald</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29024562754/in/dateposted/" title="Almost at the summit"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8256/29024562754_862a199ca5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Almost at the summit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="a-ride-with-the-wlderbhnle">A Ride with the Wälderbähnle</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://waelderbaehnle.at">Wälderbähnle</a> is what puts big smiles on kids’ faces - and adults if they’re trainspotters! My son is a big, big railroad fan and the possibility to ride on a train in great mountain scenery was a highlight for him. From the moment he woke up until we finally went to the railway station he was asking about it, and then it finally was time to climb aboard our carriage and enjoy the journey.</p>

<p>The Wälderbähnle offers two different rides: One with an old Diesel engine which runs most often and the more rare Steam Engine which pulls the eight or so carriages - including a Café! - from Bezau to Schwarzenberg through the beautiful mountains of the Bregenzerwald. We were pulled by the red Diesel engine and took a look at the Steam engine in the halls of the railway station of Bezau as we were back. It’s a short ride - the from Bezau to Schwarzenberg and back takes a bit over an hour, this includes the engine switching from one side to the other one when it goes back. All along the way you could see the mountains, crossed the Bregenzer Ache river and passed cows which were enjoying the fresh grass on the meadows along the tracks.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29360205760/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Sonderzug"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8500/29360205760_45be850d44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sonderzug" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29539881442/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Checking out the views"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8533/29539881442_b09c1b885d_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Checking out the views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688674862/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="On the narrow gauge train Wälderbähnle"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7373/27688674862_a4be77cb47_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the narrow gauge train Wälderbähnle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29539885482/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Our carriage"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8414/29539885482_229847d3bb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Our carriage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The ride was very popular with families and our carriage had at least a dozen kids between 0 and 12 in it - and as Kids under six are free of charge it’s not expensive either. You buy your ticket at the railway station in Bezau before you jump on the train, although you can <a href="http://waelderbaehnle.at/fahrplanbetrieb-preise-2016">reserve a ticket online</a> too, which is probably recommended for the days when the steam engine pulls the train.</p>

<h2 id="hiking-around-mellau">Hiking around Mellau</h2>

<p>We stayed with the Family Wüstner in Mellau, at one of their <a href="http://appartements-wuestner.at">Apartments</a> which were great for a family of four. Mellau is a small village which has everything we needed: A Supermarket for grocery shopping, very frequent bus connections to any place in the region, a cable car up the mountain, bike rentals and outdoor shops, plenty of Cafés &amp; restaurants and last, but certainly not least: A big hiking trail network. Right in front of our house started the Flusswege Path which runs along the Bregenzer Ache and explains on pretty info boards about the flora &amp; fauna of the river. At the end of the path you also can make a short stroll over to the impressive waterfall and then head back to Mellau, where one of the nice Cafés is waiting to help you with a good serving of coffee &amp; strudel =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29024548784/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Hiking along the Bregenzer Ache"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8462/29024548784_e0c318f7c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking along the Bregenzer Ache" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29615629736/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Hiking along the Bregenzer Ache"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8054/29615629736_fccbc76bbe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking along the Bregenzer Ache" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29615630776/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Hiking along the Bregenzer Ache"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8376/29615630776_29ce974540_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking along the Bregenzer Ache" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29615667256/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Coffee!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8188/29615667256_7697f927fb_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Coffee!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I also stole away for an evening hike up towards the Gopfberg, and again the trail started pretty much in front of our house. It was a nice walk up into the dusk and once I reached the start of the forest after all the meadows I was tempted to make a run for the summit and back, but without a headlamp on me I decided it’s smarter to simply stroll back down and watch the night fall over the small village. There is, however, the possibility to walk around the Gopfberg, something I want to do on my next trip there!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29360205020/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Evening hike above Mellau"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8022/29360205020_ede3f1d802_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Evening hike above Mellau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29024576514/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Evening hike above Mellau"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8545/29024576514_6f2454e764_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Evening hike above Mellau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29026413643/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Evening hike above Mellau"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8322/29026413643_7d3831b4b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Evening hike above Mellau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="a-visit-to-metzler-naturhautnah">A Visit to Metzler Naturhautnah</h2>

<p>When it rained just too much for a hiking trip we went and visited <a href="https://www.molkeprodukte.com">Metzler Naturhautnah</a>, a dairy farm with 100 goats and 20 cows which also produces cosmetics from the whey. We got a guided tour of the dairy and saw how tasty cheese was made, petted the goats in their adventure playground stable and then also tasted the delicious cheeses.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29026415093/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Goats!"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8285/29026415093_0f2bfec54b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Goats!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>From the bus stop in Egg it is a short walk up to the farm of Family Metzler. It lays scenically up a hill with a great view of the mountains, and the buildings themselves are also aesthetically very pleasing to look at, the big stables being constructed from wood in a modern design. The tour started at the shop where the daughter in law welcomed us and showed us around, answering all our questions about cheese making, goats and cosmetic products. ly stopped, too, and so we walked through the wet and cloudy hills down to catch our bus back to Mellau =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29026415553/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Metzler Hautnah products"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8328/29026415553_5a469b1f7a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Metzler Hautnah products" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We then continued to the stable where we spent some quality time with the lovely goats, petting them and looking how they “played” around. This was great for our son, as nowadays it isn’t so often that you can get up close and friendly with a goat and other animals. Hungry we continued to the pretty Conference room slash Café where we had a super-tasty cheese lunch, with almost a dozen different cheeses and fresh bread. Once it was time to leave the rain happi</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29026414573/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Making cheese at Metzler Hautnah"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8523/29026414573_f2e29f55d7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Making cheese at Metzler Hautnah" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29360219420/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Cheese lunch at Metzler Hautnah"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8462/29360219420_0a205bd130_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cheese lunch at Metzler Hautnah" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29024553954/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Dreamy goat"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8423/29024553954_2706b51e3f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dreamy goat" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="inatura-museum">Inatura Museum</h2>

<p>The next morning it was again raining hard. Happily we had another rainy-day alternative on our list: A visit to the <a href="http://www.inatura.at/home/">inatura Erlebnis Naturschau Museum</a>. Situated in Dornbirn¹ it was an hour bus ride from Mellau to get there, but with the great local bus system it meant we jumped on just one bus and get out in Dornbirn an hour later!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29569577291/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Innatura Museum"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8088/29569577291_dd889afc82_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Innatura Museum" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Located in an old factory the museum is from the outside and inside a real pearl and such a great place to visit that we really enjoyed our time in it. From the temporary exhibition about beavers to the five permanent exhibitions, the inatura is a museum which wets the appetite of old &amp; young for knowledge and which encourages its visitors to touch and try things; especially in the Sciences Zones which one finds throughout the buildings you can see how magnetism works, play with cog wheels and see lots of fish swim happily in big tanks. Add in a nice Café, friendly &amp; helpful staff and you have a great destination to spend a rainy day and keep the kids happy!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29024553444/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Innatura Museum"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8196/29024553444_6af0710c4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Innatura Museum" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29026419613/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Innatura Museum"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/8/7576/29026419613_769c2a4c67_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Innatura Museum" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29569573581/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Innatura Museum"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8510/29569573581_9eb75ee4d6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Innatura Museum" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29615676076/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Innatura Museum Sciences Stations"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8374/29615676076_f25a6ffbe7_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Innatura Museum Sciences Stations" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29615676906/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Innatura Museum"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8357/29615676906_69e0009c84_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Innatura Museum" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29569578961/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Innatura Museum"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8359/29569578961_8a4d22e3bb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Innatura Museum" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sunrise-hike-up-the-kanisfluh">Sunrise hike up the Kanisfluh</h2>

<p>Wednesday: Rain.
<br />Thursday: Rain. 
<br />Friday: Sunshine.</p>

<p>I guess that means I will get up at 2:30 am so I can watch the sun rise from the summit of the Kanisfluh, the landmark of the Bregenzerwald. I have seen the impressive mountain every day from Mellau &amp; our adventures there, and was eager to pay the summit a visit to enjoy the vast views from the summit. Combining it with the best light of the day was a no-brainer, and so I sneaked out of the apartment while the family continued to sleep. In the middle of the night I met mountain guide Matthias and my fellow sunrise hikers at the Tourist Office in Mellau; then we squeezed into Matthias’ car to ride to the other side of the mountain where our hike would start.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29026430193/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Darkness over the valley"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8601/29026430193_e732258f49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Darkness over the valley" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29569587891/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Up in the light"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8061/29569587891_5761c00c78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up in the light" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The stars were still out when we set off from the car, but it wasn’t long until that magic light of pre-dawn started to arrive and colour the sky into the prettiest pastel colours.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29569588801/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Matthias leading the way"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8534/29569588801_28d0eec9a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Matthias leading the way" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29569589401/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="That morning colour"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7561/29569589401_8065bcf6fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="That morning colour" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We reached the summit cross a mere 45 minutes after we started hiking and weren’t the only ones up there who were waiting for the sun to rise. A group of friends  which set off way before us was shivering at the cross, waiting for the warm rays of the sun to warm them up. I slipped into my puffy jacket, took my camera and looked for the best angles.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29650830395/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Not alone"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8378/29650830395_77a280a624_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Not alone" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then the sun came.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29024563664/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Sunrise"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7554/29024563664_3e538de954_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunrise" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We watched fascinated as the sun rose slowly over the horizon, and pastel colours slowly gave way to oranges and yellows, but before long the light of day was around us. Matthias shared a zip from his flask, and then it was time to start the descent.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29024562294/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Way down"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8891/29024562294_9fd6505fca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Way down" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29024558474/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Berghütte"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8070/29024558474_225863f991_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Berghütte" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>While it would have been tempting to eat breakfast on the mountain hut close to our car I promised my family to be back for breakfast, and low &amp; behold: As I arrived back at the apartment with fresh, warm rolls from the supermarket the kids were just getting up. Over breakfast we were pondering what we should do on this beautiful, sunny day together!</p>

<h2 id="want-more">Want more?</h2>

<p>There was more on this holiday and I hope to have the next instalment out next week. In the meanwhile you can take a sneak peek at the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157667276500013">Vorarlberg Flickr Album</a> where you can see a lot more photos from these adventures and those yet to come. And if you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29615685566/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Happiness"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8577/29615685566_31ac0cbac1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happiness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>¹ Dornbirn belongs to the <a href="http://www.bodensee-vorarlberg.com/en/">Bodensee-Vorarlberg</a> Region in Vorarlberg, and is just a wee bit in front of the Bregenzerwald Region.</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>I thank Tourism Vorarlberg for the invitation to their region. They helped with getting there, accommodation and activities, but as always this does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions from the Bregenzerwald in Vorarlberg, Austria]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/06/impressions-from-the-bregenzerwald-in-vorarlberg-austria.html"/>
    <updated>2016-06-20T20:16:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/06/impressions-from-the-bregenzerwald-in-vorarlberg-austria</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to take my family on holidays to Austria so I could share my passion for the mountains with them. While it rained unreasonably much, we still had a great time and enjoyed the mountains, hills and meadows of the Bregenzerwald in Austria.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688672802/in/dateposted/" title="Lonely sunrise watcher on the Kanisfluh"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7119/27688672802_8b36462c1a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="648" alt="Lonely sunrise watcher on the Kanisfluh" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688670752/in/dateposted/" title="Clouds over Mellau"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7686/27688670752_9189f50266_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Clouds over Mellau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The clouds would hang a lot over the local hills of Mellau, the small village where we stayed.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688670432/in/dateposted/" title="Along the River Trail in Mellau"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7708/27688670432_62a13f3199_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Along the River Trail in Mellau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On our first day in the area we had some nice, hot sunshine in the morning, though.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688674862/in/dateposted/" title="On the narrow gauge train Wälderbähnle"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7373/27688674862_a4be77cb47_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the narrow gauge train Wälderbähnle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And we rode on a narrow-gauge train, which our son loved.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688672042/in/dateposted/" title="Innatura Museum, Dornbirn"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7427/27688672042_436fe8b22a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Innatura Museum, Dornbirn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>When there was no end in sight of the epic downpour we took the bus to Dornbirn and visited the superb innatura museum, which we all enjoyed heaps.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688673862/in/dateposted/" title="Goats at Metzler Naturhautnah"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7189/27688673862_c460efc799_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Goats at Metzler Naturhautnah" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On another rainy day we visited the cheese and cosmetics manufacturer Metzler Naturhautnah, got to pet goats and eat their delicious cheeses.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688677472/in/dateposted/" title="Natursprünge Weg Brandnertal"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7352/27688677472_de2c35c4c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Natursprünge Weg Brandnertal" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the next sunny day we went on the Natursprünge Trail in the Brander Valley close by where the views were superb.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688671282/in/dateposted/" title="Frööd"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7215/27688671282_21857a6a06_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Frööd" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It was tempting to just sit in the sun and drink tasty drinks that day, for sure!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688676152/in/dateposted/" title="Barefoot Trail Bizau"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/8/7296/27688676152_a182827560_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Barefoot Trail Bizau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Rain and clouds didn’t stop us to go barefoot hiking in Bizau, either.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688675722/in/dateposted/" title="Kässpätzle at Jadggasthaus Egender, Schönenbach"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7469/27688675722_96b71c5617_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kässpätzle at Jadggasthaus Egender, Schönenbach" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Especially if you can eat Kässpätzle afterwards and sit out the rain =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688675332/in/dateposted/" title="The rain is coming"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7255/27688675332_a7e43d7d3b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The rain is coming" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And even in the rain we took the gondola up the local mountain and enjoyed the cloudy views. More on all of these wee family adventures soon here on the blog. But if you can’t wait for the trip report you can view more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157667276500013">Flickr Album</a> or check my photos on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> account for a whole bunch of photos and anecdotes!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27688673122/in/dateposted/" title="Traditional houses"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7323/27688673122_872c73ca59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Traditional houses" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I thank Tourism Vorarlberg for the invitation to their region. They helped with getting there, accommodation and activities, but as always this does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
