<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: how does it taste | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/how-does-it-taste/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-11-20T10:16:42+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Does It Taste? Ambronite Supermeal]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/10/how-does-it-taste-ambronite-supermeal.html"/>
    <updated>2017-10-30T16:32:51+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/10/how-does-it-taste-ambronite-supermeal</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the fourth Episode of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/how-does-it-taste/">How Does It Taste?</a> the stove stays cold and I try an Ambronite Supermeal Shake!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38011092551/in/photostream/" title="Ambronite Snack Portions"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4510/38011092551_ac0df2000b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ambronite Snack Portions" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with food by Ambronite. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>I have tried <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/01/the-ambronite-supermeal-diet.html">Ambronite</a> last year (check out the short hair &amp; beard!) and did so in not the intended way. This time around I’m smarter, Ambronite updated their recipe <em>AND</em> introduced three new flavours <em>AND</em> added smaller pouches to their offerings which makes it more attractive to the outdoorsy person. <a href="https://youtu.be/09kMJLEYJW8">Watch the video</a> to see how I like this meal:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/09kMJLEYJW8?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>In short:</strong> I still think all the vitamins, minerals, protein and other healthy stuff in Ambronite make it a smart <em>addition</em> to a normal (freeze-dried/ dehydrated) backpacking diet. If I look at my own backpacking diet, which consists of a MYOG Müsli &amp; Coffee for breakfast, a couple of Müsli and Chocolate Bars for lunch, and a Main Meal for Dinner I see room for improvement when it comes to the stuff I usually eat at home (Smoothies, quite a lot of fruit and vegetables). As carrying vegetables and fruits into the outdoors is from a weight-perspective not smart (unless dehydrated) Ambronite Supermeal with it’s full load of <em>healthy stuff</em> is a really smart way to get those things your body needs to perform at its best. The taste is better than the version I tried last year - Ambronite tweaked the recipe a bit - and given that it is Vegan and mostly made up of organic ingredients there’s really not much which should keep most people from at least trying Ambronite. And if you’re now curious: You can try 4 <a href="https://eu.ambronite.com/hikinginfinland">Ambronite Supermeals</a> for the price of 1 if you follow that link - in my opinion the perfect way to test it and see if you like the taste of it!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26234909929/in/photostream/" title="Shaken, not stirred!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4480/26234909929_dfe02e495c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shaken, not stirred!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed the 4th Episode of <strong>How Does It Taste?</strong> you should subscribe to my <a href="http://youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube Channel</a> and <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> (because I love coffee!). In case you didn’t know: I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to see what I’m up to between writing blog posts and filming videos!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Does It Taste? Trek'N Eat Balkan Risotto]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/10/how-does-it-taste-trekneat-balkan-risotto.html"/>
    <updated>2017-10-17T09:24:54+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/10/how-does-it-taste-trekneat-balkan-risotto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the third Episode of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/how-does-it-taste/">How Does It Taste?</a> I try the Balkan Risotto from Trek’N Eat.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23896044348/in/dateposted/" title="Trek&#x27;N Eat Balkan Risotto II"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4480/23896044348_95a749c7b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trek&#x27;N Eat Balkan Risotto II" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with food by Katadyn. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>Oh, how I love the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/snow-and-sunshine-on-the-via-dinarica.html">Balkans</a> and their tasty food! I have very fond memories of Kenan cooking up some excellent meals on our Via Dinarica hikes, so trying the Balkan Risotto from Trek’N Eat should be like a trip down memory lane. This is the first meat meal I’m eating in the <em>How Does It Taste?</em> Series, and I do like me some meaty meals after a long day on the trail or when I was out mountaineering. <a href="https://youtu.be/4jBr_W4iGi4">Watch the video</a> to see how I like this meal:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4jBr_W4iGi4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>In short:</strong> This is a very good backpacking meal that’s pretty neutral in taste - there’s nothing that dominates and in a time where you can get very salty or very spicy foods it is nice to test a meal that is more neutral and fills your belly with good, natural ingredients. It’s a bit heavy maybe at 190 g and I find the package design a wee bit untidy, but as Trek’N Eat is updating the design for 2018 I imagine this will be a thing of the past. If you’re now curious about the Balkan Risotto you can buy it directly from <a href="https://www.trekneat.com/en/de/108-8018568-tne-balkan-risotto">Trek’N Eat</a> or at the <a href="https://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/en/beef/37-balkan-risotto-by-trekn-eat-4015753185689.html">Outdoor Food Shop</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37039558864/in/dateposted/" title="Trek&#x27;N Eat Balkan Risotto - Guten Appetit!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4464/37039558864_cc5fd70a03_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trek&#x27;N Eat Balkan Risotto - Guten Appetit!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed the 3rd Episode of <strong>How Does It Taste?</strong> you should subscribe to my <a href="http://youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube Channel</a> and <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> (because I love coffee!). In case you didn’t know: I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Does It Taste? Lyofood Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/how-does-it-taste-lyofood-barley-lentils-risotto-with-avocado-mousse.html"/>
    <updated>2017-07-24T19:42:14+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/how-does-it-taste-lyofood-barley-lentils-risotto-with-avocado-mousse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the second Episode of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/how-does-it-taste/">How Does It Taste?</a> I test again a Vegan meal, this time LYO Food’s Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35737991450/in/dateposted/" title="LYO Food Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4310/35737991450_f7053654aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="LYO Food Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with food by LYO Food. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>One can’t eat enough healthy food. Sure, we all might fantasize after several days on the trail about Pizza or Hamburgers, but when you arrive at your camping spot or the belay ledge half-way through the wall what your body really need is a tasty &amp; healthy portion of food. And the Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse from LYO Food is exactly that. <a href="https://youtu.be/EB2p6nyQx5M">Watch the video</a> to see how this vegan meal tastes:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EB2p6nyQx5M" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>In short:</strong> This is the most tasty vegan backpacking meal I have tried yet. Excellently spiced with a nice crunch from the barley and lentils this is a meal I could always eat anywhere and if you’d served it to me on a plate in a Restaurant I wouldn’t doubt that a Chef would have made it in the kitchen for me. The only downside I can think of is that it packs only 433 kcal for the 110 g pouch which might be to little after a hard day outdoors, but other than that I find this an excellent meal. If you’re now curious about the Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse you can buy it directly from <a href="https://lyofood.com/collections/main-meals/products/barley-lentils-risotto-with-avocado-mousse">LYO Food</a> or at the <a href="https://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/de/vegane-outdoornahrung/193-graupen-linsen-risotto-avocado-lyofood-5902768107647.html">Outdoor Food Shop</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35288475724/in/dateposted/" title="Ready to start boiling &amp; eating"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4301/35288475724_b09b46338b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Ready to start boiling &amp; eating" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35288474144/in/dateposted/" title="How does the Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse taste?"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4307/35288474144_dfeb9885a6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="How does the Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse taste?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed the 2nd Episode of <strong>How Does It Taste?</strong> you should subscribe to my <a href="http://youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube Channel</a> and <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> (because I love coffee!). In case you didn’t know: I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Does It Taste? - Firepot Dal and Rice with Spinach]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/how-does-it-taste-firepot-dal-and-rice-with-spinach.html"/>
    <updated>2017-07-17T22:41:12+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/how-does-it-taste-firepot-dal-and-rice-with-spinach</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the first Episode of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/how-does-it-taste/">How Does It Taste?</a> I test a Vegan meal from the new UK Brand Firepot: Dal and Rice with Spinach.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35147389234/in/dateposted/" title="Firepot Dal and Rice with Spinach"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4322/35147389234_5c9d38b6b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Firepot Dal and Rice with Spinach" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with food by Firepot. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>I like vegetarian food. Sure, I don’t say know to a good piece of cheese or some fresh reindeer meat, but if I can choose I always go vegetarian. Truth be told, I’m pondering since years to make the jump and go plant-based in my nutrition. So when I was talking with Firepot about testing their meals (and I tested them all!) it was an easy choice for me to pick their vegan backpacking meal for my video review. There are simply not many (good) vegan options available if you do not want to make the meals yourself, and as an increasing number of backpackers, climbers, cyclists and runners go without meat &amp; dairy I felt it’s a good idea to test Firepot’s vegan meal. Watch the video to see how I like Dal and Rice with Spinach:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TFIJ8rN3Mrs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>In short</strong>: I think it’s a great Vegan meal for outdoor persons. The right mix of spices which let the other ingredients come through, and if you love lentils like I do you won’t be disappointed. Salt is a personal taste and while I find it could do with a bit more of it, I reckon Northern Europeans who generally use less salt in their food will find it just fine. All in all a nice addition to the vegan meal options for plant-powered outdoor persons of all kind. If you’d like to try Dal and Rice with Spinach you can order it directly from <a href="https://www.outdoorfood.com/collections/firepot-dehydrated-meals/products/dal-and-rice-with-spinach?variant=35639591306">Firepot</a> in the UK or from the <a href="https://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/en/vegan/710-daln-rice-w-spinach-by-firepot-5060517780043.html?search_query=firepot&amp;results=5">OutdoorFoodShop</a> in Germany.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this first Episode of <strong>How Does It Taste?</strong> you should subscribe to my <a href="http://youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube Channel</a> and <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> (because I love coffee!). In case you didn’t know: I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
