<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: how does it taste | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/blog/categories/how-does-it-taste/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-18T15:39:54+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Does It Taste? Lyofood Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/2017/07/how-does-it-taste-lyofood-barley-lentils-risotto-with-avocado-mousse.html"/>
    <updated>2017-07-24T19:42:14+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/2017/07/how-does-it-taste-lyofood-barley-lentils-risotto-with-avocado-mousse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the second Episode of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/how-does-it-taste/">How Does It Taste?</a> I test again a Vegan meal, this time LYO Food’s Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35737991450/in/dateposted/" title="LYO Food Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4310/35737991450_f7053654aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="LYO Food Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with food by LYO Food. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>One can’t eat enough healthy food. Sure, we all might fantasize after several days on the trail about Pizza or Hamburgers, but when you arrive at your camping spot or the belay ledge half-way through the wall what your body really need is a tasty &amp; healthy portion of food. And the Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse from LYO Food is exactly that. <a href="https://youtu.be/EB2p6nyQx5M">Watch the video</a> to see how this vegan meal tastes:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EB2p6nyQx5M" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>In short:</strong> This is the most tasty vegan backpacking meal I have tried yet. Excellently spiced with a nice crunch from the barley and lentils this is a meal I could always eat anywhere and if you’d served it to me on a plate in a Restaurant I wouldn’t doubt that a Chef would have made it in the kitchen for me. The only downside I can think of is that it packs only 433 kcal for the 110 g pouch which might be to little after a hard day outdoors, but other than that I find this an excellent meal. If you’re now curious about the Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse you can buy it directly from <a href="https://lyofood.com/collections/main-meals/products/barley-lentils-risotto-with-avocado-mousse">LYO Food</a> or at the <a href="https://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/de/vegane-outdoornahrung/193-graupen-linsen-risotto-avocado-lyofood-5902768107647.html">Outdoor Food Shop</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35288475724/in/dateposted/" title="Ready to start boiling &amp; eating"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4301/35288475724_b09b46338b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Ready to start boiling &amp; eating" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35288474144/in/dateposted/" title="How does the Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse taste?"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4307/35288474144_dfeb9885a6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="How does the Barley-Lentils-Risotto with Avocado Mousse taste?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed the 2nd Episode of <strong>How Does It Taste?</strong> you should subscribe to my <a href="http://youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube Channel</a> and <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> (because I love coffee!). In case you didn’t know: I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Does It Taste? - Firepot Dal and Rice with Spinach]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/2017/07/how-does-it-taste-firepot-dal-and-rice-with-spinach.html"/>
    <updated>2017-07-17T22:41:12+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com/hikinginfinland/2017/07/how-does-it-taste-firepot-dal-and-rice-with-spinach</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the first Episode of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/how-does-it-taste/">How Does It Taste?</a> I test a Vegan meal from the new UK Brand Firepot: Dal and Rice with Spinach.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35147389234/in/dateposted/" title="Firepot Dal and Rice with Spinach"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4322/35147389234_5c9d38b6b8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Firepot Dal and Rice with Spinach" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with food by Firepot. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>I like vegetarian food. Sure, I don’t say know to a good piece of cheese or some fresh reindeer meat, but if I can choose I always go vegetarian. Truth be told, I’m pondering since years to make the jump and go plant-based in my nutrition. So when I was talking with Firepot about testing their meals (and I tested them all!) it was an easy choice for me to pick their vegan backpacking meal for my video review. There are simply not many (good) vegan options available if you do not want to make the meals yourself, and as an increasing number of backpackers, climbers, cyclists and runners go without meat &amp; dairy I felt it’s a good idea to test Firepot’s vegan meal. Watch the video to see how I like Dal and Rice with Spinach:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TFIJ8rN3Mrs" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>In short</strong>: I think it’s a great Vegan meal for outdoor persons. The right mix of spices which let the other ingredients come through, and if you love lentils like I do you won’t be disappointed. Salt is a personal taste and while I find it could do with a bit more of it, I reckon Northern Europeans who generally use less salt in their food will find it just fine. All in all a nice addition to the vegan meal options for plant-powered outdoor persons of all kind. If you’d like to try Dal and Rice with Spinach you can order it directly from <a href="https://www.outdoorfood.com/collections/firepot-dehydrated-meals/products/dal-and-rice-with-spinach?variant=35639591306">Firepot</a> in the UK or from the <a href="https://www.outdoorfoodshop.de/en/vegan/710-daln-rice-w-spinach-by-firepot-5060517780043.html?search_query=firepot&amp;results=5">OutdoorFoodShop</a> in Germany.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this first Episode of <strong>How Does It Taste?</strong> you should subscribe to my <a href="http://youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube Channel</a> and <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> (because I love coffee!). In case you didn’t know: I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
