<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hiking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/hiking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2022-10-03T14:16:05+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Planning your first Hike (Post COVID-19)]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/planning-your-first-hike.html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-23T09:13:28+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/planning-your-first-hike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Five weeks in self-distancing Mode, and many of us are sitting at home with itchy feet: When can we go hiking &amp; camping again? I’m using this time to think about &amp; plan the future hikes I wanna do, once the lockdown is lifted!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812710111/in/dateposted-public/" title="Planning!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812710111_6d4b456c63_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Planning!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Nothing to disclose here, except some Affiliate links 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>Air traffic is now 29% of what it was pre-COVID-19, trains and busses are also substantially less frequent, cars are standing at home unused, and on the other side you have National Parks, Wilderness Areas and our beautiful outdoors which is recovering, with animals appearing where they previously have been seen long ago and air pollution in cities is dropping, too. At home we also get busy thinking about the outdoors, and our post-poned outdoor adventures. I’m no different, and while I am sad about the cancelled ski trips this spring, I’m looking forward to the hiking, packrafting and bikepacking trips in the not-too-distant future!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812125413/in/dateposted-public/" title="Planning"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812125413_7ab1c1908b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Planning" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now, as I expect that planes will remain grounded (AMAZING for the environment and our #ClimateCrisis) I will continue to travel more by train and bus. I love to travel by train: You can walk around while the train rides, eat in the train restaurant when you get hungry, play games, the kids can jump around on the playground in the kids waggon, there’s functional toilets which are not the size of a shoebox, watch movies on Youtube or surf the internet, and one of the best things: Simply watch out of the window and observe the environment which passes you by. In Europe you can get quickly and affordably to most corners of the continent, and where the train tracks stop there’s usually a bus waiting to take you to the next destination.</p>

<p><em>By the way: <a href="http://tidd.ly/c0da99e4">Click this link</a> to win TWO Interrail tickets worth 800€ for when the lockdown is lifted and you can travel again!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812681426/in/dateposted-public/" title="ScotsRail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812681426_f61a95f083_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ScotsRail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, I currently also am stuck at home (relaxing while <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCwYqDhtJj1x3DXy4IPCxL2A/">painting tabletop Miniatures and terrain</a>) and besides the occasional day hike with the family or cycling along the coast I am already pondering where to go in the summer and autumn. It’s very, very likely in Finland, with small chances of heading to close-by Norway and Sweden, but unlikely to be further away. <strong>But hey!</strong> <strong>Finland is AWESOME!</strong> Beautiful, crystal-clear lakes for paddling, amazing forests full of tasty bilberries, soft trails and great camping spots, and once autumn comes by the beautiful colours of nature will delight us!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30173126067/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Bilberry fields forever!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1973/30173126067_f98ebaaf9c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bilberry fields forever!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The best thing that you can do right now, if you’re under lockdown and can not go wild camping, is to plan that next trip. <em>Anticipation is the greatest joy</em>, as we say in German. Get in a great mood by taking out your wish list of local, national trails you wanna hike or cycle, grab some maps and start planning. And not just the hike, also on how you get there (also if schedules might not yet be that reliable, so keep that in mind) - and remember my chorus of praise for trains above 😉 And as you have had to post-pone a few hikes, maybe also stay at a local B&amp;B or Hostel at the end of your backpacking trip, as a warm shower and a tasty meal before travelling home is what you deserve, and the local entrepreneurs will be grateful for your support after months of empty rooms.</p>

<p>That’s it. Planning that next hike helps you keep a positive outlook on this situation, and going over maps and pondering what to eat (and maybe ordering already some food for that trip) helps you to spend your time productively instead of watching Netflix. Maybe plan a hike that is 90% off-trail! Or a hike which visits all the sights you wanted to visit &amp; see already since a long time! Or a hike where you come out at a great Pizza place at the end 🍕 🤗 Right now there’s enough time to plan that next hike in great detail, and get the food &amp; supplies you need for it, so that when you can get back outdoors, <strong>you are ready!</strong></p>

<p>In that sense: Stay healthy, wash your hands and plan that next outdoor trip!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49805426157/in/dateposted-public/" title="Bushbuddy Ultra"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49805426157_e3a1f70c0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Bushbuddy Ultra" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WRIGHTSOCK Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/02/wrightsock-review.html"/>
    <updated>2020-02-26T19:07:05+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/02/wrightsock-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No more blisters when hiking and skiing, and good-bye sweaty feet? Sounds too good to be true? Then read on to find out if WRIGHTSOCK socks can keep their promises!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591465078/in/dateposted-public/" title="Bushbuddy Ultra + WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591465078_2c0367097a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bushbuddy Ultra + WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This review was supported financially and with socks from WRIGHTSOCK. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>I found the WRIGHTSOCK Escape and Merino Stride socks good for hiking and every-day use, but got blisters on my shins when using the Merino Coolmesh II otc socks for skiing. When hiking and in normal use I didn’t get any Blisters, and my feet were less sweaty, but I still had moist feet after a day of hiking. Overall I think they’re good socks for colder weather and activities where you usually get really sweaty feet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591965436/in/dateposted-public/" title="Hello, spring!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591965436_e5ea5e4f2b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hello, spring!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>My WRIGHTSOCK package arrived in late November, and contained a pair of COOLMESH II Merino, ESCAPE crew and MERINO STRIDE crew, all in Size Large (which fits feet between 41,5 and 45). They have been used all for several weeks, mostly for day hikes and normal, every-day use.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49592209382/in/dateposted-public/" title="A package of WRIGHTSOCK socks!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49592209382_0542d0f3e8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A package of WRIGHTSOCK socks!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The function of a sock is to absorb perspiration (= sweat!) as your feet are one of the biggest producers of sweat. Socks help to absorb the sweat from your feet and transport it to areas where air can evaporate the perspiration. And in cold weather, socks should insulate the foot and keep it toasty.</p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<ul>
  <li>All of the WRIGHTSOCK socks I tested were at least partly made from Dri-Wright, which is a Polyester fibre. Polyester dries quickly and keeps it shape/ form well, hence it is a good material for socks.</li>
  <li>All socks have an inner and outer layer, this construction is supposed to protect from blisters and help you keep dry feet</li>
  <li>Some of the socks I tested also had a Merino wool layer/ fabric, which made them less smelly and warmer</li>
  <li>And all socks also had a “stabilization zone” knitted into the metatarsal area</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49592208062/in/dateposted-public/" title="Merino Stride socks"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49592208062_b86754082d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Merino Stride socks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591962146/in/dateposted-public/" title="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks inside-out"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591962146_c3ed568698_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks inside-out" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The socks have held up well over the past three months and still look good. They can be washed at 40° which gets them nice and clean after a few days of use, and I expect them to hold at least another year or two of regular use.</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The weight of the socks, as a pair (so both socks!), in Size Large, are as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://wrightsockshop.de/wrightsock/sockenhoehen/otc-kniehoch/19/merino-coolmesh-ii-otc">Merino Coolmesh II otc socks</a>: 88 g</li>
  <li><a href="https://wrightsockshop.de/wrightsock/sportarten/outdoor-wandern/177/merino-stride-crew">Merino Stride socks</a>: 64 g</li>
  <li><a href="https://wrightsockshop.de/wrightsock/sportarten/outdoor-wandern/180/escape-crew">Escape socks</a>: 84 g</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I’ll look at two different use-cases here: Using the Merino Coolmesh II otc socks for skiing and using the Escape and Merino Stride socks for hiking and every-day use. Lets start with skiing and the Merino Coolmesh II otc socks. I sweat a LOT when I ski, and it doesn’t matter if it is skitouring and skinning up a mountain or just riding the whole day in the front country - I have soaking wet socks after a day on skis. I used the Merino Coolmesh II otc with my <a href="http://tidd.ly/5d07ff6d">La Sportiva Synchro</a> in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/02/father-son-ski-trip.html">Ruka</a> for two days, and already after the first day I had a strange feeling on my shins, but didn’t pay any attention to it. That was a mistake.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547590647/in/dateposted-public/" title="DPS Cassiar 87"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547590647_7d16bb5e33_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Cassiar 87" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591466298/in/dateposted-public/" title="Merino Coolmesh II otc socks"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591466298_f76f4d55d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Merino Coolmesh II otc socks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the second day on the slopes I had on each leg a big blister on my shins. I never had blisters on my shins, ever before, so you can imagine I was really surprised to find blisters on my legs from using socks which claim they don’t give you blisters! Needless to say, I didn’t use the socks for skiing after that anymore, and would not use the socks for skiing ever again. This is even more surprising as I was literally only downhill skiing, in a light boot which was fastened as usual. On the plus side, my feet were slightly less sweaty, but they still were moist when I took the socks off.</p>

<p>Which brings me to the Escape and Merino Stride socks, which I used for hiking and in everyday use. Currently we have the shittiest winter ever and no snow, but temps still drop down to -11°C or more in the mornings, and only slowly it rises throughout the day. In this weather these socks have been really good, and they kept my feet toasty and warm, even if I wore less warm shoes like the new <a href="http://tidd.ly/e9815221">Black Diamond Mission LT</a> shoes (I usually wear in the colder months the <a href="http://tidd.ly/ed40ce05">La Sportiva Crossover 2.0</a>). The Merino Stride socks are ideal for daily use as they can dry nicely inside, and they are toasty warm outside in the cold weather. The Escape is also great, though maybe a tiny bit less warm. Overall, as this are double-layer socks, they are warmer than other socks of a comparable weight, as in between the layers air is trapped, which helps keep your feet warm.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49592210972/in/dateposted-public/" title="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks + Black Diamond Mission LT"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49592210972_99ca71d410_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks + Black Diamond Mission LT" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Two things, though: I usually never get Blisters anymore as I use good shoes for hiking, backpacking, trailrunning and in every-day use, so I can not say that the claim of not getting Blisters when hiking with these socks works. Secondly, I still had moist feet when I took the socks off after a day outside, however, they were less sweaty than with normal socks. So while I still got sweaty feet they were less moist than with a normal pair of socks. I also liked the extra “cushioning” these socks had because of the two layers, and they also felt nice and comfortable on my feet - the white inner sock has a minimal amount of seams, which is really positive in my book.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591961861/in/dateposted-public/" title="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591961861_e98909d904_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I don’t have suggestions for improvement, to be honest.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Overall I liked the WRIGHTSOCK Escape and Merino Stride socks, and will use the Merino Coolmesh II otc socks for normal use when it’s cold, but not for skiing anymore. The Escape and Merino Stride socks are both well suited for backpacking and hiking, and the Escape sock definitely is the better pick for multi-day backpacking trips as it is made completely from synthetic materials and hence should dry faster than the Merino Stride socks. However, as most ultralight backpackers are well-used to hiking in wet footwear and hence moist socks, I think also the Merino Stride socks should be fine for backpacking. Especially if you have a problem with Blisters and really sweaty feet you might want to try these socks (<em>and please let me know if the “No Blisters System” works for you!</em>)!</p>

<script async="" src="//z0a.de/outtra-739.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=5490" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1735490" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="5490"></script>

<p><strong>Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><img src="https://173.publisher.outtra.com/226724467/87225/qM7e5yBe2v/" width="0" height="0" style="display: none;" /></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591645988/in/dateposted-public/" title="At the Beach &#x3D;)"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591645988_5c5690ca78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the Beach &#x3D;)" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wild Foods of Lapland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/wild-foods-of-lapland.html"/>
    <updated>2019-09-30T18:01:34+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/wild-foods-of-lapland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When backpacking I like to pick the treats which nature has on offer along the trail. However, this time I went out with Minna from Arctic Sky to pick berries, search for mushrooms, and then create a tasty 3-course meal out of it!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743928347/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Most awesome shrooms"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743928347_a601a7499b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Most awesome shrooms" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This trip was supported financially by the Arctic Outdoor project. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>We rolled into the <a href="https://arcticskylapland.com">Arctic Sky</a> parking lot and I immediately felt like this is a good place. Beautiful wooden buildings, a herb garden on the side, and a traditional <em>Kota</em> being built to gather in in the evenings. Minna welcomed us in, and it almost felt like I entered my own home. Minna and her partner Aarno have built this small resort - ten people can stay here – from 400 year old lumber which they picked up in southern Finland and transported here to the far North, and then continued to decorate their house and the Guesthouse in a wonderful cozy style, from the hand-made woolen socks which you can slip into at the door to the beautiful animal prints which give each of the five guest rooms their names. Yes, you can stay at Arctic Sky, but I was here for an introduction to nordic Herbs and then some searching and cooking some wild food, as part of my <a href="https://polarlifeoutdoor.com">Polarlife Outdoors</a> experience.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48826257552/in/dateposted/" title="Arctic Sky Lapland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48826257552_567c8b0f6a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Arctic Sky Lapland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48826256792/in/photostream/" title="Arctic Sky Lapland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48826256792_e98c99c47e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Arctic Sky Lapland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48826257827/in/photostream/" title="Arctic Sky Lapland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48826257827_051b09da42_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Arctic Sky Lapland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So after a look through the cozy house we shouldered our packs, grabbed each a woven basket and headed into the woods to find some Mushrooms, pick berries, and hike to a Laavu to prepare our findings into a tasty meal.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743747866/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Shrooms"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743747866_b4380edc27_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Shrooms" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743750446/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Red"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743750446_02ed691429_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Red" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743926902/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Bilberries"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743926902_e6243172ec_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Bilberries" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We hiked on the Ruijanpolku, a trail I didn’t exist, and which is a rather old and long trail. I might need to return to go backpacking on it some day in the future, but right now I was more occupied with finding tasty mushrooms and bilberries for our desert. It’s funny how I can completely can zoom-in on searching mushrooms, and the hunter &amp; gatherer in me is also one which isn’t happy with having a full basket of mushrooms - I always want to find more 😃</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743926192/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Ruijanpolku"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743926192_314866f63c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Ruijanpolku" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a very successful search for mushrooms, and learning to identify a few new ones (that is one of the benefits of going mushroom picking with someone!) we arrived at a very wonderful Laavu next to a lovely stream. We weren’t alone, though - many dayhikers enjoyed this beautiful spot, eating snacks, drinking tea, and grilling sausages. Also, I made a new friend.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743934682/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Siberian Jay"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743934682_c54826a8dd_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Siberian Jay" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>While I was busy snapping the next Konsta Punkka image Minna was busy preparing our food.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743752121/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Preparing shrooms"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743752121_1ba5987ca0_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Preparing shrooms" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The smell of mushrooms which sizzle over the fire in a pan is something so mouth-watering, just the thought of them makes me want to grab my coat and head out into the forest to go find some mushrooms!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743417398/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Tasty starter!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743417398_fae60f2fe5_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Tasty starter!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But while the mushrooms were frying in the pan we ate our starter, which we prepared ourselves from the things Minna brought along. We garnished it with some of the herbs we picked in her garden, and yes, it was as tasty as it looks!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743418023/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Even more tasty Main!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743418023_2549c115da_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Even more tasty Main!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Then it was time for the main course, our fried mushrooms were served with a vegan nettle pancake and some again we could use the different herbs we picked earlier to garnish it. These mushroom pancakes were so tasty that I ate three of them - just so much to leave some space for the dessert!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743419953/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Dessert Volume II"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743419953_65b9833a8c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Dessert Volume II" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A lingonberry mousse in a dark chocolate coat, together with a bilberry sauce which we prepared from the berries we picked along the way. Oh my, this indeed was a sweet finish to an outstanding meal! If you now feel hungry - then no worries, Minna is happy to take you out on a hike like this! When you stay with Minna and Aarno at the <a href="https://www.booking.com/hotel/fi/arctic-sky-lapland.en.html?aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">Arctic Sky Resort</a> you can pick and choose from a <a href="https://arcticskylapland.com/your-own-arctic-wellness-week">great variety of activities</a>, including the one you just read about! I definitely would recommend going with a few friends or the family, that way you can enjoy sitting in the cozy kitchen in the evenings, play some UNO or another board game, and chat while it slowly gets dark outside!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743758731/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Wood"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743758731_5c2a1e9a1b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Wood" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After all that tasty food and the hike back I got a ride to the <a href="https://www.booking.com/hotel/fi/muotka-igloos.en.html?aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">Wilderness Hotel Muotka</a>, but not to lay down and rest - nope. I did the most typical thing you can do in Finland: Going to Sauna.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48826135788/in/dateposted/" title="Sauna Timelapse"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48826135788_6662724415_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Sauna Timelapse" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743938062/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743938062_027221443c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743942342/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Sauna Stream"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743942342_701dd2e6f2_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Sauna Stream" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now while I didn’t much enjoy my river crossings in the Hammastunturi Wilderness, at Muotka I even went to swim in the stream several times! I reckon if a warm Sauna and dry clothes are waiting for you, going into a cold stream is less of an issue 😃 Obviously going to chill by a fireplace in the sun afterwards makes a dip in the cold stream even less of a problem.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48826512636/in/photostream/" title="Cozy Fireplace at Wilderness Hotel Muotka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48826512636_caf4ae0cf4_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Cozy Fireplace at Wilderness Hotel Muotka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities!</h2>

<p>I stayed in Saariselkä, which is probably <em>THE</em> place to be when you want to explore the North-Eastern corner of Finnish Lapland - or you stay at <a href="https://www.booking.com/hotel/fi/arctic-sky-lapland.en.html?aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">Arctic Sky</a> if you want to be enjoy a more silent stay. Besides a dozen or more options for accommodation options - I stayed at the <a href="https://www.booking.com/hotel/fi/lapland-riekonlinna.en.html?aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna‎</a> - the village lays right at the border of the Urho Kekkonen National Park and is just a short 2 hour stroll away from the Hammastunturi Wilderness Area. This means you don’t need a car to go outdoors in Saariselkä, as you can walk in a few minutes from your Hotel or log cabin to the start of a trail. Here’s the <a href="https://www.booking.com/searchresults.en.html?city=900040403&amp;aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1&amp;room1=A">full list of Hotels and Cabins in Saariselkä</a>, and feel free to use that Affiliate Link when you’re making a reservation!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743375433/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna Room"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743375433_e869ca2dad_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna Room" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Getting to Saariselkä happens in one of three ways: You drive your car north for a veeeeeeery long time but are mobile there. Useful if you want to drive to different places, but hopefully you’re not alone in that car! The second and best option is to take the train and Bus. Taking the Bus from Rovaniemi to Saariselkä is a short and scenic 3 hour ride, and it really gets you in the mood for the outdoors as you ride past lakes and forests and every so often slow down to let the Reindeer get off the road. Taking an (overnight) train to Rovaniemi from Southern Finland is also very convenient, as you wake up well rested and just a short ride away from your next outdoor adventure. This is also a good way to travel if you want to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki.html">explore Helsinki</a> before or after a visit in Lapland. Finally, if you come from abroad you also can fly directly to Ivalo, from where you can take a bus or Taxi to Saariselkä.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0i3st0" title="Oulu - Tromso"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48780910708_729d052bdf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Oulu - Tromso" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Saariselkä has for a village its size a variety of different options for eating out, from Anne’s Garden which serves delicious Burgers (great for backpackers who just returned to civilization!) to fine dining at Santa’s Hotel Tunturi and Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna‎ or the tasty Buffet at the Holiday Club. Cafe Porotupa at the market square makes really good coffee (On a side note, I’m always baffled how much bad coffee you get served in a variety of places in Finland, the World Champion in coffee consumption) and also fresh pancakes and cakes. If you rather cook yourself, then the supermarket in the village has everything you need, or if you need to stock-up on dehydrated meals for another backpacking trip then visit the <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/myymalat/saariselka/">Partioaitta Saariselkä</a>, probably the most-northern Outdoor Store in Finland!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743386333/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Starter at Santa&#x27;s Hotel Tunturi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743386333_a58790587b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Starter at Santa&#x27;s Hotel Tunturi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743458333/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Love me some bread"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743458333_7e5c6e62bf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Love me some bread" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>During my visit at Saariselkä I participated in many different <a href="https://polarlifeoutdoor.com">Polarlife Outdoors</a> activities, include going to the Sauna and Spa at the Holiday Club, hiking on one of the dozen of trails around the village, visiting the AMAZING Aurora Open Wilderness Hut when you want to see Northern Lights, participate in a wild herbs Workshop, visit a Sauna and going to swim in a stream, or rent a Mountainbike and explore one of the many single track trails and holler with joy when you ride down the fjell! During the next weeks you’ll be able to read more about my adventures in the far north and some of these activities, so consider <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">becoming a Fan on Facebook</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to not miss the next instalments!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743877782/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Aroma Sauna at Holiday Club Saariselkä"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743877782_85b4aca859_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Aroma Sauna at Holiday Club Saariselkä" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743408513/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Aurora Hut in Saariselkä"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743408513_0655fe190d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Aurora Hut in Saariselkä" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743938062/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743938062_027221443c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743912072/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="16:9"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743912072_834de8507d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="561" alt="16:9" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiking to Akupää Summit]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/hiking-to-akupaa-summit.html"/>
    <updated>2019-09-23T12:27:15+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/hiking-to-akupaa-summit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Akupää might be one the least visited summits in the Ivalo region. Once you have seen it’s views, though, you’ll want to come back during every season!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743732731/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Akunpää Views"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743732731_5b47671a7c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Akunpää Views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This trip was supported financially by the Arctic Outdoor project. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>During my visit at Saariselkä I participated in several <a href="https://polarlifeoutdoor.com">Polarlife Outdoors</a> activities, and hiking with Henna was one of the highlights. Not only do I know how to hike, after five days in the Wilderness of Hammastunturi it was nice to have a chat with another person again! Henna from <a href="https://www.laplandlife.net/">Laplandlife</a> picked me up at my Hotel in Saariselkä and we hit it off right from the bat. She’s an upbeat, happy young women who after studying across Finland decided to return home to Lapland and combine all her passions and create her own business. That business is Laplandlife, and with it Henna takes people who visit the Ivalo-Saariselkä Region hiking, camping and berry picking in the summer, and snowshoeing, arctic swimming and ice fishing in the winter. As a professional massage therapist she also can help you relax after a day outdoors, and her <a href="https://www.laplandlife.net/wilderness-cabins/">Wilderness Cabins</a> are so far off-the-beaten track that you can be sure to not encounter anyone else during your stay there!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48780880326/in/dateposted/" title="Along the lake"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48780880326_99d464e289_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Along the lake" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Henna and I, however, were off to hike to the summit of Akupää. <em>“It’s in my backyard”</em> she told me as we drove to Ivalo, and silently I was wondering what that meant. What it meant became clear when we arrived: We passed a gate while she explained that all this land here, hundreds of hectares, belong to her dad. We drove to the end of a gravel road next to a most picturesque lake, the start of our hike. <em>“At the other side of the lake, well-hidden between the trees and far apart, are the two cabins”</em> Henna hold me, and I was already wondering how amazing it must be to spend a holiday here. No noise except the wind in the trees and the calls of birds could be heard, it’s exactly the kind of sounds I love and which you don’t get in the city.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743901177/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Autumn light"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743901177_787b3c0e11_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Autumn light" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Along the lake we hiked on game trails and small forest roads, all the time chatting about outdoor life in Lapland. After half an hour Henna offered me some home-made berry juice which was delicious, and then we set off slowly to climb towards the summit of Akupää. Completely off-trail we hiked through the most beautiful autumn birch and pine forests, often stopping to pick some bilberries and lingonberries which were growing in abundance on the floor of the forest.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743903127/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Henna on the way up"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743903127_218c9c73c2_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Henna on the way up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743903767/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Lonely Bilberry"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743903767_2949d7c9fa_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Lonely Bilberry" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743904647/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Light and Shadow"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743904647_af95318595_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Light and Shadow" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Here and there the forest opened up where trees have fallen, and we revelled in the beauty of it all under the sunshine on this autumn day. The conversation was flowing, we laughed together while steadily climbing higher and higher on this fjell. And then, through the low-grown birch trees, the summit came into view. My natural reaction when seeing the summit is to turn around and see what kind of view is to be seen, and here, just below the summit of Akupää, the view was beautiful. Low, pine-covered hills with small lakes who were glistening from the sunlight, we could see far into the distance.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743394023/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Sharpness Volume II"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743394023_d93dc7ae42_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Sharpness Volume II" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743397008/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Star"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743397008_3d85326225_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Star" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743732731/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Akunpää Views"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743732731_5b47671a7c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Akunpää Views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But, this wasn’t the summit yet. It was a few minutes further, and what awaited me there really was gorgeous.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743733536/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="That way be Russia!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743733536_06ebf52146_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="That way be Russia!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743734096/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Views"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743734096_aa9625879c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743895052/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Views to the North"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743895052_8e6dc0118e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Views to the North" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We could see till Russia from the summit, observed how two Raven and an Eagle were having an air show, and in every direction you could see forest-covered hill after forest-covered hill, creating an absolutely stunning panorama of silhouettes. After spending over half an hour at the summit Henna was ready to continue, and while I could have stood there and take in the view till past sunset, I shouldered my backpack and followed her. We passed beautiful little ponds which were so still and created dazzling mirror images, and soon we were back in the embrace of the forest with its golden leafs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743895947/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Autumn"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743895947_d7ce2db1c5_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Autumn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743382288/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Double Henna"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743382288_0d4ed88c97_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Double Henna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a while we made a proper break, with a fire, sitting down, eating a tasty meal and drinking fresh coffee. I lay down on the soft forest floor, on my bed of moss and shrubbery, while lounging in the sun and drinking another cup of coffee. <em>“This is the good life”</em> I proclaimed, and Henna agreed. We sat there in the forest, silently, happy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743896817/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Fall"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743896817_cbda0bb41b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Fall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A small detour on the way back was made, to a gorge, and Henna showed me where she takes guests to go camping in Tentsile tree-tents - a beautiful spot high above the gorge, which must have great views at night to the stars. We didn’t wait for the stars to come out, though - we continued on game trails back to the lake.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743740056/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Sun. Lake."><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743740056_0fe67744ca_h.jpg" width="1067" height="1600" alt="Sun. Lake." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743915547/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Dragonfly"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743915547_e6f59d817b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1103" alt="Dragonfly" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>At the lake I was able to get very close to the Dragonfly you see above. Dragonflies are without a doubt my favourite insects, I love their grace and how beautiful they are. If I ever would get a tattoo, then the tattoo of a dragonfly would be high up on the list. Back at the car I thanked Henna for the beautiful hike in her backyard, and thought to myself that if more people would have a backyard like her, and care as deeply for it, the world would be a better place. On the drive back to Saariselkä I spotted a juvenile Golden Eagle which made me smile, as these birds are not so often seen that dar in the north. I also wished for a longer lens to capture it even more up-close (<a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">You can send me a tip via PayPal</a> if you want that I can take better photos of wildlife in the future!), but I think the photo underneath is pretty good, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743917447/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Golden Eagle"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743917447_66a63e3abc_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Golden Eagle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities!</h2>

<p>I stayed in Saariselkä, which is probably <em>THE</em> place to be when you want to explore the North-Eastern corner of Finnish Lapland. Besides a dozen or more options for accommodation options - I stayed at the <a href="https://www.booking.com/hotel/fi/lapland-riekonlinna.en.html?aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna‎</a> - the village lays right at the border of the Urho Kekkonen National Park and is just a short 2 hour stroll away from the Hammastunturi Wilderness Area. This means you don’t need a car to go outdoors in Saariselkä, as you can walk in a few minutes from your Hotel or log cabin to the start of a trail. Here’s the <a href="https://www.booking.com/searchresults.en.html?city=900040403&amp;aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1&amp;room1=A">full list of Hotels and Cabins in Saariselkä</a>, and feel free to use that Affiliate Link when you’re making a reservation!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743375433/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna Room"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743375433_e869ca2dad_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna Room" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Getting to Saariselkä happens in one of three ways: You drive your car north for a veeeeeeery long time but are mobile there. Useful if you want to drive to different places, but hopefully you’re not alone in that car! The second and best option is to take the train and Bus. Taking the Bus from Rovaniemi to Saariselkä is a short and scenic 3 hour ride, and it really gets you in the mood for the outdoors as you ride past lakes and forests and every so often slow down to let the Reindeer get off the road. Taking an (overnight) train to Rovaniemi from Southern Finland is also very convenient, as you wake up well rested and just a short ride away from your next outdoor adventure. This is also a good way to travel if you want to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki.html">explore Helsinki</a> before or after a visit in Lapland. Finally, if you come from abroad you also can fly directly to Ivalo, from where you can take a bus or Taxi to Saariselkä.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0i3st0" title="Oulu - Tromso"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48780910708_729d052bdf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Oulu - Tromso" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Saariselkä has for a village its size a variety of different options for eating out, from Anne’s Garden which serves delicious Burgers (great for backpackers who just returned to civilization!) to fine dining at Santa’s Hotel Tunturi and Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna‎ or the tasty Buffet at the Holiday Club. Cafe Porotupa at the market square makes really good coffee (On a side note, I’m always baffled how much bad coffee you get served in a variety of places in Finland, the World Champion in coffee consumption) and also fresh pancakes and cakes. If you rather cook yourself, then the supermarket in the village has everything you need, or if you need to stock-up on dehydrated meals for another backpacking trip then visit the <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/myymalat/saariselka/">Partioaitta Saariselkä</a>, probably the most-northern Outdoor Store in Finland!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743386333/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Starter at Santa&#x27;s Hotel Tunturi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743386333_a58790587b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Starter at Santa&#x27;s Hotel Tunturi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743458333/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Love me some bread"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743458333_7e5c6e62bf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Love me some bread" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>During my visit at Saariselkä I participated in many different <a href="https://polarlifeoutdoor.com">Polarlife Outdoors</a> activities, include going to the Sauna and Spa at the Holiday Club, hiking on one of the dozen of trails around the village, visiting the AMAZING Aurora Open Wilderness Hut when you want to see Northern Lights, participate in a wild herbs Workshop, visit a Sauna and going to swim in a stream, or rent a Mountainbike and explore one of the many single track trails and holler with joy when you ride down the fjell! During the next weeks you’ll be able to read more about my adventures in the far north and some of these activities, so consider <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">becoming a Fan on Facebook</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to not miss the next instalments!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743877782/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Aroma Sauna at Holiday Club Saariselkä"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743877782_85b4aca859_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Aroma Sauna at Holiday Club Saariselkä" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743408513/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Aurora Hut in Saariselkä"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743408513_0655fe190d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Aurora Hut in Saariselkä" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743938062/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743938062_027221443c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743912072/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="16:9"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743912072_834de8507d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="561" alt="16:9" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meteora, Greece]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/11/meteora-greece.html"/>
    <updated>2016-11-09T23:02:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/11/meteora-greece</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A place so unbelievable, you have to visit it, immerse yourself into it, to comprehend it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30821081176/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset over Meteora"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5702/30821081176_42d29f254a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset over Meteora" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I fell in love with Meteora in 2014 before I ever have been there. As the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/petzl-roctrip-2014-turkey.html">Petzl RocTrip</a> was announced and I saw the photos from Meteora I knew that it must be a magical place, not only for climbing, but also for just being there, exploring these mountains, hiking through the forests, sucking in the famous Greek hospitality. Things turned out well in 2014 as Petzl invited me on the RocTrip, though I would join it later in Turkey (which is a gorgeous place, too). But then things again turned out well and I was invited to the AdventureNEXT Conference in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/multi-adventures-in-macedonia.html">Macedonia</a>, and after my fantastic Pre-Adventure I was super-psyched to finally see the rock towers of Meteora myself.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/t0N8CbE7Zu4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>But before I would lay my eyes on Meteora I and my travel companions were treated to a night in a 5 Star Hotel, a visit in a winery and a sunset hike in the gorgeous mountains of Northern Greece. And after having seen this beauty I’m surprised that most people seem to be thinking about Athens, Kalymnos and the beaches when one mentions Greece. Because Greece is a lot more than those destinations, and it is off-the-beaten track where real adventure awaits.</p>

<h2 id="metsovo">Metsovo</h2>

<p>So our first off-the-beaten-track stop took us to the town of Metsovo. A calm town nestled into the side of the mountain it has a picturesque square where old men meet on Saturday morning to have a chat, narrow cobblestone streets create a maze in which you can get yourself lost and original Tabernas where you are treated to tasty greek food and wine from the <a href="http://www.ariahotels.gr/en/content/katogi/winery-12">Katogi Averoff Winery</a>. That winery we visited, and if you imagine a winery being nothing else than a collection of dusty barrels then you’re in for surprise: Besides barrels full of tasty wine the experience of walking through the wine cellar is similar to walking through a modern art museum, as you will be surprised by each turn of a corner by new colours and art, until you arrive at the bar where you’re sitting down to try the local wines.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30769610131/in/dateposted/" title="Barrels at the Katogi Averoff Hotel &amp; Winery"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/6/5699/30769610131_d217998161_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Barrels at the Katogi Averoff Hotel &amp; Winery" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30769610991/in/dateposted/" title="About to taste some wine!"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5528/30769610991_11a010b08c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="About to taste some wine!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30769611761/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Tasty Red at Katogi Averoff Hotel &amp; Winery"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5702/30769611761_8f32b41d30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tasty Red at Katogi Averoff Hotel &amp; Winery" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After tasting these fine wines we continue our walk through Metsovo, passing fine old houses which enjoy wide views on the mountains around us. Locals eye us curiously and smile when we walk past, a local Taberna being our goal. A few logs burn in the open stove, from the table we enjoy a view into the kitchen, and it doesn’t take the attentive waiter to bring us some tasty starters and glasses of Katogi Averoff Wine. Laughter and smiles fill the room as we eat, and we speculate what might be next in store for our group.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30556598650/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Kids in Metsovo"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5333/30556598650_d2f81c3ed7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kids in Metsovo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30821053296/in/dateposted/" title="Metsovo Marketsquare"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5767/30821053296_f86dd3e356_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Metsovo Marketsquare" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30556600300/in/dateposted/" title="Into the Taverna in Metsovo"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5609/30556600300_8383a8258b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Into the Taverna in Metsovo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Turns out it is a visit to the new <a href="http://www.grand-forest.gr/en">Grand Forest Metsovo</a> Hotel, which sits above the town and is surrounded by forests. But before enjoying the luxury of a warm shower and a glas of Scottish Whiskey we hit the local trail which starts in front of the hotel. The Ursa Trail is not just a pretty trail which takes one high up the mountain behind the hotel, it also hosts a <a href="http://metsovorace.gr/home-page-en">trailrunning race</a> each spring. My companions descent while I linger high up the mountain, enjoying the far views and the fresh wind in my face. I watch the sun disappear behind the hills, treasuring that memory of the lines of mountains which build up in front of me, like waves in the sea. On the way down I keep up a happy tune, because bears are indeed not seldom here, and I’d rather not be the dinner of Brown Bear tonight.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30741229202/in/dateposted/" title="On the Ursa Trail"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5599/30741229202_db72ba747b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the Ursa Trail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30769615831/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Views towards Metsovo"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5344/30769615831_8abbf13c03_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views towards Metsovo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30613973862/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Sunset in Northern Greece"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5708/30613973862_5072194856_b.jpg" width="1024" height="340" alt="Sunset in Northern Greece" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Back at my room I am enjoying the feeling of hot water on my skin, rubbing down the sweat and dust of a day well spent, and look forward to sit down at the table with my friends for what was a very tasty Dinner. After a final glass of wine we all go down to our suites, laying down on comfy beds and dreaming of the rock pillars of our next destination.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30769614591/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Views at the Grand Forest Metsovo"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5336/30769614591_c8e6b98143_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views at the Grand Forest Metsovo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30857629745/in/dateposted/" title="Tasty Salad at the Grand Forest Metsovo Hotel"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5638/30857629745_5380bff5a9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tasty Salad at the Grand Forest Metsovo Hotel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30857630865/in/dateposted/" title="Cheese Cake!"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5609/30857630865_c97c33c89a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cheese Cake!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next day started as sunny and warm as the last one, and after a delicious breakfast at the Grand Forest Metsovo Hotel we check out and board our Minibus to Meteora. It are just a few hours of driving, but already after a while I could make out from high in the mountains the faint outlines of the mountains of Meteora. The closer we got, the more excited I became. I finally would be able to see the rocks of Meteora, hike around, climb them, experience them and will never forget them. And then we were there.</p>

<h2 id="meteora">Meteora</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30222134583/in/dateposted/" title="Roofs of Kastraki"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5755/30222134583_84cfd6f86e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Roofs of Kastraki" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="https://www.visitmeteora.travel">Meteora</a>, that are immense monolithic pillars and hills that are composed of sandstone and conglomerate. Small and large pebbles stick out of them, making them one of very few places on this planet where you can see, climb and experience such rocks. And while these rocks themselves are reason enough for many people (<em>climbers!</em>) to visit Meteora, it are the seven active Eastern Orthodox monasteries on top of some of these rocks and their inhabitants which draw many, many more people. My companions and me, we were there for both - and then some. After checking in to my <a href="http://www.guesthouse-sotiriou.gr/en/index.asp">accommodation</a> (see the last photo of my wee house!) and a tasty lunch at the Restaurant Meteora we were hitting the trail up one of the rocks.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30874897625/in/dateposted/" title="Off hiking!"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5817/30874897625_7bbd88443b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Off hiking!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26505575123/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Hiking in Meteora"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7060/26505575123_422cb17f12_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Hiking in Meteora" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30874897975/in/dateposted/" title="Towers"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5589/30874897975_abf60e5663_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Towers" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30874898605/in/dateposted/" title="Little shrine up on the mountain"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5696/30874898605_b1047ecfa7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Little shrine up on the mountain" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30874898935/in/dateposted/" title="Happy Hendrik"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5629/30874898935_376641392d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happy Hendrik" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Hiking and scrambling up these pillars is a great way to get a feel of the land. We hiked quite a bit over the next few days, through shady Oak forests, past small, hidden monasteries, up unlikely paths with stunning views, never far away from the big monasteries but never meeting another soul out on the trail.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30874899975/in/dateposted/" title="Scenic views"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5722/30874899975_b5690d8b59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scenic views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27109586945/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Luna Sandals Mono"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7520/27109586945_8163019e61_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Luna Sandals Mono" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30741244172/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Flowers along the trail"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5713/30741244172_81b2f2ca76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Flowers along the trail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30786366281/in/dateposted/" title="Luna Sandals &lt;3"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5709/30786366281_016d0e933d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Luna Sandals &lt;3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That changed when we went to visit some of the monasteries. There many souls were looking for something, while those living there were sometimes happy enough to pass on ancient wisdom which they have studied in their books. I joined in on these monastery visits, curious to see if an atheist like me can find spiritual enlightenment here, but alas all I found was beautiful architecture and even prettier views on the surrounding nature. Nature is probably as close to my religion as Islam and Buddhism are to others, and as long as we don’t get preachy or hostile with each others I believe we all can happy co-exist on this planet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30857638735/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Holy Monastery of Great Meteoron"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5342/30857638735_f444b7323c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Holy Monastery of Great Meteoron" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30556599410/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Skulls &amp; Bones"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5608/30556599410_d514fd7963_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skulls &amp; Bones" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30222133923/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Lighting candles"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/6/5513/30222133923_2f7750b9dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lighting candles" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30239434783/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Photo Session"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5679/30239434783_4c55c73e7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Photo Session" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30222129233/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="View towards the Monastery of Varlaam"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5342/30222129233_645c172f03_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="View towards the Monastery of Varlaam" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And what brings me close to my god? Hiking, packrafting, cycling, flying, skiing and climbing in it. In this case I chose to worship nature by going climbing. Together with my Greek partner Kosta, a local Mountain Guide, we hit up the Pillar of the Rain, an easy 5c route to get me into familiarity with the rock of Meteora. Climbing these routes which are <em>boldly bolted</em> (as in, you better be fine by standing five meters over your last pro) was such an amazing experience, I probably was smiling all the time being able to climb on this fantastic rock. It is just so much fun. Too quick we topped out, then left a note in the summit register and then rappelled down. I could have continued the rest of the day climbing, though I know there will be more days of climbing in Meteora in my future so I have no regrets of not having climbed more that day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30874899695/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="The Traumpfeiler, one of the longest routes in meteora"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5803/30874899695_a93aef1980_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Traumpfeiler, one of the longest routes in meteora" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30240558913/in/dateposted/" title="Pillar of the Rain, 1st Pitch"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5828/30240558913_84e1c10be3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pillar of the Rain, 1st Pitch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30876163295/in/dateposted/" title="Happy Belay Hendrik"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5459/30876163295_c2df064a69_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Happy Belay Hendrik" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30876165265/in/dateposted/" title="Going down"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5782/30876165265_b14fec7cca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Going down" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, actually we also went scrambling that same morning. Scrambling up on a Via Cordata Tour we were clipped in to ropes while climbing up steep hills, navigating on airy ledges to arrive on a look-out over the city of Kalambaka. It was another great experience of climbing &amp; scrambling among these pillars, and if you’re less inclined to rock climbing then you will surely find this a suitable and safe yet adrenaline-filled adventure.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30759775552/in/dateposted/" title="Scrambling"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5586/30759775552_f2e8243407_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Scrambling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30759773712/in/dateposted/" title="Almost there"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5565/30759773712_3928985f06_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Almost there" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30876170085/in/dateposted/" title="View over Kalambaka"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5347/30876170085_d27459db1a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="View over Kalambaka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That brings me to the food, because somehow one has to fuel his body for all these adventures. The meals were delicious, from the Saganaki we ate at Restaurant Meteora, the oldest restaurant in town, which was so tasty, my mouth is watering just writing about it. Or the Gyros we ate off the main street, and many other meals - I can not recall a dish I wasn’t excited about while eating in Greece. The fresh ingredients, the passion &amp; talent of the chefs, the great atmosphere, it all makes eating out in Greece a superb experience - and is very affordable, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30874896765/in/dateposted/" title="The Kitchen of Restaurant Meteora"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5643/30874896765_95f34f4333_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Kitchen of Restaurant Meteora" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30741293962/in/dateposted/" title="Nom nom!"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5451/30741293962_fb5376e020_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Nom nom!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And too quick to my liking our visit to <a href="https://www.visitmeteora.travel">Meteora</a> was over. Together with my friends Rupert and Bernand I was sitting on a late, sunny afternoon in our bus on the way to Thessaloniki, from where we would fly out the next morning. It was hard to leave this magical place with its friendly people, tasty food, beautiful nature and unique climbing, but I am looking forward to visit again with my family some day soon, and then share this unreal experience with them again.</p>

<h2 id="the-need-to-know-stuff">The Need-To-Know Stuff</h2>

<p>LOTS and lots of more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157666107618724">Flickr Album</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Getting There</strong>: Flying to Thessaloniki or Athens and then taking Public Transportation to reach Kalambaka (the larger of the two towns around Meteora) or Kastraki. Or check out this <a href="https://www.visitmeteora.travel/en/getting-to-meteora">Getting to Meteora Guide</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Topos</strong>: Download or print the <a href="http://www.petzl-roctrip.com/sites/www.petzl-roctrip.com/files/basecamps/pdf/topos/meteora-petzl-small.pdf">free Petzl RocTrip Topo</a> for starters and get a feel for the climbing. The <a href="https://guide.vertical-life.info/en/app/">Vertical-Life Climbing App 2.0</a> allows you to buy &amp; download a lot of Topos onto your phone, while in Kalambaka you might be lucky and find one of the old, original Topo Guides in a book shop.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30741293422/in/dateposted/" title="That way!"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5484/30741293422_db402a404c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="That way!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Food</strong>: Go eat at the <a href="http://meteora-restaurant.gr/restaurant%20in%20meteora.html">Meteora Restaurant</a> in the centre, their food is superb. The <a href="http://www.meteoronpanorama.gr/el/english/">Meteoron Panorama Restaurant</a> has great views &amp; tasty food. The Gyros in the small Fast Food Shop on the main street, not far from the Meteora Restaurant is great for lunch.</p>

<p><strong>Accommodation</strong>: If you are visiting with the family or friends check out the <a href="http://www.archontikomesohori.gr">Archontiko Mesochori</a>, spacious rooms and a great looking breakfast will convince you. If you can do with less space check out the <a href="http://www.guesthouse-sotiriou.gr/en/index.asp">Guesthouse Sotiriou</a> where I stayed and slept well. Need more luxury? Check out the <a href="https://www.meteorahotels.com">Hotel Meteora</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Things to do</strong> (<em>Other than climbing</em>): <strong>Visits to the monasteries</strong> are very popular, and for a good reason. Perched atop these pillars and constructed over centuries of hard labour, they’re inspiring places to visit. Entry fees range from 3 to 5€ and you should check beforehand when which Monastery is open for visitors.</p>

<p><strong>Hiking</strong> is free and you can combine it with a monatery visit. Lots of fine trails weave around and through the pillars, just pick one, take enough water and go for a nice stroll.</p>

<p><strong>Egyptian vultures</strong> breed at Meteora, and if your lucky you can catch a glimpse of one of these rare birds of prey (we were lucky!). There’s a feeding station where you can watch them from a safe distance - bring binoculars!</p>

<p>Oh, and don’t miss the <strong>Sunset Tours</strong>. They might seem kitschy, but watching the sun set on these pillars is a memorable experience - not just for photographers!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30821091596/in/album-72157666107618724/" title="Midnight over Meteora"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5606/30821091596_4f999b7290_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Midnight over Meteora" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I was invited to Meteora as part of the <a href="http://www.adventuretravel.biz/events/adventurenext/balkans-2016/">AdventureNEXT Balkans</a> conference. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
