<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ponderings | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/ponderings/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-09-29T11:20:53+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10 Years Hiking in Finland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/05/10-years-hiking-in-finland.html"/>
    <updated>2019-05-06T18:57:43+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/05/10-years-hiking-in-finland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ten years on and I am still blogging, photographing and enjoying the outdoors. <em>A look back at a decade of outdoor blogging.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40820176213/in/dateposted/" title="Yo!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/40820176213_c2bc289f33_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Yo!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-beginning">The Beginning</h2>

<p>Ten years ago, at the beginning of April 2009, I opened up my blog at the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/archives/">hikinginfinland.com</a> domain (<em>actually, back then I was still at Blogspot, but that changed soon</em>). Why did I start my blog? Well, I’ll need to start a few years earlier for that story.</p>

<p>In 2008 I hiked with my best friend Martin on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2009/06/karhunkierros-i.html">Karhunkierros Trail</a> in Lapland. Back then I was far from hiking ultralight, and both Martin and me hiked with well over 20 kg on our backs this popular trail in Finland. On the the last day, motivated by the thought of a nice warm Sauna at home, cold beers and Pizza, we hiked as fast as possible to reach the early bus from Kuusamo to Oulu. This is where things went wrong: Sitting in our sweaty and smoke-smelling clothes in the bus, a fire alarm went on in the bus toilet - NOT caused by us 😊. The Bus pulled over, and a few minutes later it was burning with meter high flames flickering in the sky. Not only did we miss our connecting train to Tampere, but also lost all our backpacking gear which burned to ash in the luggage compartment of the bus.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40820173553/in/dateposted/" title="And it burns, burns, burns"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/40820173553_4eacfc83e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="And it burns, burns, burns" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I still loved hiking, and so decided to buy with the insurance money new backpacking gear. But I remembered that carrying 20+ kg on my back didn’t add to a pleasurable experience, and so, little by little, I found out that <a href="">ultralight backpacking</a> was a thing. So why the blog?</p>

<p>Back then the Summit &amp; Valley blog, <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com">Chris Townsend</a> and a few others were a huge inspiration for me to start blogging. I enjoyed the accounts of Bristish backpackers going out into the hills and documenting their trips, and as I felt there was no blog documenting the hiking and backpacking possibilities in Finland I registered the Hiking in Finland domain without much thought for a brand name or such. I published trip reports, gear reviews, and even made videos back in 2009 already, though they were quite different from what I produce nowadays. Together with Roger, Joe, Jörgen, Martin and Gustav we founded <a href="https://www.facebook.com/nordiclightpacking/">Nordic Lightpacking</a> and even got together to go <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/06/the-ul-fellowship.html">backpacking in Vålådalen</a> in 2010.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46997178644/in/dateposted/" title="Ultralight Backpackers!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/46997178644_a578059447_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ultralight Backpackers!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Things took off for me well and magazines and companies started to ask if I could write and photograph for them. As the financial crisis from 2008 still made my work as an environmental management consultant quite hard, I decided to switch careers and have been working in this content creation, photography and outdoor business since 2011 full-time. Without this blog that wouldn’t have happened, and the amazing readers and friends I made during the last ten years helped me a lot so that I can work on my own with amazing outdoor brands, creating inspiring content from Northern Europe and across the globe. So thank you to the millions of readers who have read my articles over the last decade - it’s because of you that I am able to live this life!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46997177904/in/dateposted/" title="Cold"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/46997177904_08287fb6db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cold" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hiking-climbing-skiing">Hiking, Climbing, Skiing</h2>

<p>… as well as Packrafting, bikepacking and trailrunning are what I do mostly nowadays. Quickly I realized that limiting myself to only hiking would mean I’d sit six months a year inside, so on came the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">XC skis</a> in winter, and since four years I also go ski touring in Finland, Norway, Sweden, and the Alps. With over 180.000 Lakes in Finland the addition of a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/08/packrafting-in-finland-first-strokes.html">packraft</a> was a logical first step, and also <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/06/bikepacking-in-pirkanmaa.html">bikepacking</a> felt like a good way to explore my surroundings.</p>

<p>I was dabbling for some years in climbing but because of having small kids I never was able to train as much as I wanted, so lately I haven’t been climbing on ice or rocks that much, but with the kids growing fast I hope to get back into that activity at some point. I did pick up <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/08/my-trailrunning-gear.html">trailrunning</a> to stay fit as I can easily go run from the front of my house, and it is an activity which also gives me a good fitness for backpacking. Yes, backpacking, the activity of hiking and camping in nature, is still one of the best things in life. Even better, I am fortunate enough to call this work, mainly because I carry a camera, tripod and notepad with me when I go out, and am able to create compelling stories, photos and videos about my trips. It is something I truly love, because not only do I know that spending time is nature is healthy in many ways, it also inspires people to protect our planet better.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46997178234/in/dateposted/" title="Sun Pillar"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/46997178234_9af91b2e46_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sun Pillar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-future">The Future</h2>

<p><em>What is next?</em> you might think, and it is a good question. Ten years ago I already started to write and talk about the negative effects of climate change, but society was not ready for it. Now, in 2019, thanks to a 16-year old girl and the movement she has inspired, old politicians finally start to listen up and ponder the future of the human species and the planet (though I feel these old politicians simply will continue business-as-usual). I feel the time is right now for me to again start talking about how we outdoor enthusiasts can do small things which can make this planet better - from picking up other people’s trash which we find on the trail to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">cycling more</a>, eating healthier and flying less.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40820176023/in/dateposted/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/40820176023_5b9c8da3ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As you might have seen on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> I enjoy making videos again, and most of my reviews and trips will feature a video. I love the creativity video allows me, both in shooting and editing, and it is something that I feel better communicates what I want to say. Don’t worry, this blog will not go away. I see this blog as my home base, a sustainable and lasting place for the content I create, from the much-loved <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-week-in-review/">The Week In Review</a> to trip reports and other content series. As I hate Instagram and equally despise Facebook I will spend less time on these necessary evils, but you will still be able to find me on Twitter and engage with me there. I also plan to give this blog an visual overhaul. The last one is too long ago, and I hope to find the time in 2019 to give this blog the look I wish it had. Don’t worry, it will not look like every other cookie-cutter blog out there but retain it’s quirkiness, although in a slightly less 90s-internet look 😂</p>

<p>Finally, I have to thank you, my readers, for returning for so long to read Hiking in Finland. It always makes me happy when I receive tweets, comments, Emails and messages from people who went to hike somewhere because of my trip reports, bought an item because of my review or decided to make a change because one of my ponderings. It is because of you that I create content, and it means so much to me to hear that it matters to you and that you enjoy it. Thank you for reading and following me ❤️</p>

<p>If you feel like you’d like to support me and say <strong>Thanks”</strong> my content, the best way to do so is via <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a>. It’s a monthly subscription and you can give as little as $3 per month to enable me to do what I do. As a reward you get to hang out with me on a chat server and can pick my brains on where to go hiking in Finland, what to pack and which shoes to wear, or we can discuss the latest Game of Thrones Episode! In that sense, <strong>Happy trails!</strong></p>

<p><em>All photos in this article are from 2009 and 2010.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46997177334/in/dateposted/" title="Back in the day"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/46997177334_87c4984569_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Back in the day" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Backpacking a Sustainable Hobby?]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/sustainable-backpacking.html"/>
    <updated>2019-03-21T19:26:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/sustainable-backpacking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being outdoors, sleeping in nature, hiking through the forest, paddling on rivers and cycling on beautiful single trails - being outdoors seems on a first look to be a very sustainable hobby. But is it really?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199759745/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Storådörren Valley from the other side n better weather"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1903/44199759745_b4b7e1753e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Storådörren Valley from the other side n better weather" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>This article is part of the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> Series of “Sustainable Outdoors” and several bloggers write about this topic - you can find a list with the other articles at the end. We are not paid to write these articles and have full editorial control.</em></p>

<p>Going outdoors feels like a sustainable hobby - especially if you compare it to sports and hobbies which need large buildings or areas to be played &amp; practiced. But is it really sustainable to drive in a big car to a trail head, being dressed in garments made from oil-based materials and hiking in sensitive areas which contributes to land erosion and degradation? That is a question which I am pondering in this article, so read along to find out what in my opinion are our biggest “sins” as backpackers.</p>

<h2 id="getting-there">Getting there</h2>

<p>Only very few of us life in nature and can start hiking or skiing from their doorstep - most of us life in towns and villages and need to travel to the start of a trail or to the hills. Those who read me since a while know that I neither have a driving license and our family also does not own a car. If I go backpacking somewhere it is always by public transportation, most usually a combination of train and bus when in Finland, or by ferry, plane and then bus or train when abroad. As I have been travelling like this since 20 years this is normal for me, but for those who have grown up with a car in front of their house this might seem strange. Yes, I am dependent on schedules and trains and busses to get somewhere, but I have learned to life with that and it usually works out nicely. My waiting time I use for reading and studying the map, or stocking up on calories!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33621497524/in/album-72157681559831330/" title="Bikepacking Season is upon us!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4160/33621497524_40fe81d861_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Bikepacking Season is upon us!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Getting to a local trail here in Pohjanmaa means either jumping on a bike or taking a bus or train and possibly a Taxi. Sometimes I make the bike ride part of the journey and just call it a <em>Bikepacking and Hiking Adventure</em> as cool and catchy names are important =) I really love to ride my bike and it’s my favourite way to get around when in town or if I’m travelling, it just feels great. Going by train or bus is fine, though - I can charge my phone and listen to music or chat on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Discord</a> and the speed is good and if going by bus I usually also can get off quite close to a trailhead and just hike the last bit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44739826010/in/dateposted/" title="Golden Hour"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7863/44739826010_b8ec02619e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Golden Hour" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>When going abroad flying is something I hate. I hate the noise, the people and the emissions I accumulate while travelling by plane, but for long distances in a short time there’s no alternative for me right now. I am cutting down on my flights and assignments abroad drastically, though, and each trip I can realize by taking the ferry, train, bus and Taxi are a win in my book. Plus going by plane also often means I have to add a night in an <a href="https://www.airbnb.ca/c/hmorkel">AirBnB</a> or Hotel at the beginning or end, depending on the connections at the destination to get where I want to go which adds to the costs and length of a trip. But some trips are just too good to miss out on, like my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/06/hiking-the-causeway-coast-way.html">Causeway Coast Way thru-hike</a> or backpacking on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/snow-and-sunshine-on-the-via-dinarica.html">Via Dinarica</a> in Bosnia Herzegovina. These were amazing hikes and totally worth getting into a plane for, and also the John Muir Trail is high on my list, as well as several other trails abroad.</p>

<p>My take-away for <strong>getting there</strong> is probably to try to enjoy your local outdoors as much as possible. I know I am guilty of dreaming and hiking on distant trails, while I have a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/pack-sail-rafting-in-the-kvarken-archipelago.html">UNESCO Natural World Heritage Site</a> on my doorstep which would be great for packrafting, cycling and hiking. But the benefits of hiking locally are so many: You can hike more - have a free afternoon and day ahead? Just go to a local trail for a night out! Take the bike instead of the car if you feel like it, and for longer trips why not explore more of your own country?! If you fly somewhere for your yearly long backpacking trip - and you can! - <a href="https://mossy.earth/collections/carbon-offsetting">offset your emissions</a> by supporting reforestation measures or similar.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45049302961/in/dateposted/" title="Umeå C"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1975/45049302961_acef721b0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Umeå C" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-gear">The Gear</h2>

<p>Another topic which we have to ponder is how sustainable our outdoor gear is. Unless you use exclusively natural materials like cotton, hemp, flax, wood or Merino wool chances are you have something that’s made from oil =&gt; plastic in any form or shape (it can be called Dyneema, XPac, Cuben fibre, Polyester, Nylon, Cordura or or or). The good thing is that most of our outdoor gear is so well made that it can last us a life-time with some proper care, so the environmental footprint of a tent which gets used several times per year is relatively small after 15 years of use.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797321574/in/album-72157634403205347/" title="HMG UltaMid in a wet forest"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5502/9797321574_0b9435d015_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG UltaMid in a wet forest" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Also, most new outdoor equipment is made from recycled or recyclable materials which is an amazing step forward. I remember my first <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/outdoor-news-i.html">OutDoor</a> where the sustainability topic was still in it’s baby shoes and I had more the feel of “Greenwashing” here and there. But now, five years later, it’s front and centre for many companies, and one of their most important messages. From <a href="http://bit.ly/2UNDeN1">Patagonia</a> who doesn’t want you to buy their jackets to Houdini which lets you <a href="https://www.houdinisportswear.com/ca/sustainability/houdini-rental">rent their garments</a> instead of buying them, many companies wake up and realize we need to do something to keep our outdoors healthy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46495574344/in/album-72157678997220548/" title="100%"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7826/46495574344_e4e77a6ca4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="100%" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But what’s even better is that many of our outdoor gear also can find it’s way into our everyday life. Don’t be dumb and only use your <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/hydro-flask-standard-mouth-with-standard-flex-cap/?pid=10239">Hydroflask</a> on the trail - take it with you when you go to work or walking the dog! Get a <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/primus-vacuum-commuter-mug-isolierbecher/?pid=10239">good mug</a> for your coffee on the go, and also your lunch can be packed in a Light My Fire meal box. I also wear my outdoor clothes all the time - my <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/houdini-womens-thrill-twill-mtm-pants-jeans/?pid=10239">hiking pants</a> are my every day pants as well, when I pick up my kids I wear my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody.html">Alpine Start Hoody</a> or a shell jacket and I don’t really use any other shoes than my trailrunning and hiking shoes. If you’re working at a office where a suit is mandatory you might not get away with wearing your outdoor garments all the time, but if your employer is relaxed about the dress code there’s no good reason why you can’t wear your flannel shirt and hiking trousers to the office.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47298836431/in/dateposted/" title="Time for some Coffee!"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7857/47298836431_ab751f6d7a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Time for some Coffee!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, instead of buying a new piece of kit once an old one is broken might not be necessary - many pieces of equipment can be fixed, from stoves to garments. If a rain jacket doesn’t keep the rain out anymore it often just needs a wash with a good detergent to re-activate its waterproof properties, and if a tear is too big you can have it often much more cheaply fixed than buying a new one.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35450694064/in/album-72157686898441076/" title="Unscrew everything!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4307/35450694064_e2e659e43d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Unscrew everything!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="land-degradation">Land degradation</h2>

<p>Land degradation and erosion is especially a problem at very popular trails and areas - from the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2009/06/karhunkierros-i.html">Karhunkierros</a> in Finland to certain trails in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse.html">Lake District</a> and elsewhere, where a lot of people hike or ski the earth under our feet gets eroded and with rain and wind popular trails quickly can look like deep scars in the landscape. Well built and maintained trails minimize this problem, and also we can - by choosing to hike on “less popular” trails. Now less popular does not equal less beautiful, and as many of us go into nature to escape busy cities it’s a smart thing to search out these less popular trails and enjoy them on your own.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29831354255/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Clearing up"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8528/29831354255_4688f96fa0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Clearing up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If a trail gets really popular then trail erosion is often the smallest problem - often rubbish which is left behind, from 💩 to plastic bottles and tissues - are a much bigger issue. What we as knowledgable outdoors men and women can do is to educate our fellow hikers when we catch them in the act, or collect the trash and carry it out. Carrying a small Ziplock bag for these situations is common for me, because I really hate it to see rubbish left in nature.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221050166/in/album-72157644166894052/" title="The Old Man of Coniston"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5489/14221050166_7c850e257d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Old Man of Coniston" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline--what-you-can-do">Bottomline &amp; What you can do</h2>

<p>My conclusion is that being outdoors, be it hiking, backpacking, biketouring, packrafting or ski-touring is inherently a sustainable activity. By spending time outdoors in nature we learn to care more about our planet, and in the long run we will adapt many of the things I have suggested throughout this article, though if you’re at the start of your hiking career and just started with backpacking you can now of course skip ahead and pick up these good behaviours and ideas!</p>

<p>To sum them up, these would be my three take-aways:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Adventure more locally and take the bike, train and bus to get to the trailhead!</li>
  <li>Use your gear until the end! Resist the urge to buy new gear, repair what you have and consider renting or buying used gear.</li>
  <li>Search out less popular trails, keep <em>Leave No Trace</em> principles in mind and pick up other people’s trash if you encounter it outdoors.</li>
</ol>

<p>I also want to encourage you to not geo-tag your images online and generally share &amp; spend less time on un-social networks like Instagram and Facebook which both promote <strong>F</strong>ear <strong>O</strong>f <strong>M</strong>issing <strong>O</strong>ut and other negative feelings. Finally, <a href="https://twitter.com/gretathunberg">#FridaysForFuture</a> are not just for kids - also responsible Adults who are not happy about how those in our governments misuse their loaned power can take to the streets and demonstrate for politics which ensure our planet, including all these amazing National Parks, hiking trails and mountains remain for future generations. Take the ext Friday off and go demonstrate!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748741131/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Bodensee"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8007/29748741131_a681170dde_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bodensee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="further-reading">Further Reading</h2>

<p>The Bergfreunde write about <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/basislager/nachhaltiger-winterurlaub/?pid=10239">sustainable winter holidays</a>, Stefanie ponders the topic of <a href="https://www.gipfel-glueck.de/reisen-und-nachhaltigkeit/">travelling and sustainability</a>, Heiko shares <a href="https://www.people-abroad.de/blog/nachhaltig-leben-tipps/">11 sustainable tips for home &amp; outdoors</a>, Björn reports about the DAV Day <a href="https://bergtouren-im-allgaeu.de/natuerlich-auf-tour-eine-aktion-des-dav">Sustainable on Ski Tour</a>, the Climbing Plus guys show how <a href="https://climbing.plus/blog/nachhaltigkeit-einst-und-jetzt-im-klettersport">climbing has changed over the years</a>, Ulrich writes about <a href="https://www.auf-den-berg.de/wandern/island/nachhaltiger-urlaub-in-island/">Sustainable Tourism on Iceland</a> and Dennis ponders <a href="https://www.outdoor-blog.com/nachhaltigkeit-beim-wandern-trekking/">about sustainability when hiking and backpacking</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28906677698/in/album-72157669754047208/" title="The clouds are moving in"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/899/28906677698_be2173bbb2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The clouds are moving in" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
