<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: trailrunning | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/trailrunning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-09-07T14:04:57+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Trailrunning Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/08/my-trailrunning-gear.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-29T23:20:15+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/08/my-trailrunning-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You’re psyched about UTMB this week? Good on ya, me too! Hence I find it is now the right time to tell you about my red running dress 💃, fast shoes and accessories which have made me run like the wind this summer.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/43627772284/in/dateposted/" title="Airtime"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1862/43627772284_9b08d8cea6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Airtime" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has in part been supported with gear from Alpinetrek.co.uk. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>As I wrote <a href="">elsewhere</a>, I have fallen in love with running again this summer. I try to run three times a week, sometimes I succeed, sometimes I fail, and sometimes I run even more often. Down in Helsinki I was exploring the city during my evening runs, while here in Vaasa I stick mostly to my home round (and I have to admit, that does at times get boring, but on the other hand it is nice to see how I get faster). This goes in line in trying to build up a better level of fitness and also I am trying to lose some weight. As I have been running for the last four years or more basically in the same running shorts and shirt (and still run in them, as they still are in great shape and not broken) and only have been switching shoes, I felt that now that I run so often it’d be nice to have a second set of clothes to wear when I hit the trails when the other one is in the laundry (I do sweat a lot and while I wear them a minimum of two times and air dry them after each run, that’s about as much runs I get out of one pair of running clothes 😂). Without much further ado, I give you all the kit I use when out running!</p>

<h2 id="salomon-exo-twinskin-shorts--s-lab-exo-hz-ss-tee">Salomon Exo Twinskin Shorts &amp; S-Lab Exo Hz S/S Tee</h2>

<p>At a regular retail price of around 140 € for the shorts and 100 € for the shirt this is a piece of kit which I think is only for those who really run a lot and think they need it. A word of warning, too: These seem to not be sized correctly - I have a Size M Shirt which I barely get on and off (I usually wear Size S) and the Shorts in Size S are also a snug fit. I also got an <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/salomon-explore-s-s-tee-t-shirt/?pid=10239">Salomon Explore S/S Tee</a> and that’s true to size. Anyway, lets look a wee bit at these two exceptional pieces.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/salomon-exo-twinskin-short-running-shorts/?pid=10239">Salomon Exo Twinskin Shorts</a> are a compression tights and a shorts in one. They do their job well and if I wear these I can run longer and am less fatigued. I do think Salomon could have been more generous with the sizes of the pockets, though - there’s a tiny zippered pocket on the back and an open mesh pocket on the front. Except a key and some Gels I won’t be able to get much stored in these, which is a shame as that means for my runs I need to somehow carry the iPhone (which I need for Music) in another way (my old Arc’teryx shorts has five pockets, one of which is massive enough for the phone). It has a long list of features - Skin fit with Exo Sensifit Agility compression, 37.5 technology, 360 degree reflective details, amongst others - but in short this is a great shorts for me for the coming months when it will be a bit cooler. / <em>122 g in Size S</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30477242018/in/dateposted/" title="Stabile Seitenlage"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1850/30477242018_e69f614653_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Stabile Seitenlage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/salomon-s-lab-exo-hz-s-s-tee-running-shirt/?pid=10239">S-Lab Exo Hz S/S Tee</a> has zero pockets, a zipper in the front which helps with venting, silicone prints on the sleeves and hem to keep the shirt in place, and then this <em>“Exe-Skeleton”</em> structure which also seems to help me to run faster and get less tired. The fabric dries really fast and does not feel moist or cold after a long run, which is pretty good as it starts to be cooler in the evenings (it’s soon autumn after all). All that said, I’m not sure if this is a shirt for every runner out there - while it certainly is great, it’s also pretty expensive. / <em>102 g in Size M</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30477246368/in/dateposted/" title="Salomon Exo Twinskin Shorts &amp; S-Lab Exo Hz S/S Tee"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1861/30477246368_3cb89165e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon Exo Twinskin Shorts &amp; S-Lab Exo Hz S/S Tee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="salomon-s-lab-speedcross">Salomon S-Lab Speedcross</h2>

<p>I haven’t worn the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/salomon-s-lab-speedcross-trail-running-shoes/?pid=10239">Salomon S-Lab Speedcross</a> heaps as of yet, but two things: They are fast &amp; light, and they have very little ankle support. I don’t think I need to say much about the former (my pair in 42 weighs 560 g), but about that ankle support: I like to think of myself of having strong ankles, because I very seldom wear boots and pretty much all the time wear Luna Sandals, light <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/08/la-sportiva-tx2-review.html">approach shoes</a> or some other trailrunning shoe. And I don’t know if it was because it now gets earlier dark and I often run during dusk, or something else, but I have the feeling that I twist my ankle more often in these shoes. Now if I say <em>“twist my ankle”</em> I don’t mean that I injure myself, but when I am out running on my home trail then on the washed-out downhills and narrow, rocky forest path I did have a little slip of the ankle more often than in other shoes I have worn this summer. Another <em>design flaw</em> in my opinion is that the pocket for the laces is a wee bit too long, it makes it more difficult to store the laces in it. Other than that I really like these shoes (they’re light! they’re fast!) and will continue to run in them, after which I might follow up on the thing with the ankles. / <em>560 g for the pair in Size 42</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/43627770424/in/dateposted/" title="Salomon S-Lab Speedcross"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1865/43627770424_c4ff297688_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon S-Lab Speedcross" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="suunto-spartan-ultra-all-black-hr">Suunto Spartan Ultra All Black HR</h2>

<p>I admit that before I owned the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/suunto-spartan-ultra-black-multi-function-watch/?pid=10239">Suunto Spartan Ultra All Black HR</a> I didn’t use a watch at all - the Apps and clock on my iPhone where good enough. But about two years ago Suunto sent me this watch, and it has been on my wrist ever since. It does a lot of good things for me - it counts my steps each day and hence reminding me to walk more, it has GPS for backpacking and several functions which I value. But for running I really love it, as together with the HR Belt I can keep an eye on my heart rate and get an idea how well I am doing. It is paired with the Movescount App on the phone and when I am back from a run it doesn’t take me long to have my run online, and I usually share it also with my brother so we keep each other motivated to go running =) This is likely for the vast majority the last bit of kit which should be considered (as Apps on phones can do almost all of what the watch does, too). / <em>75 g for the Watch and 44 g for the HR Belt</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44343934841/in/dateposted/" title="Suunto Spartan Ultra All Black HR"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1862/44343934841_4f688c4894_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Suunto Spartan Ultra All Black HR" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="inov-8-socks">Inov-8 Socks</h2>

<p>If you wear shoes, you’re likely also wearing socks. My <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/running-socks/?pid=10239">running socks</a> of choice right now are from <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/brands/inov-8/running-socks/?pid=10239">Inov-8</a>, I bought these several years ago and they work well for me - they’re a low cut, light, dry quick and don’t smell too bad after one run. / <em>36 g in Size M</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44343934321/in/dateposted/" title="Inov-8 Socks"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1860/44343934321_cb7d4c65cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8 Socks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="inov-8-race-ultra-hydration-system">Inov-8 Race Ultra Hydration System</h2>

<p>I also refer to this as my <em>Waterbottle Thingy</em> but inov-8 calls this a <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/inov-8-race-ultra-hydration-system/?pid=10239">Hydration System</a>. I bought this as I don’t want to always carry a pack, belt or vest when I go running, and this works really well for me. You strap it to your hand, put the bottle in [I bought the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/inov-8-softflask-05-folding-bottle/?pid=10239">500 ml soft flask</a> because that 250 ml bottle it comes with is a joke] and running I go. The 500 ml flask is good for an hour of running, anything longer and I likely will take a vest or belt to stay hydrated. In the <em>Waterbottle Thingy</em> there’s two small pockets so I also can put a key safely away and carry a gel. Pretty handy, and despite my concerns that it might not be comfortable or such, I have been running all summer with it and find it fantastic. / <em>19 g for the strap, 29 g for the empty 500 ml soft flask</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30477247218/in/dateposted/" title="Inov-8 Race Ultra Handflask"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1895/30477247218_cbcbab2853_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inov-8 Race Ultra Handflask" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="salomon-air-logo-cap-and-active-gloves">Salomon Air Logo Cap and Active Gloves</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/salomon-active-glove-gloves/?pid=10239">Active Gloves</a> haven’t seen any use yet, but I expect them to come in handy when it will be single digits in the mornings and evenings when I head out for a run. They allow me to use the phone and are light at 34 g, now I just need to see if they keep my fingers warm and if they’re not too hot to make my hands sweat! / <em>34g in Size L</em></p>

<p>I wish I would have bought the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/marken/salomon/?pid=10239">Air Logo Cap</a> earlier. It is really breathable with the mesh back, reasonably light at 44 g and most importantly, it is comfortable, all day long. I tried another cap earlier in the summer and was disappointed, but this one is really good and I reckon it will also come along on backpacking trips with me. / <em>44 g</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30477244428/in/dateposted/" title="Salomon Air Logo Cap and Active Gloves"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1857/30477244428_8167f1b57e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salomon Air Logo Cap and Active Gloves" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="other-shoes">Other shoes</h2>

<p>I have written in my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/08/gear-outtakes-summer-2018.html">Gear Outtakes</a> article about a few other trailrunning shoes I have used this summer, all of which I have liked. Each pair seems to excel in different conditions, and some of the shoes I got (like the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/s/La--Sportiva--VK/category--outdoor-shoes/?pid=10239">La Sportiva VK</a>) really are superb shoes for my local trails, while some other ones I will be using when I go running in the mountains later in the autumn. I might follow this article up with another article before the winter when I have ran a decent amount of kilometres in each pair.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44343936961/in/dateposted/" title="Shoes!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1900/44343936961_bbd2f8034a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoes!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="petzl-nao">Petzl NAO+</h2>

<p>I have used the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/petzl-nao-headlamp-bf/?pid=10239">NAO+</a> for a long time (I was a Beta tester for it) and still find it my favourite lamp for running and other activities when it gets dark (hiking, cycling, ice climbing and ski-touring, for example). At 195 g it is not the lightest headlamp out there, but with a maximum of 750 lumen it illuminates the trails really well and I don’t need to worry about not seeing a root or slippery rock. It sits secure on my head, the weight is well distributed and it’s easy to control the lamp via the iPhone app to change settings. If you run in the dark and want a light that adjusts it’s output depending on where you look - this is the one you want! / <em>195 g</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44343935911/in/dateposted/" title="Petzl NAO+"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1883/44343935911_dd8c6ba15d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Petzl NAO+" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="jaybird-freedom-2-headphones-buff-and-oakley-latch-shades">Jaybird Freedom 2 Headphones, BUFF and Oakley Latch Shades</h2>

<p>I don’t run without music. I find it helps me to lose my mind when running, power up hills and get energy when I think I can’t continue anymore. In the middle of the summer I got the <a href="http://bit.ly/2PMkyLz">Jaybird Freedom 2 Headphones</a> and it has been such an update from the standard iPhone headphones. The latter had the cable, but the Jaybird Freedome 2 are wireless which is such a treat. On a full charge they play music for 4 hours, the block out noise really well, and they don’t have trouble with sweat as they’re Sweat-proof &amp; water resistant. The headphones come with several interchangeable tips and fins which makes getting a perfect fit with them a breeze - and most importantly, they sound fantastic! (<a href="https://open.spotify.com/user/spotify/playlist/37i9dQZF1DX06VUQ1GoKge?si=sWCKALEKRWy4kl8E0nj_1A">This is the playlist I mostly listen too when running</a>) / <em>20 g incl. the clip</em></p>

<p>My <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/buff-original-buff-multi-function-bandana/?pid=10239">BUFF</a> is ancient and I use it mainly to keep the sweat from my face and the hair outta my eyes. On those super-sunny runs it also helps protect my head from the sun, and after the run it’s easy to wipe the sweat and grime off with it. When it will turn colder it can function has a beanie or around my neck, making this a great multi-use piece throughout the year. / <em>44 g</em></p>

<p>My <a href="http://bit.ly/2olyUWR">Oakley Latch Shades</a> I bought early in the winter of 2018 and boy do I love them. They’re small in size and fit my head well, they really are anti-fog as they’re pretty open and yes, they also look cool. They are very light, super comfortable for all-day long use (and I do use them all the time when I am outside) and when I run they sit securely on my head in combination with the Buff. In the forest they keep pine needles, leaves and twigs outta my eyes, and out in the open the sun and it’s UV rays have no chance of getting into my eyes. / <em>22 g</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44343937871/in/dateposted/" title="Shades, BUFF and Jaybird Freedom 2"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1865/44343937871_39734a102d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shades, BUFF and Jaybird Freedom 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="energy-for-my-runs">Energy for my runs</h2>

<p>I have used these <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/clif-bar-shot-gel-razz-energy-gel/?pid=10239">Clifbar Gels</a> and <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/clif-bar-shot-margarita-citrus-energy-gel/?pid=10239">Bloks</a> for many years now and like them, but as I am slowly transforming my diet (I aim to be Vegan, nutrition-wise, by the end of the year) I hope to find something which suits me better. I tried Trailbutter at the #OutDoorFN and loved that, but sadly it isn’t possible to get these in Europe just yet. Thus for now I will stick to the gels and blocks from Clifbar, which I can use without much problems to my stomach or digestion, and they give me a good boost when I am out on a long run!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44343939191/in/dateposted/" title="Energy"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1852/44343939191_2cb70920c8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Energy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>That’s it!</strong> All the gear (minus some packs, which I don’t want to write about just yet) I use when I go running. It might seem a lot, though in reality it’s a pretty lightweight and compact kit and easily always comes along on my trips where I’m not backpacking for a week. Best of all, it makes me happy to put it on, head out and get my head free when I’m running through my local forests 🏃!</p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44343928751/in/dateposted/" title="Love my local trails"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1895/44343928751_6883e10962_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Love my local trails" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kilian Jornet: Run Or Die]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/08/kilian-jornet-run-or-die.html"/>
    <updated>2015-08-28T23:42:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/08/kilian-jornet-run-or-die</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you don’t know who Kilian Jornet is you have a great opportunity to get to know him in this personal look at what motivates him, why he runs and why he enjoys being outdoors.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20959699761/in/dateposted/" title="Run Or Die"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5748/20959699761_61679e92f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Run Or Die" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In nine chapters and 181 pages you get to know Kilian rather well. From his cycling adventures with his mom and sister, training for races and what goes on in his mind when he runs and competes. I don’t really like competitions, especially in the outdoors, but still found it interesting to read &amp; understand what drives him to go stand in a line and compete. I could very well relate to the difficulty at times to overcome one’s inner swine which just wants to stay in bed or chill on the sofa instead of going out for training, but Kilian trains (or competes) 360 days per year so I think many of use can learn in that department something from him!</p>

<p>The book is written in a pleasant way which is easy to read. Kilian takes you on a journey from his days as a child over his youth to a love story and onwards to the Western States Endurance and a run up &amp; down Kilimanjaro. You learn about his preparation for races, his music taste, where he loves to run and what goes on in his head when he runs the UTMB and other competitions. And in the end you learn that he, like you &amp; me, also really just enjoys to be outside and be active.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20959700571/in/dateposted/" title="Run Or Die"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5622/20959700571_6f982521e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Run Or Die" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The desire I feel is the same as I felt in the United States: I want to challenge myself, give the best of myself, and try to discover what my thresholds are, to know myself better.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So for whom is this book? I think it’s a good read for anyone who is interested in being outside and ponders what others think &amp; feel when being in nature. Trailrunners, ski mountaineers and fans of Kilian definitely should pick up his book, too, and learn what drives the most dominating endurance athlete of our time to push the envelope.</p>

<p>Buy Run Or Die at your local bookstore or ordered it online at <a href="http://amzn.to/1VhXcKh">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Ip3nTz">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1JBIsSv">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Christopher McDougall: Born To Run]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/05/christopher-mcdougall-born-to-run.html"/>
    <updated>2015-05-22T22:48:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/05/christopher-mcdougall-born-to-run</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s rare that I read a science/ novel/ diet/ adventure book which with each turn of the page has me think just one thing: I wanna go out for a run. Barefoot. <em><a href="http://amzn.to/1EnnrUf">Born to Run</a></em> is that book, and it is fortunate that the sun doesn’t set until 23 o’clock, leaving plenty of time for a quick run after reading in the evening.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17966167111" title="Born To Run by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7728/17966167111_9cc4bcb40f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Born To Run" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Born to Run sat for a while on my book shelf, and finally a couple of weeks ago I started reading it. Like many <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">books</a> it was difficult to put down and but as the clock was going towards midnight I resistantly put the book down and went to sleep, just to read a couple more pages in the morning. As an ultralight backpacker and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a> enthusiast I have been since a long time an advocate of minimalist footwear, this book serves you with a great story why modern running (and hiking) shoes are bad for you &amp; great reasons why you should go for a run if you feel stressed.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Suffering is humbling. It pays to know how to get your butt kicked.</em> -Caballo Blanco</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But from the start. Christopher McDougall, the author, is a running enthusiast - but after plenty of problems with achilles tendons, knees and back pain he’s about to put his running shoes on the hook. After seeing a photo of a Tarahumara runner in a magazine while being on assignment in Mexico McDougall starts the search for these runners, which takes him deep down into the Copper Canyons in search of them and the mystical Caballo Blanco. What evolves is part adventure novel, part science &amp; nutrition journal and part sports history, in which you find out how McDougall went from almost stopping to run to running an Ultra in the Copper Canyon, meeting Scott Jurek and running with the elusive Tarahumara indians.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17777626938" title="Born To Run by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5321/17777626938_555fa11535_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Born To Run" /></a></p>

<p>Born to Run is mandatory reading for runners, and also backpackers - because the latter are just endurance runners that go a tad slower. It’s a gripping read that will have you forget the time while you turn each page in anticipation, ditch your running shoes, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Aju8Ms">try new foods</a>, ponder your first Ultra and having the itch to go out for a run. Pick Born To Run up at your local bookshop or order it from <a href="http://amzn.to/1EnnrUf">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1FHztyZ">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1K8Ebns">Amazon.de</a> - and be prepared to wanna go running after reading a couple of pages!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outdoor Gift Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/11/the-outdoor-gift-guide.html"/>
    <updated>2013-11-19T14:02:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/11/the-outdoor-gift-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is that time of the year again, even if I see <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2012/">Advents Calendars</a>, Spekulatius and Stollen already already since September in the stores. Time to ponder what is the best gift for hikers, armchair adventurers, climbers, and trail runners.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/mjanicki/5295571160/" title="Presents under the Tree by M. Janicki"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5210/5295571160_d78c515584_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Presents under the Tree" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>The Best Gifts are No Gifts or Services.</strong> <em>Despite what follows, I strongly believe the best gift you can give your loved ones are non-tangible gifts, as in services and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/guided-trips/">experiences</a>. Go for a hike or climb together (or let him/ her go for one!), maybe eat out or a give a nice Spa visit. Also arranging time off for your loved ones, so that they could pursue what they’d like to do, are great gifts. They’re better for the planet, too =)</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7751496934/" title="Up by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7279/7751496934_f2be74de50_b.jpg" width="1024" height="487" alt="Up" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gifts-for-the-hiker">Gifts for The Hiker</h2>

<p>High on the list of any hiker are gifts from his favourite cottage. Here is whats definitely worth getting for your hiking friend:</p>

<ul>
  <li>You can’t go wrong with a <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/hiking-climbing-shelters/mids.html">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Mid</a>. Light, spacious and easy to pitch, you also can find shelter under it when you head outdoors with your hiking buddy!</li>
  <li>Outside it is getting cold, so a warm <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/Schlafsaecke/Quilts:::2_78.html?refID=hif">down quilt</a> from <a href="http://www.trekking-lite-store.com/trekkingshop/index.php?refID=hif">Trekking-Lite-Store.com</a> will ensure warm nights during winter camps.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.laufbursche-gear.de/">Laufbursche Gear</a> is coming out with four completely re-designed packs in 2014. There’s never such a thing as too many backpacks, so getting a brand new 2014 huckePACK is definitely something to wait for January 2014 and get!</li>
  <li>And as its cold and wet outside, a <a href="http://www.outdoorline.sk/en/32-synthetic-insulation">synthetic insulation garment</a> would work well also in the summer. Warms even when moist, synthetic is the way to go in wet &amp; cold environments.</li>
  <li>Finally, <a href="http://www.avantlink.com/click.php?tt=ml&amp;ti=9933&amp;pw=73183">REI Gift Cards or e-Gift Cards</a> are a one-size-fits-all gift for your favourite outdoor enthusiast. Don’t trouble yourself picking up the wrong gift - just give a gift card!</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8544632349/" title="Anders leading a route by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8508/8544632349_56e6a0a150_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Anders leading a route" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gifts-for-the-climber">Gifts for The Climber</h2>

<p>Ah, the climber. Divided into many sub-species - the Boulderer, the Sports Climber, the Trad Climber, the Mountaineer or the Alpinist - you hopefully know which kind of climbing the receiver of your gift is practicing. Because a boulder doesn’t do much with a pair of crampons!</p>

<ul>
  <li>The ice climber will be giving you extra hugs and thanks for a pair of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/petzl-nomic-ice-tools.html">Petzl Nomic ice tools</a>.</li>
  <li>Boulderers fall. That the fall is more soft, put a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/ocun-paddy-dominator-crashpad.html">Ocún Paddy Dominator Crashpad</a> under the tree for them - large, light and functions as a mattress in a pinch, this is a superb crashpad to fall on when the holds are just too small to hold on to any longer.</li>
  <li>The Sport &amp; Trad Climber alike will welcome the gift of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/dmm-classic-rope-bag.html">DMM Classic Rope Bag</a> for their ropes, be they single, twin or halfs.</li>
  <li>Alpinsts and Mountaineers need helmets for their adventures. At the moment there’s no lighter and fully certified helmet on the market than the <a href="http://bit.ly/1apnPXN">Sirocco Climbing Helmet</a>, and I can say out of <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/climbing-at-havukallio.html">experience</a> that it survives falls just great!</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/scarpa/">Scarpa climbing shoes</a> will be a welcome gift for any climber. <a href="http://www.bergzeit.co.uk/scarpa-instinct-vc-climbing-shoe-silver-orange/">Instinct VCs</a> for the boulderers &amp; sports climbers, <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots.html">Scarpa Phantom Ultra Boots</a> for the alpinists, ice climbers and mountaineers, Scarpa makes great shoes for all!</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/garryknight/8560855544/" title="Mounted Police on a City Street by garryknight, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8392/8560855544_eb1a0bc3df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="678" alt="Mounted Police on a City Street" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gifts-for-the-urban-hiker">Gifts for The Urban Hiker</h2>

<p>The urban hiker, also called Armchair Adventurer, would like to spend more time in the wild but finding enough time between family, work and other commitments proves difficult. You could make sure he has a free weekend for some hiking/ climbing/ packrafting/ cycling, and maybe consider one of these items for the everyday outdoor adventure:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Is there a backpack which can do everything? Yes, it’s the <a href="http://www.goruck.com/en/gr1">GORUCK GR1</a>. Wear it to work, go climbing, travel for a week and then head out backpacking, cycling to work. The GR1 does it all, and will last you a lifetime.</li>
  <li><a href="http://us.shop.ecco.com/men-outdoor/men-outdoor,default,sc.html#sz=60">ECCO shoes</a> look the deal and will perform on the way to the office and for the after-work hike to the scenic lookout.</li>
  <li>Trousers. Some call them pants. Whatever you call them, with a pair from <a href="http://shop.outlier.cc/retail/pants/">Outlier</a> you will sport a functional pair that looks great in the city and takes you everywhere your bike and feet can take you, keeping you dry and warm in nasty weather.</li>
  <li>Again a late day at the office? A fine <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">outdoor book</a> is just what’s needed then. Sit down at home, take a dram and skim through one of these fine books to let at least the mind escape the urban environment. A good option is also a <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/abonnement">subscription to trekking Magazin</a>.</li>
  <li>Also in an urban environment it is useful to know the time. And the barometric pressure. And where is north. That’s why a <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/garmin-fenix.html">Garmin fēnix</a> might be an useful gift for those that easily get lost in the city, and need to find their way back.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/akunamatata/2821684589/" title="UTMB 2008 (160) by akunamatata, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3291/2821684589_0fbf842eeb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="UTMB 2008 (160)" /></a></p>

<h2 id="gifts-for-the-trailrunner">Gifts for The Trailrunner</h2>

<p>The trailrunner is the kind of person who will head out in pretty much any weather. Snow? Extra fun! Rain? Where’s that hardshell? Cold feet? Run faster!</p>

<ul>
  <li>You can not go wrong with a Vest from <a href="http://bit.ly/17Iug9J">Ultimate Direction</a>. Hands-down the best running vests, your trailrunning mate will run in happy circles around you!</li>
  <li>A second pair of his favourite <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/trailrunningschuhe/fuer--maenner/">trailrunning shoes</a>. Chances are his first pair are at the end of the life already, so why not get her/ him a new pair?!</li>
  <li>Chances are your trailrunning gift receiver also is just now outside running, despite the weather being close to 0°C and it’s rainy. Time to get some sweet <a href="http://www.theomm.com/products/clothing/">The OMM</a> garments which will keep him/ her warm in this fresh weather!</li>
  <li><a href="https://guenergy.com/">GU Energy</a> makes top notch gels, and getting a mix of these will be the best running nutrition stuff you can get to keep him running.</li>
  <li><a href="http://bit.ly/1bAKKwa">Running glasses</a> create shade and keep wind, dirt and rain from the eyes, so that they can stay focussed on the trail ahead. Being able to change lenses is a big advantage - the light is different in the snow than in the desert!</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hades2k/6598576457/" title="Christmas presents by Hades2k, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7029/6598576457_8234fc4768_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Christmas presents" /></a></p>

<p><em>Pssst! All of the above not good enough? May I then recommend getting a <a href="https://www.alpackaraft.com/index.cfm/store.catalog/Packrafts">packraft</a> &amp; <a href="http://surlybikes.com/bikes/moonlander">Fatbike</a>? You sure may get me one ;) !</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Inov-8 TrailRoc 235]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/10/inov-8-trailroc-235.html"/>
    <updated>2013-10-28T15:34:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2013/10/inov-8-trailroc-235</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.inov-8.com/New/Global/Product-View-Trailroc-235-Aqua-Lime-Red.html?L=26&amp;A=Trail&amp;G=Male">inov-8 TrailRoc 235</a> is a minimalistic trail shoe which gives you plenty of grip while being very lightweight. An excellent choice for those who want to try barefoot shoes for hiking and trail-running, the TrailRoc 235 features the new Tri-C Sole and has a fairly wide toebox. <em>A living review.</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9769597455/" title="Fording by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5463/9769597455_bec44fa062_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Fording" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The TrailRoc 235 arrived in August and have been worn pretty exactly for</p>

<ul>
  <li>45 backpacking km</li>
  <li>42,2 trail marathon km</li>
  <li>115 backpacking km</li>
  <li>20 urban asphalt km</li>
</ul>

<p>So a tad over 220 km (<a href="http://www.moves-app.com/">Moves App</a> is pretty nifty) over 14 days. Unlike other shoes I decided to exclusively use the TrailRoc 235 for backpacking and trailrunning, and not for e.g. walking to the supermarket and cycling =)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10534478445/" title="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Bird-eye view by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5482/10534478445_a234f7b629_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Bird-eye view" /></a></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>A shoes function is to protect you from, like, stepping on sharp stones with bare feet. Or bumping your toes into roots on the trail. They give you grip on wet, muddy slopes. So grip and protection is its job, which the TrailRoc 235 does very well.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10534482115/" title="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Sole by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3748/10534482115_0fdbd1e79b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Sole" /></a></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Meta-Flex - a groove in the forefoot that provides a natural flex point in the shoe, allowing the forefoot to function naturally with each step</li>
  <li>Tri-C: Three sticky rubber compounds in different hardness give optimal wear and maximum grip on dry and loose trails</li>
  <li>5-finger polymer Meta-Shank™</li>
  <li>6 mm Footbed</li>
  <li>Zero Drop</li>
  <li>Natural Fit</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="fit">Fit</h2>

<p>inov-8 shoes fit me perfectly. As I said before, it’s difficult to judge fit - as your feet are different than mine. They have, what I find, a wide-ish toebox which offers plenty of space, and my toes can play piano in them (just, well, I haven’t found a small enough piano yet).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10534518184/" title="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Outside by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7367/10534518184_81ae325c5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Outside" /></a></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Hard to say, though possibly the Tri-C - the three sticky rubber compounds in different hardness - count as an innovation.</p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>After only two weeks of trail use its hard to judge on quality, though so far the shoe has held up very well, apart from some parts of the tread already starting to rub off. But then I have been <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/run-or-die-nuuksio-classic-trail-marathon.html">trailrunning</a> and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">backpacking</a> on a lot of rocks with them, so that’s to be expected. Other than that the shoe has held up very well, with no failures.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10534448805/" title="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Sole front by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5518/10534448805_c797939b45_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Sole front" /></a>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10534674323/" title="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Sole heel by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3796/10534674323_0d39604cf8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Sole heel" /></a></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My pair in UK Size 8.5 is 494 gram, or 247 g per shoe. Not the lightest, but so light that I felt the difference after using slightly heavier shoes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10534475746/" title="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3669/10534475746_140b1d8c17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="inov-8 TrailRoc 235" /></a></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>Inov-8 still has a nice little story on their website entitled “<a href="http://www.inov-8.com/New/Global/Environment.html?L=26">Inov-8, the environment and climate change</a>”. Inov-8 has undergone an Environmental Footprint audit, and they tell us about their carbon footprint (Surprise: Shoes &amp; packaging account for only 17% of it - the biggest impact comes from staff travel). I still am not aware if Inov-8 offers a take-back of their shoes for recycling (via retailers, for example).</p>

<p>Another aspect is the ethical question. The shoes are made in China, though that happily nowadays is more positive than in the past. Inov-8 also tell us about their <a href="http://www.inov-8.com/New/Global/Manufacturing-Ethics.html?L=26">Manufacturing Ethics</a>, in which they highlight that there’s no child labour involved in the making of their products, and that employees are paid above average salaries.</p>

<p>All in all I applaud that Inov-8 are transparent in their communications about these matters, though I’d welcome to see a Name &amp; Email there for interested people to contact them, as well as an independent source of the provided information for even more transparency.</p>

<p>Recyclability is also still a hard question, though as these hopefully will be in use for another few hundreds of trail kilometres it isn’t yet a pressing question.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9522122121/" title="New shoes: Inov-8 TrailRoc 235 by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5506/9522122121_cd3204a299_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="New shoes: Inov-8 TrailRoc 235" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>As said above, I used the TrailRoc 235 exclusively for backpacking and trailrunning, and for that I loved them right away. Their first outing they had on a Ultralight Backpacking Basics course, out of the box, fresh and never used before. It’s also where I managed to get them their nice muddy look as we navigated through a swamp. They were dry again an hour later, which I liked a lot.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9643589034/" title="There were roots. by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5461/9643589034_54a12afb22_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="There were roots." /></a></p>

<p>They also dry quickly after wading though a cool river - maybe an hour or two walking in warm temps and the shoes were dry again. Their mesh uppers don’t absorb a lot of water, and the shoe is quite airy - excellent for warm weather, for certain. It’s also stretchy, so if I find that little toe piano, I can insert it and still play it, because the mesh gives way a bit.</p>

<p>The protection against rocks &amp; roots is good, there’s a toe bumper, a thin plastic coating, which keeps your toes sane when you bump them against rocks and roots. It also helps to prevent getting stuff in, though if sand wants to get in, it will just try its luck via the mesh or that big hole where your foot goes in. The grip on rocks, mud and roots is very good in my opinion, I had no problems fording through rivers/ jumping from wet stone to wet stone. Even slippery and wet roots on forest trails didn’t make me slip, and not even the most slippery thing we have in Finland could stop me: Moist duckboards.</p>

<p>The Laces are much better than previous laces on inov-8s I had before, these tended to disintegrated at the top quickly, though these look like new still. They also don’t slip and once put closed (with a double knot) they stay closed.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9643679440/" title="There were soft muddy trails by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3718/9643679440_95bd03cc9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="There were soft muddy trails" /></a></p>

<h2 id="competing-products">Competing Products</h2>

<p>Well, there’s the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/07/inov-8-x-talon-190.html">X-Talon 190</a> and the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/salomon-speedcross-3.html">Salomon Speedcross 3</a>, but the latter have more cushioning than the TrailRoc here. The <a href="http://bit.ly/17nJZLe">TrailRoc 150</a> and the <a href="http://www.inov-8.com/New/Global/Product-View-BareGrip-200.html?L=26&amp;A=Off%20Trail&amp;G=Male">Bare-Grip 200</a> are Zero Drop shoes from inov-8, the <a href="http://bit.ly/17nJl0o">New Balance Minimus</a> shoes and the <a href="http://bit.ly/1eZBS72">Salomon S-Lab shoes</a>. Oh, and <a href="https://www.lunasandals.com/">Luna Sandals</a> with the Oso also should be considered a competitor. Amongst other, I’m certain!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10534465145/" title="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Inside by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7300/10534465145_f537a9e3c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="inov-8 TrailRoc 235 Inside" /></a></p>

<h2 id="what-others-say">What Others Say</h2>

<p>Damien compares his <a href="http://www.toesalad.com/reviews/trail-shoe-showdown-the-vivobarefoot-breatho-trail-vs-the-inov-8-trailroc-235/">Inov-8 TrailRoc 235 with the VIVOBAREFOOT Breatho Trail</a>, Peter <a href="http://www.runblogger.com/2013/01/inov-8-trailroc-235-trail-running-shoe.html">rates them very high</a> and Ryan finds it’s a <a href="http://www.borntorun.com/blogs/barefoot-bulletin/7422436-inov-8-trailroc-235-review">superb trail runner</a>.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Hiking and running in the TrailRoc 235s has been a pleasure. Great grip, lightweight, nice colours, quick-drying - I couldn’t ask for more. They have carried me safely up the highest mountain in Eastern Finland across extensiv boulder fields, helped me finish my first trailrunning marathon, and I’m looking forward to wear them soon again for late autumn backpacking!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157637044274066/">More photos</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-buy-the-inov-8-trailroc-235">Where to buy the Inov-8 TrailRoc 235</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/inov-8-trailroc-235-trailrunningschuhe/">Bergfreunde</a></td>
      <td> <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/inov8-trailroc-235-schuhe-aqua-lime-red/">Bergzeit</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763631271/" title="Bridge by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3809/9763631271_9270fc0f99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Bridge" /></a></p>

<h2 id="in-the-next-update">In the next update</h2>

<p>These obviously have not been used so much that they’re at the end of their life-cycle. Hence there shall be updates:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Usage after 500 km, 600 km, 700 km, etc.</li>
  <li>Failures</li>
  <li>Recycled?</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
