<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: advent calendar 2016 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/advent-calendar-2016/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2017-12-13T19:08:06+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Send-off 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/adzhifako-2016.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-25T23:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/adzhifako-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <em>“Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off 2016”</em> is a Send-Off this year - Happy holidays!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31176518325/in/dateposted/" title="Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off 2016"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5772/31176518325_23a994985b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Annual Day Zero HiF Advent Calendar Kick-off 2016" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>I really missed talking to you. Twelve months is a long time of radio-silence, and I have a lot to tell you. Like all the awesome trips I have been on this year, from <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/lyngen.html">Ski-touring in Lyngen</a> to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/autumn-backpacking-in-the-dolomites.html">backpacking in the Dolomites</a>, 2016 has been fantastic. I spent great moments <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/family-adventures-in-the-bregenzerwald.html">with my family in the mountains</a>, and am looking very much forward to winter backpacking and other adventures.</p>

<p>But lets get down to business and start talking about the holiday season and the awesome <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/advent-calendar-2016/">Hiking in Finland Advent Calendar</a>. I saw it was again very nicely filled with prizes worth over 5.000€, and what better way to celebrate an awesome #HiFAdventCalendar season than with a sweet ADZHiFASO package from some small companies!</p>

<p><a href="https://whoopieslings.com/">whoopieslings.com</a> make a complete Hammock and Tarp Suspension Systems, and as I decided to give hammocks another chance what would be better than having a smart suspension system for it? A set of 6” whoopie slings, a pair of 6’ tree huggers and a pair of toggles should make setting up my hammock a breeze!</p>

<p>Similar to hammocking I think it is time to step up my trailrunning again! A <a href="http://www.ks-ultralightgear.com/p/blog-page_13.html">VRV8 Pack</a> from KS ultralight gear would be ideal for that - the pack is super simple yet efficient and packs all I need for a day out running in the forests and hills. It carries my poles, soft flasks or water bottles, and 8 l of gear fit into the main compartment, all with restricting movement.</p>

<p>One thing I have learned which should always be along is a pair of rain mitts. The <a href="http://www.mountainlaureldesigns.com/shop/product_info.php?cPath=37&amp;products_id=51">Mountain Laurel Design eVent Rain Mitts</a> are the lightest rain mitts on the market and rumour has it that if one carries a pair rain usually doesn’t bother one when outside, so they’re kind of a good charm, too!</p>

<p>Also a pair of <a href="https://goosefeetgear.com/products/1-down-socks">GooseFeet Gear Down Socks</a> have been on my list for a long time - not just because I get awfully could feet at camp in winter, but also because they pack so tiny &amp; light when I’m hiking throughout the day. Filled with 850 fill power DownTek down these socks keep me toasty on my winter adventures, which is especially great after a long day in boots!</p>

<p>And finally, a <a href="https://www.hydroflask.com/32-oz-wide-bottle#92=20">32 oz Wide Mouth Bottle</a> from Hydro Flask would be swell - not just for plenty of coffee the whole day but also for keeping drinks cold in the heat. It is BPA-Free, Toxin-Free and comes with a Lifetime Warranty - so this would be the last bottle I’d ever ask for!</p>

<p><em>To win this sweet prize package</em> just enter via the Rafflecopter Widget below:</p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd89586/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd89586" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_c4nk8l5v">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/advent-calendar-2016-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prizes are sent directly from the companies, possible <strong>import duty fees need to be paid by the winner</strong>. You can choose the colour of the Hydro Flask and whoopieslings, the size of the socks and rain mitts.*</p>

<p><em>I was abroad in Mexico and there were technical difficulties in the backend of the blog. While I fix a few little things you can read <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/packing-for-ski-touring.html">how I pack for a ski-touring trip</a> =) </em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 24]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/advent-calendar-door-24.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-24T00:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/advent-calendar-door-24</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/e208W7" title="Mammut"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3682/11277513273_f4fd79af1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Mammut" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>also for freeriding and ski-touring lighter means better: A lighter ski, boot and backpack allows you to skin up in more comfort &amp; faster, while at the same time preserving energy for the ride down. <a href="https://www.mammut.ch/">Mammut</a> updated their <a href="https://www.mammut.ch/INT/en/B2C-Kategorie/Skiing-Boarding/Ride-Removable-Airbag-3-0/p/2610-01250-0001-1030">Ride Removable Airbag 3.0 Backpack</a> which got even lighter this year, with the Removable Airbag System 3.0 getting even more compact &amp; dependable while remaining just as removable and transferable to other compatible packs as before. The airbag system itself is just 690 g and with a carbon cartridge it tips the scales at barely over 1 kg. The 30l backpack on the other hand fits enough gear for a long day in the mountains, with a front pocket for avalanche safety equipment &amp; a padded google pocket, it carries skis or a snowboard and an integrated helmet carrier carries the helmet when skinning up, too. All in all it’s a might fine pack and Airbag System that helps to keep me safe during deep powder days where the avalanche risk is high! Now lets hope that this winter is going to be better than the last one!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31712245731/in/dateposted/" title="Advent Calendar Mammut Ride Removable Airbag"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/1/432/31712245731_d9276d7a11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Advent Calendar Mammut Ride Removable Airbag" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895113/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895113" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_6jhkau0l">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/advent-calendar-2016-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prize, a Ride Removable Backpack 3.0 incl. the Airbag System, is sent directly from Mammut in Switzerland. <em>Possible import duty fees need to be paid by the winner</em>.</p>

<p><em>I was abroad in Mexico and there were technical difficulties in the backend of the blog. While I fix a few little things you can read <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/packing-for-ski-touring.html">how I pack for a ski-touring trip</a> =) </em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 23]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/advent-calendar-door-23.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-23T00:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/advent-calendar-door-23</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31691873471/in/dateposted/" title="Advent Calendar Paramo"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/1/735/31691873471_a3c4ba841c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Advent Calendar Paramo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>you know what I like (you probably do by now =)? Small companies which make innovative gear. <a href="http://www.paramo-clothing.de/">Páramo</a> is such a company, which not only designs &amp; makes great garments for outdoor activities, they also do good and foster ethical &amp; sustainable production. Take their <a href="">Enduro Jacket</a> for example, which is made from their directional Nikwax Analogy Waterproof fabric. It is Made in Colombia, is 100% PFC Free, at the end of its long life it can be recycled via the Páramo Recycling Scheme and the company helps to fund conservation projects across the globe. That’s a lot of good things a single jacket can do for people, planet and the one wearing it. Made for the mountains the Enduro can accompany one ski-touring and alpine climbing with its great freedom of movement, while the many pockets keep important kit close at hand. The large peak on the helmet-compatible hood keeps snow and rain at bay, and large arm vents help to stay cool when skinning up a mountain. And after a long season of use &amp; fun it can be made like new again by washing it with Nikwax products! Yeps, that are exactly the kind of things I like and wish there would be more from!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31691873351/in/dateposted/" title="Advent Calendar Paramo Enduro Jacket"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5612/31691873351_6bb898e511_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Advent Calendar Paramo Enduro Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895112/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895112" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_djv68ext">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/advent-calendar-2016-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prize, an Enduro Jacket (Winner can pick the Size), is sent directly from Páramo in the UK. <em>Possible import duty fees need to be paid by the winner</em>.</p>

<p><em>I was abroad in Mexico and there were technical difficulties in the backend of the blog. While I fix a few little things you can read this Layering Guide and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">How to Dress for Winter</a>!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 22]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/advent-calendar-door-22.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-22T00:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/advent-calendar-door-22</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31671903601/in/dateposted/" title="Advent Calendar Ruta Locura"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/1/777/31671903601_91da1e6a8e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Advent Calendar Ruta Locura" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p><a href="http://www.rutalocura.com/">Ruta Locura</a> is one of those small cottages which know their trade and their ultralight materials, in in their case that’s carbon fibre. Josh has been building since the mid-2000s carbon fibre and titanium goods for ultralight backpackers, campers, fishermen and hunters alike, and their <a href="http://www.rutalocura.com/trekking_poles.html">Yana Trekking Poles</a> are some of the most versatile poles on the market. Not just are they great to pitch Pyramid shelters and tarps at the end of the day, they also can be transformed into a tenkara rod when you want to add some trout to the Menu in the evening! The poles are also light, as you would expect, and so durable that a pair should last with some proper care and maintenance at least half a lite time!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31788281185/in/dateposted/" title="Advent Calendar Ruta Locura Yana"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/1/364/31788281185_7a98b6b907_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Advent Calendar Ruta Locura Yana" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895111/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895111" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_mo0hq0o9">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/advent-calendar-2016-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prize, a pair of Yana 2017 trekking poles, is sent directly from Ruta Locura in the USA. <em>Possible import duty fees need to be paid by the winner</em>.</p>

<p><em>I was abroad in Mexico and there were technical difficulties in the backend of the blog. While I fix a few little things you can read this Layering Guide and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">How to Dress for Winter</a>!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advent Calendar Door 21]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/advent-calendar-door-21.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-21T00:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/12/advent-calendar-door-21</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31652260101/in/dateposted/" title="Advent Calendar Mountain Equipment"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/1/416/31652260101_85d55cacb3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Advent Calendar Mountain Equipment" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Dear Santa,</p>

<p>Winter is also the time for wearing toasty warm down jackets. But down does not equal down, and hence we as consumers need to sometimes steer companies into the right direction. One company which doesn’t need steering but is leading in responsibly manufactured down is <a href="http://www.mountain-equipment.de">Mountain Equipment</a> with their <a href="http://www.thedowncodex.co.uk">Down Codex</a>. Since many years they offer customers the ability to 100% trace the down in their sleeping bags and jackets, which means one can have peace of mind in knowing that the down which keeps one warm was gathered with animal welfare in mind. So back to that toasty jacket I mentioned: With winters being warmer in the last few years a jacket like the <a href="http://www.mountain-equipment.de/arete-hooded-jacket">Men’s Arete Hooded Jacket</a> is ideal for the temperatures one encounters in our winters. The 320 g light jacket comes with two zippered pockets for cold hands &amp; camera batteries, and the hood ensures also ears and neck don’t need to freeze. Best of all: The water-resistant down doesn’t collapse when the snow turns to slush, and with some smart layering one could use this down jacket all year around!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31621673522/in/dateposted/" title="Advent Calendar ME Arete Hooded Jacket"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5609/31621673522_ed44e133fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Advent Calendar ME Arete Hooded Jacket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a class="rcptr" href="http://www.rafflecopter.com/rafl/display/2eafd895110/" rel="nofollow" data-raflid="2eafd895110" data-theme="classic" data-template="547b1bf514e3887a6c34e3c0" id="rcwidget_zvfdkq8f">a Rafflecopter giveaway</a>
<script src="https://widget-prime.rafflecopter.com/launch.js"></script></p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/11/advent-calendar-2016-the-rules.html">Read The Tips &amp; Rules</a>. The prize, a Mountain Equipment Men’s or <a href="http://www.mountain-equipment.de/arete-hooded-wmns-jacket">Women’s Arete Hooded Jacket</a> (you can choose Sex, Size, Colour), is sent directly from Mountain Equipment in Germany. <em>Possible import duty fees need to be paid by the winner</em>.</p>

<p><em>I was abroad in Mexico and there were technical difficulties in the backend of the blog. While I fix a few little things you can read this Layering Guide and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/02/layering-guide-how-to-dress-for-winter.html">How to Dress for Winter</a>!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
