<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: huckepacks | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/huckepacks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-09-18T10:17:00+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/09/huckepacks-phoenix-lite-review.html"/>
    <updated>2020-09-10T19:28:37+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/09/huckepacks-phoenix-lite-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“When will you review the HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite?”</em> has been one of the most asked questions I have received in the past year - pretty much since I <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B3GwSM3jA_C/">posted this pic</a> last autumn. Well, after 12 months of use, the review is finally here!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327475092/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS in the GREEN"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327475092_0c8791ea0e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS in the GREEN" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from HUCKEPACKS. There are Affiliate links in this article which are marked with an ∞ Infinity Sign 😊 You can use these <strong>AT NO EXTRA COST TO YOU</strong> but I get a small provision from the company. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on the affiliate links in this article &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/phoenix-lite/">HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite</a> is a 50 l Volume backpack which carries ridiculously comfortable up to 10 kg, and that for a weight of under 300 g. Add in the ZLite backpanel and the Hipbelt Plus and you can carry even more weight, in more comfort. It’s unique Accordion closure makes accessing the content easy without opening the rolltop, and gives this stylish pack a clean, functional look. It is ideal for backpackers who already have a base weight of four to five kilogram and are familiar with the ideas of ultralight backpacking. Watch the <a href="https://youtu.be/3tV8alDSVMo">Video</a> to see the pack in action:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3tV8alDSVMo" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received my Phoenix Lite in August 2019, and it has been with me <a href="https://youtu.be/-AYVkZf61UE">backpacking in Hammastunturi Wilderness</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/vPzDSYp71I4">hiking &amp; packrafting the Björkö-Panike Trail</a> and on many shorter trips around Vaasa.</p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>This <strong>ULTRALIGHT</strong> backpack is made to enable your outdoor adventures without carrying a gram too much. It does carry really damn comfortable, though =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744082458/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744082458_873ca178ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Phoenix Lite with a Medium back length weighs 296 g including all straps. Together with the optional <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/hipbelt-plus-lite/">Hipbelt Plus Lite</a> (Size S, 57 g/ Pair), one <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/hipbelt-pocket/">Hipbelt Pocket</a> (44 g) and the ZLite back panel (4 Segments, 106 g) it weighs 474 g.</p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>As the Phoenix Lite is so light, you could imagine it doesn’t have a lot of features. Well, that’s not the case - here is its long list of features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ergonomic S-Shaped Shoulder Straps with Daisy Chains on them</li>
  <li>Adjustable and removable chest strap</li>
  <li>Two really good side pockets</li>
  <li>One large stretchy front pocket</li>
  <li>Side compression straps to minimize the Volume on the Pack</li>
  <li>Inside and Outside attachment possibilities for the included <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/therm-a-rest-z-lite-sleeping-mat/?pid=10239">∞ ZLite Mattress</a>, which functions as back cushioning</li>
  <li>The optional Hipbelt Plus lets you carry up to 12 kg in the pack</li>
  <li>And finally the Extension Collar with the innovative Accordion closure</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326621698/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Front View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326621698_b2ff721d96_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Front View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The Accordion closure of the Rolltop closure is a HUCKEPACKS innovation and makes your roll-top backpack look clean, with easier and less noisy access to the inside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327293976/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure, Top View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327293976_5e3cd40046_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure, Top View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>Hand-made in Germany, from the highest-quality and lightest materials available. The quality is absolutely topnotch, and I expect this pack to last me many years =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326621248/in/dateposted/" title="Made in Cologne"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326621248_2055c7ea0a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Made in Cologne" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>HUCKEPACKS produces in a small workshop in Cologne (you can <a href="https://youtu.be/7oWBgnSEBMY">see it in this interview</a>) where the materials are cut and sewn together to create their ultralight packs and accessories. During cutting attention is paid to minimize waste, and also otherwise they try to minimize waste during production. The packs being made from DCFW or DxG I am not certain about what their recyclability is, but the life-cycle of the backpacks is long with normal, good care.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>As always, this is the most important part of the whole article - get a cup of coffee ☕️ or tea 🍵 and then read on.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/jw76p2" title="Breaking Camp"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327526877_bb4e5ea3f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Breaking Camp" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite is the lighter brother of the <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/phoenix/">Phoenix DxG</a>, and the Lite is made from black Dyneema Composite Fabric Woven (what we called cuben back in the day) in different strengths. The material is waterproof, the pack isn’t however - because the seams aren’t taped. In reality I haven’t had any rain/ water get into the pack, and the material is durable and has survived bushwhacking and heavier loads without problem thus far.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327464042/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327464042_756c9af547_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>COM. FORT. ABLE.</strong> I really love how comfortable this pack carries. The four segments of the ZLite, which function as the backpanel on the ergonomically designed back of the pack, are really pleasant on my back. And if you’re not a fan of it you also could use a different mattress or none at all, if you for example use the Burrito Frame packing method. I do get a sweaty back, but I do get that pretty much with every backpack I use. With food for 5 days, a tripod and camera gear the pack was really comfortable to carry all day long.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327462992/in/photostream/" title="Shoulder Strap &amp; Back Pad 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327462992_e7e4e47633_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Strap &amp; Back Pad 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I always have loved the shoulder straps Mateusz has on his backpacks, and these are no different. They are really well designed and with a good, ergonomic fit that carries also heavier loads in comfort, and most importantly: I can attach my <a href="https://bit.ly/3bKwoRH">∞ Peak Design Capture V3 Clip</a> on them, for easy access to my camera. The shoulder straps are made from a 3D Mesh and Copolymer foam, in different thicknesses which makes them soft &amp; flexible and they adapt well to you body, while at the same time transferring the weight really well, ensuring a comfortable carry.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326626583/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Ergonomic S-Shaped Shoulder Straps"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326626583_0190934d17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Ergonomic S-Shaped Shoulder Straps" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327292251/in/dateposted/" title="Shoulder Straps Detail 5"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327292251_bd2f84f678_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Straps Detail 5" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327470517/in/dateposted/" title="Shoulder Straps Detail 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327470517_9f0b1d7b6b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Straps Detail 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Side pockets are spacious, and I can grab my water bottle while hiking, which I really appreciate, and there’s also space for more stuff, like my tripod, a Kuksa and my chili nuts. The front mesh pocket is big enough to fit in a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-dirigo-2.html">large shelter</a> or my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/08/200-g-hardshell-montane-podium-pull-on-and-pants.html">rain gear</a> in there without problems.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327296011/in/dateposted/" title="Phoenix Lite Front Mesh Pocket 1"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327296011_99cbaf8125_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Phoenix Lite Front Mesh Pocket 1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327286491/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Side View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327286491_06d595bdb3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Side View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Hipbelt Plus Lite which I have with the pack suits my style better - I’m not a fan of the simple 20 mm hipbelt strap it comes with, and feel the Hipbelt Plus Lite is a good alternative for me. It wraps around my narrow hips nicely, and transfers the weight really well. Also long days with 10 to 12 kg are not problem, which is often the weight I carry at the start of a trip with all my camera gear, food and water.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326623528/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Hipbelt Plus"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326623528_fb3a9a2d9d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Hipbelt Plus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327290201/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Hipbelt Plus Lite"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327290201_52d095df86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Hipbelt Plus Lite" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then finally, the collar and Accordion closure of the Phoenix Lite. Some of you might remember the original <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/03/first-look-laufbursche-huckepack.html">Laufbursche Huckepacks backpack</a>, which already had a very innovative closure that ensured that no water can get inside the pack. With the Phoenix Mateus went for a classic Toploader design with a rolltop closure – but the rolltop closure has a twist - actually, more a fold =) The Accordion closure gives this pack a really clean appearance as it folds the material, which in other backpacks comes out at the sides, to the inside. I imagine this adds to the durability of the pack, but it definitely makes it easier to get things from the inside, as you don’t even have to open the small hook as you can grab past it inside. No noisy Velcro which keeps it together, but a clean, minimalistic and durable way to close the top. I love it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326629468/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326629468_847d788bb6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326630533/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure Unrolled"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326630533_bd6a651143_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure Unrolled" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327295061/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure Accordion Closure Open"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327295061_5f5061d22c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure Accordion Closure Open" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327295581/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure Accordion Closure Really Open"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327295581_7ab0f384fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure Accordion Closure Really Open" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>From a design perspective I understand why the Phoenix Lite’s main body is 40 l Volume and not more, but I have on the start of my trips often found that I’d wish the pack had 5 or 10 l more Volume. The simple reason is that in addition to the backpacking kit and food I also carry camera gear which can range in Volume anywhere between one and ten litres. Especially at the start of a trip, when there’s food for seven days along, it’s for me really hard to figure out how I get my camera stuff inside. This is a problem which likely not many will have, but I wish that somehow the pack would have a wee bit more Volume so I could fit my camera gear easier inside (I solve this problem usually by having the camera stuff in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/05/huckepacks-beipack.html">beiPACK</a>!).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327283211/in/photostream/" title="Tripod on the right, beiPACK, Camera Gear and Phoenix Lite"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327283211_08a9d35cf3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tripod on the right, beiPACK, Camera Gear and Phoenix Lite" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I also would like to lose the grommet in the bottom. I haven’t had any water come inside through it, but similarly I never had to drain the inside of my pack. But I see as a possibility for moisture/ water to get inside the pack when I set it down where it is wet.</p>

<p>Finally, I’d like the side compression go the complete length of the pack. Now it only compress the upper 2/3 of the pack, and not the bottom, and I’d wish that the side compression straps would be more like on the <a href="https://ula-equipment.9xrw.net/P3qZN">∞ ULA Ohm</a>, which has from all the backpacks I have used in the past 20+ years the best side compression system.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327284271/in/dateposted/" title="Wallace"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327284271_35c0a3baf8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wallace" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327286846/in/photostream/" title="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Side COmpression"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327286846_db0403a272_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Side COmpression" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I love how clean the pack looks when packed - there’s nothing superfluous on there, just a functional, beautiful pack which carries extremely well. And while I find it sometimes hard to fit everything I need to have along on a trip (as you can see above) it is a spacious pack for week-long trips. One thing I really appreciate and like is that a full pack doesn’t ride above my shoulders. Usually the pack stops on the same line as my shoulders, which is from an ergonomics point-of-view for me really good. It also gives usually the impression that one is on a day trip, as the pack is so small 😆 All in all this is my go-to pack when I’m heading outdoors, and I’m looking forward to many more great trips with this durable, beautiful, comfortable and well-designed pack. Also, make sure to see my detailed <a href="https://youtu.be/3tV8alDSVMo">HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Review Video</a> to see what I carry in the pack and all the details in action!</p>

<p><strong>Convinced?</strong> Then head over to HUCKEPACKS to place an order for your <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/phoenix-lite/">Phoenix Lite</a>. In case they are Sold Out - which happens 😊 - follow HUCKEPACKS on Social Media (for example on <a href="https://twitter.com/huckepacks">Twitter</a>) to see when a new batch goes online.</p>

<p>You can see more photos of the Huckepacks Phoenix Lite in this <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157715920143562">Flickr Album</a>.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>(and you get great discount codes from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743870368/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743870368_db4f21caa2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HUCKEPACKS beiPACK]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/huckepacks-beipack.html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-06T10:12:12+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/huckepacks-beipack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Need more space for small &amp; important items on your hikes? Get a bum bag! They are ultralight, multi-use and you’ll wonder how you survived without one before!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862406217/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS beiPACK"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862406217_ce53485a37_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS beiPACK" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from HUCKEPACKS. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on the affiliate links in this article &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/bZIgPo1rubg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I’m a big fan of keeping my gear sorted on my hikes, and a problem I encountered on many trips in the past is that I miss a bag or pouch for essential stuff which I wanna keep close but not really in my pockets or inside my backpack. Enter the fanny pack (<em>or a bum bag in British English</em>). Since seven plus years <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/shoulder-and-multi-use-packs-for-hiking-and-backpacking.html">I use different kinds of shoulder and fanny packs</a>, so the <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/beipack/">HUCKEPACKS beiPACK</a> is a logical addition to my HUCKEPACKS Fanboy collection. On my hike in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/09/impressions-from-the-far-north.html">Hammastunturi</a> last autumn 🍂 I still used a <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/hipbelt-pocket/">HUCKEPACKS Hipbelt Pocket</a> to store essentials, but now that I have upgraded to the more spacious beiPACK I think the Hipbelt Pocket will only come out to play as a … Hipbelt pocket =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862091341/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 02"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862091341_54fb62f1b4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 02" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now while theoretically the beiPACK is double the volume of the Hipbelt Pocket, I have found it fits actually more than double the content (as for how much, <a href="https://youtu.be/bZIgPo1rubg">watch the Video</a> above!). At 74 g with the strap (or 42 g without it) the beiPACK is not much heavier than a Hipbelt Pocket, but the possibility to load it up with a map, snacks, an SUL hardshell and a Pocket camera makes it a lot more useable for me - especially as a wee summit pack which I can load up with the aforementioned gear at camp and then head out to explore the hills and forests around my ⛺️</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49861560053/in/dateposted/" title="Closed beiPACK"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49861560053_bd657dce67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Closed beiPACK" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49861559858/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK top view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49861559858_5f84dd3241_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK top view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49861559738/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 03"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49861559738_290980ef25_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 03" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The beiPACK also comes with a flat inside pocket, which is where I keep my passport, notebook + pen and other documents, and a large main compartment. It’s waterproof and has a comfortable 25 mm wide strap with durable and easy-to-use buckles, which obviously can be totally removed if you decide to carry it in front of your chest, connected to your pack. You also can strap it around your pack, if you don’t like to carry it around your shoulders (which is my preferred way to carry it).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862404742/in/dateposted/" title="Happy Hiker!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862404742_59be7a5eca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Happy Hiker!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I especially love the limited edition <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/specials/beipack-special/">beiPACK Special</a> series, where a dozen different beiPACKS in various materials and colours are available. It definitely wasn’t easy to pick a colour I have to say, but I am super happy with the darkgreen woven DCF version I picked 😊 So if you have the problem of having small items in your pockets and flying around in your pack, solve the problem by getting a beiPACK!</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862405102/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK straps!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862405102_e96a6339c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK straps!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Visit to HUCKEPACKS]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/10/a-visit-to-huckepacks.html"/>
    <updated>2019-10-29T10:11:16+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/10/a-visit-to-huckepacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Accompany me on a visit to the ultralight candy shop that is the HUCKEPACKS Workshop in Cologne, Germany!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48979283501/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Packs"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48979283501_fbe2f3bebf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="HUCKEPACKS Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Mateusz is a long-time friend, but I paid this trip myself and was not paid to write this article or produce the videos. I received a PHOENIX Lite for testing and giving feedback. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978727288/in/dateposted/" title="Handmade in Cologne"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978727288_7f77d42166_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Handmade in Cologne" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I remember the first call from Mateusz about the new company. I was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLqEBC4yj3FagZCjz9vfwc7r8iiwZaz63R">backpacking in Vålådalen</a> in September 2018, and was just at the beautiful turquoise lakes having a short break when my phone rang. I answered, and as usual Mateusz talked and talked and talked, until I had to tell him that I was about to continue hiking again and would like to know what it’s about. <em>“Well, I plan to open LAUFBURSCHE Gear again. But it won’t be called LAUFBURSCHE anymore. What do you think about the name HUCKEPACKS?”</em> I like it, I answered, it connects well to the old brand. From then on forward my phone would regularly ring and I’d chat for an half hour or longer with Mateusz about the new company and the new products.</p>

<p>Fast forward to the summer of 2019 and the family and me are on a train to Cologne. We have been travelling for two weeks around Germany, visiting <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B3ZtJIgDl6G/">Berlin</a>, my home town and other places, and now we arrived in the city with the cathedral. We stayed at a nice Hostel in Ehrenfeld, and one morning I was able to steal away from parental duties and visit Mateusz at his Workshop.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978725668/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Workshop"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978725668_918d68c526_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="HUCKEPACKS Workshop" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now I have seen photos of the workshop before when friends were visiting him, and it was with much anticipation that I entered these “holy halls”. And amazing they were indeed. I was welcomed by the four new packs - the PACKL and PHOENIX - in their DxG and Cuben versions, and Mateusz walked towards me with a coffee in hand. I gave him a big hug and was happy that he was still with us. He made me a coffee, and then we sat down to chat.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/7oWBgnSEBMY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>It is always enlightening to sit and talk with Mateusz, and realize how much thought he puts into the smallest of details. Case in point: The new roll-top closure of the PHOENIX backpack. Where other companies are happy to use a tried &amp; tested roll-top, Mateusz found it neither practical nor aesthetically pleasing. When he showed me the new roll-top closure, which folds and opens like an accordion, my jaw dropped. So easy, so beautiful, so practical, and such a smart continuation of the old HUCKEpack closure. And what is most amazing: He had this design already in 2015, and tested it on his HRP thru-hike that year!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978724333/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS PHOENIX"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978724333_ab1833e7de_h.jpg" width="1600" height="900" alt="HUCKEPACKS PHOENIX" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978725273/in/dateposted/" title="Mateusz and the PACKLs"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978725273_3a1074fdab_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Mateusz and the PACKLs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48979465772/in/photostream/" title="DXg x DCF"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48979465772_917b913280_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="DXg x DCF" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48979462612/in/dateposted/" title="Cutting"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48979462612_9e85d5eb8a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Cutting" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We shot two more videos after the Interview above, about the <a href="https://youtu.be/EKFC7FB76LA">PHOENIX</a> and the <a href="https://youtu.be/x32RhEvdhqw">PACKL</a>, drank another coffee and talked about the launch of the company, backpacking, and much more. Sadly, and you likely see this coming, parental duties called and so, after several hours, it was time to say good bye to Mateusz and head back to the city, so I could play with the kids and we could go have some lunch with the family =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/6q39eY" title="Cologne Playgrounds"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48979621342_b28a5f2f59_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Cologne Playgrounds" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I am so excited that my friend Mateusz not only won his battle with cancer, but that he decided to return to sewing the finest ultralight backpacks which he is well-known and loved for! A few weeks later I was fortunate enough that a PHOENIX Lite pack arrived here, which I used on a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/09/impressions-from-the-far-north.html">backpacking trip in Lapland</a>, and I still am <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/09/solo-hike-to-the-zugspitze.html">using my old PACKsack regularly</a>. If you are in the market for a pack for everyday use and Overnighters, or need a pack for long backpacking trips, give the new <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/">HUCKEPACKS packs</a> a good look! I for one am really loving these packs, and wish Mateusz all the best with the new business!</p>

<p>If you enjoyed this article and video <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48978725948/in/dateposted/" title="LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48978725948_61238ce76d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="LAUFBURSCHE PACKsack" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
