<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: outdoor 2017 | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/outdoor-2017/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-05-18T15:13:56+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OutDoor 2017 Backpacks]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/outdoor-2017-backpacks.html"/>
    <updated>2017-07-04T22:42:43+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/outdoor-2017-backpacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We take a look at new backpacks coming in 2018 from Osprey, Gregory, Ortovox, Mammut, Arc’teryx, Eagle Creek and CiloGear.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34734977903/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4290/34734977903_528036f73d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Levity 45" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Like <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-2016/">last year</a> I’ll sort the new gear posts by category - <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/OutDoor-2016-Backpacks.html">backpacks</a>, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/outdoor-2016-news-tents.html">tents</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/07/outdoor-2016-news-stoves.html">other gear</a>. Who knows, maybe I even do an apparel post this year =)</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>I’m a co-founder of the Outdoor Blogger Network and have close relationships with many of the companies mentioned in this article. However, I haven’t been paid to write this article, and also does my involvement with some of these companies not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35675084516/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity Lid"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4290/35675084516_0a69739c0b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Levity Lid" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>First up is the <strong>Osprey Levity</strong> backpack. It’s an OutDoor Award Winner, will come in spring 2018 into the shops and then is available in two sizes: 45 l (810 g) and 60l (850 g). What is special about the Levity is that while it looks like a normal Ultralight backpack it actually has a ventilated mesh back. My hand easily fit between the backpanel of the pack and the mesh frame, this should make it an excellent choice for hiking in very warm climates. The large side pockets can be accessed from the top and side, there’s a very big front pocket for gear you need throughout the day and a zippered lid which stores keys, phone, wallet and such.</p>

<p>The beauty of this pack is not just that it means lightweight packs go <em>really</em> mainstream but that this will open up lightweight backpacking up to a much wider audience. Osprey packs can be found in many brick &amp; mortar outdoor shops around the globe, and that means consumers will see this pack live in the store, can try it out, and convince themselves of the benefit of a lightweight pack that carries well. It’s, so to speak, the perfect backpack to convert many more people to the ultralight path of backpacking because it’s nice that you can e &amp; try the pack before you buy it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34873426484/in/dateposted/" title="Wearing the Osprey Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4067/34873426484_0c41b9dae5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Wearing the Osprey Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35675109566/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity Shoulder Straps"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4258/35675109566_003d418149_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Levity Shoulder Straps" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35675120856/in/dateposted/" title="It&#x27;s light, the Osprey Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4074/35675120856_d75e9d75c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="It&#x27;s light, the Osprey Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35675130556/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4237/35675130556_35d93a28a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Levity" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Another backpack which was light and innovative is  the <strong>ORTOVOX Peak Light 32 Backpack</strong>. I’m a big fan of ORTOVOX and really like their garments, but also their paired down alpine packs are really interesting. This is a pack for the alpine climbing community and comes with a Swiss Wool backpanel. The pack is 1.050 g light but can be stripped to 690 g if you take off the lid, hip belt and wire frame for the back. But the Swisswool-tec-Knit Back System is the really interesting part here, as in it Ortovox combines <em>foam and pressed Swiss wool covered with a high-tech knitted fabric with a different hole structure.</em> This processing should enable excellent temperature management and should still be comfortable if you’ve sweated on the wool back panel. As it is wool it has the same properties as your wool shirts. Does it work? Well, for that you should check out reviews once these packs are out for a while =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35583819861/in/photostream/" title="ORTOVOX Peak Light Backpack Swisswool backpanel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4230/35583819861_ceeef8ebb4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="ORTOVOX Peak Light Backpack Swisswool backpanel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35327588550/in/dateposted/" title="ORTOVOX Peak Light 32 Backpack"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4035/35327588550_e0a0308d77_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="ORTOVOX Peak Light 32 Backpack" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>To get into the Mammut booth you had to be a Blogger (Yay!) or have an appointment. I lacked the latter thus made use of my Blogger Pass to enter the booth, and here the <strong>Mammut Trion Nordwand 20</strong> pack caught my attention. That ain’t difficult as it is orange and I am drawn to everything orange (I blame my Dutch Heritage). The 20 l pack weighs 580 g, is made of a Dyneema Ripstop material, has a clean look and even is pretty water-resistant with a 5,000 mm water column. Like the garments in the Eiger Extreme Series the pack has been been developed using Mammut High Reach Technology in the carrying system, which Mammut claims makes reaching upwards easier &amp; hence provides additional freedom of movement for climbing. If your goals are fast &amp; light ascents of high mountains then this is a pack to keep in mind for summer 2018.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35675185496/in/photostream/" title="Mammut Trion Nordwand 20 Front Pocket"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4039/35675185496_f5e6654ace_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Mammut Trion Nordwand 20 Front Pocket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34905265063/in/dateposted/" title="Mammut Trion Nordwand 20"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4263/34905265063_ec09338850_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Mammut Trion Nordwand 20" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next pack brings us back to the trails and is made for backpacking. Long-time readers might recall that my first backpack was a Gregory pack, for which I paid 500 DM back when we had not yet the Euro (It’d would be 250€ in today’s money!). For a teenager that was a lot of money, and I used this pack for over ten years until I lost it in an accident (possibly I repeat this story every year anew?). Anyway, fast forward to 2018 and we’ll get the <strong>Gregory Optic</strong>, (and Octal for Women, which is a much cooler name!), Gregory’s next foray into the lightweight pack niche.</p>

<p>It isn’t as light as the Levity above at 1.120 g for the 48 l version and 1.140 g for the 58 l pack, but it comes with the Gregory-specific comfortable fit, robust materials and full functionality. It has an AeroSpan suspension system which is a further development of the Gregory VaporSpan system, and also should make the pack comfortable to wear in warmer climates. Add in the well-carrying hipbelt from gregory and you have a pack that should carry loads up to 14 kg nicely. It also has a large stretch front pocket, stretch side pockets, an integrated raincover and several bells &amp; whistles to attach things to the pack. At 190€/ 210€ it’s a bit cheaper than the Levity but almost 300 g heavier. However, this is again a step into the right direction I believe, as it makes lightweight backpacks easily available to a large audience, and hence I welcome this addition to the market.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34905263593/in/dateposted/" title="Gregory Optic &amp; Octal"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4122/34905263593_0cc9015916_b.jpg" width="886" height="1024" alt="Gregory Optic &amp; Octal" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34905261933/in/dateposted/" title="Gregory Optic 48 Close-up"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4072/34905261933_4e426ce3b5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Gregory Optic 48 Close-up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35714692995/in/photostream/" title="Gregory Optic 48"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4090/35714692995_22f71bd632_b.jpg" width="784" height="1024" alt="Gregory Optic 48" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35675171326/in/dateposted/" title="Gregory Optic 48 backpanel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4229/35675171326_8c360b0ab8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Gregory Optic 48 backpanel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>CiloGear was also again at the show and handing out backpacks to this <a href="https://www.facebook.com/CiloGear/photos/a.410469092734.196568.42853277734/10154411493187735/?type=3&amp;theater">Thomas Huber</a> guy. I also got a backpack - and then the owner whispered something into my ear, I gave back the pack (the second CiloGear backpack I returned voluntarily - yeps, I might be slightly insane =) and now am waiting for a parcel of joy from Oregon.</p>

<p>I also saw the two new Arc’teryx trailrunning backpacks - and while I have some photos of them they’re not that good, hence the stock photo underneath. The <strong>Arcteryx Norvan Hydration Vest</strong> comes in a 7 l and a 14 l Version and the 14 l version is lighter than the smaller 7 l pack. The Norvan 14 is 256 g or 417 g with the included bladder, while the Norvan 7 weighs 263 g or 424 g with the water bladder. Both packs have that <em>comfortable ‘bounce-free’ fit that wears more like clothing, yet with the functionality of a backpack</em>. The 14 l pack is carrying your snacks, water and kit for long runs, while the smaller Norvan 7 is for shorter runs where you don’t need so much gear. Both are impeccably designed as you know from <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/arcteryx-workshop-tour.html">Arc’teryx</a> and will retail for 170€ and 190€ respectively.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35718802055/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan 14 Hydration Vest"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4087/35718802055_b53f426f56_b.jpg" width="723" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan 14 Hydration Vest" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35718805835/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan 7 Hydration Vest"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4257/35718805835_e5968c62b1_b.jpg" width="808" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Norvan 7 Hydration Vest" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Which brings us to the last backpack in this article, the <strong>Eagle Creek Global Companion Travel Pack</strong>. This is a pack for my travel (blogger) friends who only take a carry-on on their journeys. Available as a 40l and a 65l pack these fold open like a book  and have zippered compartments which keep your garments and kit in place which is great for packing and unpacking - I’m not a big fan of packing a pack from the top. At 1.620 g for the 40 l pack and 2.330 g for the 65 l pack they’re not super light, but if you only need it to get your gear from the Airport to your <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/hmorkel">AirBnB</a> or Ho(s)tel it’s alright. They have side pockets, self-repairing and lockable zippers, a rainfly and have the No Matter What™ Warranty - though as they’re build from durable materials you probably don’t need to make use of it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35583883381/in/dateposted/" title="Eagle Creek Global Companion Travel Pack"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4234/35583883381_0c197c8412_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Eagle Creek Global Companion Travel Pack" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35583864671/in/dateposted/" title="Eagle Creek Global Companion Travel Pack - Open"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4020/35583864671_2bd2efdb2b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Eagle Creek Global Companion Travel Pack - Open" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Stay tuned for the next #OutDoorFN Gear post coming soon!</strong> In the meanwhile have a look at the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157685424312086">OutDoor 2017</a> Photo Album and check out my <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pg/hikinginfinland/videos/?ref=page_internal">Facebook Live Videos</a> which I shot &amp; shared during the show. <em>If you enjoy this #OutDoorFN 2017 Re-Cap &amp; other articles why not <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[#OutDoorFN 2017 Re-Cap]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/06/outdoorfn-2017-re-cap.html"/>
    <updated>2017-06-26T19:50:39+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/06/outdoorfn-2017-re-cap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just realized that the 2017 Edition of the OutDoor Show in Friedrichshafen was my 5th time at the OutDoor =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34734948543/in/dateposted/" title="Hallways of Always, 2017 Edition"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4284/34734948543_116850a9cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hallways of Always, 2017 Edition" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>I’m a co-founder of the Outdoor Blogger Network and have close relationships with many of the companies mentioned in this article. However, I haven’t been paid to write this article, and also does my involvement with some of these companies not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35157179300/in/dateposted/" title="Chilling in the Helsport Lofoten"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4231/35157179300_88baec6593_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Chilling in the Helsport Lofoten" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a week at Lake Constance and an almost 38 h long trip home (Thanks Frankfurt Airport!) it’s time to pen down some thoughts from the 2017 OutDoor Show in Friedrichhafen. This was, as I just realized, my fifth OutDoor Show - I haven’t missed it since I <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2013/">first went in 2013</a>. As I blog professionally since several years the show is a mandatory visit to meet partners new &amp; old (I’m a Helsport Ambassador, sponsored by La Sportiva and talking with a handful of companies for specific projects). While at the beginning of my OutDoor visits the new gear was of course quite exciting (and still is) it is more and more about the people I meet at the fair which makes the fair so valuable &amp; exciting for me.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34734985353/in/dateposted/" title="Glen Van Peski and Chris Townsend on the #OutDoorFN"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4256/34734985353_4d91b1387c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Glen Van Peski and Chris Townsend on the #OutDoorFN" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Take for example Glen Van Peski, the founder of Gossamer Gear, and Chris Townsend, the renown Backpacking Writer. I met Glen and his wife by pure co-incidence (funnily enough at the Osprey booth while we were all checking out the Levity backpack) and we later in the afternoon managed to meet-up again for a beer and chat more. I also ran a couple of times into Chris and we had a nice evening chatting with fellow bloggers. Add in that I also met again my long-time friend Jotaro from Locus Gear, many, many blogger, photographer and journalism colleagues and you will quickly realize that the show is for me about the people I meet here. The same goes for my contacts as the various companies I visit - many are much more than just “work contacts” but friends with whom we talk about family &amp; life (which means sometimes only around 10 minutes remain to check out the new gear!).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34734958003/in/dateposted/" title="Alastair Humphreys on the OutDoor Stage"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4213/34734958003_7e3324c12d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Alastair Humphreys on the OutDoor Stage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Speaking of gear, it felt industry-wise lightweight is getting more &amp; more to the front - a good things for us ultralight everything enthusiasts. Lighter garments, lighter shoes, lighter backpacks, lighter tents &amp; shelters, lighter stoves &amp; food, lighter climbing gear, lighter packrafting equipment, lighter bikepacking kit - across the board you’re able to find much more lighter gear for your outdoor activities. Functionality didn’t suffer, though - this lighter kit should be able to perform just as well as heavier counterparts.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35376626162/in/dateposted/" title="Best Booth of the Fair: The Houdini Garden"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4229/35376626162_33cd381407_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Best Booth of the Fair: The Houdini Garden" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>My favourite booth this year was the Houdini Garden above - it was just wonderful and happily the temperatures this year (up to 32°C!) meant it was nice to sit outside in the shade. Add in that the smoothies &amp; cocktails they served from the herbs which they have grown in the composted Houdini garments soil were super tasty.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35157176010/in/dateposted/" title="Awesome new Vaude Performance Mats"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4259/35157176010_53842e349e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Awesome new Vaude Performance Mats" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I’ll try to delve into depth in more articles about the gear I saw at the show, but in this post I want to highlight some kit which I remember from the top of my head. First is probably the new series of Vaude sleeping mats. These are so well engineered that I believe they will be super-successful when they hit the market as so many details on them are just <strong>Wow!</strong></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34734943163/in/dateposted/" title="New Arc&#x27;teryx Konseal FL Approach Shoe"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4264/34734943163_74b2d06ff4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="New Arc&#x27;teryx Konseal FL Approach Shoe" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>These new Arc’teryx Konseal FL Approach shoes are beautifully designed and so light, I hope to get a pair for my feet before 2018!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35376671012/in/dateposted/" title="New Paramo Manu Shirt"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4262/35376671012_3256998877_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="New Paramo Manu Shirt" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Paramo’s new design is superb - gone the more conservative and boxy cuts &amp; colours, welcome to youthful &amp; fresh designs which promise to also perform well outdoors.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34735997253/in/dateposted/" title="Rab Mythic 400"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4290/34735997253_9fb8ced02e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rab Mythic 400" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Rab launched a 7D sleeping bag line, and the Mythic 400 sleeping bag here will tip the scales at 660 g and has a comfort rating of -1°C. Feels great on the skin and could shed quite some weight in the sleeping bag department.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35157981650/in/dateposted/" title="Kupilka 37"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4266/35157981650_6e8908f43e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Kupilka 37" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The new Kupilka 37 Kuksa has 370 ml of volume and is thus quite a bit bigger than the regular good old Kupilka 21 - an increase in size which is very welcome as this could make it the one cup for all your trips! I got one and will put it through its paces the next months to see if it is a worthy addition to the gear closet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34734977903/in/dateposted/" title="Osprey Levity 45"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4290/34734977903_528036f73d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Osprey Levity 45" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Osprey Levity backpack looks like a well designed lightweight backpack with a ventilated back.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34734969483/in/dateposted/" title="Houdini Garments can be composted!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4233/34734969483_0371c4a6c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Houdini Garments can be composted!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Another trend is that sustainability, recycling and closing the loop is no longer just on the mind of a few outliers - across the board you could see an uptake of this topic on the show. From shoes which are Made in Europe to garments which can be recycled, composted and repaired, many companies I visited talked about sustainability and doing good for the outdoors. As I have a background in this area I’m delighted to see that more and more outdoor brands start to act to keep our outdoor playgrounds in a good condition.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34702820614/in/dateposted/" title="Smoothies at the Houdini Booth"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4238/34702820614_4be54a8bbc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Smoothies at the Houdini Booth" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So much for now - as I said, I’ll try to dive into detail into some areas of gear and news later on. In the meanwhile have a look at the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157685424312086">OutDoor 2017</a> Photo Album and check out my <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pg/hikinginfinland/videos/?ref=page_internal">Facebook Live Videos</a> which I shot &amp; shared during the show. <em>If you enjoy this #OutDoorFN 2017 Re-Cap &amp; other articles why not <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35376619682/in/dateposted/" title="Easy Walking Days this year at the #OutDoorFN"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4278/35376619682_9ea409f6df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Easy Walking Days this year at the #OutDoorFN" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
