<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gestalten verlag | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/gestalten-verlag/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-05-15T15:24:50+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wildside - The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/wildside-the-enchanted-life-of-hunters-and-gatherers.html"/>
    <updated>2017-07-10T20:42:03+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/wildside-the-enchanted-life-of-hunters-and-gatherers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers</em> is another book by <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/wildside.html">Gestalten</a> that caters to the lifestyle outdoor Instagram person. At least that was my first impression when I saw the book - but covers can lie, and once I started to read I actually quite liked it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35703340791/in/photostream/" title="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4235/35703340791_3a545d6ede_b.jpg" width="970" height="1024" alt="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The Gestalten Publishing house has published a host of books - <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open.html">The Great Wide Open</a>, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/off-the-road.html">Off the Road</a>, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/hide-and-seek.html">Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/the-outsiders.html">The Outsiders</a>  - which all look a bit like they garner to the Instagram crowd - and probably that’s what they want and do. And while some of these are not really a success for me, others are good. <a href="http://amzn.to/2tLQ9EM">Wildside</a> is in the latter camp, even if the Cover can be deceiving and you might just think this book is like Instagram photos you’ve seen a thousand times just printed on nice paper, but it has more to offer on its 250 something pages.</p>

<p>There’s essays of #Vanlife Dwellers in the book, inspiring and artsy photos, little businesses are showcased, you learn more about hunting in Germany and Sweden, you go foraging in Finland and then you are taken surfing and to Switzerland. It’s a visual journey interspersed with short stories and essays, and even if some of these topics might not interest you much you might find a little piece of joy or wisdom from another one, so take the time to read each - because if not you might miss out.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35703340211/in/photostream/" title="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers Book"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4255/35703340211_24b639e221_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers Book" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So whom is this book aimed at? If you feel like you’d like to see what else is possible than running the rat race from 9-to-5 every day, then this book certainly can plant some ideas into your mind. Or if you’re looking for inspiration where to travel next. Or even how to travel - by #Vanlife, on foot or in a canoe, there’s better options than flying for a week to an all-inclusive resort (<em>but that you, as a reader of an outdoor blog, knew either way already</em> ;).</p>

<p>Also for those who look for culinary ideas this book obviously will be of interest, be it from gathering mushrooms or catching fish - modern Hunters &amp; Gatherers will enjoy this book without a doubt. Overall it is a beautiful book that inspires to try something new, presented in a visually pleasing way, though I do find the chosen typefaces for much of the text unsuccessful as it isn’t pleasing to read. Other than that - if you’re interested in one thing I told about of this book - check out a copy at your local library or order a copy home to sit down with it, out in the summer sun. You can buy Wildside directly at Gestalten or via one of these Affiliate Links at <a href="http://amzn.to/2tLQ9EM">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/2utIyrZ">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/2tPxSpX">Amazone.de</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>The book has been provided by the Gestalten Verlag for review. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Off The Road]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/04/off-the-road.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-08T23:17:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/04/off-the-road</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You like to go outdoors and love a tricked out van or off-road vehicle to get there? Then <em>Off the Road</em> is the book for you - but careful, you might want to sell your house and move into a van!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26210796662/in/dateposted/" title="Off the Road Cover"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1665/26210796662_6361a93f26_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="Off the Road Cover" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I don’t have a driving license. We don’t own a car. And yet I like the idea of living in a van or tricked-out off-road vehicle. Hence <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/off-the-road.html">Off the Road</a> is such an appealing book. On over 250 pages and even more photos you get inspiration for your own #VanLife. Are you an BMW Enduro kind of guy, or an VW T4 aficionado? Does your heart beat for adventure off the beaten track in a Toyota Land Cruiser or do you prefer to have an adventure-ready trailer behind your car? This book illuminates people from all these roads &amp; more, with inspiring stories of people who rode from the most southern point in Florida to the most northerly point in Alaska or who crossed Russia from the west to the east.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/144480827?byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>But it has not only such adventurous expeditions in it, also more achievable #VanLife stories are in the book - things you can realize at the weekend or during your summer holidays. Like going to the beach with your trailer for a lonely weekend at the sea, or taking your van with the surfboards on top for a trip to search the best waves. There’s a bunch of vans, cars, trailers, motorcycles and off-road vehicle depicted in the book, complete with technical information and how to make them even more off-road worthy for your next big (or small) trip. Inspiration for how to renovate the interior of your van, why an Unimog still is one of the greatest All-terrain vehicles, and how you can transform your van into a mobile office which allows you from anywhere.</p>

<p>And the appeal also comes through to me, who is generally opposed to motorized outdoor activities. I could imagine trading the house for a small van, drive around the world and have a new view to wake up to each morning. Where I can sit in front of the car and drink a coffee, sit by the camp fire and watch the stars before going laying down on a comfortable bed, and which would allow me to just put on the skis in the morning and skin up a mountain. Of course I’d first need to get a driving license to do that =) But if you have one, and it sounds like a good life to you, pick up this book and be inspired by what is possible. Great photos and stories most likely will make you think if you really need a house, or if a nice off-road vehicle or van wouldn’t suffice for a life off the road!</p>

<p>You can support me and buy this book at one of the following affiliate links - at no extra costs for you. <a href="http://amzn.to/1qbfFgW">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1S6UkSB">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1S6WEZL">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26210796292/in/dateposted/" title="Off the Road Inside"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1708/26210796292_ac7aee5ac8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Off the Road Inside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: Gestalten sent me the book for review. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Great Wide Open]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/07/the-great-wide-open.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/07/the-great-wide-open</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The Great Wide Open</em> has the byline <em>New Outdoor and Landscape Photography</em>. If it is really new and if you should get a copy, you read in my review.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968932345/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/319/19968932345_8fc222df65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/gestalten-verlag/">Gestalten Verlag</a>. They make cool coffee table books with great photos and texts, so when <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">The Great Wide Open</a> appeared on my radar I was eager to check it out. An email and a few days later the heavy book slammed on my porch, ready to be browsed.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19780862558/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3665/19780862558_72b216d413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>However, opening the book the euphoria quickly ended. Sure, there are very fine images in there, but just as much of them look like they’re shot on an iPhone for Instagram and not for a large coffee table book. It feels like every other photo is a grainy mess that looked great on your Instagram feed when seen on a smartphone but shouldn’t have been printed in such a large format. Speaking of Instagram, if you’re on it and follow some landscape photographers then you’ll have seen the vast majority of these images in one form or another already. Another disappointment was that you could clearly see in many images that they have been taken not far away from a road or civilization - given that the Prologue of the book refers to <a href="http://amzn.to/1SFXAis">Ansel Adams</a> and how he would set off on long expeditions to capture expansive, wild landscapes that feels a bit wrong. Oh, and if you don’t like Chris Burkard - don’t get the book. Half the images are from him, and while they’re technically very good I personally find them a bit boring. On ther other hand, if you love him - get the book!</p>

<p>But for all that there’s also some very great &amp; inspiring photos in the book. The pictures from Anki Grøthe, Kilian Schönberger, Jimmy Chin, Logan Watts and a few others are crisp, sharp and with a fresh perspective on the outdoors. Add in the small stories and anecdotes from the photographers, athletes and outdoor folks and you get a book that will inspire you at least for one afternoon. Well, maybe a couple more. And if you like Instagram photos and would love to see them in a big book, you’ll probably read it every day! So if you feel like you want to give The Great Wide Open a chance and browse it yourself then order it directly at <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/great-wide-open.html">Gestalten</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1RXDe9B">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJyEz">Amazon.co.uk</a> &amp; <a href="http://amzn.to/1frJFzT">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19968931705/in/dateposted/" title="The Great Wide Open"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/374/19968931705_29152e803e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Great Wide Open" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/04/hide-and-seek.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-24T20:09:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/04/hide-and-seek</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s weekend so its time to head outdoors, to the cabin. Got none? <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/hide-seek.html">Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs</a> will give you plenty of cabins to dream of over the weekend and inspire you to dream up your own.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17066651669" title="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7606/17066651669_6213274751_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Friday is the day where the mind starts to wander to a lonely log cabin in the woods, by the lake, heated by a wood stove, no electricity. Or is it more a luxurious cabin by the sea? Maybe a sleek mountain hut that looks old and ramshackle from the outside but that’s modern and cool inside? <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/hide-seek.html">Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs</a> has them all: Coastal cabins, mountain cabins, open range cabins and the wood cabin, nicely sorted into four chapters of the finest cabins the authors could find. And they have searched far and wide, from the Isle of Skye to New Zealand and Finland to Chile, there’s bound to be a cabin for everyone in this book, Gestalten’s 2nd Cabin book after <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/03/rock-the-shack.html">Rock the Shack</a>.</p>

<p>The book presents the cabins &amp; their interiors of people who don’t want to give up life in the city but want to be able to escape to nature. And as unique as we are as humans, so unique are the cabins, their surroundings and interiors in this book. The focus clearly is on small living spaces in nature, because the outside in front of the window is your living room in many cases, your entertainment, TV and internet. The book aims to inspire you to dream up your own cabin, but you’ll not find plans or construction tips in this coffee table book. However, in the index at the end of the book you can find out more about the architects of the cabins, so that gives you a good starting point.</p>

<p>Sadly we don’t have a own cabin by the sea or lake, so a book which inspires the mind for a more simple life away from home certainly is a good way to relax. I found the book interesting, though I saw a trend to very minimalistic, modern, almost similar looking cabins - with just the scenery changing from the coast to the mountains to the forests. There was a lot of wood, concrete, steel and stones used, all in similar shapes &amp; designs, often with straight lines. Standing out were really only Steve’s Thailand Dome House, the Tree Tent, the Cocoon and the Tree Snake Houses in terms of its design - that was fresh &amp; organic architecture. While I liked most cabins in the book, I missed more organic, natural and rustic cabins and interiors - which there shouldn’t be a shortage of. Personally I also would have liked a more inhabited look in the interior photos, many had the sterile-looking feel of a Modern Art Museum.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17065096818" title="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7601/17065096818_c322948cab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs" /></a></p>

<p>Despite this I would recommend this coffee table book to anyone who likes huts &amp; cabins and can’t get enough of them. You’re bound to have seen some of the featured hide-outs in the book if you follow <a href="http://cabinporn.com/">Cabinporn</a> but there’s a host of new &amp; fresh cabins featured which will get you dreaming about a weekend (or life!) away in them. It’s a beautiful book with high-quality paper and photographs, very legible typography and a clear layout which makes for a satisfying experience when reading &amp; browsing. There’s all in all 80 cabins and hide-outs in the book on 250 pages, and the nature &amp; scenery around the hide-outs and cabins is just as gorgeous as the huts themselves. I’m now off to dream up my own hut, if you need some weekend inspiration grab the book at your local book store or order it online from <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/hide-seek.html">Gestalten</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1KbYSiH">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1duc68Y">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1ElTl8s">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Oh, and in case you’re wondering: My favourite hut probably is <a href="http://robinfalck.com/nido/">Nido</a> from Robin Falck.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outsiders]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/04/the-outsiders.html"/>
    <updated>2014-04-25T13:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/04/the-outsiders</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Going <em>Outdoors</em> is a big trend right now. So Gestalten Verlag went outdoors to meet <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/outsiders.html">The Outsiders</a>, a group of successful outdoor and lifestyle entrepreneurs, bloggers, writers, hikers, surfers, skiers - in short: People who love to be outside. The result is a book which portrays in a gorgeous way the growing outdoor trend - from hiking over cycling to paddling &amp; surfing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13981714206" title="The Outsiders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/13981714206_6177d493ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Outsiders" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>There come quite a few coffee <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/books/">books</a> across my desk, but The Outsiders was different. While many have captivating photos, I felt that each page of the The Outsiders was crafted with love &amp; attention to detail. Everything fits: Beautiful fonts, captivating photos, interesting interviews, short bios of outdoor folks and highlighting some cool products. Did I mention the inspiring photos? Oh. OK. Good.</p>

<p>What I liked a lot about the 272 page thick book was that there were a lot of familiar names and faces featured in it. There was Cass from <a href="http://www.whileoutriding.com/blog">While Out Riding</a> and Joe from <a href="http://joecruz.wordpress.com/">Pedaling in Place</a>, <a href="http://wanderlust-equipment.com/">Wanderlust Equipment</a> gear and <a href="http://www.hyperlitemountaingear.com/">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> was seen on a few pages, and a couple more people &amp; brands that you have heard about if you’re interested in the outdoor scene. Overall there was a very good balance of the known &amp; trendy and the unknown and cool in all categories.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14024833953" title="The Outsiders by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2898/14024833953_cdffce8fbd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Outsiders" /></a></p>

<p>There’s six “chapters” in the book: Hiking, Surfing, Cycling, On The Road, Snow and Water. All that comes after an Intro from Jeffrey Bowman, one of the authors of the book, and Erling Kagge, the first human to reach the South Pole, North Pole and stand on the summit of Mt. Everest. Add in interviews with Vincent Stanley from Patagonia, the Hoepner brothers who cycled from Berlin to Shanghai, designer Geoff McFetridge, amongst others, and you will have a hard time to put this book down. And even after you have read it back-to-back you will pick it up again, browse through the different sections to be inspired, or look up one of the cool kit pieces or blogs on the internet. And then you’ll want to go outside.</p>

<p>It’s a beautiful book for rainy days at home. You can get it directly from <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/outsiders.html">Gestalten</a> or order it from your favourite taste of Amazon: <a href="http://amzn.to/1faj21y">Amazon.co.uk</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1ikFiQV">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1rralzY">Amazon.de</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
