<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: running | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/running/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2021-06-03T14:34:47+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Run with Every Human]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/12/one-run-with-every-human.html"/>
    <updated>2020-12-10T12:28:40+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/12/one-run-with-every-human</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is Human Rights Day. Join me and thousands of other humans tonight at 19:00 o’clock of your local time for one hour of walking and running!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50701186118/in/dateposted/" title="One Run 10th December 2020"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50701186118_191ac12848_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="One Run 10th December 2020" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>I know one of the organizers of the One Run event, but participate and write about it as I believe this is a good cause. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>I run every week, mostly to <strong>a)</strong> stay fit for hiking and skitouring and <strong>b)</strong> because it is good for my mental health. So when I was asked if I’d like to participate today, on the <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/human-rights-day">Human Rights Day</a> in a one hour run or walk to show that love is a human right and that no child should be hated for who they are, I said yes. The event is called <a href="https://onerun.global">One Run</a> and is a truly global event every human can be part of - in fact, there’s <a href="https://onerun.global/map/">participants from all 195 countires</a>! While you’re reading this the first people are already out for a walk or run, and throughout the day humans across the globe will go at 7:00 pm of their local time out for a walk or run.</p>

<p><strong>So please join us!</strong> Walking or running is absolutely amazing for your mental health, gets your head free and your lungs full of fresh air (if you walk in the city, don’t forget to maybe wear a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/10/reuseable-face-masks.html">face mask</a> and practice social distancing). Walk with us so we can spread a wave of love, hope and unity around this beautiful planet! To get into the mood for your walk today watch the Live Stream on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/onerun_global/">Instagram</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/OneRunGlobal/">Facebook</a>, where the likes of Sopie Radcliffe and Al Humphreys will show up later today to inspire you! In that sense, put on your <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/08/my-trailrunning-gear.html">running shoes</a>, warm clothes and a beanie, and go tonight out to celebrate this Human Rights Day!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50702012377/in/photostream/" title="Into the Darkness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50702012377_b14f165daa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Into the Darkness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>(and you get great discount codes from partners - you could save 20% on your next purchase!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
