<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: finland | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/finland/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2019-10-01T10:47:29+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hiking to Akupää Summit]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/hiking-to-akupaa-summit.html"/>
    <updated>2019-09-23T12:27:15+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/hiking-to-akupaa-summit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Akupää might be one the least visited summits in the Ivalo region. Once you have seen it’s views, though, you’ll want to come back during every season!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743732731/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Akunpää Views"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743732731_5b47671a7c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Akunpää Views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This trip was supported financially by the Arctic Outdoor project. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>During my visit at Saariselkä I participated in several <a href="https://polarlifeoutdoor.com">Polarlife Outdoors</a> activities, and hiking with Henna was one of the highlights. Not only do I know how to hike, after five days in the Wilderness of Hammastunturi it was nice to have a chat with another person again! Henna from <a href="https://www.laplandlife.net/">Laplandlife</a> picked me up at my Hotel in Saariselkä and we hit it off right from the bat. She’s an upbeat, happy young women who after studying across Finland decided to return home to Lapland and combine all her passions and create her own business. That business is Laplandlife, and with it Henna takes people who visit the Ivalo-Saariselkä Region hiking, camping and berry picking in the summer, and snowshoeing, arctic swimming and ice fishing in the winter. As a professional massage therapist she also can help you relax after a day outdoors, and her <a href="https://www.laplandlife.net/wilderness-cabins/">Wilderness Cabins</a> are so far off-the-beaten track that you can be sure to not encounter anyone else during your stay there!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48780880326/in/dateposted/" title="Along the lake"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48780880326_99d464e289_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Along the lake" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Henna and I, however, were off to hike to the summit of Akupää. <em>“It’s in my backyard”</em> she told me as we drove to Ivalo, and silently I was wondering what that meant. What it meant became clear when we arrived: We passed a gate while she explained that all this land here, hundreds of hectares, belong to her dad. We drove to the end of a gravel road next to a most picturesque lake, the start of our hike. <em>“At the other side of the lake, well-hidden between the trees and far apart, are the two cabins”</em> Henna hold me, and I was already wondering how amazing it must be to spend a holiday here. No noise except the wind in the trees and the calls of birds could be heard, it’s exactly the kind of sounds I love and which you don’t get in the city.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743901177/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Autumn light"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743901177_787b3c0e11_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Autumn light" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Along the lake we hiked on game trails and small forest roads, all the time chatting about outdoor life in Lapland. After half an hour Henna offered me some home-made berry juice which was delicious, and then we set off slowly to climb towards the summit of Akupää. Completely off-trail we hiked through the most beautiful autumn birch and pine forests, often stopping to pick some bilberries and lingonberries which were growing in abundance on the floor of the forest.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743903127/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Henna on the way up"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743903127_218c9c73c2_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Henna on the way up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743903767/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Lonely Bilberry"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743903767_2949d7c9fa_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Lonely Bilberry" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743904647/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Light and Shadow"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743904647_af95318595_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Light and Shadow" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Here and there the forest opened up where trees have fallen, and we revelled in the beauty of it all under the sunshine on this autumn day. The conversation was flowing, we laughed together while steadily climbing higher and higher on this fjell. And then, through the low-grown birch trees, the summit came into view. My natural reaction when seeing the summit is to turn around and see what kind of view is to be seen, and here, just below the summit of Akupää, the view was beautiful. Low, pine-covered hills with small lakes who were glistening from the sunlight, we could see far into the distance.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743394023/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Sharpness Volume II"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743394023_d93dc7ae42_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Sharpness Volume II" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743397008/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Star"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743397008_3d85326225_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Star" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743732731/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Akunpää Views"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743732731_5b47671a7c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Akunpää Views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But, this wasn’t the summit yet. It was a few minutes further, and what awaited me there really was gorgeous.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743733536/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="That way be Russia!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743733536_06ebf52146_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="That way be Russia!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743734096/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Views"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743734096_aa9625879c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743895052/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Views to the North"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743895052_8e6dc0118e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Views to the North" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We could see till Russia from the summit, observed how two Raven and an Eagle were having an air show, and in every direction you could see forest-covered hill after forest-covered hill, creating an absolutely stunning panorama of silhouettes. After spending over half an hour at the summit Henna was ready to continue, and while I could have stood there and take in the view till past sunset, I shouldered my backpack and followed her. We passed beautiful little ponds which were so still and created dazzling mirror images, and soon we were back in the embrace of the forest with its golden leafs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743895947/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Autumn"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743895947_d7ce2db1c5_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Autumn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743382288/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Double Henna"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743382288_0d4ed88c97_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Double Henna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a while we made a proper break, with a fire, sitting down, eating a tasty meal and drinking fresh coffee. I lay down on the soft forest floor, on my bed of moss and shrubbery, while lounging in the sun and drinking another cup of coffee. <em>“This is the good life”</em> I proclaimed, and Henna agreed. We sat there in the forest, silently, happy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743896817/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Fall"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743896817_cbda0bb41b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Fall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A small detour on the way back was made, to a gorge, and Henna showed me where she takes guests to go camping in Tentsile tree-tents - a beautiful spot high above the gorge, which must have great views at night to the stars. We didn’t wait for the stars to come out, though - we continued on game trails back to the lake.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743740056/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Sun. Lake."><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743740056_0fe67744ca_h.jpg" width="1067" height="1600" alt="Sun. Lake." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743915547/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Dragonfly"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743915547_e6f59d817b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1103" alt="Dragonfly" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>At the lake I was able to get very close to the Dragonfly you see above. Dragonflies are without a doubt my favourite insects, I love their grace and how beautiful they are. If I ever would get a tattoo, then the tattoo of a dragonfly would be high up on the list. Back at the car I thanked Henna for the beautiful hike in her backyard, and thought to myself that if more people would have a backyard like her, and care as deeply for it, the world would be a better place. On the drive back to Saariselkä I spotted a juvenile Golden Eagle which made me smile, as these birds are not so often seen that dar in the north. I also wished for a longer lens to capture it even more up-close (<a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">You can send me a tip via PayPal</a> if you want that I can take better photos of wildlife in the future!), but I think the photo underneath is pretty good, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743917447/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Golden Eagle"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743917447_66a63e3abc_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Golden Eagle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities!</h2>

<p>I stayed in Saariselkä, which is probably <em>THE</em> place to be when you want to explore the North-Eastern corner of Finnish Lapland. Besides a dozen or more options for accommodation options - I stayed at the <a href="https://www.booking.com/hotel/fi/lapland-riekonlinna.en.html?aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna‎</a> - the village lays right at the border of the Urho Kekkonen National Park and is just a short 2 hour stroll away from the Hammastunturi Wilderness Area. This means you don’t need a car to go outdoors in Saariselkä, as you can walk in a few minutes from your Hotel or log cabin to the start of a trail. Here’s the <a href="https://www.booking.com/searchresults.en.html?city=900040403&amp;aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1&amp;room1=A">full list of Hotels and Cabins in Saariselkä</a>, and feel free to use that Affiliate Link when you’re making a reservation!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743375433/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna Room"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743375433_e869ca2dad_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna Room" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Getting to Saariselkä happens in one of three ways: You drive your car north for a veeeeeeery long time but are mobile there. Useful if you want to drive to different places, but hopefully you’re not alone in that car! The second and best option is to take the train and Bus. Taking the Bus from Rovaniemi to Saariselkä is a short and scenic 3 hour ride, and it really gets you in the mood for the outdoors as you ride past lakes and forests and every so often slow down to let the Reindeer get off the road. Taking an (overnight) train to Rovaniemi from Southern Finland is also very convenient, as you wake up well rested and just a short ride away from your next outdoor adventure. This is also a good way to travel if you want to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/11/outdoors-in-helsinki.html">explore Helsinki</a> before or after a visit in Lapland. Finally, if you come from abroad you also can fly directly to Ivalo, from where you can take a bus or Taxi to Saariselkä.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0i3st0" title="Oulu - Tromso"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48780910708_729d052bdf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Oulu - Tromso" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Saariselkä has for a village its size a variety of different options for eating out, from Anne’s Garden which serves delicious Burgers (great for backpackers who just returned to civilization!) to fine dining at Santa’s Hotel Tunturi and Lapland Hotels Riekonlinna‎ or the tasty Buffet at the Holiday Club. Cafe Porotupa at the market square makes really good coffee (On a side note, I’m always baffled how much bad coffee you get served in a variety of places in Finland, the World Champion in coffee consumption) and also fresh pancakes and cakes. If you rather cook yourself, then the supermarket in the village has everything you need, or if you need to stock-up on dehydrated meals for another backpacking trip then visit the <a href="https://www.partioaitta.fi/myymalat/saariselka/">Partioaitta Saariselkä</a>, probably the most-northern Outdoor Store in Finland!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743386333/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Starter at Santa&#x27;s Hotel Tunturi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743386333_a58790587b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Starter at Santa&#x27;s Hotel Tunturi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743458333/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Love me some bread"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743458333_7e5c6e62bf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Love me some bread" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>During my visit at Saariselkä I participated in many different <a href="https://polarlifeoutdoor.com">Polarlife Outdoors</a> activities, include going to the Sauna and Spa at the Holiday Club, hiking on one of the dozen of trails around the village, visiting the AMAZING Aurora Open Wilderness Hut when you want to see Northern Lights, participate in a wild herbs Workshop, visit a Sauna and going to swim in a stream, or rent a Mountainbike and explore one of the many single track trails and holler with joy when you ride down the fjell! During the next weeks you’ll be able to read more about my adventures in the far north and some of these activities, so consider <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">becoming a Fan on Facebook</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> to not miss the next instalments!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743877782/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Aroma Sauna at Holiday Club Saariselkä"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743877782_85b4aca859_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Aroma Sauna at Holiday Club Saariselkä" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743408513/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Aurora Hut in Saariselkä"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743408513_0655fe190d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Aurora Hut in Saariselkä" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743938062/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743938062_027221443c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743912072/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="16:9"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743912072_834de8507d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="561" alt="16:9" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions from the Far North]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/impressions-from-the-far-north.html"/>
    <updated>2019-09-17T12:41:58+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/impressions-from-the-far-north</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You know what is good for your well-being? A week in nature in the far north. I just came back from a trip to Saariselkä, and here are some visual impressions to get you into 🍂 autumn mood!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743913982/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Enjoying the view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743913982_9f89e25abe_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Enjoying the view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This trip was supported financially by the Arctic Outdoor project. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>I started my trip in Lapland with five days of backpacking in the Hammastunturi Wilderness Area.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743840193/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743840193_779f6733fe_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743856868/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743856868_11845d202b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744192771/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744192771_6544ae0676_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Golddiggers, fast-flowing rivers for fishing and packrafting, cozy open huts, almost no people, beautiful fjells with great views, Hammastunturi has it all.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744223086/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744223086_6c5c50f67d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744422202/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744422202_5934449e4a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744248336/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744248336_74fbd03582_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743898758/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743898758_220ca031b5_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744283366/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744283366_7d077d69c3_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I’m looking forward to returning to Hammastunturi, with more time and a packraft.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744316046/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744316046_c4b8ffebb2_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744008108/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Ivalojoen Kultaja"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744008108_05a2696ab3_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Ivalojoen Kultaja" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744067398/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744067398_bcdc50c9ee_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744139793/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744139793_ba2891d3ff_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After five days in the wilderness I returned to Saariselkä, had a hot shower and Sauna, and enjoyed several <a href="https://polarlifeoutdoor.com">Polarlife Outdoor</a> experiences. First I went hiking with Henna from Lapland Life in her backyard. A backyard with some stupendously good views, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743728211/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Sharpness Volume I"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743728211_adddf78571_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Sharpness Volume I" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743912072/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="16:9"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743912072_834de8507d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="561" alt="16:9" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743740056/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Sun. Lake."><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743740056_0fe67744ca_h.jpg" width="1067" height="1600" alt="Sun. Lake." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743740166/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Golden Eagle"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743740166_42acc5e8ac_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Golden Eagle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next day Minna from Arctic Sky Lapland went mushroom and berry picking with me, and then she prepared over the fire the most tasty vegan meal out of it. My mouth is watering just thinking about it now!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743928347/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Most awesome shrooms"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743928347_a601a7499b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Most awesome shrooms" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743418023/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Even more tasty Main!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743418023_2549c115da_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Even more tasty Main!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743756331/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Siberian Jay"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743756331_a45b96dba0_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Siberian Jay" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And on the third day Tiina and Reima, the owners of Saariselkä Training, showed me their local Mountain bike trails. And let me tell you, they’re nothing short of amazing!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743773356/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Enjoying the view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743773356_9b968fe0cc_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Enjoying the view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743791766/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Forest rides"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743791766_2bcc7a94ad_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Forest rides" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743356198/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Breakie at a Kota"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743356198_48930a2211_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Breakie at a Kota" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Obviously there also was tasty food in the village of Saariselkä, Sauna visits, dips in a lovely stream, and hikes in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho Kekkonen National Park</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743458333/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Love me some bread"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743458333_7e5c6e62bf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Love me some bread" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743938062/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743938062_027221443c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Taking a dip in the Sauna Stream at Wilderness Hotel Muotka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743373798/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Morning Coffee"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743373798_08fe33d83e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Morning Coffee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743924417/in/album-72157710868288123/" title="Aurora Hut in Saariselkä"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743924417_9905794361_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Aurora Hut in Saariselkä" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All of this you’ll be able to read about before the beginning of October! You can <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">watch all the Insta Stories via the Highlight on my Profile</a>, or watch the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/videos/503060627138216/?__xts__[0]=68.ARAWpeTSZr3lE31_SfON1700u6L7zmoCzZVTMmFPqyuLR-0-2alg30AIkUpwLpfFoqIsRoDp9YM1phRetHQlLfcU6wUmRQOLs1uSTQvFPLeIsojiN0kEHzIUsOIrqjVjU63VC-IxIGvoxHUv9pLbseKbNHhwdc-InXpbrCWBWwNszfWQDNCloj9sdKhNghReGlvzwwDrzP016yEvdaC2CcWza0rxovnBpcAPHWiU4BhxVvHBDzuQ6dKuFDDM7y1ZoRbuUyUmR6PGHk0tGK0uex48uF8Ts6oBwLG0aO3VcRRF60PUsLUiq_GIENopJsNe2EvaORfW1IDUJsXqVKOvidpqzsc34X65QDns&amp;__tn__=-R">short teaser video on Facebook</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Autumn backpacking inspiration]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/08/autumn-backpacking-inspiration.html"/>
    <updated>2019-08-22T22:01:38+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/08/autumn-backpacking-inspiration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Good bye summer, welcome AUTUMN 🍂🍄! Crisp nights, colourful forests and fjells, no mosquitos and the stars at night - autumn is the best time to go backpacking!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48599448332/in/dateposted/" title="Scotland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48599448332_dbd19521d3_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p>Can you smell that? It’s that fresh yet slightly mouldy smell which hangs in the air when you now walk through the forest, which tells us it is the end of summer. Of course also the first yellow leaves 🍂 on the ground are a tell-tale sign of the change of the season, and I always start to smile when I smell that odour and see them 🍂. But also the 🍄 which start to come now out (thanks to a lot of rain 💦 these past few weeks) tell us: Time to start planning your autumn hikes! Well, here’s some videos and photos to inspire you to experience this beautiful time outdoors!</p>

<h2 id="cairngorms-scotland">Cairngorms, Scotland</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/iq9GhCfGpCY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36941190313/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Remove Crampons"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4488/36941190313_3401386563_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Remove Crampons" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36941189873/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Loch Etchachan"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4497/36941189873_c3416f9b54_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Loch Etchachan" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48599301516/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Scotland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48599301516_1e270e69c1_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48599304051/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Scotland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48599304051_1703d67f27_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48599293826/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Scotland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48599293826_299270a94e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48599307471/in/album-72157687145392030/" title="Scotland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48599307471_1f465f8892_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/10/impressions-from-the-scottish-cairngorms.html">hiked across the Cairngorms</a> in 2017 with my best friend, and what a beautiful mountain range it is! I long to go back, and with Brexit looming now is a great time to go.</p>

<h2 id="relvsleden-trail-sweden">Öreälvsleden Trail, Sweden</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/0S3FI9kVYSY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37357998162/in/album-72157688561043576/" title="View towards Bjurholm"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4500/37357998162_ac26c9ec4d_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1199" alt="View towards Bjurholm" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37388441441/in/album-72157688561043576/" title="Petnäset"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4363/37388441441_ab28242199_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1199" alt="Petnäset" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36679311814/in/album-72157688561043576/" title="Through the birches"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4417/36679311814_2576089951_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Through the birches" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/37357959212/in/album-72157688561043576/" title="Shoes &#x27;n &#x27;Shrooms"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4482/37357959212_1457eee302_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Shoes &#x27;n &#x27;Shrooms" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23536129698/in/album-72157688561043576/" title="Rapids"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4401/23536129698_0a9ee7fbc4_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Rapids" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I was <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/11/backpacking-on-the-orealvsleden-trail.html">bckpacking on the Öreälvsleden Trail</a> also in 2017, just as autumn kicked things off. Damn, did I have a good time on this beautiful trail on the East-coast of Sweden!</p>

<h2 id="urho-kekkonen-national-park-finland">Urho Kekkonen National Park, Finland</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/mpv4kAtN_DQ" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763991044/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="That way"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/2809/9763991044_91ef9a50eb_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1063" alt="That way" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9764143326/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Up Paradise Gorge"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/3770/9764143326_e7d9e4aa20_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1063" alt="Up Paradise Gorge" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763145235/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/3700/9763145235_daf856f5c0_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1063" alt="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16799797338/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Lankojärvi Hut"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/8690/16799797338_01b905e493_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1063" alt="Lankojärvi Hut" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763627381/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Chanterelles"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/3799/9763627381_0a590daf4a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1025" alt="Chanterelles" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It’s already six years ago that I was backpacking with my brother in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">Urho Kekkonen National Park</a> in Finnish Lapland. It does feel like yesterday, these good memories. And it’s a good thing that soon I will be back there =)</p>

<h2 id="vldalen-sweden">Vålådalen, Sweden</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Zr6Ev1MFxBw" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797401337/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Can you spot my tent?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1898/29797401337_08fa784358_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1199" alt="Can you spot my tent?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199753085/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Whoop whoop!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1971/44199753085_41c8b78887_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Whoop whoop!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797401837/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="2nd Camp"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1856/29797401837_ffe944a6b4_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="2nd Camp" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797405447/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Shadows"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1891/29797405447_99926c2488_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Shadows" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Last autumn I visited <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/09/impressions-from-are-and-valadalen.html">Vålådalen</a> again, and it blew my mind. I hiked 45 km off-trail with no one around (except Reindeer 🦌) and can’t wait to go back to Sweden again!</p>

<h2 id="pyrenees-andorra-spain-and-france">Pyrenees, Andorra, Spain and France</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/m8EstxnC8uQ" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31146548867/in/album-72157702356861281/" title="Helsport Lofoten Superlite Camp 3 somewhere in the Spanish Pyrenees"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4875/31146548867_db133320e2_h.jpg" width="1600" height="900" alt="Helsport Lofoten Superlite Camp 3 somewhere in the Spanish Pyrenees" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32245635068/in/album-72157702356861281/" title="Taking in the view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4805/32245635068_74bb7883b5_h.jpg" width="1600" height="900" alt="Taking in the view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48599325096/in/album-72157702356861281/" title="Pyrenees Impressions"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48599325096_e6be793993_h.jpg" width="1600" height="900" alt="Pyrenees Impressions" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48599465507/in/album-72157702356861281/" title="Pyrenees Impressions"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48599465507_c50fb1f4fa_h.jpg" width="1600" height="900" alt="Pyrenees Impressions" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In 2018 my best friend Martin and me paid a visit to the Pyrenees. They are everything anyone who has ever hiked there tells you they are, so if you fancy a visit to Spain, France and Andorra and exploring their mountains you should jump on a train to Southern Europe for your autumn trip!</p>

<h2 id="dolomites-italy">Dolomites, Italy</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/4SkbbMIUku4" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30404195455" title="Where does the trail lead?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/5544/30404195455_c0e25b5e11_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Where does the trail lead?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30403910045" title="Things start out sunny"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/5762/30403910045_bc24e45d7f_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Things start out sunny" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30497509756/in/album-72157675269849996/" title="High Dynamic Range Anyone?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/8618/30497509756_fc0c2471f5_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="High Dynamic Range Anyone?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30287292142" title="Into the Fanes-Sennes-Prags Nature Park"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7771/30287292142_63efe6c507_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Into the Fanes-Sennes-Prags Nature Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/autumn-backpacking-in-the-dolomites.html">Backpacking in the Dolomites</a> is the experience of a life-time. Hiking beneath the Tre Cime is magical and awe-inspiring, and best of all: In autumn you won’t meet many people at all!</p>

<p>As you can see, from Northern to Southern Europe, autumn is everywhere the best backpacking season. Even better, you could start next week with your first autumn backpacking trip in Lapland, and then continually travel further south as this magical season travels across the continent, colouring the leaves, giving the mountains their first dusting of snow, and making us grin into the morning sun with our hot cup of coffee in our hands!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46035287872/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Break"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4821/46035287872_8e103d7ef1_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Break" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SUP Adventures in the Kvarken Archipelago]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/06/sup-adventures-in-the-kvarken-archipelago.html"/>
    <updated>2019-06-28T18:00:36+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/06/sup-adventures-in-the-kvarken-archipelago</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You know what’s the best with this summer heat we’re having? Going for some water-based adventures! And that’s exactly what I did - taking my SUP Board to the Kvarken Archipelago for a sunset paddle!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142239432/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset SUPing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142239432_6894d99d74_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Sunset SUPing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with equipment by Decathlon, and includes Affiliate Links to the mentioned products. But as you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>Climate Change is showing it’s HOT phase in Europe at the moment, and with temperatures above 25°C in many parts of Finland I did what I always do when things get too toasty: I go outdoors! This time I took my new <a href="http://tidd.ly/a5476407">SUP Board</a> along and went for a sunset paddle in the Kvarken Archipelago. For a long time I wanted to try SUP Paddling but adhering to normal business hours of the SUP School in town has proven difficult for me. Hence an own inflatable SUP Board and the possibility to go when it’s best for me - when the kids are in bed and the sun still shines late! - works best!</p>

<p>It’s a nice short drive to Svedjehamn on the furthest corner of the <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/kvarken">Kvarken Archipelago</a> and as always I took a short stroll along the iconic red boat houses which line the harbour. It doesn’t matter which season I come here, I always fall in love with this view.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142145816/in/dateposted/" title="Admiring Svedjehamn Harbour"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142145816_31d391154b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Admiring Svedjehamn Harbour" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With a bright and warm sun shining I walk to the secret spot I made out from the map, and start the process of inflating the SUP Board and getting it ready. Mosquitos fly around me while I handle the <a href="http://tidd.ly/34afe181">pump</a> to get the SUP sea-worthy. Five minutes inflation time was claimed on the website, and like any good digital citizen I was sceptic of this claim. However, I was proven wrong and the SUP was inflated to 15 PSI in some six Minutes - the extra Minute likely coming from me slapping Mosquitos away and making sure the tube was connected correctly.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142146261/in/dateposted/" title="Inflating my Itiwit 11&#x27; from Decathlon"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142146261_dee3d83c49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inflating my Itiwit 11&#x27; from Decathlon" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142232837/in/dateposted/" title="Almost done!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142232837_a08afb7b67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Almost done!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142144571/in/dateposted/" title="Light enough to carry"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142144571_feebe5eb49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Light enough to carry" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I changed into my shorts and shirt and then was ready to put out to sea! I was surprised by how light the whole SUP was, and when I will be paddling it again I think I can even plan in some short portages on future adventures!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142151506/in/dateposted/" title="Bird&#x27;s Eye View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142151506_0d0a87f077_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Bird&#x27;s Eye View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142146576/in/photostream/" title="Paddling"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142146576_e66ab09297_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Paddling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I simply love the Kvarken Archipelago. The moraine formations from the Ice Age which are still slowly emerging from the sea (every year they rise around 1 cm) make the Archipelago very shallow, and hence excellent for paddling - and also for a large variety of wild life. There’s White-Tailed Sea Eagles, Arctic Terns, Oystercatchers and other birds calling Kvarken their home during the summer, and under water you can find massive Pikes, Perch and many other fish. There are many beautiful sand beaches, and the water temperature is often nice and warm. There’s also some beautiful lighthouses here, and they already have me scheming for future trips!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142146886/in/dateposted/" title="SUP Paddling in Kvarken"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142146886_014dca9f82_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SUP Paddling in Kvarken" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142149251/in/dateposted/" title="Itiwit SUP Paddle"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142149251_1fbe92f4d9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Itiwit SUP Paddle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I paddle out from the small bay where I put in, birds circling around me and observing this floating human. I pass many small rock islands and almost all the time can see the rocky ground a meter or two under the clear water surface. I paddle along the shore, then out into the open where the wind blows stronger. With my packraft this would have been an uphill battle, though putting the nose of the SUP straight into the wind I am amazed by how easy it is to paddle into the wind - and even better, I think, on my way back this wind will pretty much sail me towards the beach!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142235227/in/dateposted/" title="Towards the Sun"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142235227_bd722f8d1d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Towards the Sun" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I navigate myself towards the shore for a short break, where I enjoy putting my feet into the warm Baltic Sea while the sun shines on my face. An Arctic Tern lands close by on a rock and looks interested into my direction, probably wondering how this human managed to get completely dry on this small rocky island. I smile as it takes off and decide it is also time for me to continue - the sun is nearing the horizon, and while it does not get dark at all right now it is nicer to paddle while it is still light.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142231252/in/dateposted/" title="Kick-off!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142231252_9fda02726d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kick-off!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142237637/in/dateposted/" title="Back to the Beach"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142237637_1bd3a4ffff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back to the Beach" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142239727/in/photostream/" title="Isn&#x27;t Kvarken pretty?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142239727_2d0a507893_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Isn&#x27;t Kvarken pretty?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Back at the beach I meet two Germans from Hamburg who are travelling around the Baltic Sea with their Van, and we chat about Vaasa, SUP paddling and the beauty which is around us, all while I easily deflate the SUP and pack it back up in it’s backpack. After my first journey at sea with my new <a href="http://tidd.ly/a5476407">SUP board</a> I am mighty impressed with it. It is easy to inflate to the recommended 15 PSI with the <a href="http://tidd.ly/34afe181">Pump</a>, and just as easy to deflate - the valve can be locked into a deflate position which means packing up is the easiest thing ever (and something which I imagined would take me 20 Minutes or more). Simply open the valve and then start to roll up the SUP Board from it’s tail to the front - The whole procedure didn’t even take five Minutes! And as outlined at the beginning, inflating it was just as easy and a quick affair.</p>

<p>Handling-wise, thanks to the fin which is easy to install the board is very stable and easy to manoeuvre with, and the width of 86 cm makes it very stable for a beginner like me. The sharp tip and overall long length of 335 cm make it a fast SUP, while at the same time it still is very agile and it was easy to paddle between the rocks and reeds. The reinforced sidewalls of the SUP definitely are a Plus here in the Kvarken Archipelago as sharp rocks linger everywhere, while the EVA Grippad not only made it very clear where I should stand but also gave me good grip on the wet board. The <a href="http://tidd.ly/b6abadbc">SUP Paddle</a> is both light and easy to adjust in length from 170 to 220 cm, which makes it great when the kids want to try to SUP as I won’t need to get an extra paddle for them! Overall the construction of the board (with a 9 mm Dropstich and a reinforced Stringer for more stiffness) is high-quality and I don’t doubt that the kids and me will have a lot of fun with it. It comes with it’s own backpack and everything together - SUP board, backpack, Pump and paddle - weighs ~11,5 kg, which means it’s light enough to carry it also on the bike to the beach!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142150451/in/dateposted/" title="Taking in the view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142150451_195b21a28d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Taking in the view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142238787/in/dateposted/" title="And soon deflating!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142238787_4e5895dbe9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And soon deflating!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After everything was packed up and I had killed a dozen Mosquitos it was time to head back to Vaasa. On the way home the sun was coming closer and closer towards the horizon, bathing the sky into a beautiful orange. Damn, it’s pretty to be outside!</p>

<p><em><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157709287009992">More photos on Flickr!</a></em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142153606/in/photostream/" title="That Orange"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142153606_0372f6ff46_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="That Orange" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Skiing in Ruka]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/spring-skiing-in-ruka.html"/>
    <updated>2019-04-08T19:04:43+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/spring-skiing-in-ruka</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The skiing season 2019 isn’t over just yet - there’s still great snow to be shredded in the far North of Finland, as I experienced last weekend in Ruka.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646623965/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Spring Powder"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7858/46646623965_b78d7ffb1e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Spring Powder" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This journey was supported by the local tourism bureau and partners, but I did not get paid to write about this trip. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>As part of me trying to minimize my environmental footprint but unwilling to not ski I travelled last weekend by train and bus to Ruka-Kuusamo, some 500 kilometres from Vaasa away. Even with short stop-overs between switching from the train to the Bus it’s almost a 10 hour journey to get to Ruka, though as you can walk around in the train, there’s good internet and you can work there’s nothing to worry about. Though I was happy that I was able to get out on the hills once I arrived in Ruka, and with the lifts being open till 19 o’clock I got in a few hours of skiing on the slopes after a full day of travelling - not a bad start! And to make it even better, it had been snowing the whole Thursday and would continue throughout the night.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685356208/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Thursday Evening Skiing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7894/33685356208_52fecd4a85_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Thursday Evening Skiing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the skiing I went to have Dinner at <a href="https://ruokburger.fi">RUOK Burger</a> which is just next door from my apartment in the <a href="https://www.ski-inn.fi/en/majoitus/ruka">Ruka Village Ski-Inn</a>. Their Portobello Burger was the only vegetarian option and super-tasty, and I accompanied it with a local Craft Beer from Rovaniemi, a nice Amber Lager. After that I retired to my cozy apartment, heated up the Sauna and watched how it was snowing outside. Being on ski holidays it is always great to watch it snow ❄️ as that means fresh powder the next day when you’re outside on the hills!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646623875/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="RUOK Burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7829/46646623875_4970e1c601_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="RUOK Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685357508/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="RUOK Burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7842/33685357508_757fa2a7c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="RUOK Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646623605/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Super-Tasty Portobello Burger at RUOK Burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7847/46646623605_f97ab2cb84_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Super-Tasty Portobello Burger at RUOK Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619681437/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="LOCAL BEER!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7837/32619681437_6e36cc1bc8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCAL BEER!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning a bright blue sky woke me up, and all signs were on an amazing day on and off the slopes. There’s just something great about hitting the slopes and being one of the first ones there. I love painting my curves into the still un-shredded corduroy, and then Veera and me went into the side-country to look for some powder. And powder we found.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619681717/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Fresh Corduroy"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7837/32619681717_97340350c9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fresh Corduroy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619681817/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Untouched snow"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7926/32619681817_95d39fa4c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Untouched snow" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646624275/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Chair lifts galore"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7865/46646624275_60b6b2977c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chair lifts galore" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It really feels amazing to surf through the fluffy snow and throw up big swoops of the white gold. Veera and me both had big smiles on our faces after cruising through the powder-filled forests, so once it was noon we went to <a href="http://www.hankibaari.fi">Hanki Baari</a> for lunch, where I ate a tasty vegan Mie Goreng. Hanki Baari is either way an amazing place to chill after a day on the slopes, listening to music and drinking some fancy beers, though right now we just needed some good nutrition before hitting the slopes again.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619682177/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Vegan Mie Goreng Lunch at Hanki Baari"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7802/32619682177_ce4405d1bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vegan Mie Goreng Lunch at Hanki Baari" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646624635/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ski Pride Ruka Weekend"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7818/46646624635_608e794bd0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Pride Ruka Weekend" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So, after a coffee ☕️ it was time to go ride some more. After all, the sun was shining, the slopes were in prime condition and the lifts would be running till 23 o’clock (Fridays the Ruka Ski Resort’s lifts run so late because those who journey after work to Ruka still can hit the illuminated slopes!). However, we wouldn’t ski that long, as we had another plan.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619683337/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Disembark"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7899/32619683337_d41391c1cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Disembark" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646626385/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Them views"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7813/46646626385_f4b0109446_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Them views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596169873/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="In the Shadows"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7836/40596169873_f159cf0de1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="In the Shadows" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We went on a little powder hunt with friends of Veera, which resulted in a short but exhausting climb through hip-deep snow back to the slopes from the lake 🤣 After that I went for a few more laps on the slopes before calling it a day. A quick shower later I was sitting in the <a href="https://www.pizzeriaruka.fi/en/">Pizzeria Ruka</a> which is probably the best Pizza you can get in Ruka. It’s a five minute stroll from the centre of the village to the Pizzeria, and their wood-fired oven served me in no time a delicious Tartufo Pizza. That’s exactly what I needed after almost six hours of skiing, and gave me enough energy for the hike we had planned for the evening.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596170443/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Pizza"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7810/40596170443_c0d176d536_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pizza" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596170753/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Tasty Slices at Pizzeria Ruka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7845/40596170753_19d235de5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tasty Slices at Pizzeria Ruka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As a <a href="https://www.hendrikmorkel.com">photographer</a> I hate it to spend a gorgeous sunset inside, so I was happy that Veera and her dog were up for a sunset mission to Konttainen, a hill some 10 minutes away from Ruka. A steep 11 minute climb later we were on the top of Konttainen, and strolled towards the best spot in the house while the show was just starting. It’s soooooo much better to be outside in nature when the sun sets than sitting inside, and this definitely was an evening well spent. After the sun disappeared from view we gazed for a while onto the illuminated slopes of Ruka, and for a moment I was tempted to jump back into my <a href="http://bit.ly/2D2JtFL">ski boots</a> and go for some night skiing. But then I remembered my warm Sauna and the cold beer which were waiting for me, so I skipped the night skiing and relaxed in my apartment before calling it a night.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596171763/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Sunset Show just staring"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7817/40596171763_a31c40d077_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset Show just staring" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619686237/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Getting better"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7880/32619686237_1dd76bc6a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Getting better" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619687547/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Excitement is rising"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7851/32619687547_15fce8cfa6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Excitement is rising" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596172983/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Almost there"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7882/40596172983_e03b838190_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Almost there" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596173143/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="And almost down"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7802/40596173143_cec399d4e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And almost down" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619688517/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka&#x27;s Slopes illuminated"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7874/32619688517_26d6af67f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka&#x27;s Slopes illuminated" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning white clouds hung over the mountain and gave the slopes and village a sci-fi feel. I’s the kind of weather where you ponder if you should just stay inside and chill-lax, but as I wanted to get my skis on that didn’t happen and early on Saturday morning Veera and me where again on the slopes, searching for some untracked pockets of powder.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596173853/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Misty Mornings"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7917/40596173853_5b147ff40c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Misty Mornings" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562164731/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Coming from the future"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7851/47562164731_dc69c53e4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Coming from the future" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596174403/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="First lines"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7826/40596174403_e2e0553318_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="First lines" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596174683/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Dystopian Future"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7848/40596174683_8f912da413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dystopian Future" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And slowly but surely the sun was burning through the clouds and as the day progressed the views came out again, and we also were lucky by finding some fine lines of untouched powder not far from the hustle and bustle of the slopes.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646634175/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Views again"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7819/46646634175_d07a221fc4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views again" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596175043/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="POW POW"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7891/40596175043_239e14fdb3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="POW POW" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47509265442/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Maasto"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7876/47509265442_18aae9f36f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Maasto" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After all that off-piste skiing it was time to join the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/ski-pride">Ruka Ski Pride</a> Parade. I really ❤️ that Ruka has this event which celebrates equal rites and diversity on the slopes, and the vibe was so positive and fun - I really enjoyed to be part of it 🌈 Besides this parade there were inclusive events the whole weekend, with concerts and DJs, and of course some good skiing!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685355138/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ski Pride 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7915/33685355138_926a6e9038_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Pride 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685354418/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7841/33685354418_a365919e9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619676697/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7857/32619676697_618d2b6e71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then the day was almost over again. But not before I skied one final time from the East to the West, and from the North to the South across the whole resort. I love to ski fast and go from one end of a resort to the other one, shredding down the slopes and throwing up clouds of slushy spring snow, and at the end of this Saturday my trusty <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/suunto-spartan-ultra-black-multifunktionsuhr/?pid=10239">Suunto Spartan Ultra</a> told me I had skied almost 50 km of distance this day, and I could tell by how my legs felt.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562166431/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Tuntori"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7825/47562166431_77d3603d05_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Tuntori" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562167221/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="SUPER PIPE"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7801/47562167221_1a1b79536c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SUPER PIPE" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46838345644/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="The Ruka Gondola"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7831/46838345644_293ff94e4e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Ruka Gondola" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562152021/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Towards the sun"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7909/47562152021_744e195d9a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Towards the sun" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596162833/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Views for days"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7823/40596162833_a85297ed36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views for days" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After some relaxing I met Mats for Dinner at <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/villisika">Villisika</a> from where you have the best view over the slopes, so while we were eating we could see how the snow groomers got the hill ready for the next day. Sadly, the next sunny day I wouldn’t be shredding the groomers, as I was sitting in the train and bus back south. But I have a feeling that I will travel North once more for more skiing before the winter truly ends ❄️</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562151491/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Tasty Dinner at Villisika"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7814/47562151491_0ff6a3b8e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tasty Dinner at Villisika" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47509251882/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Blueberry Dessert at Villisika"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7841/47509251882_02dd732888_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Blueberry Dessert at Villisika" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As always, there’s more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157707789591555">Photo Album</a>.</p>

<h2 id="spring-skiing-in-ruka">Spring Skiing in Ruka</h2>

<p>As you can see above, winter isn’t over just yet in Finnish Lapland, even if it may feel like it here in the south where most of the snow is already gone. Until early May there’s plenty of great skiing to be had in Northern Finland, and if you’re like me and can not get enough of skiing and winter then you too should steal away for a weekend to Ruka for some spring skiing. The slopes in <a href="https://www.ruka.fi">Ruka</a> are open till early May, and between now and the closing of the slopes there’s every weekend a weekend of fun to be had: Next weekend, from the 11.4. - 14.4.2019 is the legendary <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/spring-break">Ruka Spring Break</a> which will enlighten those who like to Party between hitting the groomers. The <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/easter">Easter Weekend</a> has winter activities for the whole family on offer, and the first of May is the traditional <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/wappulounas">Wappulounas</a>, a get-together of the international snowboard community on the slopes of Ruka. So don’t ponder longer - go and get some of that spring snow!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562152531/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Higher"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7910/47562152531_d8bef744e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Higher" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="where-to-stay">Where to Stay</h2>

<p>I stayed at the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/rukasuites">Ski Inn</a> and liked my apartment in the centre of the village. It was a two minute stroll to the Gondola and lift, a one minute walk to the supermarket, and Hanki Baari was even in the same building so I didn’t had to go far for a beer! There’s plenty more <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/where-to-stay">places to stay in Ruka</a> for any budget, and if you’re pondering where to eat: Just follow my recommendations above or try any of the other restaurants in the village and it’s surroundings.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646624975/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Village Ski-Inn"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7834/46646624975_6c51f4fbd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="650" alt="Ruka Village Ski-Inn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596173453/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="My apartment at the Ski-Inn"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7923/40596173453_1f5d8249d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="My apartment at the Ski-Inn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="getting-to-ruka">Getting to Ruka</h2>

<p>The most convenient way is to take the <a href="http://vr.fi">train</a> and <a href="https://matkahuolto.fi">bus</a> to Ruka, or if you come from abroad you can fly to the <a href="https://www.finavia.fi/en/airports/kuusamo">Kuusamo Airport</a> and take the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/getting-around">Ski Bus</a> to Ruka. On the train you can sleep, work and walk around, and during the bus trip you can enjoy the beautiful Finnish landscape while listening to your favourite tunes.</p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on a Discord Chat with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562151761/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ski Pride Ruka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7814/47562151761_f7e96bc0f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Pride Ruka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
