<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: finland | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/finland/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2019-07-19T17:00:30+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SUP Adventures in the Kvarken Archipelago]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/06/sup-adventures-in-the-kvarken-archipelago.html"/>
    <updated>2019-06-28T18:00:36+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/06/sup-adventures-in-the-kvarken-archipelago</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You know what’s the best with this summer heat we’re having? Going for some water-based adventures! And that’s exactly what I did - taking my SUP Board to the Kvarken Archipelago for a sunset paddle!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142239432/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset SUPing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142239432_6894d99d74_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Sunset SUPing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with equipment by Decathlon, and includes Affiliate Links to the mentioned products. But as you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>Climate Change is showing it’s HOT phase in Europe at the moment, and with temperatures above 25°C in many parts of Finland I did what I always do when things get too toasty: I go outdoors! This time I took my new <a href="http://tidd.ly/a5476407">SUP Board</a> along and went for a sunset paddle in the Kvarken Archipelago. For a long time I wanted to try SUP Paddling but adhering to normal business hours of the SUP School in town has proven difficult for me. Hence an own inflatable SUP Board and the possibility to go when it’s best for me - when the kids are in bed and the sun still shines late! - works best!</p>

<p>It’s a nice short drive to Svedjehamn on the furthest corner of the <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/kvarken">Kvarken Archipelago</a> and as always I took a short stroll along the iconic red boat houses which line the harbour. It doesn’t matter which season I come here, I always fall in love with this view.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142145816/in/dateposted/" title="Admiring Svedjehamn Harbour"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142145816_31d391154b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Admiring Svedjehamn Harbour" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>With a bright and warm sun shining I walk to the secret spot I made out from the map, and start the process of inflating the SUP Board and getting it ready. Mosquitos fly around me while I handle the <a href="http://tidd.ly/34afe181">pump</a> to get the SUP sea-worthy. Five minutes inflation time was claimed on the website, and like any good digital citizen I was sceptic of this claim. However, I was proven wrong and the SUP was inflated to 15 PSI in some six Minutes - the extra Minute likely coming from me slapping Mosquitos away and making sure the tube was connected correctly.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142146261/in/dateposted/" title="Inflating my Itiwit 11&#x27; from Decathlon"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142146261_dee3d83c49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Inflating my Itiwit 11&#x27; from Decathlon" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142232837/in/dateposted/" title="Almost done!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142232837_a08afb7b67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Almost done!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142144571/in/dateposted/" title="Light enough to carry"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142144571_feebe5eb49_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Light enough to carry" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I changed into my shorts and shirt and then was ready to put out to sea! I was surprised by how light the whole SUP was, and when I will be paddling it again I think I can even plan in some short portages on future adventures!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142151506/in/dateposted/" title="Bird&#x27;s Eye View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142151506_0d0a87f077_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Bird&#x27;s Eye View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142146576/in/photostream/" title="Paddling"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142146576_e66ab09297_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Paddling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I simply love the Kvarken Archipelago. The moraine formations from the Ice Age which are still slowly emerging from the sea (every year they rise around 1 cm) make the Archipelago very shallow, and hence excellent for paddling - and also for a large variety of wild life. There’s White-Tailed Sea Eagles, Arctic Terns, Oystercatchers and other birds calling Kvarken their home during the summer, and under water you can find massive Pikes, Perch and many other fish. There are many beautiful sand beaches, and the water temperature is often nice and warm. There’s also some beautiful lighthouses here, and they already have me scheming for future trips!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142146886/in/dateposted/" title="SUP Paddling in Kvarken"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142146886_014dca9f82_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SUP Paddling in Kvarken" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142149251/in/dateposted/" title="Itiwit SUP Paddle"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142149251_1fbe92f4d9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Itiwit SUP Paddle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I paddle out from the small bay where I put in, birds circling around me and observing this floating human. I pass many small rock islands and almost all the time can see the rocky ground a meter or two under the clear water surface. I paddle along the shore, then out into the open where the wind blows stronger. With my packraft this would have been an uphill battle, though putting the nose of the SUP straight into the wind I am amazed by how easy it is to paddle into the wind - and even better, I think, on my way back this wind will pretty much sail me towards the beach!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142235227/in/dateposted/" title="Towards the Sun"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142235227_bd722f8d1d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Towards the Sun" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I navigate myself towards the shore for a short break, where I enjoy putting my feet into the warm Baltic Sea while the sun shines on my face. An Arctic Tern lands close by on a rock and looks interested into my direction, probably wondering how this human managed to get completely dry on this small rocky island. I smile as it takes off and decide it is also time for me to continue - the sun is nearing the horizon, and while it does not get dark at all right now it is nicer to paddle while it is still light.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142231252/in/dateposted/" title="Kick-off!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142231252_9fda02726d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Kick-off!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142237637/in/dateposted/" title="Back to the Beach"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142237637_1bd3a4ffff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back to the Beach" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142239727/in/photostream/" title="Isn&#x27;t Kvarken pretty?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142239727_2d0a507893_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Isn&#x27;t Kvarken pretty?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Back at the beach I meet two Germans from Hamburg who are travelling around the Baltic Sea with their Van, and we chat about Vaasa, SUP paddling and the beauty which is around us, all while I easily deflate the SUP and pack it back up in it’s backpack. After my first journey at sea with my new <a href="http://tidd.ly/a5476407">SUP board</a> I am mighty impressed with it. It is easy to inflate to the recommended 15 PSI with the <a href="http://tidd.ly/34afe181">Pump</a>, and just as easy to deflate - the valve can be locked into a deflate position which means packing up is the easiest thing ever (and something which I imagined would take me 20 Minutes or more). Simply open the valve and then start to roll up the SUP Board from it’s tail to the front - The whole procedure didn’t even take five Minutes! And as outlined at the beginning, inflating it was just as easy and a quick affair.</p>

<p>Handling-wise, thanks to the fin which is easy to install the board is very stable and easy to manoeuvre with, and the width of 86 cm makes it very stable for a beginner like me. The sharp tip and overall long length of 335 cm make it a fast SUP, while at the same time it still is very agile and it was easy to paddle between the rocks and reeds. The reinforced sidewalls of the SUP definitely are a Plus here in the Kvarken Archipelago as sharp rocks linger everywhere, while the EVA Grippad not only made it very clear where I should stand but also gave me good grip on the wet board. The <a href="http://tidd.ly/b6abadbc">SUP Paddle</a> is both light and easy to adjust in length from 170 to 220 cm, which makes it great when the kids want to try to SUP as I won’t need to get an extra paddle for them! Overall the construction of the board (with a 9 mm Dropstich and a reinforced Stringer for more stiffness) is high-quality and I don’t doubt that the kids and me will have a lot of fun with it. It comes with it’s own backpack and everything together - SUP board, backpack, Pump and paddle - weighs ~11,5 kg, which means it’s light enough to carry it also on the bike to the beach!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142150451/in/dateposted/" title="Taking in the view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142150451_195b21a28d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Taking in the view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142238787/in/dateposted/" title="And soon deflating!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142238787_4e5895dbe9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And soon deflating!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After everything was packed up and I had killed a dozen Mosquitos it was time to head back to Vaasa. On the way home the sun was coming closer and closer towards the horizon, bathing the sky into a beautiful orange. Damn, it’s pretty to be outside!</p>

<p><em><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157709287009992">More photos on Flickr!</a></em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48142153606/in/photostream/" title="That Orange"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48142153606_0372f6ff46_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="That Orange" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Skiing in Ruka]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/spring-skiing-in-ruka.html"/>
    <updated>2019-04-08T19:04:43+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/spring-skiing-in-ruka</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The skiing season 2019 isn’t over just yet - there’s still great snow to be shredded in the far North of Finland, as I experienced last weekend in Ruka.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646623965/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Spring Powder"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7858/46646623965_b78d7ffb1e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Spring Powder" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This journey was supported by the local tourism bureau and partners, but I did not get paid to write about this trip. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>As part of me trying to minimize my environmental footprint but unwilling to not ski I travelled last weekend by train and bus to Ruka-Kuusamo, some 500 kilometres from Vaasa away. Even with short stop-overs between switching from the train to the Bus it’s almost a 10 hour journey to get to Ruka, though as you can walk around in the train, there’s good internet and you can work there’s nothing to worry about. Though I was happy that I was able to get out on the hills once I arrived in Ruka, and with the lifts being open till 19 o’clock I got in a few hours of skiing on the slopes after a full day of travelling - not a bad start! And to make it even better, it had been snowing the whole Thursday and would continue throughout the night.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685356208/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Thursday Evening Skiing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7894/33685356208_52fecd4a85_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Thursday Evening Skiing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the skiing I went to have Dinner at <a href="https://ruokburger.fi">RUOK Burger</a> which is just next door from my apartment in the <a href="https://www.ski-inn.fi/en/majoitus/ruka">Ruka Village Ski-Inn</a>. Their Portobello Burger was the only vegetarian option and super-tasty, and I accompanied it with a local Craft Beer from Rovaniemi, a nice Amber Lager. After that I retired to my cozy apartment, heated up the Sauna and watched how it was snowing outside. Being on ski holidays it is always great to watch it snow ❄️ as that means fresh powder the next day when you’re outside on the hills!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646623875/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="RUOK Burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7829/46646623875_4970e1c601_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="RUOK Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685357508/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="RUOK Burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7842/33685357508_757fa2a7c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="RUOK Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646623605/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Super-Tasty Portobello Burger at RUOK Burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7847/46646623605_f97ab2cb84_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Super-Tasty Portobello Burger at RUOK Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619681437/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="LOCAL BEER!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7837/32619681437_6e36cc1bc8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCAL BEER!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning a bright blue sky woke me up, and all signs were on an amazing day on and off the slopes. There’s just something great about hitting the slopes and being one of the first ones there. I love painting my curves into the still un-shredded corduroy, and then Veera and me went into the side-country to look for some powder. And powder we found.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619681717/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Fresh Corduroy"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7837/32619681717_97340350c9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fresh Corduroy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619681817/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Untouched snow"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7926/32619681817_95d39fa4c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Untouched snow" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646624275/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Chair lifts galore"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7865/46646624275_60b6b2977c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chair lifts galore" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It really feels amazing to surf through the fluffy snow and throw up big swoops of the white gold. Veera and me both had big smiles on our faces after cruising through the powder-filled forests, so once it was noon we went to <a href="http://www.hankibaari.fi">Hanki Baari</a> for lunch, where I ate a tasty vegan Mie Goreng. Hanki Baari is either way an amazing place to chill after a day on the slopes, listening to music and drinking some fancy beers, though right now we just needed some good nutrition before hitting the slopes again.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619682177/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Vegan Mie Goreng Lunch at Hanki Baari"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7802/32619682177_ce4405d1bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vegan Mie Goreng Lunch at Hanki Baari" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646624635/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ski Pride Ruka Weekend"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7818/46646624635_608e794bd0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Pride Ruka Weekend" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So, after a coffee ☕️ it was time to go ride some more. After all, the sun was shining, the slopes were in prime condition and the lifts would be running till 23 o’clock (Fridays the Ruka Ski Resort’s lifts run so late because those who journey after work to Ruka still can hit the illuminated slopes!). However, we wouldn’t ski that long, as we had another plan.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619683337/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Disembark"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7899/32619683337_d41391c1cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Disembark" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646626385/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Them views"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7813/46646626385_f4b0109446_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Them views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596169873/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="In the Shadows"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7836/40596169873_f159cf0de1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="In the Shadows" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We went on a little powder hunt with friends of Veera, which resulted in a short but exhausting climb through hip-deep snow back to the slopes from the lake 🤣 After that I went for a few more laps on the slopes before calling it a day. A quick shower later I was sitting in the <a href="https://www.pizzeriaruka.fi/en/">Pizzeria Ruka</a> which is probably the best Pizza you can get in Ruka. It’s a five minute stroll from the centre of the village to the Pizzeria, and their wood-fired oven served me in no time a delicious Tartufo Pizza. That’s exactly what I needed after almost six hours of skiing, and gave me enough energy for the hike we had planned for the evening.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596170443/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Pizza"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7810/40596170443_c0d176d536_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pizza" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596170753/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Tasty Slices at Pizzeria Ruka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7845/40596170753_19d235de5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tasty Slices at Pizzeria Ruka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As a <a href="https://www.hendrikmorkel.com">photographer</a> I hate it to spend a gorgeous sunset inside, so I was happy that Veera and her dog were up for a sunset mission to Konttainen, a hill some 10 minutes away from Ruka. A steep 11 minute climb later we were on the top of Konttainen, and strolled towards the best spot in the house while the show was just starting. It’s soooooo much better to be outside in nature when the sun sets than sitting inside, and this definitely was an evening well spent. After the sun disappeared from view we gazed for a while onto the illuminated slopes of Ruka, and for a moment I was tempted to jump back into my <a href="http://bit.ly/2D2JtFL">ski boots</a> and go for some night skiing. But then I remembered my warm Sauna and the cold beer which were waiting for me, so I skipped the night skiing and relaxed in my apartment before calling it a night.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596171763/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Sunset Show just staring"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7817/40596171763_a31c40d077_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset Show just staring" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619686237/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Getting better"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7880/32619686237_1dd76bc6a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Getting better" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619687547/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Excitement is rising"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7851/32619687547_15fce8cfa6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Excitement is rising" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596172983/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Almost there"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7882/40596172983_e03b838190_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Almost there" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596173143/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="And almost down"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7802/40596173143_cec399d4e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And almost down" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619688517/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka&#x27;s Slopes illuminated"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7874/32619688517_26d6af67f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka&#x27;s Slopes illuminated" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning white clouds hung over the mountain and gave the slopes and village a sci-fi feel. I’s the kind of weather where you ponder if you should just stay inside and chill-lax, but as I wanted to get my skis on that didn’t happen and early on Saturday morning Veera and me where again on the slopes, searching for some untracked pockets of powder.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596173853/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Misty Mornings"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7917/40596173853_5b147ff40c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Misty Mornings" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562164731/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Coming from the future"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7851/47562164731_dc69c53e4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Coming from the future" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596174403/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="First lines"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7826/40596174403_e2e0553318_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="First lines" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596174683/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Dystopian Future"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7848/40596174683_8f912da413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dystopian Future" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And slowly but surely the sun was burning through the clouds and as the day progressed the views came out again, and we also were lucky by finding some fine lines of untouched powder not far from the hustle and bustle of the slopes.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646634175/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Views again"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7819/46646634175_d07a221fc4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views again" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596175043/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="POW POW"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7891/40596175043_239e14fdb3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="POW POW" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47509265442/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Maasto"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7876/47509265442_18aae9f36f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Maasto" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After all that off-piste skiing it was time to join the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/ski-pride">Ruka Ski Pride</a> Parade. I really ❤️ that Ruka has this event which celebrates equal rites and diversity on the slopes, and the vibe was so positive and fun - I really enjoyed to be part of it 🌈 Besides this parade there were inclusive events the whole weekend, with concerts and DJs, and of course some good skiing!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685355138/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ski Pride 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7915/33685355138_926a6e9038_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Pride 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685354418/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7841/33685354418_a365919e9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619676697/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7857/32619676697_618d2b6e71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then the day was almost over again. But not before I skied one final time from the East to the West, and from the North to the South across the whole resort. I love to ski fast and go from one end of a resort to the other one, shredding down the slopes and throwing up clouds of slushy spring snow, and at the end of this Saturday my trusty <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/suunto-spartan-ultra-black-multifunktionsuhr/?pid=10239">Suunto Spartan Ultra</a> told me I had skied almost 50 km of distance this day, and I could tell by how my legs felt.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562166431/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Tuntori"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7825/47562166431_77d3603d05_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Tuntori" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562167221/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="SUPER PIPE"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7801/47562167221_1a1b79536c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SUPER PIPE" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46838345644/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="The Ruka Gondola"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7831/46838345644_293ff94e4e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Ruka Gondola" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562152021/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Towards the sun"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7909/47562152021_744e195d9a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Towards the sun" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596162833/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Views for days"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7823/40596162833_a85297ed36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views for days" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After some relaxing I met Mats for Dinner at <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/villisika">Villisika</a> from where you have the best view over the slopes, so while we were eating we could see how the snow groomers got the hill ready for the next day. Sadly, the next sunny day I wouldn’t be shredding the groomers, as I was sitting in the train and bus back south. But I have a feeling that I will travel North once more for more skiing before the winter truly ends ❄️</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562151491/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Tasty Dinner at Villisika"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7814/47562151491_0ff6a3b8e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tasty Dinner at Villisika" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47509251882/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Blueberry Dessert at Villisika"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7841/47509251882_02dd732888_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Blueberry Dessert at Villisika" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As always, there’s more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157707789591555">Photo Album</a>.</p>

<h2 id="spring-skiing-in-ruka">Spring Skiing in Ruka</h2>

<p>As you can see above, winter isn’t over just yet in Finnish Lapland, even if it may feel like it here in the south where most of the snow is already gone. Until early May there’s plenty of great skiing to be had in Northern Finland, and if you’re like me and can not get enough of skiing and winter then you too should steal away for a weekend to Ruka for some spring skiing. The slopes in <a href="https://www.ruka.fi">Ruka</a> are open till early May, and between now and the closing of the slopes there’s every weekend a weekend of fun to be had: Next weekend, from the 11.4. - 14.4.2019 is the legendary <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/spring-break">Ruka Spring Break</a> which will enlighten those who like to Party between hitting the groomers. The <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/easter">Easter Weekend</a> has winter activities for the whole family on offer, and the first of May is the traditional <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/wappulounas">Wappulounas</a>, a get-together of the international snowboard community on the slopes of Ruka. So don’t ponder longer - go and get some of that spring snow!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562152531/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Higher"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7910/47562152531_d8bef744e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Higher" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="where-to-stay">Where to Stay</h2>

<p>I stayed at the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/rukasuites">Ski Inn</a> and liked my apartment in the centre of the village. It was a two minute stroll to the Gondola and lift, a one minute walk to the supermarket, and Hanki Baari was even in the same building so I didn’t had to go far for a beer! There’s plenty more <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/where-to-stay">places to stay in Ruka</a> for any budget, and if you’re pondering where to eat: Just follow my recommendations above or try any of the other restaurants in the village and it’s surroundings.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646624975/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Village Ski-Inn"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7834/46646624975_6c51f4fbd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="650" alt="Ruka Village Ski-Inn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596173453/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="My apartment at the Ski-Inn"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7923/40596173453_1f5d8249d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="My apartment at the Ski-Inn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="getting-to-ruka">Getting to Ruka</h2>

<p>The most convenient way is to take the <a href="http://vr.fi">train</a> and <a href="https://matkahuolto.fi">bus</a> to Ruka, or if you come from abroad you can fly to the <a href="https://www.finavia.fi/en/airports/kuusamo">Kuusamo Airport</a> and take the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/getting-around">Ski Bus</a> to Ruka. On the train you can sleep, work and walk around, and during the bus trip you can enjoy the beautiful Finnish landscape while listening to your favourite tunes.</p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on a Discord Chat with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562151761/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ski Pride Ruka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7814/47562151761_f7e96bc0f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Pride Ruka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Family Skiing in Vuokatti]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/skiing-in-vuokatti.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-22T19:37:57+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/skiing-in-vuokatti</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love winter, skiing and my family. So naturally the best thing is to combine all these things into one week of family fun and head to Vuokatti!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27053282929/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="Vuokatti Ski Slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4542/27053282929_903586e363_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Vuokatti Ski Slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Visit Vuokatti who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="off-to-vuokatti">Off to Vuokatti</h2>

<p>For the third time in a row - after a visit to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">Pyhä</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html">Hetta</a> in the previous years - we packed our winter gear, warm socks and skis and travelled North to experience a proper Finnish winter. Though while in the years before we travelled really far we didn’t want to put that stress on us and our kids of then 1 and 5 years, so after some research we found out about Vuokatti, one of the most snow-secure ski resorts in what we still consider Southern Finland (technically it’s probably the South of Lapland, but lets just say it ain’t as far North as Ylläs, Hetta and Saariselkä). To Vuokatti from Vaasa it are only 400 km which you can drive in a day with some proper planning and keeping the kids entertained, which made it the perfect destination for us. Vuokatti actually is also very easy reached by train and bus, and with many accommodation options being within walking distance of the slopes you can also get around without a car.</p>

<p>Vuokatti is a fantastic destinations for families that want to ski together but don’t want to sit 12 or more hours in the car to get far up North. The <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/Vuokatti-Slopes">13 slopes in Vuokatti</a> are wide &amp; easy, there’s a Fun park with a Halfpipe and some nice big kickers, a Snowboard Tunnel and of course you can rent all the equipment right there so don’t need to travel there with all the gear along. Here’s the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/loader.aspx?id=e3625da0-e490-45b2-a45f-508558f77279">slope map</a> to give you an idea; what I missed is some <em>Lähi offarit</em> - lift-accessible backcountry runs through the forests, but that’s really just a case of getting rid of some trees to make that possible 😜!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39836691081/in/dateposted/" title="Sunny Vuokatti slopes!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4675/39836691081_d8917ae008_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunny Vuokatti slopes!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="lets-go-skiing">Lets go skiing!</h2>

<p>Did I mention that I love skiing? Ah yeah, right there at the beginning 😄. Well, my son learned to ski at age 4 in Levi and enjoyed a short refresher with one of the wonderful ski teachers at the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/Vuokatti-Slopes/Vuokatti-Ski-School">Vuokatti Ski School</a> and then hit the slopes on his own. We decided to not push him and let him go at his own speed, which we found was the right way for us because so he gradually wanted to try bigger &amp; bigger slopes and became more confident skiing them. It’s just beautiful to see your child share the same love for an activity you have yourself, and we are very blessed that our kids love to be outdoors and active as much as we.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804532442/in/dateposted/" title="Vuokatti Slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4677/39804532442_8567e515cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Vuokatti Slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It also was the first time for my wife to stand on Downhill skis, and she too enjoyed the great teaching of the Vuokatti Ski School - which is the 2nd Oldest Ski School in Finland! After a couple of days of being taught the principles of skiing she was skiing down the hills on her own, getting more and more confident and loving the experience. The best thing probably was after that week that she told me <em>“I now understand why you love skiing so much!”</em>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127039344/in/dateposted/" title="Ski School 001"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4651/39127039344_9471592108_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski School 001" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25963527478/in/dateposted/" title="Ski School 004"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4661/25963527478_d85395b83b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski School 004" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057808909/in/dateposted/" title="Ski Sirkus"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/28057808909_16189acf99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Sirkus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057800749/in/dateposted/" title="Ski Carousel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4671/28057800749_f25c3c402a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Carousel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And while there were some really small kids skiing we shared the parenting of our one-year old daughter, and I was taking care of her in the morning while my son &amp; wife were skiing, and then when it was lunch time we ate a small snack at the slopes before the rest of the family went home for naps, playing Lego and relaxing I went skiing. The slopes were for me quite a good training, it was after all only the 2nd season that I stood again on skis after a break of around 16 years! Skiing in a resort is excellent for that, ingraining these movements into ones body and mind. I usually started on one side of the resort and then skied every slope till I reached the other side, where I could step out of the skis and walk with the skis on my shoulder in ten minutes back to our accommodation at the Vuokatti Suites. There’s three main lifts which all bring you all up the slope, with some shorter connecting lifts which help you to get from one end to the other one. <a href="http://www.movescount.com/moves/move148262268">This is how a usual day on the slopes looked</a> according to my Suunto Spartan Ultra.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38937896925/in/dateposted/" title="First down!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4610/38937896925_49699d7595_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="First down!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127057454/in/dateposted/" title="Skiing with my son"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4758/39127057454_b7cc181cac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skiing with my son" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="kids-love-vuokatti">Kids Love Vuokatti!</h2>

<p>After skiing in the mornings we enjoyed family activities in the afternoons, it’s how we roll and really like it. The highlight of the trip for our son was most definitely at the Angry Birds themed <a href="https://superpark.fi/park/vuokatti/">SuperPark Vuokatti</a>, it’s a memory he looks with a smile back to and he regularly comes up to me and says <em>“Dad, we need to go back to the Angry Birds Park, it was so fun!”</em>. It’s memories like these that makes travelling with the family so beautiful, I myself have these kinds of memories of travelling with my parents and siblings, and it just gives kids so much more than some tangible thing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127083144/in/dateposted/" title="Welcome to Angry Birds Park Vuokatti!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4751/39127083144_60eb74128e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Welcome to Angry Birds Park Vuokatti!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127074864/in/dateposted/" title="Slides are fun!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4669/39127074864_ede59200f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slides are fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057824409/in/dateposted/" title="Red!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/28057824409_110ee0b823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Red!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38937888245/in/dateposted/" title="Trying bikes at Angry Birds Park Vuokatti"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/38937888245_47a700a3f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trying bikes at Angry Birds Park Vuokatti" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On another day we went to play bowling at <a href="http://www.vuokattibowling.fi/">Vuokatti Bowling</a>, which is again a memory our son recalls with joy - actually just this morning he told us the scores from our visit at Vuokatti Bowling (Him: 148, my wife: 120, me: 84 😄). The bowling alley in Vuokatti was also really child-friendly, they had a playing room for kids which had large windows which allowed our daughter to play inside but always see us. The staff was friendly and helped me figure out the “complicated” bowling computer (you’d think I’d know these things being a geek!), and the best thing is that the bowling allies are child-friendly as when our son bowled rails went up which prevented the bowling ball going into the gutter. All in all this was a great experience and we might just need to have a visit to a bowling alley with the kids again soon!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804546062/in/dateposted/" title="Vuokatti Bowling"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4718/39804546062_52189d6587_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vuokatti Bowling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then we went one afternoon to the Spa and swimming pools at the <a href="https://www.holidayclubresorts.com/fi/kohteet/katinkulta/kylpyla-ja-hoidot/">Holiday Club Katinkulta</a>. Going to the Spa with the kids is all about sharing the time of who watches the kids when, so that both parents can go in piece to the Sauna, Jacuzzi or swimming. Happily our kids love water and there was both a small kids pool and a slide, which made watching the kids easy &amp; fun. So while one of us was relaxing the other one was taking care of the kids, and after a while we high-fived and switched!</p>

<p>But this isn’t everything! We enjoyed some afternoons just exploring Vuokatti on foot (you can for example drive up the slopes from the other side and walk to the Café on the top!) and walking on the frozen lake in front of the hotel and watching the sunset. You also can go on a <a href="http://www.vuokattisafaris.com/en/tour/husky-safaris/">Husky Safari</a> in Vuokatti, enjoy the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/All-year-round/Skiing">massive XC skiing tracks</a> or check out the Vuokatti Ski tunnel. There’s definitely more than enough options for none-skiing activities in Vuokatti, so just have a look at <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/In-winter">what is possible</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127093244/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking in Vuokatti"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4604/39127093244_7125a940c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking in Vuokatti" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804531052/in/dateposted/" title="Ripa&#x27;s Slope Café"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4712/39804531052_91ac5f6820_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ripa&#x27;s Slope Café" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hungry-heres-where-to-eat-in-vuokatti">Hungry? Here’s where to eat in Vuokatti!</h2>

<p>We loved the breakfast at Vuokatti Suites where we stayed (it was hands-down the best breakfast I have eaten at any Hotel) but we were lucky enough to not needing to cook in the evenings as we went to eat out. Vuokatti gathers to many different tastes, from high-class Menus like we enjoyed at <a href="https://www.sokoshotels.fi/en/vuokatti/sokos-hotel-vuokatti/meetings-and-events/meeting-room?id=466583_392858">Restaurant Kippo</a> and really good and tasty food at <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Services/Vuokatti/Restaurants">À la Katti</a> and <a href="https://vuokattisport.fi/en/ravintolapalvelut/">O’las Restaurant</a> to more basic but good food at <a href="https://olearys.fi/holiday-club-katinkulta/">O’Learys</a>, <a href="https://www.ravintolamessi.fi">Ravintola Messi</a> and <a href="https://www.raflaamo.fi/en/sotkamo/amarillo-vuokatti">Amarillo</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804549022/in/dateposted/" title="Restaurant Kippo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4720/39804549022_1db02d4a9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Restaurant Kippo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804547392/in/dateposted/" title="Starter at Kippo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4667/39804547392_d55553a89c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Starter at Kippo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804528872/in/dateposted/" title="Amarillo Menu"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4745/39804528872_bd92bd9f99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Amarillo Menu" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="would-we-go-again">Would we go again?</h2>

<p>We loved our stay in Vuokatti, and so did the kids. The memories we made as a family are more worth to us than a car, TV or other tangible goods - we try to raise our kids and show them that you spending time with the ones you love is the best use of money &amp; time. It’s thus no surprise that family holidays are high on our list, and a perfect family vacation like we experienced in Vuokatti gives you memories for a lifetime. The small town just had it all: Great slopes for beginner skiers, fun and versatile activities for the afternoons, comfortable accommodation and tasty food. Add in that the people we met in Vuokatti - from the Ski instructors over the Café and Restaurant Staff to everyone else - was super-friendly and great with kids! So to answer the question in the heading: YES! We totally would go again to Vuokatti, and when our daughter is four or five we might need to return so she can learn to ski!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39836691701/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="Learning to love skiing!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4649/39836691701_9f7c2691cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to love skiing!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p>As always, you can find more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157689199140311">Vuokatti Flickr Album</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-stay">Where to stay</h2>

<p>We stayed at <a href="http://www.hotellivuokatti.fi/en/suites">Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites</a> and had a gorgeous Suite with lots of space for us four. Our son had his own room and our daughter slept with us in the big bed, which meant in the evenings we parents could have a glass of wine on the comfortable Sofa and watch a movie on TV (which we can’t do at home as we don’t own a TV!). There was a fully-equipped kitchen in which we prepared our afternoon coffee and evening snacks for the kids, and we had our own Sauna in the Suite which was used almost every evening. The Suite had a drying cabinet which we used to dry moist ski boots, gloves and hats, and the view from the balcony over the lake was beautiful. And if the room was an indication for the whole operation, the breakfast we enjoyed each morning at the main Hotel building was just the best ever. Kids can be tricky with new foods, but at Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites they served everything we’d have at home plus some. The delicious fried eggs, Karelian pastries and lots of <em>fresh</em> fruit made for a good start into a new day, and the coffee was good, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057804579/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Living Room"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4703/28057804579_fa56016097_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Living Room" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057805089/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Own Sauna"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4714/28057805089_8849bb91ae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Own Sauna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804540312/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Ski Storage"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4660/39804540312_53040f1343_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Ski Storage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804533732/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites from the top!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4749/39804533732_2c9760f298_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites from the top!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-there">How to get there</h2>

<p>As I said, you can travel by train &amp; bus to Vuokatti and stay close to the slopes and use the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/loader.aspx?id=643138b3-51fb-405a-a15f-d9e7cee95549">free Vuokatti SkiBus</a> so that a car is not needed. That being said, a (rental) car does make things a bit easier if you come with two kids and ski gear or want to eat in the town in the evenings. From Vaasa it is a 400 km drive to Vuokatti, which takes with breaks in winter around six hours. You also can <a href="https://www.finnair.com/fi/gb/offers?OFFER_ID=62287">fly with Finnair to Kajanni</a> via Helsinki and take the <a href="http://www.akyllonen.fi/airbus/?lang=en">Airport shuttle bus</a> and then use the aforementioned free SkiBus around town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38798598622/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="In the middle, a river"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4538/38798598622_90929ef9cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="In the middle, a river" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hetta: Winter Adventures in Finnish Lapland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html"/>
    <updated>2016-04-04T23:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friendly, calm and lots to do: Hetta in Finnish Lapland is an ideal place if you want to enjoy winter holidays without hustle &amp; bustle. <em>A Winter Trip Report.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26057151772/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Pyhäkero in blue &amp; white 2"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1528/26057151772_de1f89e375_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pyhäkero in blue &amp; white 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="hetta">Hetta</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi">Hetta</a> is in the far, far north of Finland and that means: Lots of snow, crispy cold temperatures, Northern Lights and beautiful sunny days in spring. Last year we spent our winter holiday in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">Pyhä</a> and this year we decided to visit another small and family-friendly town: Hetta. Right in the heart of Lapland it is located at the top of the <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/pallas-yllastunturinp">Pallas-Yllästunturi National Park</a> and the starting point of the <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/hettapallashikingtrail">Hetta-Pallas Trail</a> which you can ski in winter or hike in the summer. <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/poyrisjarvi">Pöyrisjärvi Wilderness Area</a> and <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/tarvantovaara">Tarvantovaara Wilderness Area</a> are right around the corner, and it isn’t far to Norway, either - which makes it an ideal base camp for outdoor and nature lovers in summer &amp; winter.</p>

<p>It has all that a winter enthusiast needs: Cafés &amp; <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/services/restaurants/">Restaurants</a>, various <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/accommodation/">accommodation options</a>, a supermarket and various other shops, the <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/felllaplandvisitorcentre">Fell Lapland Visitor Centre</a> and lots of stuff to do, from skiing on the local hill to enjoying the silence on a Husky Sled ride. With six days in Hetta we had plenty of time to try various <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/things-to-do/winter/">activities</a> and experience what the town has to offer.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546943983/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Sunshine!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1646/25546943983_f5b7a882b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunshine!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outside-with-hetta-huskies">Outside with Hetta Huskies</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.hettahuskies.com/en">Hetta Huskies</a> are probably one of the most well-known companies from Hetta, and if you meet the dogs, owners and Guides it is clear why: The dogs are lovely and will make your trip unforgettable, while the owners Pasi &amp; Anna with their friendly, international staff of Guides will ensure you have a great experience - be it just a few hours or a week!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26122490546/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Hetta Huskies"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1550/26122490546_2d432ac709_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hetta Huskies" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We were with the whole family - my four year old son, baby, wife and me - on the <a href="http://www.hettahuskies.com/en/activities/single-day-safaris">Silent Landscapes</a> Safari, in which you get a tour of the Farm, meet the dogs, get instructed on how to ride the sleigh and then are off into the winter wonderland for around 45 minutes. It’s was a great and interesting experience that we all enjoyed, especially our son thought it was a lot of fun (the baby slept!). We were accompanied by a guide who stayed mostly away but helped when the need arose - we had a small change in the configuration of dogs, for example. After I got instructed in riding the sleigh the family sat down and then we were off to the mires. I always love to explore swamps in winter, their vast area and wide views are beautiful to behold and in winter you can explore them without mosquitos and wet feet. We could see the distant fjells of the National Park, rode through the forest and loved the silence of nature. We could have gone much longer - and the dogs, too! - but after 45 minutes we were back at the farm where we helped bringing the dogs back to their compounds and said thanks for their great service!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25545774183/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Hi there!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1624/25545774183_6423523d01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hi there!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26148429495/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1490/26148429495_885653ee53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mom, dad, kids and seven huskies!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25875556930/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Through the forest"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1490/25875556930_ccd9bde31b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Through the forest" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25875557260/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Hi there again!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1646/25875557260_aa5aa4d111_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hi there again!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="a-visit-to-the-hetta-snow-castle">A visit to the Hetta Snow Castle</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nakkala.com">Näkkälä Eräpalvelut</a> offers visits to their Snow Castle which is a short 20 minute snowmobile ride over the frozen lake away from Hetta. The castle is open from the end of November and still stands there in the end of June and with walls several meters thick that’s no surprise! The kids loved it and it is easy to understand why they were fascinated by the ice castle: Consisting of three domed rooms they were adorned with ice sculptures, an ice bar and tables as well as a frozen bed! You can sleep in the ice castle, too! After exploring the snow castle for a while we had hot juice and then it was again back to Hetta in the sleigh. A great activity for the morning or afternoon after which you might find yourself again outside trying to build your own snow igloo!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26082084491/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Entering the Hetta Ice Castle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1588/26082084491_3c4f638e8e_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Entering the Hetta Ice Castle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26082084791/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="At the Bar in the Hetta Ice Castle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1466/26082084791_1836e001fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the Bar in the Hetta Ice Castle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25543654324/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Cold as ice!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1512/25543654324_9b04cb2c86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cold as ice!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26082086091/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="The Hetta Ice Castle"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1539/26082086091_c298c5a23f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Hetta Ice Castle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25875554680/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Back to Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1566/25875554680_fbdf050119_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back to Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="skiing-at-hetta-hiihtomaa">Skiing at Hetta Hiihtomaa</h2>

<p>If you <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">follow me on Instagram</a> you probably have realized that I have been ski-touring a lot this winter. <a href="http://www.hettahiihtomaa.fi">Hetta Hiihtomaa</a> is the local skiing hill and we took the chance for our son to learn a bit of skiing and I too took a ride in the lift up to go down through the snow-covered forest. The service at Hetta Hiihtomaa was superb, the two Gentlemen were super-friendly and helpful with <a href="http://www.hettahiihtomaa.fi/p/valinevuokraus.html">loaning the gear</a> and sharing local knowledge. Besides the lift and ski-rental there’s also a Café, a big sledding hill and a illuminated XC Loipe. The prizes are very affordable when compared to the large ski areas, and the people and kids all had a lot of fun on the slopes or off-piste. Hetta Hiihtomaa has also a small beginner’s hill which is excellent for learning to ski, and I can totally recommend the sledding hill, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25486428803/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Learning to ski at Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1654/25486428803_d47754d6f9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to ski at Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25816133670/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Backcountry fun on Jyppyrä, Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1675/25816133670_564e5094cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Backcountry fun on Jyppyrä, Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26022665581/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Sledding fun at Hetta Hiihtomaa"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1526/26022665581_f882f141b8_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Sledding fun at Hetta Hiihtomaa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="ski-touring-into-the-white--out-at-nkklvaara">Ski-touring into the White (-Out) at Näkkälävaara</h2>

<p>What I like more than skiing at a resort is going into the backcountry, and I was fortunate enough to go out for a morning with Riikka from <a href="http://www.wildriver.fi">Wild River Nature Adventures</a>. We decided it’d be a good idea to go to Näkkälä, a tiny village some 30 minutes from Hetta, where we’d tour up to the local fjell, Näkkälävaara. It’s an easy tour with a really cool descent through a birch forest and I had a huge smile on my face after the cool run down!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546895203/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Yay!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1464/25546895203_30c25d623d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yay!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25544790224/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Snowhare vs Skis"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1593/25544790224_06566ed3f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snowhare vs Skis" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546918523/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Never trust the weather forecast"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1605/25546918523_63fb03b0c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Never trust the weather forecast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We started next to one of the few houses and then toured over a narrow lake to the foot of the fjell. It was a cold day and a mist was hanging in the air, which would before long engulf us as we started the climb up the hill. The visibility was soon just a couple dozen metre, and first as we were starting the descent the weather cleared a bit to give a few views price. Nevertheless it was beautiful to tour through the white landscape, with trees hidden under thick covers of snow &amp; ice, arctic hare tracks running across the hill and the wind being the only sound wide &amp; far. At the summit we waited for half an hour for the weather to clear, as you could see till Pyhäkero to the south and the mountains in Norway to the north, as well as the large Pöyrisjärvi lake. Alas, they stayed all hidden!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25546929473/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Winter birch forest"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1520/25546929473_13dc3a1b94_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Winter birch forest" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26057122202/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Fun, fun, fun!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1564/26057122202_1e546f6369_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Fun, fun, fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the superb descent we skied along the lake, past the rental cabins of <a href="http://www.nakkala.com/kampat/">Näkkälä Eräpalvelut</a> and to a sacred rock of the Sami, which showed ancient reindeer paintings. Too soon we were back at the car and on our way back to Hetta, where we encountered many reindeer next to the road - and the sun also came out! There’s plenty of great ski-touring around Hetta, from the majestic Pyhäkero to smaller fjells in the area. Grab a map and go out explore!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26083255541/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Drawings"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1601/26083255541_e5e4bc0b53_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Drawings" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26123653876/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Reindeers"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1482/26123653876_3da37f61cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reindeers" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="tasty-lappish-food">Tasty Lappish food</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.hetan-majatalo.fi/en">Hotel Hetan Majatalo</a> has every Friday a Lappish Buffet which is super-tasty. Reindeer, salmon, mashed potatoes and a tasty dessert along with a great home-brewed beer it is something you should treat yourself to.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26205517916/in/dateposted/" title="Lappish Buffet at Hetan Majatalo"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1535/26205517916_286bf7a114_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lappish Buffet at Hetan Majatalo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25626691604/in/dateposted/" title="Dessert at Hetan Majatalo"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1460/25626691604_e84413b6a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dessert at Hetan Majatalo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Also the buffet at the Lapland Hotel Hetta was very tasty, with a wide variety of salads for startes, wish and meat mains and several sweet desserts. Add in a good selection of wines and beers with great service and you have a great evening!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26063083516/in/dateposted/" title="Salad buffet at Lapland Hotel Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1497/26063083516_065d21ef59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salad buffet at Lapland Hotel Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484255534/in/photostream/" title="Main course at Lapland Hotel Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1609/25484255534_00e25051e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Main course at Lapland Hotel Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="enjoying-the-silence-of-xc-skiing">Enjoying the silence of XC skiing</h2>

<p>As we stayed in a cottage next to the lake and there’s around 100 km of skiing tracks (here’s the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/wp-content/uploads/Hetan-alueen-latukartta.pdf">map</a>) going XC skiing is something that you can do any time of the day - even at night, as there’s illuminated tracks, too! I took my son in a Pulka for a few hours of skiing along, which is a great way to be outdoors. XC skiing is relatively easy, you go at a low speed and thus still can experience the nature around you but it’s fast enough to feel good after a few hours outside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26165151521/in/dateposted/" title="XC Skiing with kids"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1570/26165151521_0a3b0f0504_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="XC Skiing with kids" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25628771613/in/dateposted/" title="Skiing to Hetta across the lake"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1493/25628771613_48dbeaf9c2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skiing to Hetta across the lake" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="learning-about-sami-culture-at-the-fell-lapland-visitor-centre">Learning about Sami Culture at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre</h2>

<p>If the weather is so bad that you don’t want to be outside, head to the wonderful <a href="http://www.nationalparks.fi/en/felllaplandvisitorcentre">Fell Lapland Visitor Centre</a>. It’s open every day of the week, has also a Café with tasty cakes and pastries and the exhibitions are free of charge - hence an ideal way to spend an afternoon. There’s even a very nice children’s corner which our son enjoyed playing at! The main exhibition shows the eight seasons of the Sámi and how their life has changed over the time. To take it all in a couple of hours would be needed I reckon, though it is easy to spend even more time there to also explore the small library and the two other exhibitions.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25996473812/in/dateposted/" title="Tunturi-Lappi Luontokeskus"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1709/25996473812_9c603c6ec6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tunturi-Lappi Luontokeskus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26089003635/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1704/26089003635_69d533bf44_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484241564/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 2"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1540/25484241564_7906a223df_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25484242434/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 3"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1552/25484242434_6eaf72deff_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26063074576/in/dateposted/" title="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 7"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1624/26063074576_635461a3cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sami exhibition at the Fell Lapland Visitor Centre 7" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="more-things-to-see--do">More things to see &amp; do</h2>

<p>Hetta has many other things to offer, from festivals like the Nordic Ice &amp; Snow Sculpture competition at the end of February over regular Nature evenings in the Museum to the <a href="http://saamiskirace.fi">Saami Ski Race</a> in April. You can view the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/events/">events</a> here. There’s also two silver smiths in Hetta which are worth checking out and a church which is architecturally interesting. It’s not far to Kilpisjärvi, either, or you could go for a day trip over to Alta in Norway. If you’re looking for a few days in nature you could ski from Pallas to Hetta through the fjells (or vice versa) and you even can ski onwards to Näkkälä.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25816138370/in/album-72157665518007630/" title="Swan snow sculpture in Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1582/25816138370_0439531fd8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Swan snow sculpture in Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p>More photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157665518007630">Hetta Photo Album</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Where to stay?</strong></p>

<p>We stayed at the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/ounistieva-en/">Ounistieva Cottage</a> which is a nice cottage a bit out of town right next to the lake. It’s a self-service cottage with a nice wood-heated sauna, a warm wood stove and you can go XC skiing from the doorstep, which is awesome. Cottages are great for families as you can be as loud as you want, the kids can play safely outside in the snow and there’s plenty of space inside. If you prefer something more central then we can recommend the <a href="http://www.hetan-majatalo.fi">Hotel Hetan Majatalo</a> and the <a href="https://www.laplandhotels.com/EN/hotels-in-lapland/hetta/lapland-hotel-hetta.html">Lapland Hotel Hetta</a> which are close to the centre of town and also have their own Restaurants with great food. Their rooms, especially in the Hetan Majatalo, are very cozy and it’s nice to have breakfast &amp; dinner served each evening. There’s several more <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi/en/accommodation/">accommodation options in Hetta</a> for every budget, so have a look around and find what suits you!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26205520136/in/dateposted/" title="Ounistieva Cottage"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1617/26205520136_1638186cfb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ounistieva Cottage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How to get there?</strong></p>

<p>We travelled with a combination of <a href="https://www.vr.fi/cs/vr/fi/etusivu">train</a> and <a href="https://www.sixt.fi">car</a> instead of driving all the way up north, with a night in Rovaniemi on the way up and down - if you have small kids it is more comfortable this way, for everyone really. In the train the kids can play, nap and go easily to the toilet, and the ride from Rovaniemi to Hetta takes only around four hours by car - much better than the 12+ hours of driving it would take from Vaasa! And if you come from abroad - just fly straight to <a href="https://www.finavia.fi/en/enontekio/">Enontekiö Airport</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26063067296/in/dateposted/" title="Rush-hour in Hetta"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1467/26063067296_97c0b28cc2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rush-hour in Hetta" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: Thanks to the <a href="http://www.tosilappi.fi">Enontekiö Region</a> who invited us up north. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="http://www.outdoorbloggercodex.com/en/?noredirect=en_US">Outdoor Blogger Codex</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pirkan Taival Travel Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/03/pirkan-taival-travel-guide.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-17T10:22:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/03/pirkan-taival-travel-guide</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Where to go backpacking this year?</em>, it’s the same question each spring. I have for five years being advocating hiking in Finland, and since last year you can now take my <a href="http://www.conrad-stein-verlag.de/p/verlag/show_book.html?isbn=978-3-86686-319-4&amp;edition=1&amp;t=1395048047963">Pirkan Taival Hiking Guide</a> along on your trip on this wonderful trail in the heart of Finland. Reason enough to introduce you to the book and encourage you to come backpacking on the Pirkan Taival!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9537611324/" title="Dusk by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7312/9537611324_1787dd85ec_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dusk" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Writing a book, even a little one like my Pirkan Taival Travel Guide, is a lot of work. First there’s the hiking and collecting data: 300 km of trails were hiked several times, XC skiing trails were explored in the winter, and I went off-trail over frozen lakes with snowshoes and through blooming forests to find the best spots and areas to showcase in the book. After all that outdoors time it’s time to distill it all into a smart format, organize maps, work with the local authorities, find photos from my extensive library, and then put it into a logical whole.</p>

<p>However, I was lucky that I didn’t need to take care of the layout, printing, and drawing maps - that’s what the fabulous team from the <a href="http://www.conrad-stein-verlag.de/p/verlag/verlag_home.html">Conrad Stein Verlag</a> took care off, who is my Publisher. They got the book looking really great and into the book stores across Germany, Austria and Switzerland, from <a href="http://www.freytagberndt.at/rtc-freytagberndt/805">Freytag &amp; Berndt</a> to the <a href="http://geobuchhandlung.eshop.t-online.de/epages/Store3_Shop37170.sf/de_DE/?ObjectID=15498754">Geobuchhandlung Kiel</a> and <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/conrad-stein-finnland-pirkan-taival/">Bergzeit</a> - walk into any of the thousands of book stores in Germany and you can either pick up the book right away or get it the next day.</p>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/Y9r5yz" title="Finnland: Pirkan Taival book by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5514/9156957955_7af63cca08_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Finnland: Pirkan Taival book" /></a></p>

<p>For me it was a great pleasure to go hiking on the Pirkan Taival and write about it: I often was accompanied by good friends and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/guided-trips/">clients</a> on the trail with whom I could share my love of the outdoors. I saw the trail in each season - in early spring I was hiking through knee-deep snow, on dark and rainy autumns I listend to the rain on my tarp, during sunny summer nights the call of Swans was echoing over the lakes and sitting besides a warm fire in winter. With the book you’re able to plan and hike the Pirkan Taival yourself in any season, and see all those beautiful places along the trail. It’s easy to reach by public transportation, and you can be within half a working day from your door step to the start of the trail in Finland, which makes it excellent for even just a long weekend hike if you need a Nordic outdoor-fix.</p>

<p>But don’t just believe me: Hear <a href="http://outdoorseite.de/trekking-in-finnland-mit-hendrik-durch-den-pirkan-taival/">what Axel has to say about my book</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.de/product-reviews/3866863195/ref=dp_top_cm_cr_acr_txt?ie=UTF8&amp;showViewpoints=1">read the reviews</a>, then <a href="http://www.trekkingmagazin.com/touren/pirkan-taival-erholung-pur-im-suden-finnlands">read my trekking Magazin article</a> and browse my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/destinations/">trip reports</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Then</strong> you can go and get the book from your local book shop in Austria, Switzerland and Germany, online from <a href="http://www.freytagberndt.at/rtc-freytagberndt/805">Freytag &amp; Berndt</a>, <a href="http://geobuchhandlung.eshop.t-online.de/epages/Store3_Shop37170.sf/de_DE/?ObjectID=15498754">Geobuchhandlung Kiel</a>, <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/conrad-stein-finnland-pirkan-taival/">Bergzeit</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/Y9r5yz">Amazon.de</a> or directly from the <a href="http://www.conrad-stein-verlag.de/p/verlag/show_book.html?isbn=978-3-86686-319-4&amp;edition=1&amp;t=1395048047963">Conrad Stein Verlag</a>.</p>

<p><em>The book is in German! I might write an English or Finnish version in the future =)</em></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8147054635/" title="Tampere"><img src="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8468/8147054635_b8c6085a5f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tampere" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
