<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cycling | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/cycling/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-07-01T14:14:31+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[woom Bikes - because also kids deserve great Bikes!]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/07/woom-bikes-because-also-kids-deserve-great-bikes.html"/>
    <updated>2019-07-31T14:03:31+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/07/woom-bikes-because-also-kids-deserve-great-bikes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How do you ensure that your child likes to ride its bike, come rain, sunshine or snow? In our opinion it’s by giving it a bike which it likes and which works well throughout the seasons!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421710247/in/photostream/" title="Speeding up on the woom 5"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421710247_34bc7ced8a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Speeding up on the woom 5" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>The woom Bike was provided for free to us for this review. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>That we are a family which ride their bikes year-round I <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">wrote earlier this year</a>, and now I want to shed a bit of light on the latest addition to our bike shed: The <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/5?ls=en">woom 5</a>. woom makes bikes exclusively for kids, and that you can see in their products: They are made for the needs of kids, and not just some fancy, miniaturised version of an adult bike. The woom bikes are light, safe for the rider and safe in traffic, and there’s a host of functional and pretty accessories available for the bike. That they do it for kids you can see for yourself when you have a woom bike in front of you, as around 85% of their bike parts are individually designed and produced exclusively for woom, customized to fit the needs of small anatomies.</p>

<p>Now we have owned several non-woom bikes for our kids before we made the switch, and I have done plenty of research on the topic, too. One thing you’ll read in review after review is that the lighter a kids bike is, the better it is for the child. From our own experience with some very cheap kids bikes which were heavy as two bags of cement we can confirm: The lighter the bike, the more fun the rider has. woom bikes are around 40% lighter than comparable kids bikes, so as an ultralight backpacker this is obvious very positive, too. But enough about facts and stats, lets dive in to our subjective observations of riding the bike for almost three months.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421564311/in/dateposted/" title="Riding is fun!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421564311_d2e930696c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Riding is fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421736537/in/dateposted/" title="At the Beach"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421736537_691a52b43b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="At the Beach" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now our son was already riding a woom 4 which he and we loved, but the one thing which became obvious as time went on was that the bike got too small for him. The <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/4?ls=en#section-product">woom 4</a> is made for kids between a height of 115 and 130 cm, though realistically I’d say that after 125 cm one should switch to the bigger bike. The woom 5 is made for kids between a height of 125 and 145 cm, and for our son it’s right now the perfect bike. Where in the past I had to say several times on a trip “Please cycle faster!” nowadays, since he’s on the woom 5, I have to ask him to slow down. He’s soooo fast on the new bike that he really likes to challenge us to races, and often enough wins! Thanks to the adjustable seat post and the vario stem the bike grows with him, and we hope that he’ll be able to ride this bike for a year or two (and that simply depends on how fast he grows!).</p>

<p>Going fast also means he needs to brake, and the the V-Brakes on the bike are so good that it takes little effort for him to stop safely. The SRAM X4 8-speed derailleur and the easy grip shift make switching gears easy as pie when we go up hills or ride into the wind, and the tires it comes with have a low rolling resistance and great grip from asphalt to single track trails and gravel roads. The Geometry also is great, because he can easily get on and off the bike and if he wants to stand on his feet, for example when taking in a view or waiting at a stop light, the top tube is at a friendly height.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421563356/in/dateposted/" title="Exploring"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421563356_53ecf3db20_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Exploring" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421564006/in/dateposted/" title="Should we stop for coffee and waffles?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421564006_82cd350310_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Should we stop for coffee and waffles?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421712272/in/dateposted/" title="Taking in the view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421712272_7780173572_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Taking in the view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Just a few words on assembling the bike before we wrap up this review. The bike is delivered in a 120 x 62 x 22 cm box and weighs around 10 kg (the bike itself is 8,2 kg light), and it comes with all the tools you need to assemble the bike. You can add a host of useful accessories to the bike, from the mandatory <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/schutzbleche?ls=en">Fenders</a> (which I yet have to install!) over the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-kickstand-2018?ls=en">Kickstand</a> to the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/vienna-bell?ls=en">bell</a>. We also got a Size L <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-helmet?ls=en">woom Helmet</a> in the same colour as his bike, and while the previous helmet had some shortcomings we hope this one will survive the next Finnish winter. It is, other than the problem with the extreme cold, a great helmet which is well ventilated, easy to adjust and our son can open and close it easily thanks to the magnetic buckle closure.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421712507/in/dateposted/" title="woom Helmet &#x3D; Safe Head"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421712507_3d2e6f5f6f_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="woom Helmet &#x3D; Safe Head" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421711987/in/dateposted/" title="Single Trail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421711987_d9a7b32f9b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Single Trail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All in all our son and us are very happy with the latest addition to our bike shed. He enjoys cycling now even more (as he can go so fast) and a lot of his friends have come up to him and wanted to ride his cool bike. I keep on repeating myself, but he cycles fast thanks to the bigger tires and the correct size for his height, and I think we’ll try to squeeze in some bike trips before winter is coming as he seems to be able to easily ride 40 km a day with some ice cream and Pulla breaks in-between. I also intend to go ride some easy single trails with him here in Vaasa, as he has enjoyed the short bits where we were riding in the forests a lot.</p>

<p>So to sum things up, if you want that your child enjoys cycling then the best thing you can do is get them a bike which makes them want to ride. The <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/5?ls=en">woom 5</a> definitely is such a bike for our son, as he loves to ride (fast!) on it, be it to school, to the beach or the ice cream parlour. The bike is safe, handles really well, is specially made for kids with great attention to details and easy to maintain for me. We are looking forward to many more rides together, both in town and on trails!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421562801/in/dateposted/" title="A small break"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421562801_629c19ca1e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="A small break" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Car, No Problem: Urban Family Transportation]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html"/>
    <updated>2019-03-29T21:05:38+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/urban-family-transportation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Riding bikes is fun and healthy. Too bad too many people drive cars in our cities. <strong>Cars don’t belong in cities</strong> is a thought which we share in our family. Cars have their place, but for both humans and the environment, and also the aesthetics of our towns, it would be best if most of us would cycle to the grocery store, work and the cinema. That that is possible I want to show you in this article.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47434099322/in/dateposted/" title="Family cycling"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7888/47434099322_30dc75ef70_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Family cycling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>Some of the products in this article have been provided to us by the manufacturers. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>

<p>I admit that <strong>#FuckCarsRideBikes</strong> is probably the best Hashtag I have invented. I dislike cars as they illustrate what is wrong with our cities &amp; towns: Everywhere we have multi-lane streets so that thousands of people who sit <em>alone</em> in their car can drive from A to B. What’s wrong about this is that the distances these people drive <strong>ALONE</strong> in their cars is statistically less than 5 km, or the distance which most of the readers of this blog hike in an hour in the hills or would be able to ride on a bike in 20 to 30 minutes. Add in that nowadays seemingly every other car driver is distracted while checking his or her phone, our ageing societies mean that there are more people who are physically less able to drive <strong>safely</strong>, and the emissions from cars which are bad for our health and you start to realize that we need to get rid of the majority of cars in cities and towns. That that is possible and that one can thrive without a car and <strong>get everything done</strong> is what I want to show today, and hopefully encourage you to ride more on your bike and drive less in your car.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610376678/in/dateposted/" title="Jkl Uni"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7915/33610376678_b349aec085_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jkl Uni" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-from-a-to-b">How to get from A to B</h2>

<p>The kids have hobbies, need to be brought to school and kindergarden, there’s the occasional thing to pick up at the post office and groceries for cooking at home also need to be bought and brought home. Add in a visit to the cinema, going for lunch with colleagues, <a href="https://youtu.be/v0ae-3BQzFM">playing games with friends</a>, swimming at the beach and oh, yeah, showing up at the office for work is also smart. <strong>Can one <em>REALLY</em> do all that by bike?</strong> Well, yes 😊</p>

<p>Statistically most people use their cars for journeys of three to five kilometre in length, which if you think about it, is insane. I ride with my kids, with the trailer behind me and my son on his own bike, in 15 minutes to the centre of Vaasa, which is about three kilometre away from our house. Pretty much all of it is on cycling lanes, and in the centre there’s dozens of parking places for bikes so one never needs to ponder “Where do I park?”. It’s also free! If the weather is poor hardshells come on - living in a coastal town (= lots of wind, 🌬💨 all the time) means we are used to wearing a <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/windproof-jackets/?pid=10239">wind jacket</a> when we go outside - and when you arrive at the Café, Restaurant or school you take it off. No problem!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571687275/in/dateposted/" title="Parking for bikes"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7865/46571687275_0d5cbf2101_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Parking for bikes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This is not some kind of magic that only we can achieve. Most people have very short commutes and can do all of it by riding a bike, and did I mention that being on a bike is healthy and fun? I at least always feel very happy when I can ride my bike. I think the biggest hurdle to those who drive with a car everywhere is that they think that they can not cycle. The truth is - if you have learned to ride a bike, and own a bike, then you can bicycle. No one is expecting you to win the <a href="https://www.transcontinental.cc">Transcontinental Race</a> or going <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/10/active-holidays-in-are-sweden.html">Downhill mountain biking</a> but you likely just want go to the Café or to the beach. You also don’t need to sell your car and go all in, but gradually try what you all can do by bike. Cycle to work two days a week, instead of taking the car to the gym take the bike to go grocery shopping, and if you want to go out and meet friends why not go cycle to that lovely Café instead of taking the car? If you slowly phase out the use of a car you’ll see that going by bike everywhere is easy - and not just for adults, also kids love to ride their bike. The smile my 3 year old daughter gives me when we cycle together is amazing, and while this obviously only are short distances like going to the Kindergarden, the playground and the library bus, it still allows her to get used to cycling. For longer distances she sits in the Thule Chariot, which is also great to transport stuff. And if it doesn’t fit on the bike or in the trailer I take the bus or use a Taxi. By not owning a car we save a minimum of 400€ per month on car-related expenses, and that are even in Finland quite a few Taxi rides.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614273578/in/dateposted/" title="Happy Cycler"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7926/33614273578_e6c06abdf3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happy Cycler" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bikes">The Bikes</h2>

<p>Now I have been talking so much about our bikes - time to take a look at them! I have written before about my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Pelago Stavanger</a> which I am now riding since five years. I bought for my wife some years ago a <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com/bicycles/airisto-commuter.html">Pelago Airisto</a> which she loves, and with both of these bikes we can pull the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/thule-chariot-cross2-kinderanhaenger/?pid=10239">Thule Chariot 2</a> where our daughter sits and rides with us. The Airisto is a fantastic bike and I got my wife the front basket as it makes transporting things so much easier. The Airisto also performs well for bike tours - we cycled for a week on Åland with these bikes and had a lot of fun.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40520962753/in/dateposted/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7922/40520962753_23798cdaea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571688285/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7917/46571688285_5aa533fa0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Our son is on his fourth bike, and since about a year he is riding the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/4?ls=en">woom 4 children’s bike</a> which has been his best bike to date. It’s not just light and grew with him, it also has 8 gears which made cycling up hills and in winter a lot easier. The bike handles very well (especially if compared to his older bikes) and it’s a pleasure to see him ride his bike proudly and having fun. A good bike which is the right size and easy to use makes all the difference in getting a child being willing to ride a bike year-around, from spring till winter, and the woom 4 certainly has made it easier for us parents to go cycling together - because the bike works flawlessly. We also have cycled some longer rides around Vaasa with him, and thanks to his woom bike he’s able to cycle up to 20 km without a problem.</p>

<p>Our son is wearing the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-helmet?ls=en">woom Helmet</a> which is good, though it’s not really made for the cold weather of Finland and the width adjustment knob broke in the middle of winter - we have been using the Helmet now in the max. size, which is either way what we needed. It’s a light and well-ventilated helmet and stands up to daily use. Similarly the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-radlicht">woom bike lights</a> had a battery which had problems coping with the Finnish winter, it only worked on a charge for a day or two max and then needed recharging, though I imagine this is not a problem in warmer climates. And we also got the easy to use <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-radschloss?ls=en">woom chain lock</a>. You can put in your own code (and can change it easily, too) so that way the bike can always be securely locked when at school or in town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571691295/in/dateposted/" title="woom 4"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7865/46571691295_12bb9d92f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom 4" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571691555/in/dateposted/" title="Summer cycling in Vaasa"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7814/46571691555_271e76e918_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Summer cycling in Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47434095572/in/dateposted/" title="woom 4 + woom Helmet"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7916/47434095572_a59a09ed9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="woom 4 + woom Helmet" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Thule Chariot 2 is an amazing trailer and honestly the most important piece of cycling gear for a family with small kids which wants to rely less on the car. The <a href="http://bit.ly/2FxaMIU">Chariot 2</a> has allowed us to transport both kids at the same time when they were younger, we can use it to transport large packages and it makes grocery shopping a breeze as you can fit a child and the groceries for a week in it with room to spare. We also have travelled with the bikes and the trailer on <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/cycling-and-bouldering-on-aland.html">Åland</a> which was an amazing trip which combined the bikes, train and ferry for a lovely week of cycling in the Archipelago. The Thule Chariot also has flown with us when the kids were smaller, as it can be converted into a pram in one minute (or a sled if there’s enough snow!). This really is an amazing piece of equipment which is integral to our family not having a car, and I can foresee that even when our 3-year old daughter is old enough to cycle herself that we might keep the trailer for a while as it is so damn easy to transport large things with it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47434099002/in/dateposted/" title="Thule Chariot 2 Transporter"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7863/47434099002_f54316e494_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Thule Chariot 2 Transporter" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571689175/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7800/46571689175_b8ac2a62d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610375218/in/dateposted/" title="Family cycling in Vaasa"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7896/33610375218_358a20220e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Family cycling in Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614272628/in/dateposted/" title="Cycle Touring on Åland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7828/33614272628_29bff33595_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cycle Touring on Åland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46768405674/in/dateposted/" title="Thule Chariot 2 in the rain"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7857/46768405674_b0f7f378fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Thule Chariot 2 in the rain" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Speaking of transporting, my <a href="https://www.trekbikes.com/us/en_US/bikes/adventure-touring-bikes/920/920/p/21996/">Trek 920 Disc</a> has been an amazing bike for both transporting, urban commutes, fun rides and adventures. I can transport an unreasonable amount of stuff on it thanks to the two racks, and especially the front rack is one of the best things on a bike, ever (<em>Seriously, if there’s one thing you should get for your bike it is a front rack!</em>). I love this bike and even more after I made it <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/08/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit.html">tubeless</a> two years ago. If it would allow me to pull the Thule Chariot I probably would own only this one bike.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40524987693/in/dateposted/" title="Trek 920 All loaded up"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7886/40524987693_3f0f1a2faa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trek 920 All loaded up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571686395/in/dateposted/" title="Cockpit view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7897/46571686395_eb521756db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cockpit view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As we are a family and we have to transport kids, groceries and parcels every now and then, I think you understand why we are dreaming of a Cargobike. <a href="https://www.bakfiets.nl">There’s</a> <a href="http://www.larryvsharry.com">just</a> <a href="https://yubabikes.com">too</a> <a href="https://sblocs.bike">many</a> <a href="http://www.workcycles.com">options</a> and they’re also all a bit pricey, but maybe in the future we will change from the Thule Chariot to a Cargobike for transporting…</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115659892/in/album-72157665520832018/" title="SBlocs Cargo Bike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4720/40115659892_5b5a2abb36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="806" alt="SBlocs Cargo Bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s the kick bike which our kids used when they were small. We had a <a href="https://www.puky.de/en/home">Puky</a> kick bike for both kids, and our daughter has been riding it since she was 1,5 years old. It’s something she really enjoys a lot and she is pretty good at it, and when we go to the playground, for a walk or to the library bus she takes the kick bike as that way the longer distances are no problem for her.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610373888/in/photostream/" title="Loving to bike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7836/33610373888_00e0ca4350_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Loving to bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610374408/in/dateposted/" title="Learning to bike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7892/33610374408_d270d6610c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="come-rain-come-sunshine-we-ride">Come Rain, come Sunshine, we Ride</h2>

<p>Riding our bikes in any weather - from damn slippery roads to the rain and hot 30°C days - needs a little planning garment-wise, though as you’re likely a backpacker or skier you have everything you need to ride in any climate. We just use our hiking garments for cycling, the most important thing is that they have a good freedom of movement. A wind or rain jacket and a rain pants are needed in foul weather, while in the summer we cycle in shorts and T-shirts. My wife and kids use a Helmet while I only use one on long bike rides - because <a href="https://www.bicycling.com/news/a24110027/bike-helmet-safety/">it’s OK to not wear a helmet</a>, as bicycle lanes make cycling safe and not a helmet. <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/gloves/recommended-use--cycling/?pid=10239">Windproof gloves</a> make sure your hands don’t freeze solid (they’re also recommended in windy summers as warm hands make cycling a lot more fun).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614272908/in/dateposted/" title="Rocking the Puky Kickbike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7856/33614272908_075dbb2416_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rocking the Puky Kickbike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That’s really it what ones need to transporting oneself from A to B by bicycle - yes there’s lots of fancy things one can add to the bike but a basic bike, some gloves, maybe a helmet and depending on the weather a wind or rain jacket are all that is needed. In the future I’ll write more about useful accessories for cycling, but that’s not the focus of this post!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40524988183/in/dateposted/" title="Cycling to go skiing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7863/40524988183_1c28c90e01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cycling to go skiing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614273378/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Stavanger Cockpit"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7862/33614273378_ebbb6f6882_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Stavanger Cockpit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="cant-do-without-car">Can’t do without car?</h2>

<p>If you can not be without a car - because you actually life far away from civilization - I would encourage you to at least not drive alone. Share a car with a neighbour or two, drive together, make less trips and if your car is old get a car which is fuel-efficient or is an electric car. Generally, sharing the car and driving together makes the use of a motorized vehicle more acceptable. Alternatively you could try a e-Bike as these allow you to go a bit faster and further without too much of your own muscle power, or have a look at something like the <a href="https://www.arcimoto.com">Arcimoto</a> if it needs to be a vehicle.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23170406440/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Cabo da Roca"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/5701/23170406440_011dc7899e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cabo da Roca" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="go-ride-your-bike">Go Ride Your Bike!</h2>

<p>I hope you see it is easy, fun and healthy to not drive everywhere in a car and that using the bike for transportation in an urban environment makes a lot of sense. There’s no searching for a parking spot, you don’t need to go to the gym, you’re outside at the fresh air and are having fun. Having good bikes for the kids and getting them used from an early age to cycling helps to instil a happiness to bicycle everywhere in them, and also makes them more independent as you as a parent don’t need to drive them everywhere. So in conclusion I hope that you now, with the beginning of spring, try to cycle more! After all - it’s fun, healthy and allows you to be more outside, and isn’t that what we all enjoy the most?!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40524987853/in/dateposted/" title="Spring Races"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7902/40524987853_2430810228_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Spring Races" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614272478/in/dateposted/" title="Åland scenary"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7877/33614272478_4dbe015350_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Åland scenary" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How-to go Tubeless]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/08/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit.html"/>
    <updated>2017-08-08T19:00:59+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/08/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tired of punctures &amp; flat tires? Go Tubeless and don’t worry about them anymore. In this article I show how you can convert your bike to tubeless tires with the help of the Schwalbe Tubeless Easy Kit, your one stop solution with everything you need to go Tubeless.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35603377424/in/dateposted/" title="The Gear needed"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4385/35603377424_4229d4b0d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="The Gear needed" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>Schwalbe has provided me the Tires, Tire Booster and Tubeless Easy Kit for free for this article. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>Flat tires on 29” wheels, they where common for me back with my old 29er. Happily I started to drive more careful and punctures have been rare in the last several years, but as I welcomed the Trek 920 Disc to the family I decided I wanted to ride it Tubeless. There where some good reasons for that:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>You can save weight.</strong> I’m still a ultralight backpacker at heart and if there’s a possibility to save weight then I’ll take it.</li>
  <li><strong>Adiós, Punctures!</strong> Don’t like that sound of your inner tube going flat? I hate it, and with a healthy dose of your Latex liquid in your tube that sound is unlikely to reach your ears again.</li>
  <li><strong>Traction, baby!</strong> Less pressure on the tires means you have more traction - pretty useful in sharp curves and lose trails.</li>
</ul>

<p>So, with three good reasons to get rid of inner tubes I set out on a sunny afternoon to convert my 920 Disc to Tubeless. It isn’t a quick operation by all means so make sure you have a couple of hours of peace to go about this. Here’s what you’ll need:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Tubeless-Ready Rims</li>
  <li>Tubeless-Ready Tires, I chose the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-thunder-burt-tl-easy-29er-psc-snakeskin-faltbar/?pid=10239">Schwalbe Thunder Burt Evo SnakeSkin PaceStar 29x2,10” TL-Easy Folding</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit-23-fahrradreifen/?pid=10239">Schwalbe Tubeless Easy Kit</a></li>
  <li>Schwalbe Tire Booster or a compressor</li>
  <li>Floor pump</li>
  <li>A bucket with soapy water and some rags</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35630505293/in/dateposted/" title="Frontwheel finished!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4357/35630505293_650cc34354_b.jpg" width="1024" height="936" alt="Frontwheel finished!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Alright, with all your tools and gear ready it’s time to start.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Preparation is KEY! Your Tire Booster needs to be “primed” first, so take your floor pump and put some 11 bars of air in it - that way you don’t need to do it later. Also, a good thing to do is to unfold your tire - if you’re using a tire that comes folded like I did - before you start the whole operation - and hang it into the sun. It will warm up and get a tiny, tiny bit more flexible which makes it easier to put on the rim later.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Lets first check if your rim is Tubeless-Ready. If it is it should be written on it somewhere - either it reads <em>Tubeless Ready</em> or <em>“TLR”</em> somewhere. If they are: Great, that saved you several hundred Euros for new Rims!</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36269911182/in/dateposted/" title="Is the Rim Tubeless Ready?"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4437/36269911182_390912e928_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Is the Rim Tubeless Ready?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<ol>
  <li>Time to deflate the tube, remove tire + tube + old rim tape, and get cleaning. Take a soapy rag and clean the inside (and while you’re at it, also the outside) of the rim, remove all dirt &amp; dust and then dry it well off. That’s because the next step is quite crucial for the success of the whole operation, and if you hurry through this you might do it twice, so calm and relaxed proceed you shall. Now you grab the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-tubeless-felgenband-fahrradreifen/?pid=10239">Tubeless Rim Tape</a> (these are available in different widths, make sure to buy the one which works best for your rim!) and apply careful and precisely the tape to the inside of the rim. Start opposite of the hole where the valve will go through later, and apply it carefully and cleanly with a lot of pressure to the rim, and avoid air bubbles. I say it again: <em>This is a very important step, so don’t hurry and take your time.</em> If you’ve gone once around and reach the start go another 5 to 10 cm and then cut the tape. Now take the Tubeless Valve from the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit-23-fahrradreifen/?pid=10239">Tubeless Easy Kit</a> and put it through the rim tape where it belong. Make sure to screw it tightly onto the rim, as the area around the valve can be a point where air easily escapes.</li>
</ol>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36269912682/in/dateposted/" title="Schwalbe Tubeless Easy Kit"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4341/36269912682_197bcfa340_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Schwalbe Tubeless Easy Kit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35630508523/in/dateposted/" title="New rim tape"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4354/35630508523_5cbe19f5f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="New rim tape" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36301263271/in/dateposted/" title="Rim Tape Done!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4346/36301263271_e688da6355_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rim Tape Done!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Time to take your <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-thunder-burt-tl-easy-29er-psc-snakeskin-faltbar/?pid=10239">Tubeless Tire</a> and mount it carefully onto the rim. If you can don’t use the tire lever as it might damage the rim tape - if you had your unfolded tire hang in the sun this should be possible. Make sure that the tire’s beads are on each side of the valve before you head on.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Time to inflate! Apply a generous coating of the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/schwalbe-montagefluid-easy-fit-bike-tires/?pid=10239">Easy Fit</a> assembly liquid to both sides of the tire beads, the (clean!) soapy water would work too. For the first inflation a powerful burst of air is needed so take the Tire Booster (or if you have one, the compressor) and attach it to the valve. It makes sense to take the top of the valve off to allow more air through-flow, you get a wee tool for that in the Tubeless Easy Kit. Alrighty, this is the moment of truth: Open the Tire Booster and see how your Tubeless Tire inflates. It should set with several loud <strong>BANG!</strong> sounds onto the rim, only if you hear that you know everything went as planned. You need to check the line on the tire to control if the complete tire is correctly mounted, if not knead and push the tire to get it into the right position.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36042172070/in/dateposted/" title="Easy Fit!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4401/36042172070_5cb9d07278_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Easy Fit!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36269910952/in/dateposted/" title="Tire Booster in action"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4381/36269910952_d1dbe91ae1_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Tire Booster in action" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This can be a stressful moment if you don’t hear that loud bang which indicates that the tire beads have engaged the rim - I tried for over an hour to get it to set down. The thing is that 29” tires (and Fatbike Tires even more so) take a lot of air to fill and that in my case the Tire Booster didn’t have enough power to engage the complete tire - it didn’t set down on a couple of places which means that the air was escaping and I couldn’t move on. The solution is to empty the whole Tire Booster into the Tire to get the Tire to set down on as many places on the rim as possible, and then switch to the Floor Pump and keep on inflating the tire. This did the trick for me - the tire looked almost like it was going to burst but in the end I heard the several loud bangs which meant the tire was now fully engaged to the rim. Success, at last!</p>

<ol>
  <li>Now that the tire sits on the rim you can take the pump/ compressor/ Tire Booster off the valve. This will deflate the tire a wee bit, but that’s not a problem. Remove the valve insert if you haven’t done that already in the previous step and take a bottle of the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/schwalbe-doc-blue-professional-inner-tube/?pid=10239">Doc Blue puncture protection liquid</a> - now it’s time to put it into your Tire and make it Tubeless! You can easily fill the bottle through the valve into the tire - for 29” tires you use the whole 60 ml, smaller tires need less. Once the bottle is empty you put the valve insert back, take the floor pump and inflate the tire again - around 2 bar for these 29” tires is good for starters. Remove the pump, close the valve and now you’ll need to roll and shake the tire for quite a bit - the goal is to distribute the puncture protection liquid everywhere in the tire so that an even cover covers it from the inside. To check the tire once more for leaks you can cover the outside of the tire along the rim with your soapy water - there where there’s bubbles building up you need to move the puncture protection liquid on the inside to cover it better.</li>
</ol>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35630506573/in/dateposted/" title="Doc Blue goes in!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4372/35630506573_cb13980646_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Doc Blue goes in!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36301261941/in/dateposted/" title="Checking for leaks"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4430/36301261941_c9929cd00c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Checking for leaks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If the tire now stays inflated you can attach it back to the bike and get started on the second wheel, after which you should head out for a test ride. All good? Then pack up your bike and head out on a bikepacking Microadventure - Tubeless Edition!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36269915742/in/dateposted/" title="Schwalbe Thunder Burt Tubeless"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4370/36269915742_7e1a2ca31b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Schwalbe Thunder Burt Tubeless" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I’m now riding since over a month Tubeless and love it. I can ride my tires with less pressure on the trails which equals better traction, but of course the biggest benefit for me is that I don’t need to worry about punctures and snake bites anymore, as the puncture protection liquid seals those immediately should they happen. It’s just a great feeling to know that you can ride how you want without needing to worry that you might end up with a flat tire! Finally, if you’re a friend of moving pictures then have a look at <a href="https://youtu.be/M2fVuTqicCc">this video</a> which is by and far the best on how to convert your tires to tubeless tires! More Information on Tubeless you can find on the <a href="https://www.schwalbe.com/en/tubeless-technology.html">Schwalbe Tubeless</a> Website, while the <a href="https://www.schwalbe.com/en/tubeless.html">Tubeless FAQ</a> can answer additional questions you might have.</p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1281" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731281" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1281"></script>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this &amp; other articles why not <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35603378504/in/dateposted/" title="Off on Tubeless Adventures"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4383/35603378504_24246ae466_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Off on Tubeless Adventures" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cycling & Bouldering on Åland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/08/cycling-and-bouldering-on-aland.html"/>
    <updated>2016-08-10T23:39:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/08/cycling-and-bouldering-on-aland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Three times a charm, they say. My love affair with Åland went into the third round last week as I was photographing a story for the <a href="http://www.norrmagazin.de">NORR</a> and <a href="http://www.partioaitta.fi/365klubi/365-lehti">365 Magazine</a> about cycling, bouldering and sea kayaking on the beautiful Åland Archipelago between Finland and Sweden.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810987961/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Cloudporn over the Baltic."><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8358/28810987961_443a331b7c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Cloudporn over the Baltic." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/02/aland-in-winter.html">The last time I was on Åland</a> was just in January, and how different it was back then: The roads under snow and ice, the Baltic partially frozen, a cold wind blowing. But it was also similar to the previous <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/bouldering-on-aland.html">bouldering trip to Åland</a> and this visit: The people were fantastic and made the trip even more memorable. Which made me realize once more: It’s more beautiful to share an outdoor adventure with friends. Sure it is nice to watch the sun set over the sea, but it is more fun to share that moment with a good friend. It’s cool if you topped out on your route, but it’s cooler if you have a friend to high-five with to celebrate that success. And while Sauna is always great, also on your own, it’s much better with friends who share your passion for a good <em>löyly</em>. So when you head out on your next outdoor adventure, take someone along: Your partner, kids, mate or someone who shares the same love for the outdoors than you do. I’m certain the trip will be more fun &amp; memorable for both of you =)</p>

<p>So much for advice, here’s a couple of B-Roll photos and one-liners to wet your appetite to head over to Åland with a bike and Crashpad on your back.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810986921/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="On the way onto the ferry"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8701/28810986921_d281162f39_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="On the way onto the ferry" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Kathrin from <a href="http://luminoucity.net">Luminoucity</a>, Kristof and me rolling onto the ferry by bike. My first time to roll on a bike onto a ferry, and a good one.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810987461/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Good Bye Helsinki"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8424/28810987461_9fe00bcb5c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Good Bye Helsinki" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We said Good-By to Helsinki on the sun deck, sans sun.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28269451094/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Morning cycling through along the fields"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7783/28269451094_8364170fbc_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Morning cycling through along the fields" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>At dawn we arrived on Åland and started to cycle up north to <a href="http://www.havsvidden.com">HavsVidden</a> past golden fields and a rising sun.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810986491/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Kristof at Kasviken"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/8/7730/28810986491_0b29a9ae18_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="Kristof at Kasviken" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We slipped in a session at Kasviken as it was so conveniently on the way.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810986241/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Relaxing at HavsVidden"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8846/28810986241_95f636f677_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="Relaxing at HavsVidden" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After that it was pretty chill at the beach house.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="http://amzn.to/2beNxGI" title="The Best We Can Do Is Nothing"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8160/28798090366_542e2ab604_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="The Best We Can Do Is Nothing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I read an <a href="http://amzn.to/2beNxGI">inspiring book</a> the next morning, which motivated me to do… nothing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28798090286/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Relaxing at Fågelberget"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8269/28798090286_a9f93a9c13_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="Relaxing at Fågelberget" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In between bouts of work I succeeded in following the books advice.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28855542636/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Stallhagen Beers are tasty!"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8646/28855542636_ea16422b1f_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Stallhagen Beers are tasty!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Then I failed pretty badly by cycling close to 46 km to go eat at <a href="http://www.stallhagen.com/en/?ageok=yes">Stallhagen</a>, and yes, drink some of their fantastic beers.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28855541356/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Pelago Bicycles Capri"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8895/28855541356_f75340ee58_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Pelago Bicycles Capri" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>My friends were very happy with their <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com">Pelago Bicycles</a>, here the pretty <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com/bicycles/capri.html">Capri</a> which Vera rode.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810989711/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Portrait Sessions"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8776/28810989711_fe8e83bd40_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Portrait Sessions" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I myself had my much loved <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Stavanger</a> along, which performed flawlessly once again.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28810989151/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="On the way back to Mariehamn from Kobba Klintar"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8695/28810989151_1951188c9e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1200" alt="On the way back to Mariehamn from Kobba Klintar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Jonas from <a href="http://www.paddelboden.com">The Paddle Shack</a> took us out to Kobba Klintar, the old pilot station which is really a great destination for a day of paddling.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28798090336/in/album-72157672041470976/" title="Seakayaking with Paddelboden"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8895/28798090336_ebc0d4057a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1069" alt="Seakayaking with Paddelboden" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the way back we had back wind and choppy seas, so it was nice when we weaved back into the Archipelago and let ourselves just drift in the wind back towards the shack. Then it was just about cycling back to the ferry harbour and waiting for our big boat back to Helsinki. It was once again a fantastic visit and I can highly recommend you to spend a week or more on Åland if you’re into any of the above activities. And I’ll let you know where to read the good story and see the proper photos when it’s out!</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> I was invited to Åland to photograph a story for <a href="http://www.norrmagazin.de">NORR magazine</a> which you can read next summer. Thanks to <a href="http://www.visitaland.com">Visit Åland</a> and its partners who supported us with this trip. A huge thanks also to <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com">Pelago Bicycles</a> and <a href="http://www.gamlastanscykel.se">Gamla Stan Cykel</a> for the awesome bicycles and <a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/en_FI/homepage">Black Diamond</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.oacsport.fi">OAC</a> for loaning us the crashpads. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this post and would like more, why not <a href="http://ko-fi.com/?i=8d16909703c77d0">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Outdoor Guide to Vaasa]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/09/the-outdoor-guide-to-vaasa.html"/>
    <updated>2015-09-29T22:59:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/09/the-outdoor-guide-to-vaasa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Outdoor Guide to Vaasa - Finland’s sunniest city!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21593581188/in/dateposted/" title="Öjberget, Vaasa"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5769/21593581188_bc0746168b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Öjberget, Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="outdoor-destinations">Outdoor destinations</h2>

<p>There’s plenty of nice nature trails around Vaasa which all can be found <a href="http://www.merenkurkku.fi/koe-merenkurkku/vaellusreitit/">here</a>. You can find coordinates and pdf maps on that website, though in general the trails are well marked and there’s an info board + map at the start. If you have a car or bike, I can recommend the <a href="http://www.merenkurkku.fi/koe-merenkurkku/vaellusreitit/ojenin-luontopolku/">Öjenin luontopolku</a> which is a nice 4 km loop with a fire place at the middle, which makes it ideal for adventures with kids. On the island of Vaskiluoto there’s a large forest trail which also is also groomed in winter for cross country skiing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21594552609/in/dateposted/" title="Öjenin luontopolku"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5704/21594552609_dc9de34f58_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Öjenin luontopolku" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.kvarkenworldheritage.fi/visit-kvarken/">Kvarken Archipelago</a> is Finland’s only UNESCO World Heritage site and an ideal destination to go birdwatching, a family or weekend hike or a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/pack-sail-rafting-in-the-kvarken-archipelago.html">packrafting adventure</a>. You will need a car or bike to get there (walking along the road is no fun), but it is worth it - the raising land is a sight to behold.</p>

<p>You prefer water sports? Good that Vaasa has at least half a dozen of fine <a href="http://www.visitvaasa.fi/fi/haku/Pages/tulos.aspx?paikka=436&amp;pakti=2&amp;a1akti=288">beaches</a>, with the one at Hietasaari probably being the easiest to reach and the most popular, too. The <a href="http://www.supstation.fi/vaasa/">Vaasa SUP Station</a> is also located there and a great opportunity to rent a SUP board and try our Stand Up Paddling. The photos from their sunset paddles look awesome, so check out their Instagram feed. In winter Hietasaari is also a good starting point to go Nordic Skating on the Baltic, or take your kite-surfing gear and hit the ice on the Eteläinen Kaupunginselkä.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21593424660/in/dateposted/" title="Vaasa SUP Station"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5680/21593424660_c0216dcf0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vaasa SUP Station" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Bouldering outdoors in Vaasa is so easy, you almost stumble over the blocs! <a href="http://27crags.com/areas/vaasa/">27 Crags</a> has you covered and is your guide to the best bouldering and climbing in town. If you actually prefer climbing with a rope then <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/falkiin-kallio">Falkiin Kallio</a> is the nearest crag of note, or you take the ferry to Umeå where there’s bigger and longer routes! In winter the crag at Höstvesi is good for whacking some ice, too.</p>

<p>Skiing in Vaasa is also possible at the nearby <a href="http://www.vaasa.fi/palvelut/talviurheilukeskus-ojberget">Öjberget Ski Centre</a>. You can check if its open from <a href="http://www.ski.fi/en/author/ojberget/">ski.fi</a>, though at 45 m elevation and the longest slope being 325 m long don’t expect long runs! However, in town there are <a href="http://www.latukartta.fi/vaasa/">14 cross country skiing loipes</a>, so if you come here in winter and enjoy some kick’n’glide take your skis along!</p>

<p>You can go packrafting and kayaking in town right from any of the many beaches and shores, but be careful around the harbour. At <a href="http://varppi.fi/en/">Varppi</a> you can rent a kayak or rowing boat if you don’t bring your own. A much nicer area to go paddling is the Kvarken Archipelago or one of the rivers. And if you prefer a <a href="http://www.visitvaasa.fi/fi/haku/Pages/tulos.aspx?paikka=436&amp;pakti=2&amp;a1akti=66">short cruise</a>, also that is possible in summer, with the old post boat being the most beautiful cruise as it has been sailing since 1679.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21160399993/in/dateposted/" title="Öjberget, Vaasa"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/734/21160399993_8dfd5f1d97_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Öjberget, Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If you want to do long bicycle rides you’re in luck, though. There’s plenty of great cycling here, and Vaasa being in Pohjanmaa - the “flat country” - you won’t need to bother with long climbs. However, because we’re next to the Baltic expect wind, and as it goes - if there’s wind there’s going to be headwind. If you prefer to cycle around town, then the ride along the shore is a nice way to explore some of the best views of Vaasa and also grab an ice cream or a Toast Skagen at <a href="http://www.strampen.com/english">Strampen</a>. And if you look for some singletrack to shred check out the trail on the <a href="http://vsmtb.net/wp/reitit/">Vaasanseudun MTB</a> website.</p>

<p>Nice parks for a pick nick include the Satamapuisto next to <a href="http://kuntsi.vaasa.fi">Kuntsi</a> and the adjoining Hovioikeudenpuisto as well as Hietasaari, the tiny island just in front of Vaasa.</p>

<h2 id="in-case-of-rain-outdoors-indoors">In case of Rain: Outdoors, Indoors</h2>

<p>There’s plenty of gyms and sports halls in Vaasa, though you likely will need a membership to train in them. A better choice if the weather is not cooperating is the nice <a href="http://www.vaasa.fi/palvelut/uimahalli">swimming hall</a> of Vaasa, which has a 50 m pool for good work outs as well as a jump pool and a couple of kids’ pools. And this being Finland it obviously has a fine Sauna, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21755324106/in/dateposted/" title="Vaasa Vesitorni"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5759/21755324106_58df849764_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Vaasa Vesitorni" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Watertower of Vaasa houses the city’s <a href="http://www.highsport.fi/node/262">climbing gym</a>, which has public hours each Wednesday and Sunday from 18 to 20 o’clock. There’ currently two walls, one 17 m long with some overhang and one 20 m high wall, with a third wall being under construction.</p>

<p>The modern art museum <a href="http://kuntsi.vaasa.fi">Kuntsi</a> is well worth a visit if you like art, and there’s also the rather nice <a href="http://www.tikanojantaidekoti.fi">Tikanojan taidekoti</a> which is a good place to spent time. The <a href="http://www.pohjanmaanmuseo.fi/?page=Home&amp;setlang=l3">Pohjanmaa Museum</a> is actually four museums in one, of which the Terranova natural science exhibition is interesting to learn more about the Kvarken Archipelago.</p>

<p>There are only limited outdoor-sy happenings in Vaasa, but the yearly <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Luontoliikuntapäivä-Naturmotionsdag-Outdoor-Recreation-Day-338517656254113/timeline/">Outdoor Recreation Day</a> which usually happens every February is a good event to attend. You can learn about ice climbing, try nordic touring skating and ice fishing, eat a Pulla or Makkara and learn about other winter activities offered in the area.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/12723806373/in/photostream/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid &amp; IcePack"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7408/12723806373_c1bf2dc325_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear UltaMid &amp; IcePack" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-shopping">Outdoor shopping</h2>

<p>Vaasa’s offerings in terms of outdoor equipment are OK. Don’t expect to find gear from Arc’teryx, Patagonia, Norrøna, Primus or Helsport in town, though if you like Fjällräven, Haglöfs, Salomon et al. you will find them at the Intersport shop just off the main square. Also the Hypermarkets just a wee bit outside of the centre carry some outdoor equipment, from fishing tackle to sleeping pads and backpacks.</p>

<p>On the other hand there are at least half a dozen Bike Shops in Vaasa, with <a href="http://www.pyoraviertola.fi/">Pyöräliike Viertola</a> in Rauhankatu 20 being my favourite. They carry <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Pelago Bicycles</a> and are friendly &amp; professional, and also sell used bikes.</p>

<p>As fas as I know there’s no possibility to rent gear in town, but you can always check <a href="http://www.kuinoma.fi">kuin oma</a> for renting gear in Finland.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21575445089/in/dateposted/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5734/21575445089_526faf99d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sleeping-outdoors--indoors">Sleeping outdoors &amp; indoors</h2>

<p>Stealth camping in Vaasa is no problem whatsoever. There are so many forests and parks close to the centre that camping out is not a problem. Some of the beaches are a great option, or if you want to be really on your own cycle or walk out to Pilvilampi and camp there. The Everymen’s Right is your friend in Finland, so just stay at least 100 m away from a house and you’re good to go.</p>

<p>If you prefer to sleep indoors, then check the <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/hmorkel?s=8">AirBnB listings</a> in Vaasa, there’s currently 28 houses, flats and rooms on offer in town which range from cozy old wooden houses to modern flats with sea view. <a href="http://www.visitvaasa.fi/fi/alasivut/Pages/nuku.aspx">Hotels, Cottages and B&amp;Bs</a> can be found on the Vaasa website, and if you want to go camping then the <a href="http://www.topcamping.fi/fi/vaasa_fi/">Top Camping Vaasa</a> place is your only option.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18572119925/in/dateposted/" title="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/266/18572119925_8e67987dba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Locus Gear Hapi Sil &amp; Salsa Mukluk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="food--cafs">Food &amp; Cafés</h2>

<p>What are the best Cafés in Vaasa? Well, all those that are closed on Sundays. Seriously though, don’t expect a Café to be open on Sunday in this town. I haven’t figured out <em>why</em> they are closed, but on the rare occasion that they are open on a Sunday they are full. But any other day of the week they welcome your business, and it’s a hard toss-up which of these four Cafés is my favourite.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.loftet.fi/ravintola-konsulinnan-kahvihuone/">Konsulinnan kahvihuone</a> serves a great lunch with a delicious salad table, their coffee is arguably the best in town and you get a free 2nd cup. Also their cakes are superb, and the atmosphere in the old building is wonderful. <a href="http://www.sweetvaasa.fi">Sweet Vaasa</a> makes tasty cakes and salads, the <a href="http://www.othello-products.fi">Othello Bakeries</a> also have great traditional pastries and the <a href="http://www.wasakonditori.fi">Wasa Konditoria</a> in the old market hall has a great atmosphere and sells goods from Finland’s best bakery, <a href="http://www.aroma.fi">Aroma</a>. Aroma itself is located a bit outside of town in Kvevlax and a great stop for a coffeeneuring trip with your bike. <a href="http://www.caferaawka.fi">Café Raawka</a> should be on your list if you like raw food - it’s on my list for this weekends Café trip to town!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21184299813/in/dateposted/" title="Brita Cake at Konsulinnan kahvihuone"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5625/21184299813_03900082dd_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Brita Cake at Konsulinnan kahvihuone" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://magokoro.fi">Magokoro</a> is Vaasa’s Sushi Restaurant and my favourite option for a tasty lunch in the centre. Their sushi are fresh, tasty and will always make you wish you’d have taken one more. For Dinner the <a href="http://www.pizzabistromarcopolo.fi">Pizzabistro Marco Polo</a> is the best choice for Pizzas in town. Delicious, freshly made pizzas and a cozy atmosphere with friendly staff will make for a good start into the evening. <a href="http://www.tomyumthai.fi">Tom Yum Thai</a> is a great Thai Restaurant which makes tasty food and has very friendly staff, and my choice for Asian food when eating out. I haven’t yet been to <a href="https://villdravintola.wordpress.com/2015/08/31/villd-poytavarauksia-otetaan-vastaan-nu-tar-vi-emot-reservationer/">Villd</a>, the Pop-Up Restaurant from Ossi Palonevan, but plan to go there while it is here in Vaasa till the end of October. Locally sourced foods from the Baltic and forests for a uniquely Finnish dining experience - what’s not to look forward to?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21183941504/in/photostream/" title="©Veera Kujala"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/645/21183941504_42ea79e25a_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="©Veera Kujala" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="microadventures">Microadventures!</h2>

<p>More than a couple of days in Vaasa? Take a bike and ride to Isokyrö and visit the <a href="http://www.kyrodistillery.com">Kyrö Distillery Company</a> and taste the worlds best Gin for Gin &amp; Tonic! You also might be able to grab a bite and witness some live music at this small distillery, but check their website and reserve a table if you plan to visit.</p>

<p>If you’re more than a couple of days in town you owe it to yourself to head out to the <a href="http://www.kvarkenworldheritage.fi/visit-kvarken/">Kvarken Archipelago</a>, Finland’s only UNESCO World Heritage Site and see how the land rises from the sea, spot a white-tailed eagle and traditional boat sheds. It’s a great place to visit summers as winters, and will surely will make you feel like you’re in a far-away, wild place.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8609916055/in/album-72157633438534075/" title="Svedjehamn harbour"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8121/8609916055_a79bbce51e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Svedjehamn harbour" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://www.meteoria.fi/en">Meteoria Söderfjärden</a> is probably the biggest meteorite crater in Finland, and right in the middle there’s a birdwatching tower to observe the cranes and other birds passing through in spring an autumn. Meteoria is the most important resting and feeding place for cranes in Finland and a great place to observe these birds. There’s also a small museum next to the tower, and it’s easy to reach by bike or car.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.stundars.fi/?lang=en">Stundars</a> is an open air museum with over sixty traditional buildings from the region, from a windmill to a fishermen’s hut. It’s a great place to visit in summer when it is open, or during one of the special events like the handcrafts fair. There’s also trail that leads to it from the Meteoria and it’s close to <a href="http://www.sundom.fi/en">Sundom</a>, the small village just a few kilometres away from Vaasa.</p>

<h2 id="getting-around-town-and-to-vaasa">Getting around town and to Vaasa</h2>

<p>The centre of Vaasa is compact enough that you can walk from the Railway Station to Hietasaari in 15 minutes, or from the Swimming Hall to Palosaari in about 25 minutes. There’s no easy way to loan a bike in Vaasa, and the public transportation is also not good - a couple of busses with drivers who seem to think they’re in a rally car, you’re better off walking.</p>

<p>Getting to Vaasa is fastest and most affordable by airplane. The airport is small and efficient and it’s just a 35 minute flight to Helsinki. If you like to see more of the country then travelling by bus is an option, either by <a href="https://www.matkahuolto.fi/fi/">Matkahuolto</a> or with the cheap <a href="http://www.onnibus.com/en/index.htm">Onnibus</a>. If you prefer unreliable transportation which is expensive then the <a href="https://www.vr.fi/cs/vr/fi/etusivu">Finnish Railways</a> should be your choice. If you’re in Sweden you also can fly from Stockholm to Vaasa, or take the <a href="http://www.wasaline.com/en/">Wasaline Ferry</a> from Umeå for a more relaxed way to arrive in town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/21182653664/in/dateposted/" title="Flying with Finnair to Vaasa"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/764/21182653664_e6a003f2eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Flying with Finnair to Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="outdoor-folks-in-vaasa">Outdoor folks in Vaasa</h2>

<p>There are outdoorsy people in Vaasa, though they are mostly organized in Clubs for their specific sports as you saw above, so you might want to check out their happenings if you want to socialize. However, to find like-minded outdoorsy people you can browse the <a href="https://instagram.com/explore/tags/vaasa/">Instagram Tag for Vaasa</a> and also search on Twitter for <a href="https://twitter.com/search?f=users&amp;vertical=default&amp;q=vaasa&amp;src=typd">tweeps from Vaasa</a>. And then there’s obviously me on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/14600027980/in/photolist-oypywx-of9XEm-owBYKE-ofadcg-ownNer-of9XAU-ofacnk-owBZTb-ofacpz-ofajmk-ouC46E-ofaeGu-6XnhwZ-89wNEi-89A8yA-89zZDu-89wWe2-89wRLR-89wJ7T-89wTpg" title="Crossing of one of the ridges ended up as a muddy wade through a bed of reeds and what not, while being chased by a flight of hungry horse flies - part of the game :)"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3881/14600027980_0567d7110c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Crossing of one of the ridges ended up as a muddy wade through a bed of reeds and what not, while being chased by a flight of hungry horse flies - part of the game :)" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="london-tokyo-stockholm-and-onwards">London, Tokyo, Stockholm and onwards!</h2>

<p>Liked this Outdoor Guide to Vaasa, but you’re more likely to visit Stockholm, Tokyo and San Francisco next? Well, you’re in luck! Direct your browser to the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/09/outdoor-guide-directory.html">Outdoor Guide Directory</a> and check out the other Guides from across the globe!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
