<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: cycling | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/cycling/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2021-11-26T13:29:32+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[reTyre Gravel Chaser Skins Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/11/retyre-gravel-chaser-skins-review.html"/>
    <updated>2021-11-19T08:45:49+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/11/retyre-gravel-chaser-skins-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last spring I installed the last time new tires on my Pelago Stavanger Bike - the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2021/07/switching-tires-never-again-thanks-to-retyre.html">reTyre One</a> tires, which are compatible with a variety of reTyre Skins. During the past months I rode the Gravel Chaser Skin whenever the asphalt stopped and the off-road adventures started, and these skins gave me confidence when cornering and great grip in uneven surfaces.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51689312735/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Stavanger with reTyre Gravel Chaser Tires"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51689312735_ef039dd96c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Stavanger with reTyre Gravel Chaser Tires" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This article was supported with equipment and financially by reTyre. There are Affiliate links in this article which are marked with an ∞ Infinity Sign 😊 As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>I want to start off with something I wrote in the late spring: <em>The skins and the reTyre One have zippers which allows you to connect the Skin - and there’s four different Skins available for different cycling needs - to the <a href="https://rty.re/3yCIarN">reTyre One</a>. The reTyre One itself is a fully functional bicycle tire but with the different Skins you’re able to put on a new “Tire” onto your bike without the hassle of actually switching the tire. Zipping on a Skin takes me about two Minutes and it’s even quicker taking it off. It’s a great way to adapt the bike to different terrains and seasons - zip on the Winter Traveler Skin as soon as the snow starts falling, and take them off in spring.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51689307540/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51689307540_098e604059_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51689303180/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin Box"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51689303180_d1e326e08c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin Box" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This still holds true and it is such a great invention as it makes my life as the bicycle-tire-changing person in our family so much easier (I still have to switch the tires on my son’s <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2021/07/woom-off-off-review.html">woom OFF AIR bike</a> 😒). Financially speaking it is also a bit cheaper to own a set of <a href="https://rty.re/3yCIarN">reTyre One tires</a> and Skins according to your need than two sets of summer and winter tires (a set of our good winter tires costs easily 120 € and the same I usually pay for good summer tires), wheras a set of reTyre On + e.g. a Set of <a href="https://rty.re/3yCIarN">Winter Traveler Skins</a> would be 170 € - so around 70 € cheaper. The main benefit for me is, however, the amount of time saved. I can not stress this enough, it really makes the procedure so much faster, it’s wonderful.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51689085354/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin Inside"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51689085354_c8d647001c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin Inside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51688675308/in/dateposted/" title="Zipping on the reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51688675308_958c154f12_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Zipping on the reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="https://rty.re/3hhzjpx">Gravel Chaser</a> Skin was just as easy to zip on as the Winter Traveler Skin, even if the reTyre One was a bit dirty. I guess if you’re concerned about the zipper getting stuck you could clean the tire with some <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/muc-off-pit-kit-8-in-one-reinigungsset/?pid=10239">∞ Muc-Off products</a> but I didn’t bother at all and they went on without a hassle in a minute. There’s a wee gap between the ends of the skin but during riding I did not feel it at all, so it wasn’t a problem.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51689311020/in/dateposted/" title="Zipper on the reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51689311020_d41d1c6fa0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Zipper on the reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The most important aspects of a tire is for me that it has grip and is long-lasting. I can’t comment on the longevity of the Gravel Chaser yet, but the grip has been very good. It has brillant grip on gravel roads and muddy forest paths, and they give me great confidence when I go through muddy or rocky bends in the trails and roads. Thanks to the higher shoulder knobs on the tire you have more control on uneven surfaces, and I had not slip my tires once during my rides. At the same time it has a fast-rolling centre tread, which means you can get some nice speed with them when you feel like it. It’s a great addition to the reTyre line-up for those of us who like to go bikepacking and ride gravel roads!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51689295470/in/dateposted/" title="Top-Side View of the reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51689295470_ee944f7286_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Top-Side View of the reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51689304335/in/dateposted/" title="Mud on the reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51689304335_64b8364dc3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mud on the reTyre Gravel Chaser Skin" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In conclusion I can say that the reTyre System of a base tire plus different skins is an excellent solution for those who use one bike for all their riding and don’t want to go through the hassle of changing tires before a ride or when the seasons change. Soon I will take the Gravel Chaser skins off again and put the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2021/07/switching-tires-never-again-thanks-to-retyre.html">Winter Traveler Skins</a> on, making my bike ready for winter. But I am already planning some rides in Pohjanmaa with the Stavanger and the Gravel Chaser skins next spring, and I am happy to know that I can switch tires in a couple of minutes and be ready!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51688409936/in/dateposted/" title="Wood"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51688409936_08ca86be01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wood" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> (and you get great discount codes from partners - you could save 20% on your next purchase!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2021 Bikepacking and Bike-Touring Gear Setup]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/09/2021-bikepacking-and-bike-touring-gear-setup.html"/>
    <updated>2021-09-22T19:12:44+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/09/2021-bikepacking-and-bike-touring-gear-setup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Exploring the country by bike and camping out - bikepacking and bike-touring has been massively popular during the last year, for a good reason - it’s a much better way to go for a road-trip than by car, and you’re able to see more than by hiking. I too went exploring <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2021/08/impressions-from-northern-norway.html">Northern Norway</a> this <em>“summer”</em> (it was slightly moist!) and used a combination of traditional bike-touring Panniers and bikepacking bags, which allowed me to have all my kit close at hand while on the road. This setup has been working a charm for me and continues to serve me well on my local trips - a good reason to tell you more about it though!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51502442102/in/dateposted/" title="Taking in the View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51502442102_a44a990497_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Taking in the View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This article has been supported financially and with equipment by Bikester. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>My <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/06/bikepacking-in-pirkanmaa.html">first proper bikepacking trip</a> was 9 years ago with Peter and Toni - and yes, that’s quite a while ago! Things have changed since then, too, as big brands have picked up on the topic of bikepacking, there have been innovations in bikes, bags and techniques, and more and more people have started to explore single trails with bikepacking kit since. Good stuff!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503243186/in/dateposted/" title="The road goes on and on"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503243186_c58d5e38e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="The road goes on and on" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I knew that on my Norway trip I will be mostly cycling on roads, using the Hurtigbåt to move from island to island to cycle and hike there. I also didn’t take my own bike with me, but loaned an electric Trekking Bike from Tromsø Outdoors to get around. All that made me decide to take more classic Pannier bags for the majority of my kit. To be precise, these would transport my quilt, bivy, mattress, stove, food and clothes, as well as some tech stuff. I own two small Porcelain Rocket Pannier bags, but I knew they’d be too small for the kit in question, so I had a look around and found the <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/vaude-aqua-back-light-pannier-laukku-2-kpl-948558_2484678.html">Vaude Aqua Back Light Pannier bags</a>, which tip the scales at a mere 548 g for one or 1.096 g for the pair. These were super spacious with almost 20 l of Volume per bag and I also liked that they have on the inside two pockets (one zippered), which are ideal for storing documents and small stuff. The backplate gives the whole bag some form and a stable platform to load it up, while the welded 100% recycled Econyl fabric - it is also 100% PVC-free! - is 100% waterproof. And rain I had on my trip in Norway more than enough =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503471783/in/dateposted/" title="Beach Bum"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503471783_fdd0c54939_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Beach Bum" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503977044/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Aqua Back Light Pannier Bag top attachment mechanism"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503977044_0686f7d26b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vaude Aqua Back Light Pannier Bag top attachment mechanism" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503482598/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Aqua Back Light Pannier Bag"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503482598_9da4d8e161_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vaude Aqua Back Light Pannier Bag" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503492488/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Aqua Back Light Pannier Bag lower attachment hook"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503492488_4bea063c0b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vaude Aqua Back Light Pannier Bag lower attachment hook" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The attachment tech on the bag of the Pannier, called Quick Mount Release Hook QMR 2.0, is 100% adjustable to the rack on your bike - the lower hook can easily be moved 360° around the plate, and the two hooks at the top can easily be moved closer together or wider apart, and the inner diameter can also simply be adjusted to the diameter of your rack. They are just as easy to remove from the bike, which means setting up the tent and moving the gear inside is super-easy. If you want you also can use these bags as shoulder bags with the included straps, but I found the two handles more than enough to carry the bags around. The roll top closure provides quick access, the cargo net - the bungee straps - at the front provide some compression of the content, but also allow to keep your rain jacket or spare shirt close at hand (I wouldn’t do that, but should be safe to do).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51502441172/in/dateposted/" title="Vaude Aqua Back Light Pannier Bag, back"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51502441172_05d91e9419_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vaude Aqua Back Light Pannier Bag, back" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The total volume of both bags is a claimed 38 litres with a recommended maximum load of 10 kg per bag. Overall I was a bit sceptical and not sure if these would work for my needs, but after 10 days on the road in Norway with them I’m a convert and love these Aqua Back Light Pannier bags from Vaude! Add in that they are Made in Germany with a short supply chain from 100% recycled Econyl that’s 100% PVC-free and you have a great Pannier for your bikepacking and cycle-touring adventures! In terms of aerodynamic I didn’t find that they slowed me down - I usually had an above 20 km/h average speed, which is similar to what I cycle on my bike without any bags. For relaxed bikepacking and cycle-touring trips they shouldn’t slow you down at all, which is what I expect you’re planning to do too =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503244221/in/dateposted/" title="Bikepacking"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503244221_41f7666e4d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bikepacking" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51355649985/in/album-72157719684005710/" title="Arnøya Selfie"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51355649985_82a4e2e2da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arnøya Selfie" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Up next are the three <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/revelate-designs/">Revelate Designs</a> bikepacking bags I ordered from Bikester. I have been using bikepacking bags from various well-known brands since almost a decade, and it’s something I always want on my bikes for ease of access to important kit while riding. The three Revelate Designs bags I ordered are the <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/revelate-designs-jerrycan-ylaputkilaukku-regular-364638_412644.html">Jerrycan</a>, <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/revelate-designs-mountain-feedbag-pyoralaukku-971555_2563652.html">Mountain Feedbag</a> and the amazing <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/revelate-designs-mag-tank-2000-runkolaukku-vaakaputkeen-1193575_3363727.html">Mag Tank 2000</a>. Lets start with the Jerrycan, as ideally this is the bag I access the least.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503260091/in/dateposted/" title="Revelate Designs Jerrycan"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503260091_f003fb80cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Revelate Designs Jerrycan" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That’s because the Jerrycan holds on my own bikes all my repair kit: A bike tool, a spare tire + repair kit, a knife, some paper (in case the chain drops) and a Tire Lever or two. With these tools I can fix most issues I usually encounter on a trip (it are flat tires on my Tubeless rides 😆) and they are easily accessed but still out-of-the-way on the bike. The <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/revelate-designs-jerrycan-ylaputkilaukku-regular-364638_412644.html">Jerrycan</a> is durable, with a waterproof zipper and construction, and has about 500 ml Volume - really plenty for me. There’s a rubberized patch at the lower strap so it does not damage the paint job on your bike, and at the back strap a foam insert protects your seat post from damage. All in all a good piece of kit which does what it does, and that it does well!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503976304/in/dateposted/" title="Revelate Designs Jerrycan with all my tools"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503976304_28af6c7686_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Revelate Designs Jerrycan with all my tools" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>More flexible in use is the <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/revelate-designs-mountain-feedbag-pyoralaukku-971555_2563652.html">Mountain Feedbag</a>. It can hold your water bottle in the main compartment (also around 500 ml Volume) or all the snacks you want to stuff in there.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51504186630/in/dateposted/" title="Revelate Designs Mag Tank 2000 + Revelate Designs Mountain Feedbag 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51504186630_c4a88d34a7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Revelate Designs Mag Tank 2000 + Revelate Designs Mountain Feedbag 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I am Team Waterbootle in the Mountain Feedbag, but with it’s three Stretch pockets you also can put bars, gels or even a <a href="https://youtu.be/bw7cc_xXock">GoPro HERO9</a> in there. It is a 102 g light and has three attachment points, and can be attached on either side of your handlebar (so yes, you could get two!). What I really love about it is that you can open and close it with only one hand, thanks to the smart attachment system Revelate Designs has developed. This means on bumpy rides you can easily close the Mountain Feedback and not have any of the content drop out. Some people also transport their cameras or lenses in them, which doesn’t work for me (lenses &amp; cameras too big 😬) but could be a good way for some to have their camera close by.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503259286/in/dateposted/" title="Revelate Designs Mountain Feedbag + Waterbottle"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503259286_2f24cf5b4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Revelate Designs Mountain Feedbag + Waterbottle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503257891/in/dateposted/" title="Revelate Designs Mountain Feedbag with my bottle"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503257891_6f36d65aed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Revelate Designs Mountain Feedbag with my bottle" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>“And where do all the Snacks go?”</em> you might wonder. In the <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/revelate-designs-mag-tank-2000-runkolaukku-vaakaputkeen-1193575_3363727.html">Mag Tank 2000</a> obviously! It is 149 g light and has a massive volume of around 1 litre or, all the snacks you might eat in a day or three. It also can hold a massive bike lock chain, but as you really can’t eat that I would put snacks of your liking in there. I absolutely LOVE the magnetic closure on it, it’s again such a feature which makes life while riding so much easier that you might wonder how you were able to survive without magnetic buckles on your previous trips. Also this piece has a durable construction that has kept the content dry on my trips, is easy to attach to the bike (also with the same protective features for your frame + paint job as on the Jerrycan) and it makes snacking while riding a breeze.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503255376/in/dateposted/" title="Lots of snacks in the Revelate Designs Mag Tank 2000"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503255376_59f0ffd14d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lots of snacks in the Revelate Designs Mag Tank 2000" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51502443502/in/dateposted/" title="Reflection"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51502443502_be1da3a4e2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Reflection" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All in all these four (five) bag setup has held all my camping, hiking and bikepacking gear with room to spare. As I carry a Full-Frame camera + lenses + tripod + a GoPro + a Drone and spare batteries + cables I need a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/09/huckepacks-phoenix-lite-review.html">backpack</a>, but if you are happy with photos from your phone or a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/10/sony-rx100-iv-field-report.html">small camera</a> then you should be fine without a backpack and can ride without a sweaty back! The combination of classical cycle-touring Pannier bags + accessible bikepacking bags has worked well for me on my trips this summer, and while I own a handlebar bag and a seatpost bag for 100% bikepacking I find the Panniers easier and more comfortable to use - and on roads, be they asphalt or gravel, it is not a disadvantage at all in my experience.</p>

<p>If you currently are planning a biketouring trip and still are unsure of how to pack all the gear, I hope I could inspire you to try this or a similar setup. It has handled lots and lots of rain 🌧 really well, kept me well hydrated and fed, with easy access to all my gear. I also found it cool to find with <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/">Bikester</a> a Store in Europe which carries a lot of gear from <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/revelate-designs/">Revelate Designs</a> but also many other brands - like <a href="https://www.bikester.fi/vaude/">Vaude</a>! Shipping from Bikester was super-quick, with some of the kit being with me in Vaasa after just two days after ordering, for no extra costs! In the end I am very satisfied with this setup, and can’t wait to head out with the bike for a trip and camping out!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503965469/in/dateposted/" title="Side View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503965469_78492a577e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Side View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503474373/in/dateposted/" title="Selfielicious"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503474373_67bd0f2305_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfielicious" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> (and you get great discount codes from partners - you could save 20% on your next purchase!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51503246761/in/dateposted/" title="Ready to roll"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51503246761_1976184483_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ready to roll" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[woom OFF AIR Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/07/woom-off-off-review.html"/>
    <updated>2021-07-22T09:26:39+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/07/woom-off-off-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After many years of riding very happily on his <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/woom-bikes/">woom Bikes</a> it was once again to size up to the next one - but this time we decided to for the woom OFF AIR as it will allow us to go explore the local Mountain Bike trails! It of course also works great for riding to school and to the beach, as we have seen during the past three months, but it really shines on trails!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327790178/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 in its natural habitat"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327790178_7dcd01ab76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 in its natural habitat" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>The woom Bike was provided for free to us for this review. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>The <a href="https://woom.com/de_DE/fahrraeder/off-air-6">woom AIR OFF 6</a> is my son’s third woom Bike in four years - we started with the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">woom 4</a> in 2018, a great bike which our smallest is starting to ride now. In 2019 we got the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/07/woom-bikes-because-also-kids-deserve-great-bikes.html">woom 5</a> which he rode very happily in all seasons for nearly two years, before now in 2021 getting the woom OFF AIR 6. The numbers in Sizing of the woom Bikes is brilliant, it makes it very easy to know which bike to get next - and the Bikes themselves also grow nicely with the kids, and often can be used over a year or two as you can adjust the seat and handlebar. That just as a side note - now onwards to the woom OFF AIR 6.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51326855692/in/dateposted/" title="Downhill with the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51326855692_e19283d706_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Downhill with the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The first question probably is: Why the woom OFF AIR 6 and not a regular <a href="https://woom.com/de_DE/fahrraeder/woom-6">woom 6</a> or the <a href="https://woom.com/en_INT/bikes/off-6">woom OFF</a>? The answer is easy: The woom OFF AIR 6 gives us more possibilities. The possibility to go ride MTB Trails and some easier Downhill Trails - things the regular woom 6 also can do, but which are more comfortable, fun and safe with the woom OFF AIR. If you want your kids to go outdoors instead of sitting inside and playing video games all day, then good equipment is key in our experience. And getting the kids to want to go outside means they spend all that energy on something useful - in this case riding their bikes in nature - instead of fighting, nagging and other unproductive stuff. So, good gear gets the kids outside where they exhaust their power, and everyone in the family benefits 😊</p>

<p>The Specs of the OFF AIR are made for trail riding, with hydraulic disc brakes, an hydraulic air suspension fork with 80 mm travel, SRAM X5 gears and Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires for maximum grip on the trails. My son finds the woom saddles very comfortable and also long or rocky rides are no problem. Equally the handlebar grips are comfortable, with the brake and shifting levers in easy reach of smaller children hands. The bike also comes with flat pedals which is nice, so you don’t need to go hunt for some pedals when the bike arrives. Finally, the geometry of the bike is good for pedalling and not too aggressive, which means the bike also can be used for riding to school and the beach. You can check out the full specs on the woom website and be delighted about the high-quality components woom used on this kid’s bike - they are great!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327790363/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 backside"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327790363_8ce1ee8e68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 backside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327589981/in/dateposted/" title="Brakes on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327589981_0a2edcdf0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Brakes on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328581330/in/dateposted/" title="SRAM X5 Gears on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328581330_4bb6796112_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SRAM X5 Gears on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This being a woom bike obviously also means it is light, something which is SO IMPORTANT for a kids bike that I can not stress it enough. The woom OFF AIR 6 weighs just 11 kg as it is made from high-quality 6061 T6 aluminum (with butted and hydroformed tubes), which makes this a nimble bike on the trails and despite “only” nine gears my son was racing up the hills and it was a joy to watch - if you ever had your child complain about not wanting to ride an uphill, you know what I mean! On the downhill and the singletrack trails the bike reacts fast and gets through tight corners with ease - even if these corners are full of roots and rocks. And even without much training it was easy for my son to lift the fork over obstacles like trees on the trail, which is another benefit of the light build and the good geometry.</p>

<p>Something I liked was that the bike has high-quality 6 x 2.35″ Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires with the addition of the ADDIX SPEED rubber compound, which makes the tires more durable. It’s great to see woom giving their bikes high-quality tires instead of cutting corners and saving some €£$ and go with cheaper non-branded ones. These Schwalbe tires have a low rolling resistance and great grip on trails and gravel roads alike. The tires are high-volume which means they helps absorb some vibration and provide a plusher ride compared to skinnier tires. I didn’t really care for the Car-type valves for easy filling at any gas station, but happily our tire pump has an adapter for these so it’s just a small issue =) You probably have noticed on the photos that the woom OFF AIR has thru-axles on both the front and rear wheel. These provide superior stability in comparison to the quick-release skewers you’ll find on most kids bikes, and shows once more the bike’s trail credentials.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328580575/in/dateposted/" title="Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328580575_6522da691e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328580935/in/dateposted/" title="Top View of the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328580935_d091b96cb7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Top View of the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now the Suspension fork is made my RST, it is an AIR fork as the name suggests which means you’re easily able to adjust the pressure to the weight of your child. The Suspension fork works great (and also gets a lot of use, even on normal non-trail rides 😊), with the stanchions sliding effortlessly through the lowers with a super smooth feel, without any noticeable friction. The rebound is smooth, even with the lower pressure we put on it as our son is lightweight. The 80 mm of the AIR fork provide plenty of travel for most types of riding, and it has a lockout switch which is useful on longer climbs. Once I explained what it’s for and how to use it, it was also easy to operate by my son himself. If you feel your child doesn’t need a suspension fork - there’s the <a href="https://woom.com/en_INT/bikes/off-6">woom OFF</a> which comes with a rigid, light carbon fork and which is only 9,3 kg heavy in Size 6. It’s also cheaper than the AIR version, but otherwise nearly identical to the OFF AIR 6 in this review.</p>

<p>The handlebars on the woom OFF AIR 6 are 680 mm wide, which is a good size for our son. Sure, you could have a wider handlebar but he feels this is fine at the moment and does not need to be changed. In the beginning my son had some problems with the SRAM trigger shifter on the OFF AIR, as he was used to the grip-shifter found on his old woom bikes. After I explained how to use them (something you always should do, it’s too easy to think “<em>They will know!</em>” as an adult!) he is now easily shifting gears - though still sometimes forget on an uphill climb that he can shift in a lower gear 😆</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327590491/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327590491_2a09b25115_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327791083/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork Lock Switch"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327791083_5130204c03_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork Lock Switch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327590156/in/dateposted/" title="Suspension fork on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327590156_77d094afc7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Suspension fork on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327790878/in/dateposted/" title="Handlebars on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327790878_1a17220902_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Handlebars on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328581185/in/dateposted/" title="Brakes and SRAM Trigger Shifter on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328581185_da53bd1644_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Brakes and SRAM Trigger Shifter on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We have not rode on very technical trails (as in, very rocky and full of roots) yet, but on the “normal” trails here in Vaasa with a normal amount of roots and rocks the fork has absorb everything well. But it’s still a hard tail, so make sure your kid knows to have a good riding posture so it doesn’t get thrown around. I imagine my son should be fine to ride green and blue Trails in most Bike Parks with his woom OFF AIR 6, which means if you as a parent enjoy going to the Bike Park then with this Bike you can take your child along and don’t need to rent a bike!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327589291/in/dateposted/" title="Über STock &amp; Stein"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327589291_1b0e1f8d7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Über STock &amp; Stein" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328581430/in/dateposted/" title="Roll them planks!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328581430_e316cf547b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Roll them planks!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>In the end the <a href="https://woom.com/de_DE/fahrraeder/off-air-6">woom OFF AIR 6</a> is a great addition to our bike shed, and allows us to spend more time together in nature on our local trails. If your child is completely new to riding singletrack trails and easy downhill runs at the Bike Park, then this bike is a solid choice - also because with its light weight and child-friendly geometry it works well as a everyday bike for riding around town. But it’s obviously made for riding mountain bike trails, and that it does superbly - even with a beginner rider in the saddle. The suspension fork works great for our lightweight child, the hydraulic brakes make stopping a breeze, the SRAM X5 gears make climbing uphills fun and the Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires give the rider good grip and confidence on even the most loose surfaces. Overall we are very happy with the OFF AIR 6, and while we wish the bike would come with a quick-release seatpost collar to easier change the height of the seat, and internal cable routing, for more protection of the cables on trails, our son and us parents are very happy with this bike. I see us riding many trails in Finland and hopefully also Norway and Sweden in the future with this superb kid’s bike!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328580125/in/dateposted/" title="Going for the ramp!?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328580125_6694375297_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Going for the ramp!?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> (and you get great discount codes from partners - you could save 20% on your next purchase!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Switching Tires: Never Again Thanks To reTyre]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/07/switching-tires-never-again-thanks-to-retyre.html"/>
    <updated>2021-07-05T17:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/07/switching-tires-never-again-thanks-to-retyre</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I truly dislike switching tires on our bikes. Switching the tires on four bikes every autumn and spring is for me one of the most tedious jobs I have to do, and I try to pro-long this task until it’s no longer possible. All that changed with reTyre, though: Now switching tires is as easy as zipping up the fly of a tent!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292337700/in/dateposted/" title="Zippit"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292337700_b280609b80_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Zippit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This article was supported with equipment and financially by reTyre. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="installation">Installation</h2>

<p>Strangely, installing the <a href="https://rty.re/3yCIarN">reTyre One</a> made me happy. I wasn’t 100% sure if it would fit on my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Pelago Stavanger</a> bike as the reTyre One needs some “large” clearance but in the end I had plenty of space with room to spare. But from the start. Knowing that this might be the last time ever for me to switch tires on this bike, I was looking forward to installing the reTyre One. Installation was easy - I have many years practice in this after all, doing it for the three to four bikes of our family twice a year. Old tire off, reTyre One on, test-fitting to check clearance: Perfect, with plenty of room to spare for the Skins. The same procedure with the back wheel and then installing the <a href="https://rty.re/3yCIarN">Winter Traveler</a> Skin as we still had ice and snow on the roads back in March when I installed the reTyre One.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51290583167/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre One with the Winter Tarveler and Gravel Chaser Skins"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51290583167_807a6c0c3c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="reTyre One with the Winter Tarveler and Gravel Chaser Skins" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51290583707/in/dateposted/" title="Installed reTyre One"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51290583707_2d952535d7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Installed reTyre One" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292337575/in/dateposted/" title="Installed reTyre One 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292337575_1f076af9f3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Installed reTyre One 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292336680/in/dateposted/" title="Zippers on the Winter Traveler Skin"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292336680_c1f7af0583_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Zippers on the Winter Traveler Skin" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292336265/in/dateposted/" title="Zipping on the WInter Traveler SKin."><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292336265_c5995a5a71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Zipping on the WInter Traveler SKin." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I also want to briefly write about the installation of the Skins, which are zipped on to the reTyre One. The skins and the reTyre One have zippers which allows you to connect the Skin - and there’s four different Skins available for different cycling needs - to the reTyre One. The reTyre One itself is a fully functional bicycle tire - indeed I have been using it the past two months - but with the different Skins you’re able to put on a new “Tire” onto your bike without the hassle of actually switching the tire. Zipping on a Skin takes me about two Minutes and it’s even quicker taking it off. It’s a great way to adapt the bike to different terrains and seasons - zip on the Winter Traveler Skin as soon as the snow starts falling, and take them off in spring. Then just as easy I can zip on the <a href="https://rty.re/3hhzjpx">Gravel Chaser</a> Skin when I head bikepacking and offroad.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51291330496/in/dateposted/" title="Layers"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51291330496_71212b846c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Layers" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="riding-the-winter-traveler">Riding the Winter Traveler</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://rty.re/3yCIarN">Winter Traveler</a> Skin was my first experience of riding with the reTyre Skin System. We had a good winter this year in Vaasa and had snow till late March, with some more snow in April and even May. Especially the snow in April was a good way to see the benefit of these zip-on tyres: I already was riding with just the reTyre One but when the snow and subsequent ice came, it was easy to zip on the studded Winter Traveler tire in a few minutes and the I could continue to safely cycle in these <em>Takaa Talvi</em> conditions. reTyre has two different Winter Skins, besides the Winter Traveler which I am riding there’s also the Ice Racer which has more studs. The Winter Traveler however has been perfectly adequate for the icey roads I rode on, and I had no feeling of insecurity while riding with these tires in slippery conditions. I reserve long-term judgement for a later point in the future, but in the few weeks I rode them on snow and ice I was satisfied and can recommend them.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292338050/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre Winter Traveler Skin in the snow"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292338050_f4cdb57503_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="reTyre Winter Traveler Skin in the snow" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292046389/in/dateposted/" title="Studs on the Winter Traveler"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292046389_3a8fe30fce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Studs on the Winter Traveler" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51291510443/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre Winter Traveler Skin on ice"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51291510443_5cbf16e78e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="reTyre Winter Traveler Skin on ice" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292338085/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre Winter Traveler Skin on ice"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292338085_e9b5f87024_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="reTyre Winter Traveler Skin on ice" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>One of the best things about the Winter Traveler skins where however the ease of use to get rid of the “Winter Tires” once all the snow was gone. In a few seconds the Skins were off and I could ride on the reTyre One on the ice-free asphalt roads. What previously was accompanied by a few swear words when changing the complete tire was now done with a smile on my face =) I do not know how the zipper system will live up to prolonged use, dirt and the elements but thus far it has been a fantastic experience and worked flawless.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292044959/in/photostream/" title="reTyre One 1"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292044959_d8e8abbcd8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="reTyre One 1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="riding-the-retyre-one">Riding the reTyre One</h2>

<p>So the <a href="https://rty.re/3yCIarN">reTyre One</a> is not only the base tire to which you can zip-on skins, but it also is a fully functional bicycle tire on its own. I’ll test and use the <a href="https://rty.re/3hhzjpx">Gravel Chaser</a> Skin soon on a few bikepacking trips, but at the moment, when all my cycling is to the beach, supermarket, to different hobbies and around town the reTyre One feels like the perfect tire for my needs in town. It has good grip both on dry and wet surfaces (though with the current heatwave going on, we have had really little rain so no idea how it is on very wet surfaces). Besides the grip the rolling resistance is good =&gt; which means it is low and fast-rolling. I rode over the past 7 years a mix of different tires from different brands on my bikes, from smooth slicks for fast road cycling to hardcore gravel and downhill tires which were slower on Asphalt but had great, secure grip on offroad surfaces. I usually prefer something in the middle, with a tendency towards more offroad capabilities, but I really like how fast I can go with the reTyre One (you see, I go towards 40 and a fast bike is for me more attractive than a fast car!). Maybe also because I know how quickly I could zip on a more offroad worthy Skin to get that additional grip on gravel roads.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51291329671/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre One 3"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51291329671_7f4e12c2b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="reTyre One 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292045799/in/dateposted/" title="Summer Vibes with the reTyre One"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292045799_fb127a5b6d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Summer Vibes with the reTyre One" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The reTyre One is also very competitevely priced at 29,00 € - similar tires from other brands easily cost just as much or more (as you often pay for the brand name) while with the reTyre One you also get the additional benefit of its multifunctionality. For example, you could now get a pair of <a href="https://rty.re/3yCIarN">reTyre One</a> tires and use them for all you cycling this summer and autumn, and then get a pair of <a href="https://rty.re/3yCIarN">Winter Traveler</a> Skins in November, zip then on and continue using your bike without the massive hassle of switching tires the traditional way.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51291329976/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre One isn&#x27;t afraid of gravel"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51291329976_ec835b74b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="reTyre One isn&#x27;t afraid of gravel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Overall I am really happy with the reTyre One tire and the Winter Traveler Skin - the ease of use of zipping of the studded winter tire was amazing, and the reTyre One is a great tire for my everyday kind of cycling. Also, those blue details on the reTyre One look amazing - so 👍 for the great design! The Set of Winter Traveler and reTyre One are also similar in price, if not cheaper, than two pairs of tires - plus they use a lot less space than normal tires in storage!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51292045724/in/dateposted/" title="Thumbs up for reTyre"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51292045724_5b5e6f70a5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Thumbs up for reTyre" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>However, there’s maybe one thing that I hope reTyre will come out with in the future, and that’s a Tubeless Version of their reTyre One tire. I much prefer riding tubeless and while I always had tires with an inner tube on my Pelago Stavanger bike, I prefer the peace of mind of a Tubeless setup. Sure, the reTyre One has a puncture protection and with a Skin on there would need to be some serious sharp/ spikey thing 🌵 coming my way to give me a flat tire - though then I seem to have some knack for finding just these 😆 After three months of riding nothing like that has occurred yet, and I remain hopeful that it won’t.</p>

<p>In a future article I will share also my experiences with the <a href="https://rty.re/3hhzjpx">Gravel Chaser</a> Skin, so if you’re interested in that please keep subscribe via RSS or Follow along on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> where new articles always get posted, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51291510653/in/dateposted/" title="reTyre One checking out town"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51291510653_03ce608994_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="reTyre One checking out town" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> (and you get great discount codes from partners - you could save 20% on your next purchase!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Car in 2021: Still the Exception, and sometimes a Problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/06/no-car-in-2021-still-the-exception.html"/>
    <updated>2021-06-01T19:07:38+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/06/no-car-in-2021-still-the-exception</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We still don’t own a car, we still don’t want to own a car, and there’s still no alternatives to owning a car available in Vaasa (or any other small town in Finland/ Scandinavia) in 2021. It’s frustrating if you want to go to a hiking trail a bit further away with the family or if you have to pick up stuff you can not transport with a bike. And it makes me wonder: Will we still have to own a car in 2030 or will there soon come Mobility As A Service options also to smaller cities and towns?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51217433153/in/dateposted/" title="Find Your Car"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51217433153_5622a0eb81_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Find Your Car" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>In March 2019 I blogged that not owning a car isn’t a problem for us, as <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">we can do everything with the bike</a>. This still holds true 95% of the time today, but then there’s those 5%. Much of these 5% involve kid’s hobbies, especially during winter (so the time between November and April here in Vaasa), where it’s not easy to motivate kids (and adults) to ride at -15°C on badly ploughed roads to a swimming lesson in the evening - and back home. You might think: <em>“Don’t complain, just cycle there!”</em> and it’s definitely the attitude I also have - but forcing a child to go cycle in such weather is a sure way to make them hate the hobby as they don’t want to bother with the cycling there and back in such weather. So this past winter we cheated a bit, as we had a car loaned to us (I’m calling it “The Coffin” as it’s 30+ years old and has a lot of problems).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/872x51" title="Herbie"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51216467167_9417f69dee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Herbie" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hours">168 hours</h2>

<p>One Day has 24 hours and thus a week has 168 hours. We moved with the car around 3 hours a week, which means it sat 165 hours in the driveway - or 98,21% of the time. Is it worth it to own a car so that it can sit 98% of the time in your driveway? I think not. Sure, we are again an exception to this situation, as our neighbours have one, two, three, four or more cars sitting in their driveways and seem to move around with them a bit more than us (because we still cycle almost everywhere), but even they probably don’t move their cars for more than 20 hours a week - which would be 12% of the weekly hours and means a car is sitting idly on a parking spot for 78% of the week.</p>

<p>Do you see where I go with this? The majority of <strong>cars only stand around</strong>. Yes, it’s nice to jump in a heated car in winter and drive the 10 minutes to the swim lesson if there’s a snow storm raging outside. If you want to support a local restaurant it’s nice to go pick-up tasty Take-Away Food. Have to transport four bags of cement? That’s one easy ride with the car. But it still means the car stands around, in our case, 98% of the time. Which for me means it’s a waste of space (I don’t like that it blocks the bigger part of the driveway) and also resources, as even this loaned car has costs - gasoline for use, insurance, Parking fees in the city and electricity costs for pre-heating it in winter.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/AJDft6" title="Yellow"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51216467097_67c70c4755_b.jpg" width="766" height="1024" alt="Yellow" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="a-new-car">A New Car</h2>

<p>So over the past months we have had many discussions about if we should buy a car once <em>“The Coffin”</em> leaves us in a few weeks. There are happily many good Electric Car Alternatives available today, which at least make the driving part more environmentally friendly - I want to avoid buying a gasoline powered car for many reasons. Thus we looked at many small EVs or electric car alternatives - from the Arcimoto FUV over the Citroën Ami and Next e.Go to the BMW i3 and “bigger” cars like a Skoda Enyaq, Volkswagen ID.3/ ID.4 and even a Tesla. But we always came back to the same conclusion: We don’t want to buy a car. We don’t want to own a car. But for these two to three hours a week where a car is useful, it would be AMAZING to have easy access to a car without needing to travel (by bike or Taxi) to a pick-up point to get a loan car for an hour or less.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/n2706N" title="Tesla Model 3"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51217390878_a95a2d6368_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tesla Model 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="mobility-as-a-service">Mobility As A Service</h2>

<p>As we don’t want to own a car, we looked at Mobility as a Service Options. It would be great to have a MaaS Provider like <a href="https://www.greenmobility.com/fi/en/greenmobilitys-cities/">GreenMobility</a> in Vaasa, alas they are at the moment only in Helsinki (and Copenhagen, Gothenborg, Ghent and more). It’s a modern System that works with an App and the thing I like the most is that it are all Electric Vehicles and that it’s a Pay as you need System - so if you only need a car for driving 10 Minutes to the Swimming Hall, you pay for 10 minutes - all within the App. And something which is very convenient too is that Insurance is also included, and it should be very easy to find a Parking Spot thanks to the App and the VIP Parking Spots of GreenMobility in the cities they are. The single best thing is that you can unlock the car with the App, so if you see the car in on the street you simply can walk there, unlock it, and drive away. It’s super easy and really how I envision MaaS to work 🚙😊 And no, sadly this article isn’t sponsored by them!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51216485507/in/photostream/" title="GreenMobility App"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51216485507_de58f011c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="GreenMobility App" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="https://whimapp.com/helsinki/en/">Whim</a> is another MaaS Provider in Helsinki (and Turku, Vienna, and more) which is including even more options: You can easily buy a (seasonal) ticket for Public Transportation, rent a car, drive a Citybike, E-Scooter or a Taxi. It also works with an App and makes it very convenient to e.g. ride a Citybike to a Metro Stop, ride the Metro to your destination and then there walk (or use a E-Scooter) to your final destination. This has a lot more mobility options which makes it a great All-In-One Place to book transportation of any means.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Here’s an <a href="http://www.shapehelsinki.com/project/whimapp">interesting case study</a> on the creation of the Whim App.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In Helsinki you also have the <a href="https://citycarclub.fi/en">City Car Club</a>, a real innovator in the Car Sharing area as they exist since 1999. If you join you can use their cars to do your driving, from one hour to several days. There are many benefits to car sharing, like one car sharing car replaces between 8 - 10 private cars and there are less cars standing around (remember that in my example above our car would be standing around 165 hours a week!). Sharing a car with multiple neighbours or people from our neighbourhood could work great, as long as not everyone needs the car at the same time. There’s things like working out the insurance stuff and such, but generally car sharing would be a great way for us to have access to a car, but not owning a car. Sadly, such an option is currently not available in Vaasa, so we might need to bring up this idea with the neighbourhood.</p>

<p>A MaaS Provider which is available in Vaasa is 24Rent. Sadly they only have Vans available for renting, otherwise this would be a good opportunity to rent a car for short amounts of time. But if I need to transport large amounts of stuff, this will come in useful in the future!</p>

<p><em>Update 02.06.2021</em>: Matti from 24Rent reached out to me to inform me that they soon also will offer passenger cars in Vaasa for rent. And even better, they also have a service called <a href="https://24go.fi">24Go</a> which is already available in the Capital Region, Tampere, Lahti and Oulu and they also are planning on launching it to Vaasa at some point - which would another perfect solution for us as it works easy with an App and would allow us to loan a car for simply 15 minutes when needed!</p>

<h2 id="so-what-now">So what now?</h2>

<p>Yeah, that is a good question. If you don’t want to have a car standing around in your driveway for 98% of the time you are sadly in a minority, as most people seem to be happy to have one or more cars standing in front of their house. There’s no good MaaS Provider available in Vaasa (yet!) so currently the only option is to either start a Car Sharing Initiative in the neighbourhood/ city or get an own car. Happily right now it is summer, our daughter &amp; son are very enthusiastic about cycling, so for the next three months we won’t need to think too much about a car. But once November rolls around with lots of rain, darkness and then winter with snow and cold temperatures, the discussion of how to get to the Hobbies will come up again, and till then we’d like to have a viable solution on the table. Of course being able to drive to hiking trails which are a bit further away during the summer is nice, too! If you have an idea, feel free to reach out on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a>! And if you are living in Vaasa and want to start a car sharing initiative - get in touch, too 😎</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/1HNh1E" title="Defender"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51217184231_8eb5b9299b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Defender" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> (and you get great discount codes from partners - you could save 20% on your next purchase!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
