<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: woom bikes | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/woom-bikes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2021-09-23T10:18:11+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[woom OFF AIR Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/07/woom-off-off-review.html"/>
    <updated>2021-07-22T09:26:39+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2021/07/woom-off-off-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After many years of riding very happily on his <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/woom-bikes/">woom Bikes</a> it was once again to size up to the next one - but this time we decided to for the woom OFF AIR as it will allow us to go explore the local Mountain Bike trails! It of course also works great for riding to school and to the beach, as we have seen during the past three months, but it really shines on trails!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327790178/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 in its natural habitat"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327790178_7dcd01ab76_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 in its natural habitat" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>The woom Bike was provided for free to us for this review. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>The <a href="https://woom.com/de_DE/fahrraeder/off-air-6">woom AIR OFF 6</a> is my son’s third woom Bike in four years - we started with the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">woom 4</a> in 2018, a great bike which our smallest is starting to ride now. In 2019 we got the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/07/woom-bikes-because-also-kids-deserve-great-bikes.html">woom 5</a> which he rode very happily in all seasons for nearly two years, before now in 2021 getting the woom OFF AIR 6. The numbers in Sizing of the woom Bikes is brilliant, it makes it very easy to know which bike to get next - and the Bikes themselves also grow nicely with the kids, and often can be used over a year or two as you can adjust the seat and handlebar. That just as a side note - now onwards to the woom OFF AIR 6.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51326855692/in/dateposted/" title="Downhill with the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51326855692_e19283d706_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Downhill with the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The first question probably is: Why the woom OFF AIR 6 and not a regular <a href="https://woom.com/de_DE/fahrraeder/woom-6">woom 6</a> or the <a href="https://woom.com/en_INT/bikes/off-6">woom OFF</a>? The answer is easy: The woom OFF AIR 6 gives us more possibilities. The possibility to go ride MTB Trails and some easier Downhill Trails - things the regular woom 6 also can do, but which are more comfortable, fun and safe with the woom OFF AIR. If you want your kids to go outdoors instead of sitting inside and playing video games all day, then good equipment is key in our experience. And getting the kids to want to go outside means they spend all that energy on something useful - in this case riding their bikes in nature - instead of fighting, nagging and other unproductive stuff. So, good gear gets the kids outside where they exhaust their power, and everyone in the family benefits 😊</p>

<p>The Specs of the OFF AIR are made for trail riding, with hydraulic disc brakes, an hydraulic air suspension fork with 80 mm travel, SRAM X5 gears and Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires for maximum grip on the trails. My son finds the woom saddles very comfortable and also long or rocky rides are no problem. Equally the handlebar grips are comfortable, with the brake and shifting levers in easy reach of smaller children hands. The bike also comes with flat pedals which is nice, so you don’t need to go hunt for some pedals when the bike arrives. Finally, the geometry of the bike is good for pedalling and not too aggressive, which means the bike also can be used for riding to school and the beach. You can check out the full specs on the woom website and be delighted about the high-quality components woom used on this kid’s bike - they are great!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327790363/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 backside"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327790363_8ce1ee8e68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 backside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327589981/in/dateposted/" title="Brakes on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327589981_0a2edcdf0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Brakes on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328581330/in/dateposted/" title="SRAM X5 Gears on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328581330_4bb6796112_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SRAM X5 Gears on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This being a woom bike obviously also means it is light, something which is SO IMPORTANT for a kids bike that I can not stress it enough. The woom OFF AIR 6 weighs just 11 kg as it is made from high-quality 6061 T6 aluminum (with butted and hydroformed tubes), which makes this a nimble bike on the trails and despite “only” nine gears my son was racing up the hills and it was a joy to watch - if you ever had your child complain about not wanting to ride an uphill, you know what I mean! On the downhill and the singletrack trails the bike reacts fast and gets through tight corners with ease - even if these corners are full of roots and rocks. And even without much training it was easy for my son to lift the fork over obstacles like trees on the trail, which is another benefit of the light build and the good geometry.</p>

<p>Something I liked was that the bike has high-quality 6 x 2.35″ Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires with the addition of the ADDIX SPEED rubber compound, which makes the tires more durable. It’s great to see woom giving their bikes high-quality tires instead of cutting corners and saving some €£$ and go with cheaper non-branded ones. These Schwalbe tires have a low rolling resistance and great grip on trails and gravel roads alike. The tires are high-volume which means they helps absorb some vibration and provide a plusher ride compared to skinnier tires. I didn’t really care for the Car-type valves for easy filling at any gas station, but happily our tire pump has an adapter for these so it’s just a small issue =) You probably have noticed on the photos that the woom OFF AIR has thru-axles on both the front and rear wheel. These provide superior stability in comparison to the quick-release skewers you’ll find on most kids bikes, and shows once more the bike’s trail credentials.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328580575/in/dateposted/" title="Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328580575_6522da691e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328580935/in/dateposted/" title="Top View of the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328580935_d091b96cb7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Top View of the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now the Suspension fork is made my RST, it is an AIR fork as the name suggests which means you’re easily able to adjust the pressure to the weight of your child. The Suspension fork works great (and also gets a lot of use, even on normal non-trail rides 😊), with the stanchions sliding effortlessly through the lowers with a super smooth feel, without any noticeable friction. The rebound is smooth, even with the lower pressure we put on it as our son is lightweight. The 80 mm of the AIR fork provide plenty of travel for most types of riding, and it has a lockout switch which is useful on longer climbs. Once I explained what it’s for and how to use it, it was also easy to operate by my son himself. If you feel your child doesn’t need a suspension fork - there’s the <a href="https://woom.com/en_INT/bikes/off-6">woom OFF</a> which comes with a rigid, light carbon fork and which is only 9,3 kg heavy in Size 6. It’s also cheaper than the AIR version, but otherwise nearly identical to the OFF AIR 6 in this review.</p>

<p>The handlebars on the woom OFF AIR 6 are 680 mm wide, which is a good size for our son. Sure, you could have a wider handlebar but he feels this is fine at the moment and does not need to be changed. In the beginning my son had some problems with the SRAM trigger shifter on the OFF AIR, as he was used to the grip-shifter found on his old woom bikes. After I explained how to use them (something you always should do, it’s too easy to think “<em>They will know!</em>” as an adult!) he is now easily shifting gears - though still sometimes forget on an uphill climb that he can shift in a lower gear 😆</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327590491/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327590491_2a09b25115_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327791083/in/dateposted/" title="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork Lock Switch"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327791083_5130204c03_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom OFF AIR 6 Air Fork Lock Switch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327590156/in/dateposted/" title="Suspension fork on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327590156_77d094afc7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Suspension fork on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327790878/in/dateposted/" title="Handlebars on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327790878_1a17220902_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Handlebars on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328581185/in/dateposted/" title="Brakes and SRAM Trigger Shifter on the woom OFF AIR 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328581185_da53bd1644_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Brakes and SRAM Trigger Shifter on the woom OFF AIR 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We have not rode on very technical trails (as in, very rocky and full of roots) yet, but on the “normal” trails here in Vaasa with a normal amount of roots and rocks the fork has absorb everything well. But it’s still a hard tail, so make sure your kid knows to have a good riding posture so it doesn’t get thrown around. I imagine my son should be fine to ride green and blue Trails in most Bike Parks with his woom OFF AIR 6, which means if you as a parent enjoy going to the Bike Park then with this Bike you can take your child along and don’t need to rent a bike!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51327589291/in/dateposted/" title="Über STock &amp; Stein"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51327589291_1b0e1f8d7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Über STock &amp; Stein" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328581430/in/dateposted/" title="Roll them planks!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328581430_e316cf547b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Roll them planks!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>In the end the <a href="https://woom.com/de_DE/fahrraeder/off-air-6">woom OFF AIR 6</a> is a great addition to our bike shed, and allows us to spend more time together in nature on our local trails. If your child is completely new to riding singletrack trails and easy downhill runs at the Bike Park, then this bike is a solid choice - also because with its light weight and child-friendly geometry it works well as a everyday bike for riding around town. But it’s obviously made for riding mountain bike trails, and that it does superbly - even with a beginner rider in the saddle. The suspension fork works great for our lightweight child, the hydraulic brakes make stopping a breeze, the SRAM X5 gears make climbing uphills fun and the Schwalbe Rocket Ron tires give the rider good grip and confidence on even the most loose surfaces. Overall we are very happy with the OFF AIR 6, and while we wish the bike would come with a quick-release seatpost collar to easier change the height of the seat, and internal cable routing, for more protection of the cables on trails, our son and us parents are very happy with this bike. I see us riding many trails in Finland and hopefully also Norway and Sweden in the future with this superb kid’s bike!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/51328580125/in/dateposted/" title="Going for the ramp!?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/51328580125_6694375297_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Going for the ramp!?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> (and you get great discount codes from partners - you could save 20% on your next purchase!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[woom Bikes - because also kids deserve great Bikes!]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/07/woom-bikes-because-also-kids-deserve-great-bikes.html"/>
    <updated>2019-07-31T14:03:31+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/07/woom-bikes-because-also-kids-deserve-great-bikes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How do you ensure that your child likes to ride its bike, come rain, sunshine or snow? In our opinion it’s by giving it a bike which it likes and which works well throughout the seasons!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421710247/in/photostream/" title="Speeding up on the woom 5"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421710247_34bc7ced8a_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Speeding up on the woom 5" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>The woom Bike was provided for free to us for this review. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>That we are a family which ride their bikes year-round I <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">wrote earlier this year</a>, and now I want to shed a bit of light on the latest addition to our bike shed: The <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/5?ls=en">woom 5</a>. woom makes bikes exclusively for kids, and that you can see in their products: They are made for the needs of kids, and not just some fancy, miniaturised version of an adult bike. The woom bikes are light, safe for the rider and safe in traffic, and there’s a host of functional and pretty accessories available for the bike. That they do it for kids you can see for yourself when you have a woom bike in front of you, as around 85% of their bike parts are individually designed and produced exclusively for woom, customized to fit the needs of small anatomies.</p>

<p>Now we have owned several non-woom bikes for our kids before we made the switch, and I have done plenty of research on the topic, too. One thing you’ll read in review after review is that the lighter a kids bike is, the better it is for the child. From our own experience with some very cheap kids bikes which were heavy as two bags of cement we can confirm: The lighter the bike, the more fun the rider has. woom bikes are around 40% lighter than comparable kids bikes, so as an ultralight backpacker this is obvious very positive, too. But enough about facts and stats, lets dive in to our subjective observations of riding the bike for almost three months.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421564311/in/dateposted/" title="Riding is fun!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421564311_d2e930696c_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Riding is fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421736537/in/dateposted/" title="At the Beach"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421736537_691a52b43b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="At the Beach" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now our son was already riding a woom 4 which he and we loved, but the one thing which became obvious as time went on was that the bike got too small for him. The <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/4?ls=en#section-product">woom 4</a> is made for kids between a height of 115 and 130 cm, though realistically I’d say that after 125 cm one should switch to the bigger bike. The woom 5 is made for kids between a height of 125 and 145 cm, and for our son it’s right now the perfect bike. Where in the past I had to say several times on a trip “Please cycle faster!” nowadays, since he’s on the woom 5, I have to ask him to slow down. He’s soooo fast on the new bike that he really likes to challenge us to races, and often enough wins! Thanks to the adjustable seat post and the vario stem the bike grows with him, and we hope that he’ll be able to ride this bike for a year or two (and that simply depends on how fast he grows!).</p>

<p>Going fast also means he needs to brake, and the the V-Brakes on the bike are so good that it takes little effort for him to stop safely. The SRAM X4 8-speed derailleur and the easy grip shift make switching gears easy as pie when we go up hills or ride into the wind, and the tires it comes with have a low rolling resistance and great grip from asphalt to single track trails and gravel roads. The Geometry also is great, because he can easily get on and off the bike and if he wants to stand on his feet, for example when taking in a view or waiting at a stop light, the top tube is at a friendly height.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421563356/in/dateposted/" title="Exploring"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421563356_53ecf3db20_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Exploring" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421564006/in/dateposted/" title="Should we stop for coffee and waffles?"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421564006_82cd350310_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Should we stop for coffee and waffles?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421712272/in/dateposted/" title="Taking in the view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421712272_7780173572_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Taking in the view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Just a few words on assembling the bike before we wrap up this review. The bike is delivered in a 120 x 62 x 22 cm box and weighs around 10 kg (the bike itself is 8,2 kg light), and it comes with all the tools you need to assemble the bike. You can add a host of useful accessories to the bike, from the mandatory <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/schutzbleche?ls=en">Fenders</a> (which I yet have to install!) over the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-kickstand-2018?ls=en">Kickstand</a> to the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/vienna-bell?ls=en">bell</a>. We also got a Size L <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-helmet?ls=en">woom Helmet</a> in the same colour as his bike, and while the previous helmet had some shortcomings we hope this one will survive the next Finnish winter. It is, other than the problem with the extreme cold, a great helmet which is well ventilated, easy to adjust and our son can open and close it easily thanks to the magnetic buckle closure.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421712507/in/dateposted/" title="woom Helmet &#x3D; Safe Head"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421712507_3d2e6f5f6f_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="woom Helmet &#x3D; Safe Head" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421711987/in/dateposted/" title="Single Trail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421711987_d9a7b32f9b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Single Trail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All in all our son and us are very happy with the latest addition to our bike shed. He enjoys cycling now even more (as he can go so fast) and a lot of his friends have come up to him and wanted to ride his cool bike. I keep on repeating myself, but he cycles fast thanks to the bigger tires and the correct size for his height, and I think we’ll try to squeeze in some bike trips before winter is coming as he seems to be able to easily ride 40 km a day with some ice cream and Pulla breaks in-between. I also intend to go ride some easy single trails with him here in Vaasa, as he has enjoyed the short bits where we were riding in the forests a lot.</p>

<p>So to sum things up, if you want that your child enjoys cycling then the best thing you can do is get them a bike which makes them want to ride. The <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/5?ls=en">woom 5</a> definitely is such a bike for our son, as he loves to ride (fast!) on it, be it to school, to the beach or the ice cream parlour. The bike is safe, handles really well, is specially made for kids with great attention to details and easy to maintain for me. We are looking forward to many more rides together, both in town and on trails!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48421562801/in/dateposted/" title="A small break"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48421562801_629c19ca1e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="A small break" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Car, No Problem: Urban Family Transportation]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html"/>
    <updated>2019-03-29T21:05:38+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/urban-family-transportation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Riding bikes is fun and healthy. Too bad too many people drive cars in our cities. <strong>Cars don’t belong in cities</strong> is a thought which we share in our family. Cars have their place, but for both humans and the environment, and also the aesthetics of our towns, it would be best if most of us would cycle to the grocery store, work and the cinema. That that is possible I want to show you in this article.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47434099322/in/dateposted/" title="Family cycling"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7888/47434099322_30dc75ef70_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Family cycling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>Some of the products in this article have been provided to us by the manufacturers. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>

<p>I admit that <strong>#FuckCarsRideBikes</strong> is probably the best Hashtag I have invented. I dislike cars as they illustrate what is wrong with our cities &amp; towns: Everywhere we have multi-lane streets so that thousands of people who sit <em>alone</em> in their car can drive from A to B. What’s wrong about this is that the distances these people drive <strong>ALONE</strong> in their cars is statistically less than 5 km, or the distance which most of the readers of this blog hike in an hour in the hills or would be able to ride on a bike in 20 to 30 minutes. Add in that nowadays seemingly every other car driver is distracted while checking his or her phone, our ageing societies mean that there are more people who are physically less able to drive <strong>safely</strong>, and the emissions from cars which are bad for our health and you start to realize that we need to get rid of the majority of cars in cities and towns. That that is possible and that one can thrive without a car and <strong>get everything done</strong> is what I want to show today, and hopefully encourage you to ride more on your bike and drive less in your car.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610376678/in/dateposted/" title="Jkl Uni"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7915/33610376678_b349aec085_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jkl Uni" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-from-a-to-b">How to get from A to B</h2>

<p>The kids have hobbies, need to be brought to school and kindergarden, there’s the occasional thing to pick up at the post office and groceries for cooking at home also need to be bought and brought home. Add in a visit to the cinema, going for lunch with colleagues, <a href="https://youtu.be/v0ae-3BQzFM">playing games with friends</a>, swimming at the beach and oh, yeah, showing up at the office for work is also smart. <strong>Can one <em>REALLY</em> do all that by bike?</strong> Well, yes 😊</p>

<p>Statistically most people use their cars for journeys of three to five kilometre in length, which if you think about it, is insane. I ride with my kids, with the trailer behind me and my son on his own bike, in 15 minutes to the centre of Vaasa, which is about three kilometre away from our house. Pretty much all of it is on cycling lanes, and in the centre there’s dozens of parking places for bikes so one never needs to ponder “Where do I park?”. It’s also free! If the weather is poor hardshells come on - living in a coastal town (= lots of wind, 🌬💨 all the time) means we are used to wearing a <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/windproof-jackets/?pid=10239">wind jacket</a> when we go outside - and when you arrive at the Café, Restaurant or school you take it off. No problem!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571687275/in/dateposted/" title="Parking for bikes"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7865/46571687275_0d5cbf2101_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Parking for bikes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This is not some kind of magic that only we can achieve. Most people have very short commutes and can do all of it by riding a bike, and did I mention that being on a bike is healthy and fun? I at least always feel very happy when I can ride my bike. I think the biggest hurdle to those who drive with a car everywhere is that they think that they can not cycle. The truth is - if you have learned to ride a bike, and own a bike, then you can bicycle. No one is expecting you to win the <a href="https://www.transcontinental.cc">Transcontinental Race</a> or going <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/10/active-holidays-in-are-sweden.html">Downhill mountain biking</a> but you likely just want go to the Café or to the beach. You also don’t need to sell your car and go all in, but gradually try what you all can do by bike. Cycle to work two days a week, instead of taking the car to the gym take the bike to go grocery shopping, and if you want to go out and meet friends why not go cycle to that lovely Café instead of taking the car? If you slowly phase out the use of a car you’ll see that going by bike everywhere is easy - and not just for adults, also kids love to ride their bike. The smile my 3 year old daughter gives me when we cycle together is amazing, and while this obviously only are short distances like going to the Kindergarden, the playground and the library bus, it still allows her to get used to cycling. For longer distances she sits in the Thule Chariot, which is also great to transport stuff. And if it doesn’t fit on the bike or in the trailer I take the bus or use a Taxi. By not owning a car we save a minimum of 400€ per month on car-related expenses, and that are even in Finland quite a few Taxi rides.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614273578/in/dateposted/" title="Happy Cycler"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7926/33614273578_e6c06abdf3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happy Cycler" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-bikes">The Bikes</h2>

<p>Now I have been talking so much about our bikes - time to take a look at them! I have written before about my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/11/pelago-bicycles-stavanger.html">Pelago Stavanger</a> which I am now riding since five years. I bought for my wife some years ago a <a href="https://www.pelagobicycles.com/bicycles/airisto-commuter.html">Pelago Airisto</a> which she loves, and with both of these bikes we can pull the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/thule-chariot-cross2-kinderanhaenger/?pid=10239">Thule Chariot 2</a> where our daughter sits and rides with us. The Airisto is a fantastic bike and I got my wife the front basket as it makes transporting things so much easier. The Airisto also performs well for bike tours - we cycled for a week on Åland with these bikes and had a lot of fun.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40520962753/in/dateposted/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7922/40520962753_23798cdaea_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571688285/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7917/46571688285_5aa533fa0f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Our son is on his fourth bike, and since about a year he is riding the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/4?ls=en">woom 4 children’s bike</a> which has been his best bike to date. It’s not just light and grew with him, it also has 8 gears which made cycling up hills and in winter a lot easier. The bike handles very well (especially if compared to his older bikes) and it’s a pleasure to see him ride his bike proudly and having fun. A good bike which is the right size and easy to use makes all the difference in getting a child being willing to ride a bike year-around, from spring till winter, and the woom 4 certainly has made it easier for us parents to go cycling together - because the bike works flawlessly. We also have cycled some longer rides around Vaasa with him, and thanks to his woom bike he’s able to cycle up to 20 km without a problem.</p>

<p>Our son is wearing the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-helmet?ls=en">woom Helmet</a> which is good, though it’s not really made for the cold weather of Finland and the width adjustment knob broke in the middle of winter - we have been using the Helmet now in the max. size, which is either way what we needed. It’s a light and well-ventilated helmet and stands up to daily use. Similarly the <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-radlicht">woom bike lights</a> had a battery which had problems coping with the Finnish winter, it only worked on a charge for a day or two max and then needed recharging, though I imagine this is not a problem in warmer climates. And we also got the easy to use <a href="https://woombikes.com/products/woom-radschloss?ls=en">woom chain lock</a>. You can put in your own code (and can change it easily, too) so that way the bike can always be securely locked when at school or in town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571691295/in/dateposted/" title="woom 4"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7865/46571691295_12bb9d92f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="woom 4" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571691555/in/dateposted/" title="Summer cycling in Vaasa"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7814/46571691555_271e76e918_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Summer cycling in Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47434095572/in/dateposted/" title="woom 4 + woom Helmet"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7916/47434095572_a59a09ed9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="woom 4 + woom Helmet" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Thule Chariot 2 is an amazing trailer and honestly the most important piece of cycling gear for a family with small kids which wants to rely less on the car. The <a href="http://bit.ly/2FxaMIU">Chariot 2</a> has allowed us to transport both kids at the same time when they were younger, we can use it to transport large packages and it makes grocery shopping a breeze as you can fit a child and the groceries for a week in it with room to spare. We also have travelled with the bikes and the trailer on <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/08/cycling-and-bouldering-on-aland.html">Åland</a> which was an amazing trip which combined the bikes, train and ferry for a lovely week of cycling in the Archipelago. The Thule Chariot also has flown with us when the kids were smaller, as it can be converted into a pram in one minute (or a sled if there’s enough snow!). This really is an amazing piece of equipment which is integral to our family not having a car, and I can foresee that even when our 3-year old daughter is old enough to cycle herself that we might keep the trailer for a while as it is so damn easy to transport large things with it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47434099002/in/dateposted/" title="Thule Chariot 2 Transporter"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7863/47434099002_f54316e494_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Thule Chariot 2 Transporter" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571689175/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7800/46571689175_b8ac2a62d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Airisto + Thule Chariot 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610375218/in/dateposted/" title="Family cycling in Vaasa"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7896/33610375218_358a20220e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Family cycling in Vaasa" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614272628/in/dateposted/" title="Cycle Touring on Åland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7828/33614272628_29bff33595_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cycle Touring on Åland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46768405674/in/dateposted/" title="Thule Chariot 2 in the rain"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7857/46768405674_b0f7f378fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Thule Chariot 2 in the rain" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Speaking of transporting, my <a href="https://www.trekbikes.com/us/en_US/bikes/adventure-touring-bikes/920/920/p/21996/">Trek 920 Disc</a> has been an amazing bike for both transporting, urban commutes, fun rides and adventures. I can transport an unreasonable amount of stuff on it thanks to the two racks, and especially the front rack is one of the best things on a bike, ever (<em>Seriously, if there’s one thing you should get for your bike it is a front rack!</em>). I love this bike and even more after I made it <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/08/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit.html">tubeless</a> two years ago. If it would allow me to pull the Thule Chariot I probably would own only this one bike.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40524987693/in/dateposted/" title="Trek 920 All loaded up"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7886/40524987693_3f0f1a2faa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Trek 920 All loaded up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46571686395/in/dateposted/" title="Cockpit view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7897/46571686395_eb521756db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cockpit view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As we are a family and we have to transport kids, groceries and parcels every now and then, I think you understand why we are dreaming of a Cargobike. <a href="https://www.bakfiets.nl">There’s</a> <a href="http://www.larryvsharry.com">just</a> <a href="https://yubabikes.com">too</a> <a href="https://sblocs.bike">many</a> <a href="http://www.workcycles.com">options</a> and they’re also all a bit pricey, but maybe in the future we will change from the Thule Chariot to a Cargobike for transporting…</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40115659892/in/album-72157665520832018/" title="SBlocs Cargo Bike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/4720/40115659892_5b5a2abb36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="806" alt="SBlocs Cargo Bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s the kick bike which our kids used when they were small. We had a <a href="https://www.puky.de/en/home">Puky</a> kick bike for both kids, and our daughter has been riding it since she was 1,5 years old. It’s something she really enjoys a lot and she is pretty good at it, and when we go to the playground, for a walk or to the library bus she takes the kick bike as that way the longer distances are no problem for her.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610373888/in/photostream/" title="Loving to bike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7836/33610373888_00e0ca4350_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Loving to bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33610374408/in/dateposted/" title="Learning to bike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7892/33610374408_d270d6610c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to bike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="come-rain-come-sunshine-we-ride">Come Rain, come Sunshine, we Ride</h2>

<p>Riding our bikes in any weather - from damn slippery roads to the rain and hot 30°C days - needs a little planning garment-wise, though as you’re likely a backpacker or skier you have everything you need to ride in any climate. We just use our hiking garments for cycling, the most important thing is that they have a good freedom of movement. A wind or rain jacket and a rain pants are needed in foul weather, while in the summer we cycle in shorts and T-shirts. My wife and kids use a Helmet while I only use one on long bike rides - because <a href="https://www.bicycling.com/news/a24110027/bike-helmet-safety/">it’s OK to not wear a helmet</a>, as bicycle lanes make cycling safe and not a helmet. <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/gloves/recommended-use--cycling/?pid=10239">Windproof gloves</a> make sure your hands don’t freeze solid (they’re also recommended in windy summers as warm hands make cycling a lot more fun).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614272908/in/dateposted/" title="Rocking the Puky Kickbike"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7856/33614272908_075dbb2416_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Rocking the Puky Kickbike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That’s really it what ones need to transporting oneself from A to B by bicycle - yes there’s lots of fancy things one can add to the bike but a basic bike, some gloves, maybe a helmet and depending on the weather a wind or rain jacket are all that is needed. In the future I’ll write more about useful accessories for cycling, but that’s not the focus of this post!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40524988183/in/dateposted/" title="Cycling to go skiing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7863/40524988183_1c28c90e01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cycling to go skiing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614273378/in/dateposted/" title="Pelago Stavanger Cockpit"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7862/33614273378_ebbb6f6882_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pelago Stavanger Cockpit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="cant-do-without-car">Can’t do without car?</h2>

<p>If you can not be without a car - because you actually life far away from civilization - I would encourage you to at least not drive alone. Share a car with a neighbour or two, drive together, make less trips and if your car is old get a car which is fuel-efficient or is an electric car. Generally, sharing the car and driving together makes the use of a motorized vehicle more acceptable. Alternatively you could try a e-Bike as these allow you to go a bit faster and further without too much of your own muscle power, or have a look at something like the <a href="https://www.arcimoto.com">Arcimoto</a> if it needs to be a vehicle.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23170406440/in/album-72157659581645884/" title="Cabo da Roca"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/5701/23170406440_011dc7899e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cabo da Roca" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="go-ride-your-bike">Go Ride Your Bike!</h2>

<p>I hope you see it is easy, fun and healthy to not drive everywhere in a car and that using the bike for transportation in an urban environment makes a lot of sense. There’s no searching for a parking spot, you don’t need to go to the gym, you’re outside at the fresh air and are having fun. Having good bikes for the kids and getting them used from an early age to cycling helps to instil a happiness to bicycle everywhere in them, and also makes them more independent as you as a parent don’t need to drive them everywhere. So in conclusion I hope that you now, with the beginning of spring, try to cycle more! After all - it’s fun, healthy and allows you to be more outside, and isn’t that what we all enjoy the most?!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40524987853/in/dateposted/" title="Spring Races"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7902/40524987853_2430810228_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Spring Races" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33614272478/in/dateposted/" title="Åland scenary"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7877/33614272478_4dbe015350_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Åland scenary" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
