<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2021-03-29T16:26:29+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[10 Years Hiking in Finland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/05/10-years-hiking-in-finland.html"/>
    <updated>2019-05-06T18:57:43+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/05/10-years-hiking-in-finland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ten years on and I am still blogging, photographing and enjoying the outdoors. <em>A look back at a decade of outdoor blogging.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40820176213/in/dateposted/" title="Yo!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/40820176213_c2bc289f33_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Yo!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-beginning">The Beginning</h2>

<p>Ten years ago, at the beginning of April 2009, I opened up my blog at the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/archives/">hikinginfinland.com</a> domain (<em>actually, back then I was still at Blogspot, but that changed soon</em>). Why did I start my blog? Well, I’ll need to start a few years earlier for that story.</p>

<p>In 2008 I hiked with my best friend Martin on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2009/06/karhunkierros-i.html">Karhunkierros Trail</a> in Lapland. Back then I was far from hiking ultralight, and both Martin and me hiked with well over 20 kg on our backs this popular trail in Finland. On the the last day, motivated by the thought of a nice warm Sauna at home, cold beers and Pizza, we hiked as fast as possible to reach the early bus from Kuusamo to Oulu. This is where things went wrong: Sitting in our sweaty and smoke-smelling clothes in the bus, a fire alarm went on in the bus toilet - NOT caused by us 😊. The Bus pulled over, and a few minutes later it was burning with meter high flames flickering in the sky. Not only did we miss our connecting train to Tampere, but also lost all our backpacking gear which burned to ash in the luggage compartment of the bus.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40820173553/in/dateposted/" title="And it burns, burns, burns"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/40820173553_4eacfc83e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="And it burns, burns, burns" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I still loved hiking, and so decided to buy with the insurance money new backpacking gear. But I remembered that carrying 20+ kg on my back didn’t add to a pleasurable experience, and so, little by little, I found out that <a href="">ultralight backpacking</a> was a thing. So why the blog?</p>

<p>Back then the Summit &amp; Valley blog, <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com">Chris Townsend</a> and a few others were a huge inspiration for me to start blogging. I enjoyed the accounts of Bristish backpackers going out into the hills and documenting their trips, and as I felt there was no blog documenting the hiking and backpacking possibilities in Finland I registered the Hiking in Finland domain without much thought for a brand name or such. I published trip reports, gear reviews, and even made videos back in 2009 already, though they were quite different from what I produce nowadays. Together with Roger, Joe, Jörgen, Martin and Gustav we founded <a href="https://www.facebook.com/nordiclightpacking/">Nordic Lightpacking</a> and even got together to go <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/06/the-ul-fellowship.html">backpacking in Vålådalen</a> in 2010.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46997178644/in/dateposted/" title="Ultralight Backpackers!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/46997178644_a578059447_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ultralight Backpackers!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Things took off for me well and magazines and companies started to ask if I could write and photograph for them. As the financial crisis from 2008 still made my work as an environmental management consultant quite hard, I decided to switch careers and have been working in this content creation, photography and outdoor business since 2011 full-time. Without this blog that wouldn’t have happened, and the amazing readers and friends I made during the last ten years helped me a lot so that I can work on my own with amazing outdoor brands, creating inspiring content from Northern Europe and across the globe. So thank you to the millions of readers who have read my articles over the last decade - it’s because of you that I am able to live this life!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46997177904/in/dateposted/" title="Cold"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/46997177904_08287fb6db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cold" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hiking-climbing-skiing">Hiking, Climbing, Skiing</h2>

<p>… as well as Packrafting, bikepacking and trailrunning are what I do mostly nowadays. Quickly I realized that limiting myself to only hiking would mean I’d sit six months a year inside, so on came the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/backcountry-cross-country-skiing.html">XC skis</a> in winter, and since four years I also go ski touring in Finland, Norway, Sweden, and the Alps. With over 180.000 Lakes in Finland the addition of a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/08/packrafting-in-finland-first-strokes.html">packraft</a> was a logical first step, and also <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/06/bikepacking-in-pirkanmaa.html">bikepacking</a> felt like a good way to explore my surroundings.</p>

<p>I was dabbling for some years in climbing but because of having small kids I never was able to train as much as I wanted, so lately I haven’t been climbing on ice or rocks that much, but with the kids growing fast I hope to get back into that activity at some point. I did pick up <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/08/my-trailrunning-gear.html">trailrunning</a> to stay fit as I can easily go run from the front of my house, and it is an activity which also gives me a good fitness for backpacking. Yes, backpacking, the activity of hiking and camping in nature, is still one of the best things in life. Even better, I am fortunate enough to call this work, mainly because I carry a camera, tripod and notepad with me when I go out, and am able to create compelling stories, photos and videos about my trips. It is something I truly love, because not only do I know that spending time is nature is healthy in many ways, it also inspires people to protect our planet better.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46997178234/in/dateposted/" title="Sun Pillar"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/46997178234_9af91b2e46_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sun Pillar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-future">The Future</h2>

<p><em>What is next?</em> you might think, and it is a good question. Ten years ago I already started to write and talk about the negative effects of climate change, but society was not ready for it. Now, in 2019, thanks to a 16-year old girl and the movement she has inspired, old politicians finally start to listen up and ponder the future of the human species and the planet (though I feel these old politicians simply will continue business-as-usual). I feel the time is right now for me to again start talking about how we outdoor enthusiasts can do small things which can make this planet better - from picking up other people’s trash which we find on the trail to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/03/urban-family-transportation.html">cycling more</a>, eating healthier and flying less.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40820176023/in/dateposted/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/40820176023_5b9c8da3ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As you might have seen on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> I enjoy making videos again, and most of my reviews and trips will feature a video. I love the creativity video allows me, both in shooting and editing, and it is something that I feel better communicates what I want to say. Don’t worry, this blog will not go away. I see this blog as my home base, a sustainable and lasting place for the content I create, from the much-loved <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/the-week-in-review/">The Week In Review</a> to trip reports and other content series. As I hate Instagram and equally despise Facebook I will spend less time on these necessary evils, but you will still be able to find me on Twitter and engage with me there. I also plan to give this blog an visual overhaul. The last one is too long ago, and I hope to find the time in 2019 to give this blog the look I wish it had. Don’t worry, it will not look like every other cookie-cutter blog out there but retain it’s quirkiness, although in a slightly less 90s-internet look 😂</p>

<p>Finally, I have to thank you, my readers, for returning for so long to read Hiking in Finland. It always makes me happy when I receive tweets, comments, Emails and messages from people who went to hike somewhere because of my trip reports, bought an item because of my review or decided to make a change because one of my ponderings. It is because of you that I create content, and it means so much to me to hear that it matters to you and that you enjoy it. Thank you for reading and following me ❤️</p>

<p>If you feel like you’d like to support me and say <strong>Thanks”</strong> my content, the best way to do so is via <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a>. It’s a monthly subscription and you can give as little as $3 per month to enable me to do what I do. As a reward you get to hang out with me on a chat server and can pick my brains on where to go hiking in Finland, what to pack and which shoes to wear, or we can discuss the latest Game of Thrones Episode! In that sense, <strong>Happy trails!</strong></p>

<p><em>All photos in this article are from 2009 and 2010.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46997177334/in/dateposted/" title="Back in the day"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/46997177334_87c4984569_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Back in the day" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Backpacking a Sustainable Hobby?]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/sustainable-backpacking.html"/>
    <updated>2019-03-21T19:26:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/03/sustainable-backpacking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being outdoors, sleeping in nature, hiking through the forest, paddling on rivers and cycling on beautiful single trails - being outdoors seems on a first look to be a very sustainable hobby. But is it really?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199759745/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Storådörren Valley from the other side n better weather"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1903/44199759745_b4b7e1753e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Storådörren Valley from the other side n better weather" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>This article is part of the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde</a> Series of “Sustainable Outdoors” and several bloggers write about this topic - you can find a list with the other articles at the end. We are not paid to write these articles and have full editorial control.</em></p>

<p>Going outdoors feels like a sustainable hobby - especially if you compare it to sports and hobbies which need large buildings or areas to be played &amp; practiced. But is it really sustainable to drive in a big car to a trail head, being dressed in garments made from oil-based materials and hiking in sensitive areas which contributes to land erosion and degradation? That is a question which I am pondering in this article, so read along to find out what in my opinion are our biggest “sins” as backpackers.</p>

<h2 id="getting-there">Getting there</h2>

<p>Only very few of us life in nature and can start hiking or skiing from their doorstep - most of us life in towns and villages and need to travel to the start of a trail or to the hills. Those who read me since a while know that I neither have a driving license and our family also does not own a car. If I go backpacking somewhere it is always by public transportation, most usually a combination of train and bus when in Finland, or by ferry, plane and then bus or train when abroad. As I have been travelling like this since 20 years this is normal for me, but for those who have grown up with a car in front of their house this might seem strange. Yes, I am dependent on schedules and trains and busses to get somewhere, but I have learned to life with that and it usually works out nicely. My waiting time I use for reading and studying the map, or stocking up on calories!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33621497524/in/album-72157681559831330/" title="Bikepacking Season is upon us!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4160/33621497524_40fe81d861_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Bikepacking Season is upon us!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Getting to a local trail here in Pohjanmaa means either jumping on a bike or taking a bus or train and possibly a Taxi. Sometimes I make the bike ride part of the journey and just call it a <em>Bikepacking and Hiking Adventure</em> as cool and catchy names are important =) I really love to ride my bike and it’s my favourite way to get around when in town or if I’m travelling, it just feels great. Going by train or bus is fine, though - I can charge my phone and listen to music or chat on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Discord</a> and the speed is good and if going by bus I usually also can get off quite close to a trailhead and just hike the last bit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44739826010/in/dateposted/" title="Golden Hour"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7863/44739826010_b8ec02619e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Golden Hour" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>When going abroad flying is something I hate. I hate the noise, the people and the emissions I accumulate while travelling by plane, but for long distances in a short time there’s no alternative for me right now. I am cutting down on my flights and assignments abroad drastically, though, and each trip I can realize by taking the ferry, train, bus and Taxi are a win in my book. Plus going by plane also often means I have to add a night in an <a href="https://www.airbnb.ca/c/hmorkel">AirBnB</a> or Hotel at the beginning or end, depending on the connections at the destination to get where I want to go which adds to the costs and length of a trip. But some trips are just too good to miss out on, like my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/06/hiking-the-causeway-coast-way.html">Causeway Coast Way thru-hike</a> or backpacking on the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/snow-and-sunshine-on-the-via-dinarica.html">Via Dinarica</a> in Bosnia Herzegovina. These were amazing hikes and totally worth getting into a plane for, and also the John Muir Trail is high on my list, as well as several other trails abroad.</p>

<p>My take-away for <strong>getting there</strong> is probably to try to enjoy your local outdoors as much as possible. I know I am guilty of dreaming and hiking on distant trails, while I have a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/pack-sail-rafting-in-the-kvarken-archipelago.html">UNESCO Natural World Heritage Site</a> on my doorstep which would be great for packrafting, cycling and hiking. But the benefits of hiking locally are so many: You can hike more - have a free afternoon and day ahead? Just go to a local trail for a night out! Take the bike instead of the car if you feel like it, and for longer trips why not explore more of your own country?! If you fly somewhere for your yearly long backpacking trip - and you can! - <a href="https://mossy.earth/collections/carbon-offsetting">offset your emissions</a> by supporting reforestation measures or similar.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45049302961/in/dateposted/" title="Umeå C"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1975/45049302961_acef721b0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Umeå C" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-gear">The Gear</h2>

<p>Another topic which we have to ponder is how sustainable our outdoor gear is. Unless you use exclusively natural materials like cotton, hemp, flax, wood or Merino wool chances are you have something that’s made from oil =&gt; plastic in any form or shape (it can be called Dyneema, XPac, Cuben fibre, Polyester, Nylon, Cordura or or or). The good thing is that most of our outdoor gear is so well made that it can last us a life-time with some proper care, so the environmental footprint of a tent which gets used several times per year is relatively small after 15 years of use.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9797321574/in/album-72157634403205347/" title="HMG UltaMid in a wet forest"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5502/9797321574_0b9435d015_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="HMG UltaMid in a wet forest" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Also, most new outdoor equipment is made from recycled or recyclable materials which is an amazing step forward. I remember my first <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/07/outdoor-news-i.html">OutDoor</a> where the sustainability topic was still in it’s baby shoes and I had more the feel of “Greenwashing” here and there. But now, five years later, it’s front and centre for many companies, and one of their most important messages. From <a href="http://bit.ly/2UNDeN1">Patagonia</a> who doesn’t want you to buy their jackets to Houdini which lets you <a href="https://www.houdinisportswear.com/ca/sustainability/houdini-rental">rent their garments</a> instead of buying them, many companies wake up and realize we need to do something to keep our outdoors healthy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46495574344/in/album-72157678997220548/" title="100%"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7826/46495574344_e4e77a6ca4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="100%" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>But what’s even better is that many of our outdoor gear also can find it’s way into our everyday life. Don’t be dumb and only use your <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/hydro-flask-standard-mouth-with-standard-flex-cap/?pid=10239">Hydroflask</a> on the trail - take it with you when you go to work or walking the dog! Get a <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/primus-vacuum-commuter-mug-isolierbecher/?pid=10239">good mug</a> for your coffee on the go, and also your lunch can be packed in a Light My Fire meal box. I also wear my outdoor clothes all the time - my <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/houdini-womens-thrill-twill-mtm-pants-jeans/?pid=10239">hiking pants</a> are my every day pants as well, when I pick up my kids I wear my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody.html">Alpine Start Hoody</a> or a shell jacket and I don’t really use any other shoes than my trailrunning and hiking shoes. If you’re working at a office where a suit is mandatory you might not get away with wearing your outdoor garments all the time, but if your employer is relaxed about the dress code there’s no good reason why you can’t wear your flannel shirt and hiking trousers to the office.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47298836431/in/dateposted/" title="Time for some Coffee!"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7857/47298836431_ab751f6d7a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Time for some Coffee!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, instead of buying a new piece of kit once an old one is broken might not be necessary - many pieces of equipment can be fixed, from stoves to garments. If a rain jacket doesn’t keep the rain out anymore it often just needs a wash with a good detergent to re-activate its waterproof properties, and if a tear is too big you can have it often much more cheaply fixed than buying a new one.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35450694064/in/album-72157686898441076/" title="Unscrew everything!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4307/35450694064_e2e659e43d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Unscrew everything!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="land-degradation">Land degradation</h2>

<p>Land degradation and erosion is especially a problem at very popular trails and areas - from the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2009/06/karhunkierros-i.html">Karhunkierros</a> in Finland to certain trails in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/a-lake-district-traverse.html">Lake District</a> and elsewhere, where a lot of people hike or ski the earth under our feet gets eroded and with rain and wind popular trails quickly can look like deep scars in the landscape. Well built and maintained trails minimize this problem, and also we can - by choosing to hike on “less popular” trails. Now less popular does not equal less beautiful, and as many of us go into nature to escape busy cities it’s a smart thing to search out these less popular trails and enjoy them on your own.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29831354255/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Clearing up"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8528/29831354255_4688f96fa0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Clearing up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If a trail gets really popular then trail erosion is often the smallest problem - often rubbish which is left behind, from 💩 to plastic bottles and tissues - are a much bigger issue. What we as knowledgable outdoors men and women can do is to educate our fellow hikers when we catch them in the act, or collect the trash and carry it out. Carrying a small Ziplock bag for these situations is common for me, because I really hate it to see rubbish left in nature.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14221050166/in/album-72157644166894052/" title="The Old Man of Coniston"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5489/14221050166_7c850e257d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="The Old Man of Coniston" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline--what-you-can-do">Bottomline &amp; What you can do</h2>

<p>My conclusion is that being outdoors, be it hiking, backpacking, biketouring, packrafting or ski-touring is inherently a sustainable activity. By spending time outdoors in nature we learn to care more about our planet, and in the long run we will adapt many of the things I have suggested throughout this article, though if you’re at the start of your hiking career and just started with backpacking you can now of course skip ahead and pick up these good behaviours and ideas!</p>

<p>To sum them up, these would be my three take-aways:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Adventure more locally and take the bike, train and bus to get to the trailhead!</li>
  <li>Use your gear until the end! Resist the urge to buy new gear, repair what you have and consider renting or buying used gear.</li>
  <li>Search out less popular trails, keep <em>Leave No Trace</em> principles in mind and pick up other people’s trash if you encounter it outdoors.</li>
</ol>

<p>I also want to encourage you to not geo-tag your images online and generally share &amp; spend less time on un-social networks like Instagram and Facebook which both promote <strong>F</strong>ear <strong>O</strong>f <strong>M</strong>issing <strong>O</strong>ut and other negative feelings. Finally, <a href="https://twitter.com/gretathunberg">#FridaysForFuture</a> are not just for kids - also responsible Adults who are not happy about how those in our governments misuse their loaned power can take to the streets and demonstrate for politics which ensure our planet, including all these amazing National Parks, hiking trails and mountains remain for future generations. Take the ext Friday off and go demonstrate!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29748741131/in/album-72157667276500013/" title="Bodensee"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8007/29748741131_a681170dde_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bodensee" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="further-reading">Further Reading</h2>

<p>The Bergfreunde write about <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/basislager/nachhaltiger-winterurlaub/?pid=10239">sustainable winter holidays</a>, Stefanie ponders the topic of <a href="https://www.gipfel-glueck.de/reisen-und-nachhaltigkeit/">travelling and sustainability</a>, Heiko shares <a href="https://www.people-abroad.de/blog/nachhaltig-leben-tipps/">11 sustainable tips for home &amp; outdoors</a>, Björn reports about the DAV Day <a href="https://bergtouren-im-allgaeu.de/natuerlich-auf-tour-eine-aktion-des-dav">Sustainable on Ski Tour</a>, the Climbing Plus guys show how <a href="https://climbing.plus/blog/nachhaltigkeit-einst-und-jetzt-im-klettersport">climbing has changed over the years</a>, Ulrich writes about <a href="https://www.auf-den-berg.de/wandern/island/nachhaltiger-urlaub-in-island/">Sustainable Tourism on Iceland</a> and Dennis ponders <a href="https://www.outdoor-blog.com/nachhaltigkeit-beim-wandern-trekking/">about sustainability when hiking and backpacking</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28906677698/in/album-72157669754047208/" title="The clouds are moving in"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/899/28906677698_be2173bbb2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The clouds are moving in" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The No Gear Year Experiment]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/05/the-no-gear-year-experiment.html"/>
    <updated>2017-05-16T20:20:52+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/05/the-no-gear-year-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of 2016 I announced my intention of having a #NoGearYear - not taking in any new outdoor gear &amp; equipment, either buying it or getting it for free. Here’s the low-down on how that went.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34692167335/in/dateposted/" title="Checking out the impassable Kesch Step"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4155/34692167335_452e9e5b90_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Checking out the impassable Kesch Step" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>My intentions were simple for 2016: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/01/zero-gear-year.html">No New Outdoor Gear</a>. I have enough of everything, from stoves over backpacks, quilts, shelters to shoes and apparel. And so I informed my partners that this gear nerd here is trying not to test &amp; use the <em>latest and greatest</em> but stick to my tried and used equipment. The months slipped by, I visited the ISPO without taking any of the free kit offered home, went on a lot of fantastic skiing trips, until <strong>BANG</strong> the post man stumbled into my house on a sunny April afternoon. While we knew each other well and he had no problems finding me in the prior years, he now asked me questioningly <em>“Hendrik Morkel?”</em>. I was just as surprised as him, as I hadn’t ordered anything. I took the parcel inside, worried about my #NoGearYear and opened it. It was a <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/therm-a-rest-evolite-plus-isomatte/?pid=10239">Therm-A-Rest Evolite Plus</a> which I had inquired about in the autumn of 2015.</p>

<p>I was bummed. Does this mean I ruined my #NoGearYear? I put the pad into a corner so I didn’t needed to see it anymore and carried on like it nothing happened. Went skiing, cycling and backpacking - without that pad. But even trying to not use it it meant I had a new piece of kit in the house, a fact I couldn’t make go away even if I ignored the offender. May and June passed without visits from the post man, and then I was off to the OutDoor in Friedrichshafen. There I met Graham from <a href="http://www.cilogear.com">CiloGear</a> who told me he had a present for me. He must have seen the shock on my face as he quickly added <em>“No worries, I know about your #NoGearYear, this is just something I want to loan you!”</em>. Ah, that was better. Graham went on to explain me the prototype backpack which has ascended with its former bearer the Eiger Northface twice and established up a new route on a high mountain in Pakistan. It was a work of art and Graham’s passion for his design became evident - it reminded me of the LAUFBURSCHE backpacks which are made with the same love &amp; attention to detail. After he ran me through the bells &amp; whistles of the back he told me that he wants it back in 2017 when we meet again at the OutDoor (which is next month!). Such an arrangement worked well for me - it didn’t mean I owned a new piece of gear, but only loaned it, and that was in line with the rules I set myself.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32396336051/in/dateposted/" title="Staring off into the distance"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/443/32396336051_9d5ed3cd01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Staring off into the distance" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, the next shock came some time in the late summer as the zipper of my beloved <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-alpine-start-hoody.html">Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody</a> went broken. It was still several months till the year would turn, and so I was looking into getting the zipper fixed. Alas, in the end I just wore the broken jacket as sending the jacket to the USA to get the zipper fixed seemed just like too much hassle. So I was wearing it as long as possible, and then now in 2017 I got a new one (finally a Size S!).</p>

<p>But that pad from April - it wasn’t my only lapse, I’m sorry to admit. In the autumn two companies I really like got in touch and asked if we could work together, long-term. I was pondering between a <em>“Lets get back in January”</em> and a <em>“Lets do this!”</em> and in the end I decided that this possibility was worth pursuing, even if I had a #NoGearYear going on. After all, I felt, my goal of not buying/ taking any gear was going well, and so I told them that I’d be delighted to work with them, and thus far it has been a really good partnership. I also received a brand-new quilt which I helped test &amp; design - with some luck you’ll read about this one later this week - and tested a new headlamp from another long-term partner, so all in all I probably had about a dozen of items arrive in 2016.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34652159976/in/dateposted/" title="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody - Broken Zipper"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4174/34652159976_fd6c3049f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Black Diamond Alpine Start Hoody - Broken Zipper" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-aftermath">The Aftermath</h2>

<p>As you see, practically I failed my #NoGearYear. Theoretically, however, I feel I won. In 2016 I gave up the two gear editor jobs I was doing which means I now can use the gear I really want to use and do not need to test different kit all the time. Another positive side effect is also that less stuff arrives here (less than ten parcels have arrived here this year!) and I can continue with less hassle to apply the KonMari principle to the stuff I own (Read <a href="http://amzn.to/2pQcqwj">The Life‑Changing Magic of Tidying Up</a> and make your life better!). I also started to charge for gear reviews on the blog if a company or PR Agency inquires if I’d like to test something or just say “No thanks”. I also was and am more outdoors, on more trips (even if you don’t read about them here yet - my other company is keeping me very busy, sorry) and spend more time with my family. So all in all this #NoGearYear has been a very positive experience for me, and I can only encourage everyone to try it, too - even if you might fail it, it should be a good opportunity to get less stuff you don’t really need and save money for trips you really want to go on!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/34530900242/in/photostream/" title="#NoGearYear with loaned, broken &amp; new gear"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4186/34530900242_9176900c1b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="#NoGearYear with loaned, broken &amp; new gear" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Changes]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/01/changes.html"/>
    <updated>2017-01-25T23:33:03+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/01/changes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The End of Hiking in Finland as we know it and the start of something new.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32476889446/in/dateposted/" title="Myllykoski Bridge"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/607/32476889446_9d1766bcb1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Myllykoski Bridge" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Sometime last autumn I purchased a new domain. My mind is set, I need a fresh start. After eight years of blogging at Hiking in Finland I need a new challenge. It’s a bad time to do this, but if I don’t do it not now I never might. Hiking in Finland is the most-read English-language blog from Scandinavia, there’s over 30.000 Regular Readers a month, add in the close to 20.000 Followers and Fans on the different Social Media channels and you can understand the dilemma of changing something that’s so successful and generates part of my income (Yes, I work full time on the blog since 2014).</p>

<p>Things that led to this is that I do far more nowadays than hiking in Finland - just last year I was ski-touring in Norway &amp; Switzerland, on adventure travel trips in Macedonia, Greece and Mexico, on active family holidays in Vorarlberg, backpacking in South Tyrol and cycle touring in Finland. So the name is out-dated and limits me, but I also moved away a bit from what this blog was about in the beginning - ultralight backpacking. While I maintain that Ultralight is Not Dead I also have started to look over the borders - I have entered a partnership with Helsport for example, and while I always try to carry as little as possible and use the lightest gear for the occasion it’s not the be all and end all of all things like it was more in the past.</p>

<p>But mostly I feel I have become complacent. The status quo is a dangerous place to get lazy and before other’s think <em>It’s the same old</em> I myself might just kill the status quo, reinvent and embark on a new journey. It might be rough on the edges at the beginning, some of you might not like it, but I am sure that with a new challenge I am able to grow myself and the blog to a new level that’s more creative &amp; honest.</p>

<h2 id="design-or-why-does-hif-look-not-like-it-used-to">DESIGN or why does HiF look not like it used to?</h2>
<p>Last November I managed to destroy the backend of Hiking in Finland - right before the #HiFAdventCalendar should have started and while I was in Mexico. Some bacteria or virus knocked me out for two weeks once I returned from Mexico and I barely was able to publish the daily doors on the ad-hoc blog I created. As I got healthy again I had a big hacking session and managed to get HiF back online the way you see it now - still not really how it used to look like or how I would like it to look, but better than a 404. During February and March I will try to update the layout and looks, but first there’s some other priorities.</p>

<h2 id="yeps-theres-gonna-be-a-new-blog">Yeps, there’s gonna be a new blog</h2>
<p>Hiking in Finland will continue &amp; will be regularly updated in the future, but my new website Hike Climb Travel will see a lot more action. Hike Climb Travel is much broader in name as Hiking in Finland and reflects that I do much more than hiking &amp; backpacking in Finland. Hiking in Finland will be home to my adventures at home and neighbouring countries, while Hike Climb Travel will be my outlet for everything that does take place outside of my beautiful home country. It will kick off some time in February, with a pretty, responsive layout, a great brand identity and some great stories to get you hooked. The best way to stay informed about when the new blog goes online is to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the Newsletter</a> and follow me on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a>, but no worries, I also will let it be known here.</p>

<p>For some time I will try to work on both blogs, but time will show if that is possible &amp; smart or if I just move everything over to the new website. Thus, if there’s a favourite article here on the Olde Blog, now is a good time to save it as a pdf for future references. Some content will will also be moved over, so no worries that it’s gonna be all lost down the aether.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32396336051/in/dateposted/" title="Staring off into the distance"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/443/32396336051_9d5ed3cd01_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Staring off into the distance" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="twir-is-not-dead">TWIR is (Not?) Dead</h2>
<p>A couple of weeks back I asked on Instagram and Facebook for one reason why you follow me and a large part of the answers included TWIR. But a lot has changed since I started The Week In Review six years ago: I got married, have two wonderful kids and a house that still needs a wee bit of renovation (not to mention the garden). I feel I have neglected my family the last years every Sunday for several hours while writing the TWIR, and with a little daughter of one year I (maybe too late) realised it is time to kill The Week in Review, reclaim my Sundays and spend them with the people that matter the most to me - my wife and kids.</p>

<p>Also, The Week In Review is a popular post but it never generated much of income for me. I tried to monetise it in some tasteful ways by affiliate links to offers that matter to you, and a couple of times the Packrafting Store sponsored an issue, but these were not putting enough €$£ into my pocket for the time I invest into the TWIR. Because I know that so many of you love the TWIR and rely on it to find new, relevant content that matters, I am open to suggestions on how we could keep the Week In Review alive - but it would be published then on Mondays as I want to have a weekend. Maybe a PayPal subscription would be an option, but that would mean some of you would need to start to pay for the TWIR content. If you think that’s something you’d be willing to do, leave a comment underneath - and also other ideas and feedback is welcome.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31674881554/in/dateposted/" title="Ice River floating"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/700/31674881554_9d690dd7bb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ice River floating" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All in all I am very happy to have this off my chest. I felt bad leaving you loyal readers in the dark about this since last December, but now that I typed it down and re-read it a couple of times it feels good and I am happy to hit publish and see how you take these changes. Thus, comment away - here or on the Social Media channels you can find me on!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Power of Gear Photos]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/10/the-power-of-gear-photos.html"/>
    <updated>2016-10-20T23:30:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/10/the-power-of-gear-photos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What does get you more in the mood to put on your shoes and head outdoors: A photo of a tent in an epic location or a photo of someone staring of into an epic distance?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7807828972/in/album-72157634093995294/" title="Locus Gear Khufu CTF3, Julian Alps, Slovenia"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8300/7807828972_4d0605c010_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Locus Gear Khufu CTF3, Julian Alps, Slovenia" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Things have changed quite a bit in the time I have run this blog: When I started off with outdoor blogging people would usually not show themselves in their articles *¹ - at most a photo of oneself staring off into the distance. Maybe I was naive, young, or both, but back then I didn’t have a problem with showing myself (something that possibly has changed a bit in the last years as I have a family now and am more private). Nowadays, however, Selfies are an accepted form of portraying oneself, nowhere as ubiquitous as on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>.</p>

<p>What is also ubiquitous on Instagram are these “<em>epic</em>” shots where a tiny person stars of into what looks like the wilderness. Here’s one of these:</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-version="7" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAABGdBTUEAALGPC/xhBQAAAAFzUkdCAK7OHOkAAAAMUExURczMzPf399fX1+bm5mzY9AMAAADiSURBVDjLvZXbEsMgCES5/P8/t9FuRVCRmU73JWlzosgSIIZURCjo/ad+EQJJB4Hv8BFt+IDpQoCx1wjOSBFhh2XssxEIYn3ulI/6MNReE07UIWJEv8UEOWDS88LY97kqyTliJKKtuYBbruAyVh5wOHiXmpi5we58Ek028czwyuQdLKPG1Bkb4NnM+VeAnfHqn1k4+GPT6uGQcvu2h2OVuIf/gWUFyy8OWEpdyZSa3aVCqpVoVvzZZ2VTnn2wU8qzVjDDetO90GSy9mVLqtgYSy231MxrY6I2gGqjrTY0L8fxCxfCBbhWrsYYAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div><p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BHAgSC6vhs9/" style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;" target="_blank">A photo posted by Hendrik Morkel (@hendrikm)</a> on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2016-06-23T18:58:05+00:00">Jun 23, 2016 at 11:58am PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>
<script async="" defer="" src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>

<p><br /> Personally I really am not a big fan of them, although I do see their appeal. My main problem is usually that it is always the same places that get these shots, and what is portrayed as epic wilderness or <em>“off-the-beaten-track”</em> are in truth places where you park your car 5 minutes away and then walk on a wide path to the spot. Add in a sunrise, sunset or a headlamp &amp; the Milky Way, do some Photoshop Magic and you have the standard Instagram photo which will attract thousands of likes. Why? Well, because people have seen that image, or a minor variation of it, already hundreds of times, and what is familiar is easy to like.
<br />
<br />But this article isn’t supposed to be on the failings of Instagram photography and my dislike of it, but the power of gear photos. It’s something I have been pondering over the last months, as I occasionally also post the tiny-person-in-big-environment-photo, and while they get a lot of engagement, it are the photos of gear - tents, backpacks, stoves, even a pair of shoes - that get even more engagement. It might be that my <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook Fans</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter Followers</a> are just as big gear nerds as me, or it might be something else.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763145235/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/4/3700/9763145235_51b887b518_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That something else it is what I’d like to ponder about (because we all know that we are gear nerds ;). I think that these, lets call them in contrast to the <em>tiny-person-in-big-environment-photos</em>, great-gear-in-an-epic-environment-photos, are so popular, because a photo of a tent in a beautiful spot, the stove that’s just set up to prepare dinner or the shoes hiking on a trail allow the viewer to put oneself literally in those shoes, behind that stove and in that tent. Sure, one could imagine that that’s you who looks of into the distance high in the mountains, but somewhere inside you know you haven’t been there. But that piece of equipment there - you might own that tent or stove - allows the viewer to put him- or herself there. You can imagine how pretty it would be to lay in that tent and stare into the sunrise in the morning, or sit behind that stove, ready to put the water on so that dinner can be served in a wee bit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14193489569/in/album-72157644166894052/" title="Dinner in the making"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5568/14193489569_090587cee9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Dinner in the making" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>At least that are my thoughts why these gear photos are more popular than photos of a friend skiing down a fine line, starring up that impressive mountain face or hiking on a cool path. That person shown there, the viewer knows, isn’t her, but in that tent there, that could be where he’d like to go to bed. And with that comes maybe also the idea that it’d be nice to own that pair of shoes, that pack, tent, quilt or stove - because one could use it right there, and have with some luck of the weather fairy, the same great experience than the photographer of that gear photo.</p>

<p><strong>Agree or disagree?</strong> Leave a comment and let us know!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26741129446/in/album-72157665452784994/" title="Sunset skiing"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1719/26741129446_117610d8ae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset skiing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7728232746/in/album-72157634093995294/" title="Taking in the view"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8289/7728232746_bb9a1e666c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Taking in the view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18703316503/in/album-72157650519579023/" title="Spring snow"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/1/334/18703316503_2ff0aeff59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Spring snow" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14376799841/in/album-72157644166894052/" title="Camp"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5592/14376799841_388679cf67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Camp" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17482621798/in/album-72157650519579023/" title="Lunch with a view"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5455/17482621798_55e05af41e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lunch with a view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/26634876793/in/album-72157666107618714/" title="Happy hiking!"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7674/26634876793_253babe29e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Happy hiking!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/8701207971/in/album-72157634093995294/" title="Packrafting &amp; Camping"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8257/8701207971_7bdcd68cd4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Packrafting &amp; Camping" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>*¹ An exception to that statement is <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com">Chris Townsend</a> who always has been showing himself in his photos, as far as I can remember.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
