<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bikepacking, | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/bikepacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2021-01-20T17:28:55+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How-to go Tubeless]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/08/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit.html"/>
    <updated>2017-08-08T19:00:59+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/08/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tired of punctures &amp; flat tires? Go Tubeless and don’t worry about them anymore. In this article I show how you can convert your bike to tubeless tires with the help of the Schwalbe Tubeless Easy Kit, your one stop solution with everything you need to go Tubeless.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35603377424/in/dateposted/" title="The Gear needed"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4385/35603377424_4229d4b0d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="The Gear needed" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>Schwalbe has provided me the Tires, Tire Booster and Tubeless Easy Kit for free for this article. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p>Flat tires on 29” wheels, they where common for me back with my old 29er. Happily I started to drive more careful and punctures have been rare in the last several years, but as I welcomed the Trek 920 Disc to the family I decided I wanted to ride it Tubeless. There where some good reasons for that:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>You can save weight.</strong> I’m still a ultralight backpacker at heart and if there’s a possibility to save weight then I’ll take it.</li>
  <li><strong>Adiós, Punctures!</strong> Don’t like that sound of your inner tube going flat? I hate it, and with a healthy dose of your Latex liquid in your tube that sound is unlikely to reach your ears again.</li>
  <li><strong>Traction, baby!</strong> Less pressure on the tires means you have more traction - pretty useful in sharp curves and lose trails.</li>
</ul>

<p>So, with three good reasons to get rid of inner tubes I set out on a sunny afternoon to convert my 920 Disc to Tubeless. It isn’t a quick operation by all means so make sure you have a couple of hours of peace to go about this. Here’s what you’ll need:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Tubeless-Ready Rims</li>
  <li>Tubeless-Ready Tires, I chose the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-thunder-burt-tl-easy-29er-psc-snakeskin-faltbar/?pid=10239">Schwalbe Thunder Burt Evo SnakeSkin PaceStar 29x2,10” TL-Easy Folding</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit-23-fahrradreifen/?pid=10239">Schwalbe Tubeless Easy Kit</a></li>
  <li>Schwalbe Tire Booster or a compressor</li>
  <li>Floor pump</li>
  <li>A bucket with soapy water and some rags</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35630505293/in/dateposted/" title="Frontwheel finished!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4357/35630505293_650cc34354_b.jpg" width="1024" height="936" alt="Frontwheel finished!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Alright, with all your tools and gear ready it’s time to start.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Preparation is KEY! Your Tire Booster needs to be “primed” first, so take your floor pump and put some 11 bars of air in it - that way you don’t need to do it later. Also, a good thing to do is to unfold your tire - if you’re using a tire that comes folded like I did - before you start the whole operation - and hang it into the sun. It will warm up and get a tiny, tiny bit more flexible which makes it easier to put on the rim later.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Lets first check if your rim is Tubeless-Ready. If it is it should be written on it somewhere - either it reads <em>Tubeless Ready</em> or <em>“TLR”</em> somewhere. If they are: Great, that saved you several hundred Euros for new Rims!</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36269911182/in/dateposted/" title="Is the Rim Tubeless Ready?"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4437/36269911182_390912e928_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Is the Rim Tubeless Ready?" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<ol>
  <li>Time to deflate the tube, remove tire + tube + old rim tape, and get cleaning. Take a soapy rag and clean the inside (and while you’re at it, also the outside) of the rim, remove all dirt &amp; dust and then dry it well off. That’s because the next step is quite crucial for the success of the whole operation, and if you hurry through this you might do it twice, so calm and relaxed proceed you shall. Now you grab the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-tubeless-felgenband-fahrradreifen/?pid=10239">Tubeless Rim Tape</a> (these are available in different widths, make sure to buy the one which works best for your rim!) and apply careful and precisely the tape to the inside of the rim. Start opposite of the hole where the valve will go through later, and apply it carefully and cleanly with a lot of pressure to the rim, and avoid air bubbles. I say it again: <em>This is a very important step, so don’t hurry and take your time.</em> If you’ve gone once around and reach the start go another 5 to 10 cm and then cut the tape. Now take the Tubeless Valve from the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-tubeless-easy-kit-23-fahrradreifen/?pid=10239">Tubeless Easy Kit</a> and put it through the rim tape where it belong. Make sure to screw it tightly onto the rim, as the area around the valve can be a point where air easily escapes.</li>
</ol>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36269912682/in/dateposted/" title="Schwalbe Tubeless Easy Kit"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4341/36269912682_197bcfa340_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Schwalbe Tubeless Easy Kit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35630508523/in/dateposted/" title="New rim tape"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4354/35630508523_5cbe19f5f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="New rim tape" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36301263271/in/dateposted/" title="Rim Tape Done!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4346/36301263271_e688da6355_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Rim Tape Done!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Time to take your <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/schwalbe-thunder-burt-tl-easy-29er-psc-snakeskin-faltbar/?pid=10239">Tubeless Tire</a> and mount it carefully onto the rim. If you can don’t use the tire lever as it might damage the rim tape - if you had your unfolded tire hang in the sun this should be possible. Make sure that the tire’s beads are on each side of the valve before you head on.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Time to inflate! Apply a generous coating of the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/schwalbe-montagefluid-easy-fit-bike-tires/?pid=10239">Easy Fit</a> assembly liquid to both sides of the tire beads, the (clean!) soapy water would work too. For the first inflation a powerful burst of air is needed so take the Tire Booster (or if you have one, the compressor) and attach it to the valve. It makes sense to take the top of the valve off to allow more air through-flow, you get a wee tool for that in the Tubeless Easy Kit. Alrighty, this is the moment of truth: Open the Tire Booster and see how your Tubeless Tire inflates. It should set with several loud <strong>BANG!</strong> sounds onto the rim, only if you hear that you know everything went as planned. You need to check the line on the tire to control if the complete tire is correctly mounted, if not knead and push the tire to get it into the right position.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36042172070/in/dateposted/" title="Easy Fit!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4401/36042172070_5cb9d07278_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Easy Fit!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36269910952/in/dateposted/" title="Tire Booster in action"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4381/36269910952_d1dbe91ae1_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Tire Booster in action" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This can be a stressful moment if you don’t hear that loud bang which indicates that the tire beads have engaged the rim - I tried for over an hour to get it to set down. The thing is that 29” tires (and Fatbike Tires even more so) take a lot of air to fill and that in my case the Tire Booster didn’t have enough power to engage the complete tire - it didn’t set down on a couple of places which means that the air was escaping and I couldn’t move on. The solution is to empty the whole Tire Booster into the Tire to get the Tire to set down on as many places on the rim as possible, and then switch to the Floor Pump and keep on inflating the tire. This did the trick for me - the tire looked almost like it was going to burst but in the end I heard the several loud bangs which meant the tire was now fully engaged to the rim. Success, at last!</p>

<ol>
  <li>Now that the tire sits on the rim you can take the pump/ compressor/ Tire Booster off the valve. This will deflate the tire a wee bit, but that’s not a problem. Remove the valve insert if you haven’t done that already in the previous step and take a bottle of the <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/schwalbe-doc-blue-professional-inner-tube/?pid=10239">Doc Blue puncture protection liquid</a> - now it’s time to put it into your Tire and make it Tubeless! You can easily fill the bottle through the valve into the tire - for 29” tires you use the whole 60 ml, smaller tires need less. Once the bottle is empty you put the valve insert back, take the floor pump and inflate the tire again - around 2 bar for these 29” tires is good for starters. Remove the pump, close the valve and now you’ll need to roll and shake the tire for quite a bit - the goal is to distribute the puncture protection liquid everywhere in the tire so that an even cover covers it from the inside. To check the tire once more for leaks you can cover the outside of the tire along the rim with your soapy water - there where there’s bubbles building up you need to move the puncture protection liquid on the inside to cover it better.</li>
</ol>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35630506573/in/dateposted/" title="Doc Blue goes in!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4372/35630506573_cb13980646_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Doc Blue goes in!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36301261941/in/dateposted/" title="Checking for leaks"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4430/36301261941_c9929cd00c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Checking for leaks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If the tire now stays inflated you can attach it back to the bike and get started on the second wheel, after which you should head out for a test ride. All good? Then pack up your bike and head out on a bikepacking Microadventure - Tubeless Edition!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/36269915742/in/dateposted/" title="Schwalbe Thunder Burt Tubeless"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4370/36269915742_7e1a2ca31b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Schwalbe Thunder Burt Tubeless" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I’m now riding since over a month Tubeless and love it. I can ride my tires with less pressure on the trails which equals better traction, but of course the biggest benefit for me is that I don’t need to worry about punctures and snake bites anymore, as the puncture protection liquid seals those immediately should they happen. It’s just a great feeling to know that you can ride how you want without needing to worry that you might end up with a flat tire! Finally, if you’re a friend of moving pictures then have a look at <a href="https://youtu.be/M2fVuTqicCc">this video</a> which is by and far the best on how to convert your tires to tubeless tires! More Information on Tubeless you can find on the <a href="https://www.schwalbe.com/en/tubeless-technology.html">Schwalbe Tubeless</a> Website, while the <a href="https://www.schwalbe.com/en/tubeless.html">Tubeless FAQ</a> can answer additional questions you might have.</p>

<script src="//publisher.outtra.com/themes/frontend/eom/assets/js/outtra-productwall.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=1281" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1731281" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="1281"></script>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this &amp; other articles why not <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">support me with a coffee or two</a>? I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/Habichtshorst/">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35603378504/in/dateposted/" title="Off on Tubeless Adventures"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4383/35603378504_24246ae466_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Off on Tubeless Adventures" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Bikepacking Framebag Manufacturer List]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-24T18:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fatbikes, Mountain Bikes, 29er, Road Bikes and Bikepacking go hand-in-hand. So that you are ready for your next bikepacking adventure and don’t need to rely on old panniers which make riding Singletrack simply not fun, here’s an up-to-date list of people and companies which produce framebags.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/10410128705" title="Dawn by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3799/10410128705_2ce65c655f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Dawn" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Framebags allow you to explore trails and tracks with all your gear packed in a lightweight, streamlined and rack-less method, without any panniers which hang off the back and front wheels and which make navigating singletrail tracks not pleasueable - if not impossible. With your camping gear in framebags - which covers handelbar bags, seatbags, top tube bags and (half) frame bags - you have a possibility to carry all your gear on your bike and are able to explore trails far off the beaten track, with your bike behaving as responsive and ergonomic as usual.</p>

<p>But not just for off-road travel by bike framebags are a smart choice, also for cycle-touring and commuting a half frame bag and top tube bag are great choices to store essential gear on the go. You easily can carry a pump, patch kit and more in a half frame bag, and the top tube bag stores snacks, your camera and phone with easy access during your ride. Both my bikes sport frame bags and I wouldn’t want to miss them on bikepacking adventures and commutes to town.</p>

<p>For easier reference I sorted the makers into locations - Europe, North America and the rest of the world. Know someone who should be on this list? <a href="mailto:hendrik@hikinginfinland.com">Email me</a>.</p>

<h1 id="north-american-makers">North American Makers</h1>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html" title="Porcelain Rocket Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8573/16439818958_87688c7c3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="620" alt="Porcelain Rocket Website" /></a></p>

<h2 id="revelate-designs">Revelate Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.revelatedesigns.com">Revelate Designs</a> is probably the first framebag maker which many come across. Eric and his team have been making framebags in Alaska since 2007 and nowadays also make framebags for Salsa and other bike companies. They produce the whole setup and also offer custom work. You can <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/11/interview-eric-parsons-from-revelate-designs.html">read my interview with Eric here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="porcelain-rocket">Porcelain Rocket</h2>

<p>I own a complete set of <a href="http://www.porcelainrocket.com">Porcelain Rocket</a> Framebags for my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2011/09/driving-in-the-mud-rain.html">29er</a> and love them. Scott and his team make a lot of custom bags and also have many great standard bags which will fit your bike. You can get your whole setup from PR as well as Salsa Anything Cage Bags. <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2012/08/interview-scott-felter-of-porcelain-rocket.html">Read the interview with Scott here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="bedrock-bags">Bedrock Bags</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.bedrockbags.com">Bedrock Bags</a> are from Colorado. All bags are custom order and you can get a whole set from them.</p>

<h2 id="becker-gear">Becker Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.beckergear.com">Becker Gear</a> is another Alaskan framebag maker that offers custom work.</p>

<h2 id="jpaks">J.Paks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jpaks.com">J.Paks</a> packs are made in Denver, Colorado. They have besides the standard flavours of framebags also many special versions available, like an insulated stash bag.</p>

<h2 id="nuclear-sunrise-stitchworks">Nuclear Sunrise Stitchworks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.nukesunrise.com">Nuclear Sunrise Stitchworks</a> packs are made in El Paso, Texas. Get every framebag possiblity from them.</p>

<h2 id="oveja-negra">Oveja Negra</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.ovejanegrathreadworks.com/">Oveja Negra</a> offers the whole bikepacking setup, from stock half frame bags to full custom bags. Based in Salida, Colorado.</p>

<h2 id="wanderlust">Wanderlust</h2>

<p><a href="http://wanderlust-gear.com">Wanderlust</a> is the former <a href="http://hansbagworks.com">Hans Bagworks</a> and you can get Framebags and Handlebar bags as well as some accessories from them. They’re based in Harrisonburg, Virginia.</p>

<h2 id="rogue-panda-designs">Rogue Panda Designs</h2>

<p><a href="http://roguepanda.com">Rogue Panda Designs</a> is from Flagstaff, Arizona and makes seatbags, handlebar rolls, framebags and also lightweight panniers.</p>

<h2 id="bolder-bikepacking-gear">Bolder Bikepacking Gear</h2>

<p><a href="https://bolderbikepacking.wordpress.com">Bolder Bikepacking Gear</a> has been making bikepacking gear in Boulder, Colorado since 2010. You can get the whole bikepacking setup from them.</p>

<h2 id="andrew-the-maker">Andrew The Maker</h2>

<p><a href="http://atmhandmadegoods.com">Andrew The Maker</a> is a new framebag maker tht currently only offers a handlebar bag.</p>

<h2 id="phantom-pack-systems">Phantom Pack Systems</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.phantompacksystems.com">Phantom Pack Systems</a> are a maker from Canada and also offer the full bikepacking framebag setup.</p>

<h2 id="crater-packs">Crater Packs</h2>

<p><a href="http://craterpacks.com">Crater Packs</a> are made in Telluride, Colorado. They make frame bags, seat packs and handlebar bags from cuben and vinyl.</p>

<h2 id="cleaveland-mountaineering">Cleaveland Mountaineering</h2>

<p><a href="http://cleavelandmountaineering.blogspot.fi">Cleaveland Mountaineering</a> is located in Grand Junction, Colorado and makes custom frame packs, handlebar bags, Everything bags and top tube bags.</p>

<h2 id="jandd">Jandd</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.jandd.com/bikes.asp">Jandd</a> has been making bags since 1983 (!) and offers a wide variety of bikepacking bags.</p>

<h2 id="lone-mountain-innovations">Lone Mountain Innovations</h2>

<p><a href="http://lonemountaininnovations.com">Lone Mountain Innovations</a> has been making framebags. They’re currently re-designing their products and will be back in a few months, so keep an eye on them.</p>

<h2 id="randi-jo-fabrications">Randi Jo Fabrications</h2>

<p><a href="http://randijofab.com">Randi Jo Fabrications</a> offers a lot of cycling gear, from bags to caps and saddle covers. Their bags are made from waxed canvas which looks pretty nice.</p>

<h2 id="rockgeist">RockGeist</h2>

<p><a href="http://rockgeist.com">RockGeist</a> builds <em>custom bikepacking gear designed for you and your bike</em>. From Saddlebags over partial and full frame bags to top tube bags, they make them all and for pretty good prices, too.</p>

<h2 id="arkel">Arkel</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.arkel-od.com/en/bikepacking.html">Arkel</a> from Canada, well-known for building pannier bag, now also offers a Seatpack and a handlebar bag is coming soon.</p>

<h2 id="green-guru-gear">Green Guru Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.greengurugear.com/collections/bike-gear?page=2">Green Guru Gear</a> hails from Boulder, Colorado and offer bikepacking bags in cool colours from recycled fabrics, and everything should be unique because of that.</p>

<h2 id="topeak">Topeak</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.topeak.com/global/en/products/bags">Topeak</a> offers top tube bags, and a onesize-fits-all frame bag, ahandlebar bag and a saddle bag should be coming soon.</p>

<h2 id="high-above">High Above</h2>

<p><a href="http://highabove.squarespace.com">High Above</a> from Bellingham, Washington, makes hip packs for riding your bike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/7855481330" title="Pimpin&#x27; at the beach by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8429/7855481330_49fdb544f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="681" alt="Pimpin&#x27; at the beach" /></a></p>

<h1 id="european-makers">European Makers</h1>

<h2 id="miss-grape">Miss Grape</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.missgrape.net">Miss Grape</a> hails from beautiful Italy and makes the whole set of bikepacking bags for your adventure needs.</p>

<h2 id="endless-trails-outdoor-equipment">Endless Trails Outdoor Equipment</h2>

<p><a href="http://endlesstrailsoutdoorequipment.com/?v=f003c44deab6">Endless Trails Outdoor Equipment</a> hails from Sweden makes the whole set of ultralight bikepacking bags, from Single Closure Handlebar Bag to a Bar Bottle Bucket.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html" title="Endless Trails Outdoor Equipment"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/8/7599/27192571221_abea5fc67c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="784" alt="Endless Trails Outdoor Equipment" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="gramm-tourpacking">Gramm Tourpacking</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.gramm-tourpacking.com">Gramm Tourpacking</a> makes their pretty bags in Berlin, Germany, and everything and then something you can get from them.</p>

<h2 id="cordel">Cordel</h2>

<p>Made in Madrid, Spain, are the bags from <a href="http://www.cordelcycling.com">Cordel</a>. The selection is limited - a handlebar bag and a bum bag - but I expect there’s more to come!</p>

<h2 id="restrap">Restrap</h2>

<p>Coming from the United Kingdom is <a href="http://www.restrap.co.uk">Restrap</a> who not only make frame-, seat and handlebar bags but also backpacks and other accessoires.</p>

<h2 id="everbike">Everbike</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.everbike.cz">Everbike</a> from the Czech Republic offers seat bags, handlebar bags and different accessoiries.</p>

<h2 id="burgfyr">BURGFYR</h2>

<p><a href="http://burgfyr.de">BURGFYR</a> is a German framebag manufacturer which has really good prices. They ofer framebags, seatbags, feedbags for your handlebar and accessories. They also offer used bags which need a new home!</p>

<h2 id="apidura">Apidura</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.apidura.com">Apidura</a> is a British company which makes frame bags, seat bags, handlebar bags and top tube bags - the whole shebang thus - in standard sizes. Measure your bike, pick the bags and your ready to go!</p>

<h2 id="inuvik-studio">Inuvik Studio</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.inuvik.es">Inuvik Studio</a> produces their framebags and Top Tube bags in beautiful Spain.</p>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html" title="Apidura Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8662/16007444033_7343c4d374_b.jpg" width="1024" height="617" alt="Apidura Website" /></a></p>

<h2 id="spk-werks">SpōK Werks</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.spokwerks.com/bikepacking-gear.html">SpōK Werks</a> is a German maker of framebags, with the whole setup available.</p>

<h2 id="bike-pack">Bike Pack</h2>

<p><a href="http://bikepack.pl/en/">Bike Pack</a> hails from Poland. They make all sort of frame bags and do so for a very good price.</p>

<h2 id="parsley-bags">Parsley Bags</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.parsleybags.com/">Parsley Bags</a> is another German maker. The main business is for classic cycle-touring gear, but there’s also a seatbag available.</p>

<h2 id="alpkit">Alpkit</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.alpkit.com/bikepacking">Alpkit</a> nowadays also make the whole setup. Framebags are custom-made while seatpacks, top tube bags and handlebar bags are standards.</p>

<h2 id="wildcat-gear">Wildcat Gear</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.wildcatgear.co.uk">Wildcat Gear</a> are from Wales and offer the whole framebag setup, both basic and custom options.</p>

<h2 id="bikebag">BikeBAG</h2>

<p>Jon and Helen from <a href="http://www.bike-BAG.co.uk">BikeBAG</a> are another UK maker of framebags. Only custom framebags are available.</p>

<h2 id="ortlieb">Ortlieb</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.ortlieb.com/en/bikepacking/">Ortlieb</a> from Germany, another company know for their bombproof panniers, is now making the full set of bikepacking bags.</p>

<h2 id="carradice">Carradice</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.carradice.co.uk">Carradice</a> from the UK now also offers some bikepacking packs. They’re made from waxed canvasand look more classical.</p>

<h1 id="rest-of-the-world">Rest of the World</h1>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16440220550" title="Wanderlust Equipment Website by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8631/16440220550_f24609baa9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="609" alt="Wanderlust Equipment Website" /></a></p>

<h2 id="wanderlust-equipment">Wanderlust Equipment</h2>

<p><a href="http://wanderlust-equipment.com/products/g219-blade-frame-bag/">Wanderlust Equipment</a> from Japan makes a half frame bag to order. They look pretty neat and the craftsmanship should be superb!</p>

<h2 id="bike-bag-dude">Bike Bag Dude</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.bikebagdude.com">Bike Bag Dude</a> is from Australia and offers standard bags and custom work, the whole range of framebags as well as Anything Cage Bags and Chaff Bags. They’re also a dealer for <a href="http://www.bikebagdude.com/#!oveja-negra-accessories/c1jyy">Oveja Negra Threadworks</a> framebags in Australia.</p>

<h2 id="hunt-bikes">Hunt Bikes</h2>

<p>Another Australian company, <a href="http://huntbikes.com/collections/bike-bags">Hunt Bikes</a> has the Hunt Bikes bikepacking bag collection which makes some nice black packs for your bike. While you’re shopping with them you might as weel pick up one of their awesome bikepacking frames!</p>

<h2 id="myog">MYOG!</h2>

<p>Don’t want to spend money on a framebag? That’s not needed if you can use a sewing machine. Here are a couple of Guides to get you started:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pedalingnowhere.com/gear/how-to-make-a-bikepacking-framebag-krampus/">Making a simple frame bag for the Krampus</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/oWDRiexLA0I">How to make your own frame bag for bikepacking Video</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tourintune.com/constructing-my-diy-frame-bag/">Constructing My DIY Frame Bag</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.shanecycles.com/make-your-own-gear-myog-bikepacking-frame-bag/">Make your own gear (MYOG) Bikepacking frame bag</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15923653420" title="Salsa Mukluk on the ice by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8605/15923653420_5b51d86efe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salsa Mukluk on the ice" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
