<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2021-01-11T16:16:37+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Outdoor Books for the Holidays]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/12/books-for-the-holidays.html"/>
    <updated>2020-12-21T19:15:31+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/12/books-for-the-holidays</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Dark times are coming</strong>, which means winter is the perfect season to sit down on the sofa with a hot beverage and a good book! Here are six books I have enjoyed a lot in the past months, and which would make good reading for outdoors people while you’re waiting for spring!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50744046957/in/dateposted/" title="Books!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50744046957_6777e1fb34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Books!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>I bought some of the books from my own money while others I have received for review. There are Affiliate links in this article which are marked with an ∞ Infinity Sign 😊 You can use these <strong>AT NO EXTRA COST TO YOU</strong> but I get a small provision from the company. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p><strong>Public Service Announcement:</strong> While I include Affiliate Links in this article, I recommend that you buy these books either directly from the Publishers OR, even better, <strong>get them at your favourite local bookshop</strong>. Only if those are not an option, use the Amazon Affiliate links.</p>

<h2 id="big-trails-great-britain--ireland">Big Trails: Great Britain &amp; Ireland</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50743200828/in/photostream/" title="Big Trails Great Britain &amp; Ireland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50743200828_827eb79e16_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Big Trails Great Britain &amp; Ireland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>This is my review copy of Vertebrate Publishing’s <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/walking/big-trails-great-britain-ireland/">Big Trails: Great Britain &amp; Ireland</a> book - I contributed a few images for the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/06/hiking-the-causeway-coast-way.html">Causeway Coast Way</a> in Northern Ireland to it! I might be biased thus, but this is an really good book to discover new trails and get really good information on them. The structure on how the trails are presented is very useful for future hikers, and starts off with a nice text presentation of the hike, as well as a map where in the UK or Ireland you can find this trail - and I really like that the trail is shown completely on this map, as that helps you get a feel for it. Beautiful photos make the trail look perfect and show what landscapes you can expect, which is followed by the Essential Information part: Here you get all the important information on how to get there, how long it might take to complete, the Pros &amp; Cons and where to find further information. A more detailed map of the complete trail also helps you plan the hike. There are 25 different Trails in this book, located in Northern Ireland, Scotland, Ireland, Wales and England. The trails are anything from 55 km in length to 300 km or more. If you find this book interesting but would rather stay in mainland Europe, then the sister book <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/walking/big-trails-heart-of-europe/">Big Trails: Heart of Europe</a> might be better for you.</p>

<p>Buy the book directly from <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/walking/big-trails-great-britain-ireland/">Vertebrate Publishing</a>, at your local book shop or order it from <a href="https://amzn.to/3h75cz8">∞ Amazon.com</a>, <a href="https://amzn.to/3auMaS2">∞ Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="https://amzn.to/2KOnKIn">∞ Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50743200708/in/photostream/" title="Big Trails Great Britain &amp; Ireland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50743200708_a986e9a3a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Big Trails Great Britain &amp; Ireland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="the-last-hillwalker-bothy-tales-and-sky-dance">The Last Hillwalker, Bothy Tales and Sky Dance</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50744046602/in/photostream/" title="The Last Hillwalker, Bothy Tales and Skydance"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50744046602_bf9686d269_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Last Hillwalker, Bothy Tales and Skydance" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I bought these three books, maybe in part because they got so many good reviews, because Alex Roddie was the Editor for them, and also because I wanted something “easy” to read in the evening (I have read a lot of Science Fiction in the last months =). I wasn’t disappointed with these books, and they were really good entertainment. The only bad thing was that I always wanted to go sleep in a tent under a quilt, instead of a warm bed 😆. I first read <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/narratives/the-last-hillwalker/">The Last Hillwalker</a>, then <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/narratives/bothy-tales/">Bothy Tales</a> and then <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/narratives/narratives-sky-dance/">Sky Dance</a>, which is also the recommended order by the author.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/narratives/the-last-hillwalker/">The Last Hillwalker</a> was a very good book, and takes us along on John’s adventures of the past 40 years or hiking, climbing, backpacking and camping. I think for us younger hillwalking and hiking humans it’s fun to read how it was to start hillwalking and climbing 40+ years ago, as it is rather different than nowadays where you go online to find information, help and friends to go out with. The Stories in each chapter are entertaining, make you chuckle or think or both, and it’s tempting to read “just one more chapter” before heading to bed. The Last Hillwalker is a great book, and should give you a few good evenings of reading.</p>

<p>The second book, <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/narratives/bothy-tales/">Bothy Tales</a>, was a collection of short stories about Bothies, the open wilderness huts in the UK. This book was much shorter than the other two, and also the one I enjoyed the least. Maybe it was because it felt that most stories had the same elements: Hike in with a bag of coal to a distant bothy in the darkness, with rain or snow often also included, light a fire, make food, drink a dram. The book definitely had some fun moments - especially as my best friend’s name is also Martin, and we have experienced in the past 12 years similar situations as the protagonists of this book. Overall I felt this was a weaker book, but for a completionist probably still a must-read book.</p>

<p>John’s 3rd book, <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/narratives/narratives-sky-dance/">Sky Dance</a>, is his best work to date. It’s less autobiographical, less short stories, and more a really great novel. I had a hard time each evening putting the book down to go to sleep, as the story is really well written, captivating and also about an issue which is close to my heart. The two main characters, Angus &amp; Rory, are relatable and very likeable, and <em>“do what is right”</em>. With this book it feels John has grown as an author, and it makes me looking forward to <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/books-new-and-coming-soon/books-new-and-coming-soon-wild-winter/">his fourth book in April 2021</a>. You can read this book completely on its own, as you don’t need any of the information of the previous two books, but if you have read them some things will make you chuckle as there are smart call-backs to the previous works. Overall a great book that I can highly recommend!</p>

<p>Buy the three books directly from <a href="https://www.v-publishing.co.uk/books/bundles_3/bundles-3-john-d-burns-bundle/">Vertebrate Publishing</a>, at your local book shop or order it from <a href="https://amzn.to/2J9SPWL">∞ Amazon.com</a>, <a href="https://amzn.to/37EsR77">∞ Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="https://amzn.to/38hEIXG">∞ Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50743200458/in/photostream/" title="The Last Hillwalker, Bothy Tales and Skydance"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50743200458_6b79ae5f8a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Last Hillwalker, Bothy Tales and Skydance" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="das-alpenbuch">Das Alpenbuch</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50743937486/in/photostream/" title="Das Alpenbuch"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50743937486_afb175f011_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Das Alpenbuch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I received this Review copy of <a href="https://marmotamaps.com/en/book-of-the-alps/">The Book of the Alps</a> as my good friend Björn Köcher is one of the authors. This book, which is in German language, is a feast for the eyes. It has 46 chapters, which are sub-divided into seven subject areas: Geography, Flora and Fauna, Climate and Environment, Alpinism, Mountain Sports, Society and Economy and Arts and Culture. Every single page is jam-packed full of interesting information which are in turn depicted in easy-to-understand graphics, and <em>not just some graphics out of Word</em> but carefully crafted graphics which tell you about the different topics and issues. Be it which animal lives where on a mountain, a timeline of alpinism in the Alps or which ski length to pick for which art of skiing. This is a book which I read in the afternoon, between work sessions, with a cup of coffee, and I love to absorb the useful information and the pretty graphics. A fantastic book which I would recommend to anyone who wants to learn more about the Alps in Europe &amp; everything connected to them, as it is beautiful and full-to-the-brim with information for us outdoor enthusiasts.</p>

<p>Buy the book directly from <a href="https://marmotamaps.com/en/book-of-the-alps/">Marmota Maps</a>, at your local book shop or order it from <a href="https://amzn.to/2WxYZCS">∞ Amazon.com</a>, <a href="https://amzn.to/2KL6Dam">∞ Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="https://amzn.to/2WD5vZ2">∞ Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50743201738/in/photostream/" title="Das Alpenbuch"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50743201738_fee9166c64_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Das Alpenbuch" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="wanderlust-europe">Wanderlust Europe</h2>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50743201188/in/photostream/" title="Wanderlust Europe"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50743201188_19f46b815f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wanderlust Europe" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, <a href="https://gestalten.com/products/wanderlust-europe">Wanderlust Europe</a>. My (digital) friend <a href="https://www.alexroddie.com">Alex Roddie</a> wrote this visual tome of long hikes in Europe. Every trail is accompanied by a nice text which makes you curious about the trail in question, again with beautiful images to give you a feeling of what to expect. A map at the end of each Trail shows you where you’ll be hiking and helps with planning, as does the <em>Good to know</em> section which gives basic infos. This is as much a coffee table book which is nice to flip through while you’re relaxing, as it is a book to plan the next dozen long hikes you want to do in Europe. While this book showcases some of the best-known Trails in Europe which are already pretty busy (Kungsleden, The Pennine Way, Tre Cime Circuit, etc.) it also highlights some pretty new trails. If you’re new to the hobby of hiking &amp; backpacking, and don’t know where to go in your next summer holiday, this book will give you plenty to choose from!</p>

<p>Buy the books directly from <a href="https://gestalten.com/products/wanderlust-europe">Gestalten</a>, at your local book shop or order it from <a href="https://amzn.to/2Wym1Kb">∞ Amazon.com</a>, <a href="https://amzn.to/3mMd9LH">∞ Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="https://amzn.to/2KFEuSe">∞ Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50743937286/in/photostream/" title="Wanderlust Europe"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50743937286_2bd065a4d3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wanderlust Europe" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>join the <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon tribe</a></strong> <em>(and get great discount codes from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On The Trail with Boots McFarland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/on-the-trail-with-boots-mcfarland.html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-03T14:19:09+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/on-the-trail-with-boots-mcfarland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Stuck indoors, dreaming of backpacking and sleeping under the stars? Grab a copy of <em>On The Trail with Boots McFarland</em> and be transported to the most humorous hikes you’ve ever been on!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49730698232/in/dateposted-public/" title="Boots McFarland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49730698232_1af6fa0304_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boots McFarland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>I received this book for free from the Publisher, and there are three affiliate links in this article at the end 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>This wee book arrived a while ago at Hiking in Finland HQ, courtesy of Geolyn. <a href="https://bootsmcfarland.com/">Boots McFarland</a> has been a popular web comic for a long time, detailing all the good things one experiences on the trail. If you like to have a good, loud laugh while stuck indoors, this book definitely will deliver it. It also will make you laugh out loud and affirming the stories and anecdotes in the book, from how one always is hungry, that hiking is easier than planning a hike, and much more!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49730376966/in/dateposted-public/" title="Boots McFarland II"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49730376966_d04085b29d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boots McFarland II" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Many of us really miss our weekend escapes to the mountains and forests during this Pandemic, and while Boots McFarland might make you miss them even more, Boots will also make you laugh and lift your spirits, helping you remember your own amazing trips, and maybe also helping you plan out a future hike or two 😃 While the book is short - you can read it in half an hour - it has a high re-read value, so leave it lying on your dinner table, and browse it while you have a coffee break from working at home! Grab your copy of <em>On The Trail with Boots McFarland</em> at <a href="https://amzn.to/2UXghZd">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="https://amzn.to/2wNOdiV">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/2waKP13">Amazon.de</a> via these links and I’ll get a small commission, with no extra costs to you! And for the <em>latest comic, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Boots-McFarland-Cartoon-121985657835548/">check out Boots on Facebook</a>**! *Happy trails!</em></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wildside - The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/wildside-the-enchanted-life-of-hunters-and-gatherers.html"/>
    <updated>2017-07-10T20:42:03+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/wildside-the-enchanted-life-of-hunters-and-gatherers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers</em> is another book by <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/wildside.html">Gestalten</a> that caters to the lifestyle outdoor Instagram person. At least that was my first impression when I saw the book - but covers can lie, and once I started to read I actually quite liked it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35703340791/in/photostream/" title="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4235/35703340791_3a545d6ede_b.jpg" width="970" height="1024" alt="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The Gestalten Publishing house has published a host of books - <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open.html">The Great Wide Open</a>, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/off-the-road.html">Off the Road</a>, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/hide-and-seek.html">Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/the-outsiders.html">The Outsiders</a>  - which all look a bit like they garner to the Instagram crowd - and probably that’s what they want and do. And while some of these are not really a success for me, others are good. <a href="http://amzn.to/2tLQ9EM">Wildside</a> is in the latter camp, even if the Cover can be deceiving and you might just think this book is like Instagram photos you’ve seen a thousand times just printed on nice paper, but it has more to offer on its 250 something pages.</p>

<p>There’s essays of #Vanlife Dwellers in the book, inspiring and artsy photos, little businesses are showcased, you learn more about hunting in Germany and Sweden, you go foraging in Finland and then you are taken surfing and to Switzerland. It’s a visual journey interspersed with short stories and essays, and even if some of these topics might not interest you much you might find a little piece of joy or wisdom from another one, so take the time to read each - because if not you might miss out.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35703340211/in/photostream/" title="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers Book"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4255/35703340211_24b639e221_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers Book" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So whom is this book aimed at? If you feel like you’d like to see what else is possible than running the rat race from 9-to-5 every day, then this book certainly can plant some ideas into your mind. Or if you’re looking for inspiration where to travel next. Or even how to travel - by #Vanlife, on foot or in a canoe, there’s better options than flying for a week to an all-inclusive resort (<em>but that you, as a reader of an outdoor blog, knew either way already</em> ;).</p>

<p>Also for those who look for culinary ideas this book obviously will be of interest, be it from gathering mushrooms or catching fish - modern Hunters &amp; Gatherers will enjoy this book without a doubt. Overall it is a beautiful book that inspires to try something new, presented in a visually pleasing way, though I do find the chosen typefaces for much of the text unsuccessful as it isn’t pleasing to read. Other than that - if you’re interested in one thing I told about of this book - check out a copy at your local library or order a copy home to sit down with it, out in the summer sun. You can buy Wildside directly at Gestalten or via one of these Affiliate Links at <a href="http://amzn.to/2tLQ9EM">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/2utIyrZ">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/2tPxSpX">Amazone.de</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>The book has been provided by the Gestalten Verlag for review. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/bikepacking-on-the-wild-trails-of-britain.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/bikepacking-on-the-wild-trails-of-britain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way.html">Ireland</a> to Britain: Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain takes you &amp; your bike on the most beautiful multi-day rides in Wales, Scotland and England.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101282/in/dateposted/" title="Bikepacking"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7252/27183101282_48e647f3ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bikepacking" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Bikepacking is a big trend these days (check the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html">The Bikepacking Framebag Manufacturer List</a> to see how to transform your bike into a bikepacking rig) so it was a nice surprise as I was contacted by Wild Things Publishing and a question if they could use one of my photos in the book. Sure they could! As a wee thank you they sent me a copy of the book, and as I love alternative travel guide books <em>Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain</em> was right up my alley.</p>

<p>It is another beautiful book that will inspire you to pack up your bike and head to Britain in order to ride one (<em>or more!</em>) of the presented trips. From Epic Wilderness Rides over Family Rides to Technical &amp; Coastal Trails, the book presents 30 trips which range from a night to a week or riding in the countryside of Britain. The book starts off with an introduction to bikepacking and some history, some stories to get you in the mood, tips on gear - including a cool short chapter on tarps! - and how to plan a ride. In short: All you need to get on your bike and head out for a night or more in the wild. After the introduction it takes you on the different rides, which make up the majority of the book. These are sorted by regions in the UK - from the South East to the South West of England to the Midlands, Scotland and Wales. A map of the UK in the beginning highlights where these trips are to be found (good for planning) and a table on the next page gives  quick overview of relevant data about the rides - including distance, ascent and how many percent of the ride are off-road.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101142/in/dateposted/" title="Bikepacking"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7326/27183101142_3113691725_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bikepacking" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I loved the very well designed info boxes which had all needed information ready with one look, a small map which gave a good idea of the ride (though you’ll need a real map for your adventure) and the beautiful photos. The trip descriptions are entertaining little trip reports in their own which will make you anticipate your own ride even more. All in all a unique book that is beautifully designed &amp; presented. If you’re into bikepacking and want to go to Britain for a wee adventure or more, this book is a recommended read!</p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://www.wildthingspublishing.com/product/bikepacking-book/">Wild Things Publishing</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5i3Sr">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUYI3">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5hJmE">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring Ireland's Wild Atlantic Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/wild-atlantic-way.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T22:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/wild-atlantic-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is the Wild Atlantic Way on your bucket list? Then you want to grab this travel guide to Ireland’s wild west coast!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183102302/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Cover"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7074/27183102302_ee6f87d84a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Cover" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Last year I was lucky enough to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">explore Ireland</a>, hike the IAT and go sea stack climbing. What caught my interest and brought me to the Green Isle, however, was the Wild Atlantic Way: The world’s longest coastal touring route which goes from south to north along the west coast and is over 2.500 km long. There’s all kind of adventures to be had along the WAW, from visits in picturesque Irish villages and their pubs to bigger towns and their cultural offerings. However, <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</a> helps you find the off-the-beaten-track gems and takes you outdoors into the fresh, Irish air (and occasional rain shower!).</p>

<p>On 224 pages <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> takes you from the south in Kinsale to the far north of Malin Head along the coast. In seven chapters - divided by county - you can start to explore the Wild Atlantic Way. Do you fancy surfing, sea stack climbing and lots of remote wilderness? Then head to Donegal in the north. Do you prefer a cable car ride to an island, trying your luck fishing or going cycling? Then Cork in the south is a good place to start your adventures! Wherever you decide to go, <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> will have an insider tip ready for you. The seven county chapters are further divided into sections, each coming with their own little overview map to give you a feel of the land. Hundreds of gorgeous photos will get you in the mood to explore, while the detailed introduction chapter gives tips on when to come, what to bring and any other question you may have.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101542/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Inside"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7529/27183101542_ffe5d299bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Inside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Ireland is beautiful, and <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> helps you discover the green isle beyond the hustle and bustle of Dublin and the other big towns. Jam-packed with beautiful photos that inspire to visit the described places on Ireland’s west coast this book helps you plan your ultimate outdoor adventure itinerary. Three Rocks Books has created another stunning book which showcases some of the best scenery, sights and places in Ireland, and no matter if you plan to explore the Wild Atlantic Way on a roadtrip, by bike or public transportation, it will make sure you will see the true Wild Atlantic Way. <em>My tip: Book a flight to Ireland the same time you order this book!</em></p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Three Rocks Books</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/25pjt1d">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5i48S">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUK3G">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
