<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-07-01T14:14:31+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On The Trail with Boots McFarland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/on-the-trail-with-boots-mcfarland.html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-03T14:19:09+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/on-the-trail-with-boots-mcfarland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Stuck indoors, dreaming of backpacking and sleeping under the stars? Grab a copy of <em>On The Trail with Boots McFarland</em> and be transported to the most humorous hikes you’ve ever been on!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49730698232/in/dateposted-public/" title="Boots McFarland"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49730698232_1af6fa0304_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boots McFarland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>I received this book for free from the Publisher, and there are three affiliate links in this article at the end 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>This wee book arrived a while ago at Hiking in Finland HQ, courtesy of Geolyn. <a href="https://bootsmcfarland.com/">Boots McFarland</a> has been a popular web comic for a long time, detailing all the good things one experiences on the trail. If you like to have a good, loud laugh while stuck indoors, this book definitely will deliver it. It also will make you laugh out loud and affirming the stories and anecdotes in the book, from how one always is hungry, that hiking is easier than planning a hike, and much more!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49730376966/in/dateposted-public/" title="Boots McFarland II"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49730376966_d04085b29d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boots McFarland II" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Many of us really miss our weekend escapes to the mountains and forests during this Pandemic, and while Boots McFarland might make you miss them even more, Boots will also make you laugh and lift your spirits, helping you remember your own amazing trips, and maybe also helping you plan out a future hike or two 😃 While the book is short - you can read it in half an hour - it has a high re-read value, so leave it lying on your dinner table, and browse it while you have a coffee break from working at home! Grab your copy of <em>On The Trail with Boots McFarland</em> at <a href="https://amzn.to/2UXghZd">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="https://amzn.to/2wNOdiV">Amazon.co.uk</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/2waKP13">Amazon.de</a> via these links and I’ll get a small commission, with no extra costs to you! And for the <em>latest comic, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Boots-McFarland-Cartoon-121985657835548/">check out Boots on Facebook</a>**! *Happy trails!</em></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wildside - The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/wildside-the-enchanted-life-of-hunters-and-gatherers.html"/>
    <updated>2017-07-10T20:42:03+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2017/07/wildside-the-enchanted-life-of-hunters-and-gatherers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers</em> is another book by <a href="http://shop.gestalten.com/books/wildside.html">Gestalten</a> that caters to the lifestyle outdoor Instagram person. At least that was my first impression when I saw the book - but covers can lie, and once I started to read I actually quite liked it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35703340791/in/photostream/" title="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4235/35703340791_3a545d6ede_b.jpg" width="970" height="1024" alt="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The Gestalten Publishing house has published a host of books - <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/07/the-great-wide-open.html">The Great Wide Open</a>, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/off-the-road.html">Off the Road</a>, <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/hide-and-seek.html">Hide and Seek - The Architecture of Cabins and Hide-Outs</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/04/the-outsiders.html">The Outsiders</a>  - which all look a bit like they garner to the Instagram crowd - and probably that’s what they want and do. And while some of these are not really a success for me, others are good. <a href="http://amzn.to/2tLQ9EM">Wildside</a> is in the latter camp, even if the Cover can be deceiving and you might just think this book is like Instagram photos you’ve seen a thousand times just printed on nice paper, but it has more to offer on its 250 something pages.</p>

<p>There’s essays of #Vanlife Dwellers in the book, inspiring and artsy photos, little businesses are showcased, you learn more about hunting in Germany and Sweden, you go foraging in Finland and then you are taken surfing and to Switzerland. It’s a visual journey interspersed with short stories and essays, and even if some of these topics might not interest you much you might find a little piece of joy or wisdom from another one, so take the time to read each - because if not you might miss out.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/35703340211/in/photostream/" title="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers Book"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4255/35703340211_24b639e221_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Wildside: The Enchanted Life of Hunters and Gatherers Book" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So whom is this book aimed at? If you feel like you’d like to see what else is possible than running the rat race from 9-to-5 every day, then this book certainly can plant some ideas into your mind. Or if you’re looking for inspiration where to travel next. Or even how to travel - by #Vanlife, on foot or in a canoe, there’s better options than flying for a week to an all-inclusive resort (<em>but that you, as a reader of an outdoor blog, knew either way already</em> ;).</p>

<p>Also for those who look for culinary ideas this book obviously will be of interest, be it from gathering mushrooms or catching fish - modern Hunters &amp; Gatherers will enjoy this book without a doubt. Overall it is a beautiful book that inspires to try something new, presented in a visually pleasing way, though I do find the chosen typefaces for much of the text unsuccessful as it isn’t pleasing to read. Other than that - if you’re interested in one thing I told about of this book - check out a copy at your local library or order a copy home to sit down with it, out in the summer sun. You can buy Wildside directly at Gestalten or via one of these Affiliate Links at <a href="http://amzn.to/2tLQ9EM">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/2utIyrZ">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/2tPxSpX">Amazone.de</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: <em>The book has been provided by the Gestalten Verlag for review. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/bikepacking-on-the-wild-trails-of-britain.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T23:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/bikepacking-on-the-wild-trails-of-britain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/05/wild-atlantic-way.html">Ireland</a> to Britain: Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain takes you &amp; your bike on the most beautiful multi-day rides in Wales, Scotland and England.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101282/in/dateposted/" title="Bikepacking"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7252/27183101282_48e647f3ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bikepacking" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Bikepacking is a big trend these days (check the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/02/bikepacking-bag-manufacturers.html">The Bikepacking Framebag Manufacturer List</a> to see how to transform your bike into a bikepacking rig) so it was a nice surprise as I was contacted by Wild Things Publishing and a question if they could use one of my photos in the book. Sure they could! As a wee thank you they sent me a copy of the book, and as I love alternative travel guide books <em>Bikepacking on the Wild Trails of Britain</em> was right up my alley.</p>

<p>It is another beautiful book that will inspire you to pack up your bike and head to Britain in order to ride one (<em>or more!</em>) of the presented trips. From Epic Wilderness Rides over Family Rides to Technical &amp; Coastal Trails, the book presents 30 trips which range from a night to a week or riding in the countryside of Britain. The book starts off with an introduction to bikepacking and some history, some stories to get you in the mood, tips on gear - including a cool short chapter on tarps! - and how to plan a ride. In short: All you need to get on your bike and head out for a night or more in the wild. After the introduction it takes you on the different rides, which make up the majority of the book. These are sorted by regions in the UK - from the South East to the South West of England to the Midlands, Scotland and Wales. A map of the UK in the beginning highlights where these trips are to be found (good for planning) and a table on the next page gives  quick overview of relevant data about the rides - including distance, ascent and how many percent of the ride are off-road.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101142/in/dateposted/" title="Bikepacking"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7326/27183101142_3113691725_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bikepacking" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I loved the very well designed info boxes which had all needed information ready with one look, a small map which gave a good idea of the ride (though you’ll need a real map for your adventure) and the beautiful photos. The trip descriptions are entertaining little trip reports in their own which will make you anticipate your own ride even more. All in all a unique book that is beautifully designed &amp; presented. If you’re into bikepacking and want to go to Britain for a wee adventure or more, this book is a recommended read!</p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://www.wildthingspublishing.com/product/bikepacking-book/">Wild Things Publishing</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5i3Sr">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUYI3">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5hJmE">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring Ireland's Wild Atlantic Way]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/wild-atlantic-way.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T22:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/wild-atlantic-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Is the Wild Atlantic Way on your bucket list? Then you want to grab this travel guide to Ireland’s wild west coast!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183102302/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Cover"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7074/27183102302_ee6f87d84a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Cover" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Last year I was lucky enough to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/sea-stack-climbing-in-ireland.html">explore Ireland</a>, hike the IAT and go sea stack climbing. What caught my interest and brought me to the Green Isle, however, was the Wild Atlantic Way: The world’s longest coastal touring route which goes from south to north along the west coast and is over 2.500 km long. There’s all kind of adventures to be had along the WAW, from visits in picturesque Irish villages and their pubs to bigger towns and their cultural offerings. However, <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</a> helps you find the off-the-beaten-track gems and takes you outdoors into the fresh, Irish air (and occasional rain shower!).</p>

<p>On 224 pages <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> takes you from the south in Kinsale to the far north of Malin Head along the coast. In seven chapters - divided by county - you can start to explore the Wild Atlantic Way. Do you fancy surfing, sea stack climbing and lots of remote wilderness? Then head to Donegal in the north. Do you prefer a cable car ride to an island, trying your luck fishing or going cycling? Then Cork in the south is a good place to start your adventures! Wherever you decide to go, <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> will have an insider tip ready for you. The seven county chapters are further divided into sections, each coming with their own little overview map to give you a feel of the land. Hundreds of gorgeous photos will get you in the mood to explore, while the detailed introduction chapter gives tips on when to come, what to bring and any other question you may have.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101542/in/dateposted/" title="Wild Atlantic Way Inside"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/8/7529/27183101542_ffe5d299bc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wild Atlantic Way Inside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Ireland is beautiful, and <em>Exploring Ireland’s Wild Atlantic Way</em> helps you discover the green isle beyond the hustle and bustle of Dublin and the other big towns. Jam-packed with beautiful photos that inspire to visit the described places on Ireland’s west coast this book helps you plan your ultimate outdoor adventure itinerary. Three Rocks Books has created another stunning book which showcases some of the best scenery, sights and places in Ireland, and no matter if you plan to explore the Wild Atlantic Way on a roadtrip, by bike or public transportation, it will make sure you will see the true Wild Atlantic Way. <em>My tip: Book a flight to Ireland the same time you order this book!</em></p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://threerockbooks.com/index.php/exploring-irelands-wild-atlantic-way/">Three Rocks Books</a> or from <a href="http://amzn.to/25pjt1d">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5i48S">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUK3G">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yosemite in the Fifties]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/yosemite-in-the-fifties.html"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T20:58:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2016/05/yosemite-in-the-fifties</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Big walls, inspiring stories, epic climbing photos - that’s <a href="http://bit.ly/1RvKL98">Yosemite in the Fifties</a> in a nutshell.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183101812/in/dateposted/" title="Yosemite in the Fifties Cover"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/8/7095/27183101812_79dc07e245_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yosemite in the Fifties Cover" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>“Show me a climber who doesn’t know Yosemite and I show you someone who doesn’t climb.”</em> OK, I made that up, but there’s a hint of truth in that: Climbers from across the globe know the view down the valley on El Cap, heard about the epic Dawn Wall climb of Tommy Caldwell and Kevin Jorgeson in 2015, and just long to stand underneath the towering granite walls of El Capitain before also they will start to scale it. Yosemite in the Fifties transportes you back in time to the iron age of climbing history in the valley, when climbers where pushing the envelope of what had been thought possible and established the routes we still climb today.</p>

<p>The book is a collection of beautiful photos of the valley, the protagonists and their climbs, all taken with cameras that relied on the skill &amp; knowledge of the operator. In between these inspiring photos are four chapters with over a dozen essays. These essays are from original source material - first-person narratives and anecdotes of the climbers and their friends, interspersed with archive photos and shots of memorabilia from back in the day. Stories range from a history of climbing tools over portraits to historic climbing routes. With over 200 pages and twenty essays <em>Yosemite in the Fifties</em> is captivating for a long time and a book one can go back to time &amp; again to let the imagination wander off once more while looking at the old photos or reading one of the adventurous stories.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27183102042/in/dateposted/" title="Yosemite in the Fifties Inside"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7301/27183102042_88924e20aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Yosemite in the Fifties Inside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Climbing in Yosemite is high on my bucket list so <em>Yosemite in the Fifties</em> is a book I enjoyed immensely. It’s a tasteful combination of visuals and stories, many written by John Long, one of climbing’s best writers. If climbing in Yosemite is something you also aspire to, I think you should pick up this beautiful coffee table book and immerse yourself into the history of the Iron Age of climbing in the valley. The stories and little anecdotes will surely be something that will make your wish to go to Yosemite even stronger, and once you’re standing on a ledge on El Cap Tower you will remember this book, it stories, and smile - because now you are there, and become part of its history!</p>

<p>Buy it directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/1RvKL98">Patagonia</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/25pkA0R">Amazon.com</a>, <a href="http://amzn.to/1Z5ilsg">Amazon.co.uk</a> or <a href="http://amzn.to/27UUhP2">Amazon.de</a>.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: The book was sent for free to me by the publisher. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. There are affiliate links in this article. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
