<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: backpacking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/backpacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2021-11-19T10:41:34+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anfibio REBEL 2K - The most versatile Packraft?]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/09/anfibio-rebel-2k-the-most-versatile-packraft.html"/>
    <updated>2020-09-17T20:44:56+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/09/anfibio-rebel-2k-the-most-versatile-packraft</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Packrafting, the possibility to not see water bodies as an obstacle on your trekking trips, but as an Opportunity: An opportunity to cross lakes, float down rivers, or even go white water rafting! With the Anfibio REBEL 2K the Packrafting Store has launched a packraft which is ideal for both absolute packrafting beginners and seasoned packrafters, too! It’s versatile in use and it’s compact pack size and light weight make it a dream for remote backpacking - packrafting trips!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50351663578/in/dateposted/" title="Morning"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50351663578_ff4d60896a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Morning" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from the Packrafting-Store.de. There are Affiliate links in this article which are marked with an ∞ Infinity Sign 😊 You can use these <strong>AT NO EXTRA COST TO YOU</strong> but I get a small provision from the company. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on the affiliate links in this article &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>A ridiculously small pack size and a weight of around 2 kg make the <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de/Packrafts/Anfibio-packrafts/Anfibio-Rebel-2K::889.html?language=en">Anfibio Rebel 2K</a> an absolute dream to carry on backpacking trips, especially if you go off-trail over the hills. On the water the Rebel 2K shows that it’s not a kids toy: You can run rapids in it, with the optional skeg you paddle large water bodies more efficiently and faster, and the tube bags are amazing to store your gear while paddling, without having a backpack in front of your eyes! <a href="https://youtu.be/Xp3Pkxnl_po">Watch the Video</a> to see it in action:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Xp3Pkxnl_po" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>The Rebel 2K arrived in March 2020 with me, and I have used it for paddling on lakes and rivers, paddling in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/07/bjorko-panike-trail.html">Kvarken Archipelago</a> and I paddled <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/07/impressions-from-lemmenjoki-and-ivalojoki.html">80 km on the Ivalojoki</a> in Lapland. It has seen a lot of use, and the season isn’t over yet!</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p><strong>IMPORTANT!</strong> The Anfibio Rebel 2K you see in this Review and Video is an early version (late 2019), and since then some things have been changed (e.g. the handle on the inside has been removed) and other details further improved.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50057618453/in/dateposted/" title="Camp on Sondasören"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50057618453_10835d6ca1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Camp on Sondasören" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The idea of a packraft was to allow you to ferry across large rivers and water bodies in remote areas. Nowadays packrafts are a sport on itself, and are used to run difficult, hard white water rapids, in Adventure Races, for fishing and also for trekking and relaxed paddling! Packrafts are inflated with an inflation bag and have one (rarely more) large air chamber. They are light weight - anything from 500 g to 5 kg or more.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50348476217/in/photostream/" title="Anfibio Rebel 2K"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50348476217_f790f2d211_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="Anfibio Rebel 2K" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Anfibio Rebel 2K with the optional tube bags weighs all in 2430 gram. Included in that weight is also the special Anfibio Rebel 2K Comfort Seat, which is 295 g, and the Anfibio DeckPack with 225 g. Not included, but useful to take along on large lake crossings, is the Anfibio Skeg, which is 85 g light. And obviously you also need the inflation bag, which is 108 g. You also need a paddle, PFD and a <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/petzl-meteor-helmet-climbing-helmet/?pid=10239">∞ Helmet</a> if you want to paddle rapids.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50137008502/in/dateposted/" title="Final Camp"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50137008502_a14d7aab17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Final Camp" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The features, according to the Packrafting Store:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Spacious, 37 cm wide inner with great foot space</li>
  <li>J-shaped Spraydeck which can be rolled to the side, making it an open boat</li>
  <li>Optional TubeBags for transport of your gear inside of the packraft</li>
  <li>Fin Mount for the <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de/Accessories/Anfibio-Skeg::691.html">optional Skeg</a></li>
  <li>Included Comfort Seat</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50352519212/in/dateposted/" title="Arriving"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50352519212_fb10443ac4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arriving" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Designing such a playful, versatile and lightweight yet durable packraft is an innovation, yes. You have to be more careful on low water, but with normal care and the intended use this packraft should last you long!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50352518397/in/dateposted/" title="Salamander"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50352518397_a2a08fe110_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Salamander" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The Packraft is Made in China, and this helps with it’s quality. Not many Western countries have access to the skilled labour force, the materials or tools necessary to produce such high quality packrafts which still do not cost a fortune. I found the quality, looking at the complete package, to be great. As the Packrafting Store gives an extended 3 year Warranty on the Rebel 2K, I imagine they are also convinced that it is a quality product!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50352667302/in/dateposted/" title="Read Carefully"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50352667302_ea11dfc50e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Read Carefully" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>As the packraft is Made in China it means it has to be transported by sea to Europe or elsewhere, and also labour and environmental standards are still lower in China than in Europe. On the other hand, most other packraft manufacturers also use materials which are made in China. I didn’t find a mention about sustainability or similar on the Packrafting Store website, which is something which could be addressed. In use a packraft is a long-lasting item, and always can be repaired, so I am not sure if the topic of recyclability is needed.</p>

<p><strong>Edit:</strong> <em>I found this <a href="https://www.transa.ch/marken/anfibio/">short information</a> (in German) about the materials, recyclability and fair pay. The Packrafting-Store.de also reached out to inform me that their packrafts, which are Made in China, are transported via a land route to Europe, and not via sea!</em></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I absolutely am in love with the light weight of my Anfibio Rebel 2K packraft setup. Together with the <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de/Paddle/Classic-paddles/Anfibio-Wave::875.html?language=en">920 g light Anfibio Wave paddle</a>, the <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de/Accessories/Anfibio-Buoy-Boy::950.html">Anfibio BuoyBoy Vest</a> and my <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/petzl-sirocco-helmet-climbing-helmet/?pid=10239">∞ Petzl Helmet</a> I have a packrafting setup which weighs around 4,5 kg. However, more important for me is the compact pack size which fits easily into or on top of a <a href="https://bit.ly/3l5QkTA">∞ Hyperlite Mountain Gear SouthWest 3400 pack</a> or the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/09/huckepacks-phoenix-lite-review.html">HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite</a>. Having such a compact packraft setup, which also is able to run Class II or more rapids, is immensely useful for me as it allows me to go more off-the-beaten track and run more remote waters.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50137014122/in/album-72157715182503422/" title="Summit Selfie V2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50137014122_2de7abcf10_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Summit Selfie V2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I found the Rebel 2K to perform well in rapids up to Class II+ with a good amount of water. The raft is agile and it’s easy to get it to go where I want it to go, and it also breaks well through waves. It’s OK in turning into an eddy or easy surfing, and I never capsized in it - it’s a pretty wide boat, and then packrafts generally are difficult to capsize. I haven’t tried doing an Eskimo roll in it, as I don’t have thigh straps, but you could install those for getting even more control over the raft and doing rolls. I used my legs, pushing against the inner tubes, for control, which worked good. I think also beginners will feel confident in this packraft, when running their first white water (as confident one can feel when one is for the first time running white water!)</p>

<p>The Spraydeck is a bit of a weak point for me, though - the Velcro closure will at some point let some water through, and I can’t get the Chimney to close reasonably well around my chest which means it will slide down after a while of paddling. I maybe simply should sew on some shoulder straps to solve this issue 🤔 (<strong>Edit:</strong> <em>The Spraycdeck + Chimney has been improved in current models, and should be better than mine, which is a packraft from the first batch.</em>) I also had some water pool on the Spraydeck after especially big waves, but simply pushing my knees and the Chimney up got the water off the boat. If I don’t need the Spraydeck it’s stowed away in a minute, neatly rolled and strapped to the side, making it an open boat. This is ideal for only crossing water bodies.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50352358751/in/photostream/" title="Anfibio Rebel 2K Closed Spraydeck"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50352358751_12b3529ca9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Anfibio Rebel 2K Closed Spraydeck" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50351661298/in/dateposted/" title="Anfibio Rebel 2K Open Spraydeck"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50351661298_2316213035_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Anfibio Rebel 2K Open Spraydeck" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Comfort seat which comes with the raft is good and comfortable, but the strap which you use to connect the seat to the raft ripped out of the seat after a day on the water - that should probably get a better, more durable seam in the future. In use I found this great, as that way I could take the seat easily out to inflate + deflate and use it in camp for sitting. Inflating the seat is hard work - the valve needs strong lungs to inflate, and deflating it is also not my favourite part of a trip, but practice makes perfect. Overall the cockpit of the raft is really generous - 37 cm width on the inside is plenty for me, and I can sit with legs completely stretched out in the boat. There’s a lot of space for my feet and legs, which allows me to move around to switch positions.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50137008647/in/album-72157715182503422/" title="Final Camp"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50137008647_fb866210fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Final Camp" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On calm lakes, the sea and slow-flowing rivers the Rebel 2K performed flawlessly, especially with the Fin mounted and the wind in the back. I was able to paddle 4 to 5 km an hour with it under such conditions, but even paddling into 10 m/s wind I paddled 2 km in an hour. I do feel it is best suited for paddling on rivers with a good flow - or then that’s what I prefer, as it’s less work with good speed 🤣</p>

<p>At the start of my Ivalojoki trip I got a <em>tiny</em> puncture into the main tube after I was sliding over gravel in some really low water sections (I should have simply got out and walk it, but I didn’t want to get wet feet 😬) and it drove me insane - I spent two evenings looking for an hour each for the hole, without success. On the third day on the water I by coincidence found it and was able to fix it, which gave me peace of mind. I also would recommend anyone who wants to buy a Rebel 2K to order a set of <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de/Repairs-stuff/Anfibio-LifePatch::804.html">LifePatches</a> with the raft, as strangely there’s some repair fabrics coming with the raft but nothing to attach them with. That tiny puncture wasn’t bad, I had to inflate the packraft every hour with two, three puffs to get it again fully inflated, but it still was something that made me feel uneasy when running the more demanding rapids - something which I could have avoided completely if I’d remember my Rule #1: <em>“Never slide with your packraft over gravel banks!”</em>. So, learn from my mistakes, and do it better!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50351661393/in/dateposted/" title="Anfibio Rebel 2K Bottom damage"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50351661393_bb41abdf16_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Anfibio Rebel 2K Bottom damage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, the optional Tube Bags. Well, <em>optional</em> only if you are not going to do long paddling trips with the raft, and as you’re reading this review chances are that is exactly what you have in mind. So take the Rebel 2K <strong>with TubeBags</strong>. It’s so much better than strapping the backpack with all your gear to the front of the boat, it limiting your view on the water and the possibility to transport your bike on it. I love the TubeBags. They are so easy to use, and 70 l of Volume per Tube Bag is ridiculously large. I could fit the complete content of my backpack in there, all the camera gear, and the backpack itself. It’s fantastic. You need to plan what you need throughout the day, as you can not open the TubeBags when the raft is inflated (doing that will break the TubeBags), so pack your stove, coffee and lunch into the <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de/Accessories/Anfibio-DeckPack::808.html">DeckPack</a> and you’re good to paddle the whole day without going hungry or decaffeinated.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50137010432/in/dateposted/" title="Full Deck Pack"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50137010432_91b0434902_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Full Deck Pack" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>Durability versus lightness, it’s the Battle of Eternity. In one of the <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de/Packrafts/MRS-packrafts:::43_65.html">MRS Packrafts</a> I can slide over gravel all day long without much of a problem - but then it is almost double as heavy as the Rebel 2K, and also a lot bigger in pack size. And as my packrafting style is more of a <em>“Hiking in the hills and then paddling”</em> the Rebel 2K suits me much better, as it makes the hiking and backpacking part of the trip more enjoyable. Nevertheless, I wish the Rebel 2K could be a tad more durable, while still being just as light. I also would wish for a better Chimney on the spraydeck, or a way that it gets tighter on top and doesn’t slide down so easily. I know that this is a problem which only really slim people like me will have, but this is my review, and I can wish here for things that better suit me 😆</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50137009587/in/dateposted/" title="Stuck"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50137009587_28e8f9dcac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Stuck" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50352359231/in/dateposted/" title="Anfibio Rebel 2K Bottom"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50352359231_b1b3af73f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Anfibio Rebel 2K Bottom" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>If you’re new to the world of packrafting and want the packraft to be an addition to your backpacking trips, or want to be able to paddle easy white water rapids, or cross lakes or the sea, then the Anfibio Rebel 2K is for you. This is one of the most versatile packrafts on the market, which combines a lot of great features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Light weight and compact pack size</li>
  <li>The forgiving and easy handling of the packraft in white water makes it ideal for beginners</li>
  <li>TubeBags are fantastic to transport gear on paddle trips</li>
  <li>With the optional fin you get faster on lakes and paddle more straight &amp; efficiently</li>
  <li>The fantastically low price of 827 €!</li>
  <li>Did I mention the compact size and light weight yet?</li>
</ul>

<p>All in all the Rebel 2K is for me the ultimate adventure packraft – the packraft I take when I will be hiking off-the-beaten track to get to scenic rivers, on which I then can paddle back into civilization. It is light on my backpack and great on the water - exactly what I expect from an adventure packraft!</p>

<p>If this sounds good to you, head over to the <a href="https://www.packrafting-store.de">Anfibio Packrafting Store</a> to order your Rebel 2K!</p>

<p>Make sure to <a href="https://youtu.be/Xp3Pkxnl_po">watch the in-depth Video Review</a> to see the Rebel 2K in use, and see more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157716006722083">Flickr Album</a>!</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>(and get great discount codes from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50058189326/in/dateposted/" title="Landing at Sondasören"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50058189326_1be31a2a12_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Landing at Sondasören" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/09/huckepacks-phoenix-lite-review.html"/>
    <updated>2020-09-10T19:28:37+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/09/huckepacks-phoenix-lite-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“When will you review the HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite?”</em> has been one of the most asked questions I have received in the past year - pretty much since I <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/B3GwSM3jA_C/">posted this pic</a> last autumn. Well, after 12 months of use, the review is finally here!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327475092/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS in the GREEN"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327475092_0c8791ea0e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS in the GREEN" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from HUCKEPACKS. There are Affiliate links in this article which are marked with an ∞ Infinity Sign 😊 You can use these <strong>AT NO EXTRA COST TO YOU</strong> but I get a small provision from the company. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on the affiliate links in this article &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/phoenix-lite/">HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite</a> is a 50 l Volume backpack which carries ridiculously comfortable up to 10 kg, and that for a weight of under 300 g. Add in the ZLite backpanel and the Hipbelt Plus and you can carry even more weight, in more comfort. It’s unique Accordion closure makes accessing the content easy without opening the rolltop, and gives this stylish pack a clean, functional look. It is ideal for backpackers who already have a base weight of four to five kilogram and are familiar with the ideas of ultralight backpacking. Watch the <a href="https://youtu.be/3tV8alDSVMo">Video</a> to see the pack in action:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3tV8alDSVMo" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received my Phoenix Lite in August 2019, and it has been with me <a href="https://youtu.be/-AYVkZf61UE">backpacking in Hammastunturi Wilderness</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/vPzDSYp71I4">hiking &amp; packrafting the Björkö-Panike Trail</a> and on many shorter trips around Vaasa.</p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>This <strong>ULTRALIGHT</strong> backpack is made to enable your outdoor adventures without carrying a gram too much. It does carry really damn comfortable, though =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744082458/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744082458_873ca178ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>My Phoenix Lite with a Medium back length weighs 296 g including all straps. Together with the optional <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/hipbelt-plus-lite/">Hipbelt Plus Lite</a> (Size S, 57 g/ Pair), one <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/hipbelt-pocket/">Hipbelt Pocket</a> (44 g) and the ZLite back panel (4 Segments, 106 g) it weighs 474 g.</p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>As the Phoenix Lite is so light, you could imagine it doesn’t have a lot of features. Well, that’s not the case - here is its long list of features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ergonomic S-Shaped Shoulder Straps with Daisy Chains on them</li>
  <li>Adjustable and removable chest strap</li>
  <li>Two really good side pockets</li>
  <li>One large stretchy front pocket</li>
  <li>Side compression straps to minimize the Volume on the Pack</li>
  <li>Inside and Outside attachment possibilities for the included <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/therm-a-rest-z-lite-sleeping-mat/?pid=10239">∞ ZLite Mattress</a>, which functions as back cushioning</li>
  <li>The optional Hipbelt Plus lets you carry up to 12 kg in the pack</li>
  <li>And finally the Extension Collar with the innovative Accordion closure</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326621698/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Front View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326621698_b2ff721d96_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Front View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>The Accordion closure of the Rolltop closure is a HUCKEPACKS innovation and makes your roll-top backpack look clean, with easier and less noisy access to the inside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327293976/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure, Top View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327293976_5e3cd40046_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure, Top View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>Hand-made in Germany, from the highest-quality and lightest materials available. The quality is absolutely topnotch, and I expect this pack to last me many years =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326621248/in/dateposted/" title="Made in Cologne"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326621248_2055c7ea0a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Made in Cologne" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p>HUCKEPACKS produces in a small workshop in Cologne (you can <a href="https://youtu.be/7oWBgnSEBMY">see it in this interview</a>) where the materials are cut and sewn together to create their ultralight packs and accessories. During cutting attention is paid to minimize waste, and also otherwise they try to minimize waste during production. The packs being made from DCFW or DxG I am not certain about what their recyclability is, but the life-cycle of the backpacks is long with normal, good care.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>As always, this is the most important part of the whole article - get a cup of coffee ☕️ or tea 🍵 and then read on.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/jw76p2" title="Breaking Camp"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327526877_bb4e5ea3f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Breaking Camp" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite is the lighter brother of the <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/phoenix/">Phoenix DxG</a>, and the Lite is made from black Dyneema Composite Fabric Woven (what we called cuben back in the day) in different strengths. The material is waterproof, the pack isn’t however - because the seams aren’t taped. In reality I haven’t had any rain/ water get into the pack, and the material is durable and has survived bushwhacking and heavier loads without problem thus far.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327464042/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327464042_756c9af547_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>COM. FORT. ABLE.</strong> I really love how comfortable this pack carries. The four segments of the ZLite, which function as the backpanel on the ergonomically designed back of the pack, are really pleasant on my back. And if you’re not a fan of it you also could use a different mattress or none at all, if you for example use the Burrito Frame packing method. I do get a sweaty back, but I do get that pretty much with every backpack I use. With food for 5 days, a tripod and camera gear the pack was really comfortable to carry all day long.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327462992/in/photostream/" title="Shoulder Strap &amp; Back Pad 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327462992_e7e4e47633_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Strap &amp; Back Pad 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I always have loved the shoulder straps Mateusz has on his backpacks, and these are no different. They are really well designed and with a good, ergonomic fit that carries also heavier loads in comfort, and most importantly: I can attach my <a href="https://bit.ly/3bKwoRH">∞ Peak Design Capture V3 Clip</a> on them, for easy access to my camera. The shoulder straps are made from a 3D Mesh and Copolymer foam, in different thicknesses which makes them soft &amp; flexible and they adapt well to you body, while at the same time transferring the weight really well, ensuring a comfortable carry.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326626583/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Ergonomic S-Shaped Shoulder Straps"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326626583_0190934d17_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Ergonomic S-Shaped Shoulder Straps" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327292251/in/dateposted/" title="Shoulder Straps Detail 5"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327292251_bd2f84f678_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Straps Detail 5" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327470517/in/dateposted/" title="Shoulder Straps Detail 6"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327470517_9f0b1d7b6b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shoulder Straps Detail 6" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Side pockets are spacious, and I can grab my water bottle while hiking, which I really appreciate, and there’s also space for more stuff, like my tripod, a Kuksa and my chili nuts. The front mesh pocket is big enough to fit in a <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-dirigo-2.html">large shelter</a> or my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/08/200-g-hardshell-montane-podium-pull-on-and-pants.html">rain gear</a> in there without problems.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327296011/in/dateposted/" title="Phoenix Lite Front Mesh Pocket 1"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327296011_99cbaf8125_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Phoenix Lite Front Mesh Pocket 1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327286491/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Side View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327286491_06d595bdb3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Side View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Hipbelt Plus Lite which I have with the pack suits my style better - I’m not a fan of the simple 20 mm hipbelt strap it comes with, and feel the Hipbelt Plus Lite is a good alternative for me. It wraps around my narrow hips nicely, and transfers the weight really well. Also long days with 10 to 12 kg are not problem, which is often the weight I carry at the start of a trip with all my camera gear, food and water.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326623528/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Hipbelt Plus"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326623528_fb3a9a2d9d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Hipbelt Plus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327290201/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS Hipbelt Plus Lite"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327290201_52d095df86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Hipbelt Plus Lite" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then finally, the collar and Accordion closure of the Phoenix Lite. Some of you might remember the original <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/03/first-look-laufbursche-huckepack.html">Laufbursche Huckepacks backpack</a>, which already had a very innovative closure that ensured that no water can get inside the pack. With the Phoenix Mateus went for a classic Toploader design with a rolltop closure – but the rolltop closure has a twist - actually, more a fold =) The Accordion closure gives this pack a really clean appearance as it folds the material, which in other backpacks comes out at the sides, to the inside. I imagine this adds to the durability of the pack, but it definitely makes it easier to get things from the inside, as you don’t even have to open the small hook as you can grab past it inside. No noisy Velcro which keeps it together, but a clean, minimalistic and durable way to close the top. I love it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326629468/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326629468_847d788bb6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50326630533/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure Unrolled"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50326630533_bd6a651143_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure Unrolled" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327295061/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure Accordion Closure Open"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327295061_5f5061d22c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure Accordion Closure Open" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327295581/in/dateposted/" title="Rolltop Closure Accordion Closure Really Open"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327295581_7ab0f384fe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rolltop Closure Accordion Closure Really Open" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>From a design perspective I understand why the Phoenix Lite’s main body is 40 l Volume and not more, but I have on the start of my trips often found that I’d wish the pack had 5 or 10 l more Volume. The simple reason is that in addition to the backpacking kit and food I also carry camera gear which can range in Volume anywhere between one and ten litres. Especially at the start of a trip, when there’s food for seven days along, it’s for me really hard to figure out how I get my camera stuff inside. This is a problem which likely not many will have, but I wish that somehow the pack would have a wee bit more Volume so I could fit my camera gear easier inside (I solve this problem usually by having the camera stuff in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/05/huckepacks-beipack.html">beiPACK</a>!).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327283211/in/photostream/" title="Tripod on the right, beiPACK, Camera Gear and Phoenix Lite"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327283211_08a9d35cf3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tripod on the right, beiPACK, Camera Gear and Phoenix Lite" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I also would like to lose the grommet in the bottom. I haven’t had any water come inside through it, but similarly I never had to drain the inside of my pack. But I see as a possibility for moisture/ water to get inside the pack when I set it down where it is wet.</p>

<p>Finally, I’d like the side compression go the complete length of the pack. Now it only compress the upper 2/3 of the pack, and not the bottom, and I’d wish that the side compression straps would be more like on the <a href="https://ula-equipment.9xrw.net/P3qZN">∞ ULA Ohm</a>, which has from all the backpacks I have used in the past 20+ years the best side compression system.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327284271/in/dateposted/" title="Wallace"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327284271_35c0a3baf8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wallace" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/50327286846/in/photostream/" title="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Side COmpression"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/50327286846_db0403a272_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Side COmpression" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I love how clean the pack looks when packed - there’s nothing superfluous on there, just a functional, beautiful pack which carries extremely well. And while I find it sometimes hard to fit everything I need to have along on a trip (as you can see above) it is a spacious pack for week-long trips. One thing I really appreciate and like is that a full pack doesn’t ride above my shoulders. Usually the pack stops on the same line as my shoulders, which is from an ergonomics point-of-view for me really good. It also gives usually the impression that one is on a day trip, as the pack is so small 😆 All in all this is my go-to pack when I’m heading outdoors, and I’m looking forward to many more great trips with this durable, beautiful, comfortable and well-designed pack. Also, make sure to see my detailed <a href="https://youtu.be/3tV8alDSVMo">HUCKEPACKS Phoenix Lite Review Video</a> to see what I carry in the pack and all the details in action!</p>

<p><strong>Convinced?</strong> Then head over to HUCKEPACKS to place an order for your <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/phoenix-lite/">Phoenix Lite</a>. In case they are Sold Out - which happens 😊 - follow HUCKEPACKS on Social Media (for example on <a href="https://twitter.com/huckepacks">Twitter</a>) to see when a new batch goes online.</p>

<p>You can see more photos of the Huckepacks Phoenix Lite in this <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157715920143562">Flickr Album</a>.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>(and you get great discount codes from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743870368/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743870368_db4f21caa2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Nine Best Hikes in Finland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/06/the-10-best-hikes-in-finland.html"/>
    <updated>2020-06-03T19:54:47+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/06/the-10-best-hikes-in-finland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“Finland, Finland, Finland, it’s the country where I want to be”</em>  is a great song by Monty Python, and now that you have it stuck in your head you probably want to find out about the best hiking destinations in this Northern European country which is well-known for its 180.000 lakes, 75% forest cover and more than a million of Saunas!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49967069446/in/dateposted/" title="The Best Hikes in Finland!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49967069446_1fc0f7da52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="658" alt="The Best Hikes in Finland!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Nothing to disclose here 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>Finland has the Everyman’s Right, and with it come one <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/worldheritagesites">UNESCO Natural World Heritage Site</a>, seven <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/nationalhikingareas">National Hiking Areas</a>, ten <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/wildernessareas">Wilderness Areas</a>, 40 <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/nationalparks">National Parks</a>, more than two dozen <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/othernaturesites">Nature Sites</a> and hundreds of open Wilderness Huts and Lean-to Shelters, which are accessible for every hiker, bikepacker and packrafter visiting them. You can enjoy a life-time of outdoor adventures in this country, without seeing anything twice.</p>

<p>As Finland is a large country it might be difficult to pick an outdoor destination to visit - as you see above, there’s quite some options. That’s why I got together with four outdoor-loving friends and asked them for their one recommendation where they’d go hiking in Finland, and together we created this amazing bucket list of the best hiking destinations in Finland! Any of the destinations are worth visiting in any season, so don’t be troubled if you see snow (or the lack of it!). We hope you enjoy our recommendations, find one which suits exactly what you’re looking for, and wish you a great time if you plan to visit!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744524097/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744524097_e4b54b9941_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>This list is in no particular order or ranking.</em></p>

<h2 id="hetta-pallas-trail">Hetta-Pallas Trail</h2>

<p>Fresh in my mind is the Hetta-Pallas Trail, which I skied in March this year. Besides amazingly cozy huts the scenery is MINDBLOWING. No wonder this is one of Finland’s first National Parks and one of the oldest hiking trail (it was known as Pallas-Ounastunturi National Park till 2005, when it was doubled in size as the Ylläs-Aakenus Nature Reserve was put together with the old National Park). What I loved the most on the Hetta-Pallas Trail were the fjells and the views. Going south from Hetta this amazing view of the fjells opens up, and once you have climbed the first summit you can see far into the distance and enjoy this breath-taking scenery. In the summer the trail takes you across the highest summits, and is definitely something I will return for!</p>

<p><em>Read more about the Hetta-Pallas Trail at <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/hettapallashikingtrail">outdoors.fi</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/03/impressions-from-the-hetta-pallas-hiking-trail.html">see my photos here</a>.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49715784458/in/album-72157713688204887/" title="Follow the Poles"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49715784458_99c11f4547_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Follow the Poles" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49716327811/in/album-72157713688204887/" title="Dusk"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49716327811_0353c656f1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dusk" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49715787458/in/album-72157713688204887/" title="The LIGHT SHOW"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49715787458_5f86ed7cb2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The LIGHT SHOW" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="st-olavs-trail">St. Olavs Trail</h2>

<p>The St. Olavs trail is a former pilgrimage path leading from Turku in Finland, to the Åland Islands, through Sweden and all the way to Trondheim in Norway. The Finnish part of the trail is leading you through the Finnish archipelago with stunning views of the countless islands. The trail is pretty easy and accessible, with accommodation options along the way if you don’t feel like camping. For those who love the water, this trail is a true gem - and my favourite in Finland.</p>

<p><em>Find out more about the St. Olavs Way on <a href="https://kathrindeter.com/autumn-bliss-hiking-the-st-olav-waterway-travelogue/">Kathrin’s blog</a> and <a href="https://www.instagram.com/kathrindeter/">follow her on Instagram</a>.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966439092/in/dateposted/" title="© Kathrin Deter | St. Olavs Trail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966439092_1b26c64b69_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="© Kathrin Deter | St. Olavs Trail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49965658228/in/dateposted/" title="© Kathrin Deter | St. Olavs Trail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49965658228_090f563dc1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© Kathrin Deter | St. Olavs Trail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966162321/in/dateposted/" title="© Kathrin Deter | St. Olavs Trail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966162321_d6d857a0b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="© Kathrin Deter | St. Olavs Trail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="sipoonkorpi-national-park">Sipoonkorpi National Park</h2>

<p>As we now are already pretty far south in Finland, it’s good to shed some light “<em>on the other National Park near Helsinki</em>”. Nuuksio is normally already pretty busy with hikers, and now that everyone and their dog head into the forest you better jump on a bus to Sipoonkorpi National Park. You can find some great trails and spots for a lunch here, Sipoo is small enough to explore it in a day if you hike fast, and big enough for a long weekend to see all parts of the National Park and not needing to hurry through it.</p>

<p><em>Read more about the Sipoonkorpi National Park at <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/sipoonkorpinp">outdoors.fi</a> and watch my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/microadventure-sipoonkorpi-national-park.html">Sipoonkorpi Microadventure</a>.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337485940/in/album-72157695044886921/" title="Signs &amp; Portents"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/824/40337485940_d2cae06a34_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Signs &amp; Portents" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/42144265471/in/album-72157695044886921/" title="Hiking too fast"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/970/42144265471_a7323be439_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking too fast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/41243046955/in/album-72157695044886921/" title="Goes on"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/963/41243046955_841eb20bc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Goes on" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337484140/in/album-72157695044886921/" title="Wood Anemone"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/964/40337484140_6437bfc456_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Wood Anemone" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="repovesi-national-park">Repovesi National Park</h2>

<p>Finnish climbers love Repovesi National Park, as it is home to some of the highest rock climbing routes - and definitely the most picturesque. Where else can you take a rowboat to the start of a climbing route? But also hikers, backpackers and packrafters love Repovesi National Park with its great hanging bridges, beautiful lakes and channels for paddling, not to mention the great viewing points from the top of the hills which dot the forested landscape. What is unique, too, is the possibility to use a fox-ferry, and if you want you to paddle with a packraft or canoe here, you’ll find great lakes &amp; channels which connect them.</p>

<p><em>Read more about the Repovesi National Park at <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/repovesinp">outdoors.fi</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/03/repovesi-trip-report.html">here on the blog</a>.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966875637/in/dateposted/" title="Repovesi National Park"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966875637_bbd38e657a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Repovesi National Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966092333/in/dateposted/" title="Repovesi National Park"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966092333_928b171142_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Repovesi National Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="helvetinjrvi--seitseminen-national-parks">Helvetinjärvi &amp; Seitseminen National Parks</h2>

<p>I have been a lot to these two National Parks, as they were the closest to the city of Tampere where I lived for five years. They’re pretty, with great infrastructure, cultural sights and always good for a surprise - be it the warm water of the lakes which are inviting for a swim, or the tasty mushrooms which you can find in the forest. There’s surprisingly few people around during the week, but in the weekends the famous spots attract a lot of people - these can be avoided if you go to the less popular (but just as pretty) spots in the two National Parks!</p>

<p><em>You can read about my hikes in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/05/pirkan-taival-virrat-helvetinj-rvi-np-kuru-trip-report.html">Helvetinjärvi</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2009/09/paroonin-taival-pirkan-taival-trail-parkano-seitseminen-np-kuru-trip-report.html">Seitseminen</a> here on the blog.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/nGJ3cF" title="There!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/654/20242121944_1c7a30a168_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="There!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/26X92W" title="Hay"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/769/20838446186_79eb66fa47_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Hay" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/aH250K" title="Wild Swimming"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/661/20677975689_4b6f1d92dd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Wild Swimming" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/20121805748/in/album-72157656271111848/" title="Night at the Lake"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/293/20121805748_d946d1f0ca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Night at the Lake" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="ruka-kuusamo-area">Ruka-Kuusamo Area</h2>

<p>The Ruka-Kuusamo area and Oulanka National Park are one of the most popular hiking destinations in Finland - and for a good reason. This area is known for old forests, deep river canyons &amp; rapids and in the winter you´ll find the most picturesque snowy trees here. The location in North-East Finland makes this place an interesting combination of Arctic Nature and Siberian Taiga, you can see it in both Flora and Fauna. The most famous trail is the Bear’s Trail but there are many other options for hikers too. Scrambling up the Konttainen Hill and gazing the Midnight Sun is one of our traditions that we do every Summer. There are so many beautiful Outdoor destinations in Finland but for it’s versatility this area is definitely one of our top destinations!</p>

<p><em>Find out more about Harri’s <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/">favourite hiking area here</a>, check out the <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/oulankanp?inheritRedirect=true">Oulanka National Park website</a> and definitely follow <a href="https://www.instagram.com/harritarvainen/">Harri</a> and his dog <a href="https://www.instagram.com/kaffegram/">Kaffe</a> on Instagram!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49965648123/in/dateposted/" title="© Harri Tarvainen | Ruka-Kuusamo"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49965648123_076fa34d30_b.jpg" width="1024" height="575" alt="© Harri Tarvainen | Ruka-Kuusamo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49965647778/in/dateposted/" title="© Harri Tarvainen | Ruka-Kuusamo"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49965647778_ab0859f3b7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© Harri Tarvainen | Ruka-Kuusamo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966151731/in/dateposted/" title="© Harri Tarvainen | Ruka-Kuusamo"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966151731_39e8022776_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© Harri Tarvainen | Ruka-Kuusamo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966151851/in/dateposted/" title="© Harri Tarvainen | Ruka-Kuusamo"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966151851_0943fe6cab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© Harri Tarvainen | Ruka-Kuusamo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="urho-kekkonen-national-park">Urho Kekkonen National Park</h2>

<p>The Urho Kekkonen National Park is something of a national treasure in Finland. It has it all: Amazing off-the-beaten track backpacking through the fjells, great views, lovely lakes and rivers, cozy huts and a lot of Saunas in which to relax after a day of hiking. It is the choice for more advanced backpackers who know how to navigate and feel comfortable to hike away from the few trails, and who obviously also know how to practice Leave-No-Trace. If that’s you - start planning a hike in this beautiful National Park!</p>

<p><em>Read about our <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/09/urho-kekkonen-national-park.html">backpacking trip in Urho Kekkonen National Park</a> and see the <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/urhokekkonennp">outdoors.fi website</a> for more information.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763936081/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Paradise Gorge"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/3745/9763936081_6ff6cf6a24_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Paradise Gorge" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763145235/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/3700/9763145235_51b887b518_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Mountain Laurel Designs TrailStar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/9763854414/in/album-72157635543361552/" title="Navigation in autumn can be colourful"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7382/9763854414_9995bc480b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Navigation in autumn can be colourful" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="pyrisjrvi">Pöyrisjärvi</h2>

<p>Almost like sitting in the shoulders of the Maiden of Finland (Suomineito), the Pöyrisjärvi wilderness area is a dream hiking destination for experienced hikers and people who love to fish. The area takes its name from Lake Pöyrisjärvi, surrounded by the photogenic sand dunes, large woodlands and hilly fells. Endless hiking possibilities will take you around the wilderness as long and as far as you have power to go. Pro tip: bass loves the combination of black, blue and gold. Try it, and you might have a chance to cook a delicious dinner for your crew! Remember to bring some butter and salt along!</p>

<p><em>Nella loves to fish &amp; hike, and she shares her adventures on her <a href="https://www.kaukokaipuumatkablogi.net/">Kaukokaipuu</a> blog and on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/nellahimari/">Instagram</a>. Get all the infos you need about Pöyrisjärvi Wilderness Area at <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/poyrisjarvi">outdoors.fi</a>.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49965647858/in/dateposted/" title="© MARINELLA HIMARI | Pöyrisjärvi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49965647858_5f46f06032_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© MARINELLA HIMARI | Pöyrisjärvi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49965647818/in/dateposted/" title="© MARINELLA HIMARI | Pöyrisjärvi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49965647818_d654a42df6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© MARINELLA HIMARI | Pöyrisjärvi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966151471/in/dateposted/" title="© MARINELLA HIMARI | Pöyrisjärvi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966151471_fa9bc6f8fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© MARINELLA HIMARI | Pöyrisjärvi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966470027/in/dateposted/" title="© MARINELLA HIMARI | Pöyrisjärvi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966470027_0440709226_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© MARINELLA HIMARI | Pöyrisjärvi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="ksivarsi-wilderness-area">Käsivarsi Wilderness Area</h2>

<p>My favorite hiking destination in Finland is Käsivarsi Wilderness Area. While I occasionally enjoy cruising down a well-groomed trail, nothing beats walking off-trail in a remote wilderness. While there’s a good trail system to explore parts of the area, my favorite thing is to take the seaplane to one of the lakes in the furthest corners of the area, next to the Norwegian border, and then hike my way back to Kilpisjärvi.</p>

<p><em>Isko thru-hiked the PCT in 2017 and nowadays hikes with his dog mostly in Finland. You can follow him on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/iskosalminen/">Instagram</a> and via his <a href="https://iskosalminen.com/">blog</a>, and find out more about the Käsivarsi Wilderness Area at <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/kasivarsi">outdoors.fi</a></em>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49965648923/in/dateposted/" title="© Isko Salminen | Käsivarsi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49965648923_1bb7506688_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© Isko Salminen | Käsivarsi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966430102/in/dateposted/" title="© Isko Salminen | Käsivarsi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966430102_5f072ea82b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© Isko Salminen | Käsivarsi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49966430022/in/dateposted/" title="© Isko Salminen | Käsivarsi"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49966430022_3d0ae7804e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="© Isko Salminen | Käsivarsi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, keep an eye on the <a href="https://www.nationalparks.fi/en/coronavirusguidelines">Guidelines Concerning COVID-19</a> while hiking in Finland.</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HUCKEPACKS beiPACK]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/huckepacks-beipack.html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-06T10:12:12+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/huckepacks-beipack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Need more space for small &amp; important items on your hikes? Get a bum bag! They are ultralight, multi-use and you’ll wonder how you survived without one before!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862406217/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS beiPACK"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862406217_ce53485a37_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS beiPACK" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from HUCKEPACKS. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on the affiliate links in this article &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/bZIgPo1rubg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I’m a big fan of keeping my gear sorted on my hikes, and a problem I encountered on many trips in the past is that I miss a bag or pouch for essential stuff which I wanna keep close but not really in my pockets or inside my backpack. Enter the fanny pack (<em>or a bum bag in British English</em>). Since seven plus years <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/shoulder-and-multi-use-packs-for-hiking-and-backpacking.html">I use different kinds of shoulder and fanny packs</a>, so the <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/beipack/">HUCKEPACKS beiPACK</a> is a logical addition to my HUCKEPACKS Fanboy collection. On my hike in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/09/impressions-from-the-far-north.html">Hammastunturi</a> last autumn 🍂 I still used a <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/hipbelt-pocket/">HUCKEPACKS Hipbelt Pocket</a> to store essentials, but now that I have upgraded to the more spacious beiPACK I think the Hipbelt Pocket will only come out to play as a … Hipbelt pocket =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862091341/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 02"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862091341_54fb62f1b4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 02" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now while theoretically the beiPACK is double the volume of the Hipbelt Pocket, I have found it fits actually more than double the content (as for how much, <a href="https://youtu.be/bZIgPo1rubg">watch the Video</a> above!). At 74 g with the strap (or 42 g without it) the beiPACK is not much heavier than a Hipbelt Pocket, but the possibility to load it up with a map, snacks, an SUL hardshell and a Pocket camera makes it a lot more useable for me - especially as a wee summit pack which I can load up with the aforementioned gear at camp and then head out to explore the hills and forests around my ⛺️</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49861560053/in/dateposted/" title="Closed beiPACK"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49861560053_bd657dce67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Closed beiPACK" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49861559858/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK top view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49861559858_5f84dd3241_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK top view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49861559738/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 03"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49861559738_290980ef25_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 03" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The beiPACK also comes with a flat inside pocket, which is where I keep my passport, notebook + pen and other documents, and a large main compartment. It’s waterproof and has a comfortable 25 mm wide strap with durable and easy-to-use buckles, which obviously can be totally removed if you decide to carry it in front of your chest, connected to your pack. You also can strap it around your pack, if you don’t like to carry it around your shoulders (which is my preferred way to carry it).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862404742/in/dateposted/" title="Happy Hiker!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862404742_59be7a5eca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Happy Hiker!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I especially love the limited edition <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/specials/beipack-special/">beiPACK Special</a> series, where a dozen different beiPACKS in various materials and colours are available. It definitely wasn’t easy to pick a colour I have to say, but I am super happy with the darkgreen woven DCF version I picked 😊 So if you have the problem of having small items in your pockets and flying around in your pack, solve the problem by getting a beiPACK!</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862405102/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK straps!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862405102_e96a6339c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK straps!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Planning your first Hike (Post COVID-19)]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/planning-your-first-hike.html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-23T09:13:28+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/planning-your-first-hike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Five weeks in self-distancing Mode, and many of us are sitting at home with itchy feet: When can we go hiking &amp; camping again? I’m using this time to think about &amp; plan the future hikes I wanna do, once the lockdown is lifted!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812710111/in/dateposted-public/" title="Planning!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812710111_6d4b456c63_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Planning!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Nothing to disclose here, except some Affiliate links 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>Air traffic is now 29% of what it was pre-COVID-19, trains and busses are also substantially less frequent, cars are standing at home unused, and on the other side you have National Parks, Wilderness Areas and our beautiful outdoors which is recovering, with animals appearing where they previously have been seen long ago and air pollution in cities is dropping, too. At home we also get busy thinking about the outdoors, and our post-poned outdoor adventures. I’m no different, and while I am sad about the cancelled ski trips this spring, I’m looking forward to the hiking, packrafting and bikepacking trips in the not-too-distant future!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812125413/in/dateposted-public/" title="Planning"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812125413_7ab1c1908b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Planning" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now, as I expect that planes will remain grounded (AMAZING for the environment and our #ClimateCrisis) I will continue to travel more by train and bus. I love to travel by train: You can walk around while the train rides, eat in the train restaurant when you get hungry, play games, the kids can jump around on the playground in the kids waggon, there’s functional toilets which are not the size of a shoebox, watch movies on Youtube or surf the internet, and one of the best things: Simply watch out of the window and observe the environment which passes you by. In Europe you can get quickly and affordably to most corners of the continent, and where the train tracks stop there’s usually a bus waiting to take you to the next destination.</p>

<p><em>By the way: <a href="http://tidd.ly/c0da99e4">Click this link</a> to win TWO Interrail tickets worth 800€ for when the lockdown is lifted and you can travel again!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812681426/in/dateposted-public/" title="ScotsRail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812681426_f61a95f083_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ScotsRail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, I currently also am stuck at home (relaxing while <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCwYqDhtJj1x3DXy4IPCxL2A/">painting tabletop Miniatures and terrain</a>) and besides the occasional day hike with the family or cycling along the coast I am already pondering where to go in the summer and autumn. It’s very, very likely in Finland, with small chances of heading to close-by Norway and Sweden, but unlikely to be further away. <strong>But hey!</strong> <strong>Finland is AWESOME!</strong> Beautiful, crystal-clear lakes for paddling, amazing forests full of tasty bilberries, soft trails and great camping spots, and once autumn comes by the beautiful colours of nature will delight us!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30173126067/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Bilberry fields forever!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1973/30173126067_f98ebaaf9c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bilberry fields forever!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The best thing that you can do right now, if you’re under lockdown and can not go wild camping, is to plan that next trip. <em>Anticipation is the greatest joy</em>, as we say in German. Get in a great mood by taking out your wish list of local, national trails you wanna hike or cycle, grab some maps and start planning. And not just the hike, also on how you get there (also if schedules might not yet be that reliable, so keep that in mind) - and remember my chorus of praise for trains above 😉 And as you have had to post-pone a few hikes, maybe also stay at a local B&amp;B or Hostel at the end of your backpacking trip, as a warm shower and a tasty meal before travelling home is what you deserve, and the local entrepreneurs will be grateful for your support after months of empty rooms.</p>

<p>That’s it. Planning that next hike helps you keep a positive outlook on this situation, and going over maps and pondering what to eat (and maybe ordering already some food for that trip) helps you to spend your time productively instead of watching Netflix. Maybe plan a hike that is 90% off-trail! Or a hike which visits all the sights you wanted to visit &amp; see already since a long time! Or a hike where you come out at a great Pizza place at the end 🍕 🤗 Right now there’s enough time to plan that next hike in great detail, and get the food &amp; supplies you need for it, so that when you can get back outdoors, <strong>you are ready!</strong></p>

<p>In that sense: Stay healthy, wash your hands and plan that next outdoor trip!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49805426157/in/dateposted-public/" title="Bushbuddy Ultra"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49805426157_e3a1f70c0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Bushbuddy Ultra" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
