<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: backpacking | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/backpacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-06-15T14:55:59+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HUCKEPACKS beiPACK]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/huckepacks-beipack.html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-06T10:12:12+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/05/huckepacks-beipack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Need more space for small &amp; important items on your hikes? Get a bum bag! They are ultralight, multi-use and you’ll wonder how you survived without one before!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862406217/in/dateposted/" title="HUCKEPACKS beiPACK"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862406217_ce53485a37_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="HUCKEPACKS beiPACK" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported with gear from HUCKEPACKS. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on the affiliate links in this article &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/bZIgPo1rubg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I’m a big fan of keeping my gear sorted on my hikes, and a problem I encountered on many trips in the past is that I miss a bag or pouch for essential stuff which I wanna keep close but not really in my pockets or inside my backpack. Enter the fanny pack (<em>or a bum bag in British English</em>). Since seven plus years <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/10/shoulder-and-multi-use-packs-for-hiking-and-backpacking.html">I use different kinds of shoulder and fanny packs</a>, so the <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/beipack/">HUCKEPACKS beiPACK</a> is a logical addition to my HUCKEPACKS Fanboy collection. On my hike in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/09/impressions-from-the-far-north.html">Hammastunturi</a> last autumn 🍂 I still used a <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/packs/hipbelt-pocket/">HUCKEPACKS Hipbelt Pocket</a> to store essentials, but now that I have upgraded to the more spacious beiPACK I think the Hipbelt Pocket will only come out to play as a … Hipbelt pocket =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862091341/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 02"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862091341_54fb62f1b4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 02" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now while theoretically the beiPACK is double the volume of the Hipbelt Pocket, I have found it fits actually more than double the content (as for how much, <a href="https://youtu.be/bZIgPo1rubg">watch the Video</a> above!). At 74 g with the strap (or 42 g without it) the beiPACK is not much heavier than a Hipbelt Pocket, but the possibility to load it up with a map, snacks, an SUL hardshell and a Pocket camera makes it a lot more useable for me - especially as a wee summit pack which I can load up with the aforementioned gear at camp and then head out to explore the hills and forests around my ⛺️</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49861560053/in/dateposted/" title="Closed beiPACK"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49861560053_bd657dce67_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Closed beiPACK" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49861559858/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK top view"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49861559858_5f84dd3241_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK top view" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49861559738/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 03"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49861559738_290980ef25_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK and Hipbelt Pocket 03" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The beiPACK also comes with a flat inside pocket, which is where I keep my passport, notebook + pen and other documents, and a large main compartment. It’s waterproof and has a comfortable 25 mm wide strap with durable and easy-to-use buckles, which obviously can be totally removed if you decide to carry it in front of your chest, connected to your pack. You also can strap it around your pack, if you don’t like to carry it around your shoulders (which is my preferred way to carry it).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862404742/in/dateposted/" title="Happy Hiker!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862404742_59be7a5eca_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Happy Hiker!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I especially love the limited edition <a href="https://www.huckepacks.de/store/specials/beipack-special/">beiPACK Special</a> series, where a dozen different beiPACKS in various materials and colours are available. It definitely wasn’t easy to pick a colour I have to say, but I am super happy with the darkgreen woven DCF version I picked 😊 So if you have the problem of having small items in your pockets and flying around in your pack, solve the problem by getting a beiPACK!</p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49862405102/in/dateposted/" title="beiPACK straps!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49862405102_e96a6339c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="beiPACK straps!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Planning your first Hike (Post COVID-19)]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/planning-your-first-hike.html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-23T09:13:28+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/04/planning-your-first-hike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Five weeks in self-distancing Mode, and many of us are sitting at home with itchy feet: When can we go hiking &amp; camping again? I’m using this time to think about &amp; plan the future hikes I wanna do, once the lockdown is lifted!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812710111/in/dateposted-public/" title="Planning!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812710111_6d4b456c63_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Planning!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>Nothing to disclose here, except some Affiliate links 😊. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>Air traffic is now 29% of what it was pre-COVID-19, trains and busses are also substantially less frequent, cars are standing at home unused, and on the other side you have National Parks, Wilderness Areas and our beautiful outdoors which is recovering, with animals appearing where they previously have been seen long ago and air pollution in cities is dropping, too. At home we also get busy thinking about the outdoors, and our post-poned outdoor adventures. I’m no different, and while I am sad about the cancelled ski trips this spring, I’m looking forward to the hiking, packrafting and bikepacking trips in the not-too-distant future!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812125413/in/dateposted-public/" title="Planning"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812125413_7ab1c1908b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Planning" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now, as I expect that planes will remain grounded (AMAZING for the environment and our #ClimateCrisis) I will continue to travel more by train and bus. I love to travel by train: You can walk around while the train rides, eat in the train restaurant when you get hungry, play games, the kids can jump around on the playground in the kids waggon, there’s functional toilets which are not the size of a shoebox, watch movies on Youtube or surf the internet, and one of the best things: Simply watch out of the window and observe the environment which passes you by. In Europe you can get quickly and affordably to most corners of the continent, and where the train tracks stop there’s usually a bus waiting to take you to the next destination.</p>

<p><em>By the way: <a href="http://tidd.ly/c0da99e4">Click this link</a> to win TWO Interrail tickets worth 800€ for when the lockdown is lifted and you can travel again!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49812681426/in/dateposted-public/" title="ScotsRail"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49812681426_f61a95f083_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="ScotsRail" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, I currently also am stuck at home (relaxing while <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCwYqDhtJj1x3DXy4IPCxL2A/">painting tabletop Miniatures and terrain</a>) and besides the occasional day hike with the family or cycling along the coast I am already pondering where to go in the summer and autumn. It’s very, very likely in Finland, with small chances of heading to close-by Norway and Sweden, but unlikely to be further away. <strong>But hey!</strong> <strong>Finland is AWESOME!</strong> Beautiful, crystal-clear lakes for paddling, amazing forests full of tasty bilberries, soft trails and great camping spots, and once autumn comes by the beautiful colours of nature will delight us!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30173126067/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Bilberry fields forever!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1973/30173126067_f98ebaaf9c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bilberry fields forever!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The best thing that you can do right now, if you’re under lockdown and can not go wild camping, is to plan that next trip. <em>Anticipation is the greatest joy</em>, as we say in German. Get in a great mood by taking out your wish list of local, national trails you wanna hike or cycle, grab some maps and start planning. And not just the hike, also on how you get there (also if schedules might not yet be that reliable, so keep that in mind) - and remember my chorus of praise for trains above 😉 And as you have had to post-pone a few hikes, maybe also stay at a local B&amp;B or Hostel at the end of your backpacking trip, as a warm shower and a tasty meal before travelling home is what you deserve, and the local entrepreneurs will be grateful for your support after months of empty rooms.</p>

<p>That’s it. Planning that next hike helps you keep a positive outlook on this situation, and going over maps and pondering what to eat (and maybe ordering already some food for that trip) helps you to spend your time productively instead of watching Netflix. Maybe plan a hike that is 90% off-trail! Or a hike which visits all the sights you wanted to visit &amp; see already since a long time! Or a hike where you come out at a great Pizza place at the end 🍕 🤗 Right now there’s enough time to plan that next hike in great detail, and get the food &amp; supplies you need for it, so that when you can get back outdoors, <strong>you are ready!</strong></p>

<p>In that sense: Stay healthy, wash your hands and plan that next outdoor trip!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49805426157/in/dateposted-public/" title="Bushbuddy Ultra"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49805426157_e3a1f70c0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Bushbuddy Ultra" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>If you enjoyed this article</em> <strong>Please support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>as this COVID-19 Pandemic means a severe loss of income for me (and you get Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-dirigo-2.html"/>
    <updated>2019-09-19T20:23:59+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/09/hyperlite-mountain-gear-dirigo-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Are you on the look-out for an cuben-fibre shelter with two entries &amp; vestibules, that is easy to pitch and keeps the bugs out? Then you should read my review of the Dirigo 2 from Hyperlite Mountain Gear!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48747435603/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Behind them leaves."><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48747435603_8e82c54dab_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Behind them leaves." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This article has been supported financially and with gear from Hyperlite Mountain Gear. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on the affiliate links in this article &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>Simple to pitch, spacious for one, and good for dry environments where you will encounter a lot of bugs, that’s where the <a href="http://bit.ly/2YQRTZD">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2</a> shines as an ultralight shelter. In humid and wet environments, if you’re tall or you hike with a friend then you might not find this shelter the best option.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/YTEcyaHXpmA" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I received the Dirigo 2 in the spring of 2019 and slept in it a dozen nights in Finland and Germany.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48753207373/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48753207373_825a024484_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The function of this tent is to keep you protected from bugs, critters and rain when you are sleeping outdoors. It’s a hybrid single + double wall design which pitches with two trekking poles and has two entries and vestibules.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744059288/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744059288_92d6ae9d7e_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The features as per Hyperlite Mountain Gear:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Easy entry and exit for two with dual entry</li>
  <li>Breathable panels at head and foot to combat condensation</li>
  <li>Two vestibules for exterior gear storage with #5 YKK Aquaguard® Zippers</li>
  <li>Two large mesh walls for maximum ventilation</li>
  <li>Pitches with two trekking poles and eight stakes</li>
  <li>Carbon Fiber ‘Ridge Bar’ adds superior strength and stability</li>
  <li>Reflective guy-out points</li>
  <li>Internal mesh hanging stow pocket</li>
  <li>Internal D-rings for clothesline</li>
  <li>Two side wall guy-out points for increased internal space</li>
  <li>Fully seam-sealed</li>
  <li>Line-locs on all guy-out points</li>
  <li>Includes X-Large Drawstring Stuff Sack for storage</li>
  <li>Made in Biddeford, Maine, USA</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48759617036/in/dateposted/" title="Packed Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48759617036_55578694e6_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Packed Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>In the last couple of years I have felt there haven’t been that much innovations in backpacking. This time I’d say the use of breathable DCF-WPB (that’s the breathable Cuben material, the same which is used in The Shell) is an innovation, although I’m not totally convinced that the small panels are enough or at the right place. Also, other companies already have used breathable cuben (with eVent) for several years in shelters.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48753274923/in/dateposted/" title="Breathable Side Panel of the Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48753274923_94371a0d71_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Breathable Side Panel of the Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>I found the quality of the Dirigo 2 excellent. High-quality materials assembled by precise craftsmen &amp; women in Maine - yes, this is a “Made in the USA” product that is superbly crafted and deserves this label.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48753529646/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48753529646_2af71a3486_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The weight of my <a href="http://bit.ly/2YQRTZD">Dirigo 2</a> was 802 g, that includes all guylines. The included Drawstring Stuff Sack is 13 g, while the stake set with 8 Easton Stakes is 114 g or ~14 g per stake. So everything together is 929 g for this shelter.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48753723652/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48753723652_4d2054ecc6_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>As I was just writing about weight, you’ll need to also think about the weight of your Poles, though these do not count directly to the weight of the shelter. I use Ruta Locura Yana Poles (together with the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/05/black-diamond-ultra-distance-trekking-poles.html">Black Diamond Ultra Distance Poles</a> probably my favourite trekking poles) which are 106 g per Pole. As I also use these throughout the day and do not carry them they aren’t included in the weight of the shelter, but obviously are needed. And as you read above, I use the <a href="http://bit.ly/30vnBf2">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Stake Kit</a>, and those are heavy. You could use much lighter Titanium pegs which are 5 g or less, then your stake set of 8 would be 40 g - quite a saving. However, I trust the Hyperlite Mountain Gear Stakes more in soft, wet ground and high winds, so I rather carry these instead of having some pegs pulled out by the wind.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48753722837/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48753722837_a371cb3886_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Now at 802 g the Dirigo 2 is lightweight, but there are lighter alternatives - especially for two persons. The <a href="http://bit.ly/30yZUm5">Ultamid 2</a> from Hyperlite Mountain Gear themselves is 534 g but does not include a bug netting (that would be 418 g extra if you take their own) or ground sheet. Personally I take a bivy with the Ultamid 2 as it adds to the flexibility of the shelter (I only have to pitch it when I know it will rain, and can sleep with just the bivy when the stars are out). Competitors like Big Agnes have the <a href="http://bit.ly/2IfqJpd">Scout 2</a> out, which in the Platinum Version weighs around 500 g - but also has no vestibule or dual entry. From the cottages both the StratoSpire Li from Tarptent and the ZPacks Duplex are of similar construction, weight and price.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48759613841/in/dateposted/" title="Packed Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48759613841_1ea25a9d4b_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Packed Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Dirigo 2 has a good interior height, this is achieved by the two trekking poles and the short carbon strut at the peak which creates more inside space. The trekking poles are angled and go into a grommet at the bottom and into a small reinforced pocket at the peak, this makes for a solid frame in high winds when the doors are closed. If you open the doors and roll them up you can enjoy great views, though this weakens the tent in high winds quite a bit. However, in reality you only will roll up the doors when the weather is good, so it really is a non-issue. Also on the inside is a small mesh pocket, I have used this for my headlamp to illuminate the tent and that has worked well. I really like the high roof and comfortable sitting height.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744202071/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744202071_6e6180c9f3_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>OK, for where is this tent made? It has a groundsheet (= GREAT for very wet environments) and No-See-Um mesh walls which keep the Bugs out (GREAT against mosquitos, ticks, deer flies and other critters and insects). However, in wet environments condensation is an issue and so I feel the Dirigo 2 is much better suited for trips in dry and bug-infested environments. If you mostly go backpacking in the spring and summer and encounter at your camp spots lots of bugs, this is a great choice. If you’re out year around, often in wet conditions, then this might not be the best option for you (then the <a href="http://bit.ly/30yZUm5">Ultamid 2</a> should be your choice).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48753208173/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48753208173_b6624a2071_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Something I also really liked about the tent was how easy it is to pitch. Spread it out in a square, peg out the corners, enter the trekking poles and adjust their height, peg out the doors and then the side panels and <em>Voilá!</em> you’re done. After some practice you’re able to pitch this tent in two to three minutes, and thanks to it’s design the inside will mostly stay dry if you pitch in the rain. Putting the tent down is equally simple, I like to fold it up once from each long side to the middle and then once in the middle, this lets me squeeze out any trapped air easily and I can roll up the Dirigo 2 into a small package. Attention only has to be paid to the carbon fibre strut and that it stays where it’s supposed to be, as sometimes it slips out and needs to be put back into place when you’re setting up the tent. The Dirigo 2 can be set up higher or lower depending on how much airflow you wish or how much drafts you want to avoid. I had no problems with drafts even when the outer was pitched 10 cm or more high, by choosing not completely exposed sites.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744192771/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744192771_6544ae0676_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then there’s the packed size. I was surprised by how large the tent is packed, and had to carry it usually in my front mesh pocket (which was the best choice after rainy nights). It packs, even when dry, fairly big, and I often found the included Drawstring bag too small for it - though as I usually just stuffed the rolled-up tent into the front pocket, this was not a problem.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48759804762/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Packed Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48759804762_45bc9adae5_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Packed Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I do think the Dirigo 2 could do with more interior space to make it less cramped for two people. Right now it is a solid 1-Person tent, though I would not use it with another adult. I also wonder why the Breathable Cuben was only used in the lower parts of the design, and not also at the top or over the whole side panel (it’s probably a cost thing). This would likely help to minimize or even eliminate the condensation issue. Also, while not really an issue for me, I do think the Dirigo 2 doors would benefit from a buckle at the bottom of the zipper which takes the stress of the zipper, that would make the zippers survive longer and also allow you to open the zipper while keeping the structural integrity more solid I imagine.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48747956897/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48747956897_3fbb76b422_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48747433823/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Side"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48747433823_63e8df43ae_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Side" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Are you mostly out in the summer, like to camp above the treeline, do encounter lots of bugs, like to have a groundsheet and generally a fully enclosed shelter? Then the <a href="http://bit.ly/2YQRTZD">Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2</a> is a good choice for you. It is excellently made, spacious for one, durable and sheds wind very well, while keeping the bugs and rain out. It is simple and easy to use, and does it’s job of protecting you from rain and bugs very well. All that does come at a price, as at $795 you almost pay $1 per gram of shelter. If you’re usually out with friends in wet and humid environments then you might be better off to use a modular setup with more space, something like the <a href="http://bit.ly/30yZUm5">Ultamid 2</a> or one of the many other pyramid designs out there.</p>

<p>If you found this review useful, please buy the <a href="http://bit.ly/2YQRTZD">Dirigo 2</a> directly from <a href="http://bit.ly/2OSpzjS">Hyperlite Mountain Gear</a> via my Affiliate Link. That way you support me at no additional costs to you!</p>

<p>More photos can be found in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157710871736107/">Flickr Album</a>!</p>

<p><strong>Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48753720577/in/album-72157710871736107/" title="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48753720577_1899f9c9bf_h.jpg" width="1600" height="1067" alt="Hyperlite Mountain Gear Dirigo 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Active Holidays in Åre]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/10/active-holidays-in-are-sweden.html"/>
    <updated>2018-10-02T21:36:17+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/10/active-holidays-in-are-sweden</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you want to spend an active week of holidays in Scandinavia, Åre is the place to go: Kayaking, trailrunning, hiking, kite surfing and downhill biking are just some of the activities you can do in this wonderful little village in Western Sweden. In the autumn the village is especially pretty, as the hills with their bilberry shrubs turn red and the birches add their golden leafs for that wonderful relaxing autumn feel!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44138646025/in/dateposted/" title="Jesper&#x27;s favourite view of Åre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1903/44138646025_c1a9022070_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jesper&#x27;s favourite view of Åre" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This journey was supported by the local tourism bureau and partners, but I did not got paid to write about this trip. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<h2 id="getting-to-re-sweden">Getting to Åre, Sweden</h2>

<p>As sustainability grows more and more important to me I find it harder and harder to book a flight. While you can fly to Åre I have a <a href="https://www.wasaline.com">ferry</a> in my town, that allows me to be very quickly in Umeå, Sweden. From there I can hop on a <a href="https://www.sj.se">train</a> and be in six hours in Åre, arriving right in the centre of the village. This is a very affordable and relaxing way to travel for me, as I can watch my favourite Youtube channels, read books, plot down ideas for articles and of course study the map for my upcoming backpacking trip in Vålådalen! From Finland you can also leave from Helsinki and Turku with the <a href="https://www.tallinksilja.fi">ferry to Stockholm</a>, and then take the sleeper train to Åre - allowing you to arrive well-rested in the morning and start your day in the active outdoor capital of Sweden!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002121082/in/dateposted/" title="The train, on time"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1919/45002121082_fcac469594_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="The train, on time" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="learning-downhill-biking-at-scandinavias-largest-bike-park">Learning Downhill Biking at Scandinavia’s largest Bike Park</h2>

<p>“<em>Are you Hendrik?</em>” my Guide Jesper asked me when I entered the Skistar Shop on the Main-square of Åre. “Yes, and I’m here to learn downhill biking. And I’m afraid.” “<em>That’s good!</em>” Jesper replied, and from then on I knew I was in good hands. Odin helped me get dressed in my “full-body harness” as I referred to it, a combination of a chest and back protector, hand and elbow protectors, shin and knee protectors and of course a helmet and googles. “<em>Have you ever sat on a Full-Suspension Bike?</em>” Jesper asked me when I was dressed. “No” I replied. “<em>No Problem, I’ll teach you everything there is to know about Downhill biking, from braking, getting up the mountain with the lift and safely getting down!</em>”</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002158152/in/dateposted/" title="Downhill Bikes are fun!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1966/45002158152_acf8fcdc3a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Downhill Bikes are fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“<em>Have you ever sat on a Full-Suspension Bike?</em>” Jesper asked me when I was dressed. “No” I replied.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>After I got my full-suspension bike we headed out and up towards the lift, where we stopped on a flat space and Jesper gave me the instructions I needed to get down the mountain, from the position of my feet (parallel to the ground), how to brake (with both brakes at the same time) and where to look while riding (as far ahead as possible). Then I needed to demonstrate what I was just told, and after a couple of circles Jesper decided I was ready to hit the tracks. A short instruction on how to put the bike into the chair lift followed, though attentive staff also was on hand and ready to help in case I’d mess up (I didn’t 😊).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002083102/in/dateposted/" title="Jesper enjoying the ride up"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1907/45002083102_82f5175d93_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jesper enjoying the ride up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/43238699830/in/dateposted/" title="Shadows"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1966/43238699830_7ed796cd10_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shadows" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the top of the hill it was just as easy to get the bike out and walk away, and then we were ready to drop in. “I’m still afraid” I mentioned to Jesper, upon seeing the tracks and how &amp; with what speed other bikers where racing them down. “<em>You’ll be fine. We take this slow, just brake a little all the time and you’ll just do what we talked about earlier.</em>” Jesper calmed me down, and to make it a wee bit easier we also skipped the first part of the track on this first run, and went in a wee bit further down the hill.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002085592/in/dateposted/" title="Jesper shredding in Åre Bike Park"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1938/45002085592_073810a424_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jesper shredding in Åre Bike Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/43238700880/in/dateposted/" title="Åre Bike Park"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1964/43238700880_bd80bde37b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Åre Bike Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, it went really just as fine as Jesper said. Maybe my experience of riding bike every day, bikepacking and riding on local trails had given me a good foundation and idea on how to ride downhill, but soon I was whooping as I took a curve high and fast or racing over the narrow trails. Yes, I was braking and definitely not as fast and good as many others riding in <a href="https://aresweden.com/en/are-bike-park/">Åre Bike Park</a>, but damn did it feel good to turn that fear into confidence, joy and hollers as I was riding down Åreskutan!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44330329874/in/dateposted/" title="Jesper on Organic, Åre Bike Park"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1960/44330329874_12f1c82bd4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jesper on Organic, Åre Bike Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002131842/in/dateposted/" title="Jesper on Organic, Åre Bike Park"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1902/45002131842_d9800d048d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jesper on Organic, Åre Bike Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31177171828/in/dateposted/" title="Another awesome title"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1911/31177171828_f69b18d8eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Another awesome title" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That first day we were two and half hours out in the Bike Park, and I not only got to see the best view over Åre, but I also got to ride many different trails - from the Beginner-friendly Serpentinen to the gorgeously scenic Organic. I really was overjoyed about the experience, and even if I didn’t master the jumps very well (taking off to early, with too much speed or not landing right) it was an amazing afternoon!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31177203358/in/dateposted/" title="Taking the curve"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1970/31177203358_6a4b0d156e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Taking the curve" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next day - because all good things come in pairs! - I headed back in the morning to the Ski Star Shop, and with some luck &amp; good timing Jesper and me were the first people on the lift up. There’s several chair lifts which bring bikers up the mountain, as well as the cable car, though sadly it was too windy and so the latter was grounded. That meant we wouldn’t be able to ride from the top as Jesper had planned, but he had some great trails for me to ride nevertheless. I asked if it’d be OK to ride down Serpentinen again as the first ride, so I can “<em>get back into the groove on familiar terrain</em>” and that was just what Jesper had planned.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31177213698/in/dateposted/" title="Åre Bike Park and Åresjön"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1970/31177213698_ecf52e3eb1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Åre Bike Park and Åresjön" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Then we took another lift up, rode to the other side of the mountain and enjoyed another scenic trail which brought us back down to Åre. Back up Jesper decided I was ready to ride Shimano, Åre’s most famous red trail. Shortly my fear flickered back up, but with some confidence inspiring words from Jesper I dropped in. Shimano has some 50 or so jumps (and I rolled over at least 40 or so of them 😬🤣) and 20 fat bank curves where you almost ride parallel to the ground, and it’s a trail which had me hollering quite a bit when I mastered a curve or a jump! After Shimano we had a small Fika in town, and then hit the trails a few more times before it was time for me drop off my gear and bike, say many thank yous to Jesper and leave the shop with a big, fat smile!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45049346661/in/dateposted/" title="A curve"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1917/45049346661_350805312a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A curve" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31177176678/in/dateposted/" title="Fast"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1960/31177176678_82cd4ac326_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fast" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45049349961/in/dateposted/" title="Lift"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1953/45049349961_42485ce582_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lift" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Downhill biking thus. It is strangely relaxing to ride down that narrow trail, always looking far ahead, not going too slow so you can take that curve as high as possible, and also trying to taking in that amazing scenery. You life in the present, things which you had on your mind while walking to the lift - remember that fear from the beginning? - are pushed aside, to be pondered about at another time, if ever again. The focus is on the trail in front of you, and when you arrive down at the lift station - a big smile and the excitement of that adrenaline rush leaving your brain. It’s addicting, and after years of wondering what people find in this “dangerous sport”, I know: Focus, relaxation and joy.</p>

<p>(<em>And while I feel that I already have enough hobbies, I think I need to etch out some time to go more downhill biking. And maybe I need to visit the <a href="http://arebikefestival.com">Åre Bike Festival</a> in 2019!</em>)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44330349554/in/dateposted/" title="Lean in"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1932/44330349554_a795af7d7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lean in" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="trailrunning-to-totthummeln">Trailrunning to Totthummeln</h2>

<p>Since the summer I am <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/08/my-trailrunning-gear.html">trailrunning</a> several times a week at home. Now, as some of you know, I life at the coast in Finland. Unlike, for example, the Norwegian coast, the Finnish coast is pretty similar to the Dutch coast. Which means it’s prettttttty flat over here. And while I run up and down several “hills” every week, these 15, 20 m of elevation did not really make me ready to run in the mountains. That’s the realization I came to when I was running with Björn up to Totthummeln, a scenic hill with a great view which lays between Åre and Björnen. We started from Granen, the Hotel I stayed at, and after a few hundred meters of asphalt we soon hit the Trollstigen Trail.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44138672535/in/dateposted/" title="Trailrunning on Totthummeln"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1909/44138672535_55bcb74c1a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trailrunning on Totthummeln" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44138673125/in/dateposted/" title="Trailrunning on Totthummeln"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1943/44138673125_1259752daf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trailrunning on Totthummeln" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31177183928/in/dateposted/" title="Totthummeln Summit View"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1902/31177183928_7d2857d49b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Totthummeln Summit View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>From then on it were sweet trails that took us around the mountain, with great views over Åre, the lake and Björnen, and then up to the top of Totthummeln. Björn’s personal best time around the mountain is 35 minutes, though with my help and the visit to the summit we made it in double the time back to my Hotel… Nevertheless, it was a great run, despite the rain, and if you don’t want to run to this easy summit - you always can make it a nice day hike with the family &amp; kids!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30113974717/in/dateposted/" title="A fine view over Åre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1954/30113974717_6f2cdd5655_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A fine view over Åre" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hiking-on-reskutan">Hiking on Åreskutan</h2>

<p>Before trailrunning with Björn I was out on my own in the morning, exploring the hiking trails of Åreskutan. There are over half a dozen trails which go up, around and across the mountain, and if you’re looking for a fun day hike - Åreskutan will not disappoint. Yes, you will cross the ski slopes once in a while, but most of the time you’ll be hiking in pretty forests on nice trails. There’s Cafés where you can enjoy a warm cup of coffee and a Kanelbullar, and if you don’t want to hike down you always can take one of the lifts back to the village. If the weather is good I can imagine that the hiking is very nice, and especially the Trollstigen Trail with it’s hidden treasures and wood nymphs is great for kids (it’s also only about a kilometre long, so also doable for 3 year olds!).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30113976777/in/dateposted/" title="Åreskutan"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1956/30113976777_2d81c95b4b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Åreskutan" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30113979907/in/dateposted/" title="Moody x 2"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1926/30113979907_536cba8a3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Moody x 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/43238730910/in/dateposted/" title="Share the Trail!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1975/43238730910_3bab9c2777_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Share the Trail!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/43238731630/in/dateposted/" title="Trollstigen"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1927/43238731630_c402275d10_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trollstigen" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="exploring-the-village">Exploring the village</h2>

<p>After all that hiking, running and cycling I was hungry. Already before I left to Åre I heard about the <a href="http://www.creperielogi.se/are/">Åre Crêperie &amp; logi</a>, and the place did not disappoint! It was very cozy with super-friendly staff, and the Vegan Crêpes were amazing &amp; soooooo tasty. I also went and had coffee at the <a href="http://arekafferosteri.se/">Åre Kafferosteri</a> which roast their own coffee - definitely a recommndation. As a Houdini Friend I also of course had to check out the <a href="https://houdinisportswear.com/se/vara-butiker?gclid=EAIaIQobChMIzMDAhcXn3QIV7p3tCh2bEAokEAAYASAAEgK1s_D_BwE">Houdini Store Åre</a>, though I also went to see the Shops of Peak Performance (which was founded in Åre in 1986!), Stellar Equipment and Haglöfs! Besides these stores you’ll find a couple other sports stores, and plenty of Cafés and Bars to spend the afternoons and evenings.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45049321061/in/dateposted/" title="Bergbahn"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1954/45049321061_88c68b945d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bergbahn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002085172/in/dateposted/" title="Houdini Store and Åre Kafferosteri"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1925/45002085172_83388b7b6f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Houdini Store and Åre Kafferosteri" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44138645385/in/dateposted/" title="Coffee!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1943/44138645385_10459b01c3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Coffee!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31177158568/in/dateposted/" title="Åre, Sweden"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1974/31177158568_5cbbfc50f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Åre, Sweden" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44330287344/in/dateposted/" title="It&#x27;s Fall"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1904/44330287344_cc2156a6c1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="It&#x27;s Fall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44138683435/in/dateposted/" title="A good local beer"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1939/44138683435_88987dfe12_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A good local beer" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002171692/in/dateposted/" title="Åre Centre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1906/45002171692_3991abf25a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Åre Centre" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44138718025/in/dateposted/" title="Vegan dessert crêpe at Åre Crêperie &amp; logi"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1905/44138718025_7f0699ae48_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Vegan dessert crêpe at Åre Crêperie &amp; logi" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="where-to-stay">Where to stay</h2>

<p>There’s over <a href="https://www.booking.com/searchresults.en.html?city=-2468311&amp;aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">30 Hotels and B&amp;Bs in Åre</a>, so there’s something for each wallet. I stayed my first two nights at the <a href="https://www.booking.com/hotel/se/hotell-granen.en.html?aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">Hotell Granen</a> which is a wee bit up the hill and offered a scenic view. The Hotel had an amazing breakfast, was super-beautifully decorated (I would have wished I’d had more time to just lounge in the comfy chairs by the fire place and read or drink a 🥃 in the bar) and not even three minutes on foot and one was in the centre of Åre!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45049319641/in/dateposted/" title="Hotell Granen"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1903/45049319641_f2f3f98bf2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotell Granen" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31177179578/in/dateposted/" title="Hotell Granen"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1979/31177179578_4a481ab925_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotell Granen" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002116182/in/dateposted/" title="Breakfast at Hotell Granen"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1966/45002116182_b4f2d5d097_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Breakfast at Hotell Granen" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/43238743400/in/dateposted/" title="Cozy Hotell Granen"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1903/43238743400_a85e819c52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cozy Hotell Granen" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>My last night in Åre I slept and dined at the <a href="https://www.booking.com/hotel/se/holiday-club-are.en.html?aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">Holiday Club Åre</a> which was equally impressive. This is a Holiday Club Hotel unlike any other I have seen - it’s modern, stylish and in the middle of town -  you get to the railway station via a bridge! The Holiday Club Åre has a Spa and Swimming Pool, and also is a popular Lunch place for the locals. I had twice a very delicious lunch here, and the Vegan 3-Course dinner was outstanding and so much that I couldn’t even finish my dessert! The room was very nice, I was sitting on the terrace in the sun and enjoying the view over the lake and town and a bit sad I had to leave so soon again.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/31177231818/in/dateposted/" title="Reception at Holiday Club Åre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1925/31177231818_b89d59ca1f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reception at Holiday Club Åre" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002141872/in/dateposted/" title="Holiday Club Åre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1957/45002141872_5c9c28bd3e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Holiday Club Åre" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/43238704690/in/dateposted/" title="Lemme relax!"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1948/43238704690_de5d5b5701_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lemme relax!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="wrapping-it-up">Wrapping it up</h2>

<p>A holiday in Åre can be many things: Exciting, relaxing, and tasty. I so much enjoyed my days in this small ski town, which unlike many other ski towns in the Alps or Northern Europe is open year-round. That’s right - Åre’s shops &amp; hotels are open almost the whole year, and the <a href="https://www.skistar.com/en/ski-destinations/are/">cable cars and lifts</a> run in the winter, spring, summer and autumn: In the winter they bring skiers and snowboarders up the slopes, while from spring till autumn it are hikers and downhill bikers who take a ride up to Åreskutan. Add in its proximity to several beautiful nature places like Vålådalen and just a short trip to Norway, and like me, you probably soon will fall in love with the authentic vibe of this small town &amp; its friendly people and you’ll wonder: When can I come back?</p>

<p><em>PS: Åre hosts the <a href="http://are2019.com">FIS Alpine World Ski Championships</a> in February 2019, if you’re interested in these kind of things - check out the linked website and <a href="https://www.booking.com/searchresults.en.html?city=-2468311&amp;aid=1603688&amp;no_rooms=1&amp;group_adults=1">book a room right away</a></em>!</p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/45002089712/in/dateposted/" title="Good bye Golden Hour"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1976/45002089712_d46e7122c4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Good bye Golden Hour" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions from Åre & Vålådalen]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/09/impressions-from-are-and-valadalen.html"/>
    <updated>2018-09-17T20:20:18+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/09/impressions-from-are-and-valadalen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ask a Swede about Åre and they will know: This is the place to be in the summer for Downhill biking, hiking, kayaking and many more outdoor activities, while in the winter this small village with it’s cozy Cafés, outdoor shops and restaurants becomes a bit bigger as people come to ski on Åreskutan and the surrounding mountains. I spent the last week in Åre and Vålådalen enjoying the Swedish nature &amp; hospitality - here is what you can expect!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797405447/in/dateposted/" title="Shadows"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1891/29797405447_26bd39546a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Shadows" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This journey was supported by the local tourism bureau and partners, but I did not got paid to write about this trip. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>I travelled via Ferry and train to Åre, which is very easy but it takes some time. A good book, your favourite Youtube show and naps will make the time go by fast, and before you know it you’ll be in Åre, not far away from the border with Norway. You’ll get the full information on how to get there, where to stay and what to eat soon, for the moment just enjoy these images and short tidbits about my autumn week in Åre and Vålådalen 🍂</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30863577668/in/dateposted/" title="Sign on Åreskutan"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1896/30863577668_ef064ff7ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sign on Åreskutan" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797397627/in/dateposted/" title="Björn Trailrunning"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1898/29797397627_dfc0b5111b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Björn Trailrunning" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30863578318/in/dateposted/" title="View over Åresjön"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1844/30863578318_b9972d37b0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="View over Åresjön" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797396557/in/dateposted/" title="Sunset over Tegefjäll"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1876/29797396557_4fcc5cb8da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset over Tegefjäll" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On my first day in Åre I went hiking, trailrunning and explored the little village. Even in the off-season that is now there were plenty of people out on the mountain and in the village, and after some rain throughout the day it cleared up and became a nice evening with a spectacular sunset.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797399437/in/dateposted/" title="Start of the hike"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1842/29797399437_28058402f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Start of the hike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2010/06/the-ul-fellowship.html">Eight years ago I have been in Vålådalen</a> (<em>and go read that article it’s still AMAZING!</em>) and I was excited to go back. Heck, to be honest, I want to go back there right now. The autumn colours were on point, the bilberries sweet and big, and the scenery just sublime. A detailed article only about the backpacking trip comes soon so stay tuned for that, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797398117/in/dateposted/" title="Reflections"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1878/29797398117_bd0490474c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reflections" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/30863581128/in/dateposted/" title="Blänktjärn"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1899/30863581128_7db9133c8b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Blänktjärn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797398947/in/dateposted/" title="Sommar"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1882/29797398947_4fb471976e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sommar" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44734044251/in/dateposted/" title="Nightfall"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1871/44734044251_edcbf4247e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Nightfall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797393097/in/dateposted/" title="Gregory Optic 48 far off the beaten track"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1868/29797393097_b84cbd9b50_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gregory Optic 48 far off the beaten track" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797401837/in/dateposted/" title="2nd Camp"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1856/29797401837_b4f71b3786_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="2nd Camp" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44734047971/in/dateposted/" title="Autumn in the fjell"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1852/44734047971_cb824675d1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Autumn in the fjell" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797408327/in/dateposted/" title="Not far till the finish"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1899/29797408327_d1b8373dc2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Not far till the finish" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After 92 amazing kilometres of backpacking it was back to Åre and doing something which I have never done before: Downhill Mountain Biking. A sport I had &amp; still have a massive amount respect for, and was scared of. But with my Guide Jesper I became confident and had so much fun ripping down the trails, taking these high turns, learning to jump (still learning 😂) and feeling confident on these narrow trails. Wow, that was soooo good.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797406357/in/dateposted/" title="Downhill Biking in Åre"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1898/29797406357_4e4643f66b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Downhill Biking in Åre" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797409417/in/dateposted/" title="Jesper taking a turn"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1870/29797409417_020b4662f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Jesper taking a turn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44734050251/in/dateposted/" title="On the Shimano Trail in Åre Bike Park"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1841/44734050251_809fbb7bf4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the Shimano Trail in Åre Bike Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There was great vegan food, tasty local beers, delicious crepes &amp; coffee, lots of bilberries, great views and friendly people.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797394187/in/dateposted/" title="Vegan Dinner at Holiday Club"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1880/29797394187_342f9ba477_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vegan Dinner at Holiday Club" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797393647/in/dateposted/" title="Red + Bilberries"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1889/29797393647_a50dca80fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Red + Bilberries" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoy The Week in Review &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
