<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: interviews | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/interviews/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2019-06-05T17:14:16+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cottage Interview: John Zahorian of Pa’lante Packs]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/08/cottage-interview-john-z-of-palante-packs.html"/>
    <updated>2018-08-08T19:09:01+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/08/cottage-interview-john-z-of-palante-packs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the 4th <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">Cottages Interview</a> of 2018 we get to know one part of Pa’lante Packs, John Zahorian 🇺🇸</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/2626nQ" title="13413275_135531730179792_711864439_n"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1833/43206572824_c8a029d336_b.jpg" width="1024" height="820" alt="13413275_135531730179792_711864439_n" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em><a href="https://palantepacks.com/">Pa’lante Packs</a> operates out of a garage in Arizona, and John Z as he is commonly known is one part of the company - the 2nd owner is Andrew Bentz. John Z has a great <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/johnzahorian">Youtube Channel</a> and has hiked a lot of long trails - no wonder he had some ideas how a good pack should be made! I am very happy that John took the time to answer my questions so that we can learn a bit more about Pa’lante Packs! Withour further ado - here’s the interview!</em></p>

<p><em>John, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking, and how did you start?</em></p>

<p>I grew up in Ohio and didn’t really begin adventuring until I started bike touring just after high school. Over time I grew more interested in the unpaved roads away from a steady stream of cars. And then while riding across the country one year I did an overnight hike in Glacier NP and had an incredible experience. I found out about the Pacific Crest Trail a few months later and promptly quit my job to do that.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Mt8oei" title="20902598_457268361325255_7608308817087954944_n"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1838/43206572704_cdd84a016b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="1024" alt="20902598_457268361325255_7608308817087954944_n" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</em></p>

<p>I am outdoors a lot. I live out of a compact car, constantly traveling and meeting up with hikers and hiking, in addition to nesting with my laptop in libraries all over. Additionally, every year I squeeze in a few months of longer trips.</p>

<p><em>Are you two more “weekend warriors” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</em></p>

<p>We both have long distance trips under our belt. I have hiked the triple crown (PCT, CDT, AT), the Arizona Trail, Colorado Trail unsupported fastest known time, Great Divide Trail, various sections of off-trail routes, and another 1900 miles on the PCT.</p>

<p><em>Hiking in Finland Readers &amp; me, we are gear-nerds! What is your typical baseweight?</em></p>

<p>My baseweight tends to float around 6lbs for thru hiking. Going as high as 8 in colder conditions and as low as 2 or 3 for a pleasant overnight. Another major variable in my gear selection for each trip is balancing how much I intend to focus on some quiet time outdoors vs challenging myself with higher effort hiking vs making the best video possible.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lidtJ_ya84I?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><em>Please tell us where the name “Pa’lante Packs” came from, and what it stands for.</em></p>

<p>Pa’lante came from Andrew’s time living in Panama, where “para adelante” is popularly shortened to Pa’lante, meaning onward or to keep going. This reflects our style of hiking, where you go fast and light, continually moving through the landscape. And this style is reflected in our products, which are designed for people who hike in a similar style.</p>

<p><em>What makes Pa’lante Packs different from other cottages?</em></p>

<p>Every cottage company is different and has its own area of expertise. Ours is currently characterized by our fast and light hiking style. We also are a bit different than many companies starting out in that we don’t really do custom work. We spend a lot of time iterating during the design process and making a lot of very deliberate design decisions and putting miles in to really live and connect with the designs before we are ready to release them to others.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0PRTrLdscvM?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><em>Is Pa’lante Packs your full-time job or “just a hobby”?</em></p>

<p>It’s a bit in between right now. We haven’t paid ourselves yet, but we are definitely very focused on the company. Andrew is graduating from college any day now and when he does he will be going full-time. I do the marketing/ brand /community side so my duties are a bit more abstract, but basically everything I do comes back around to “will this benefit Pa’lante?”.</p>

<p><em>Pa’lante Packs makes lightweight and stylish backpacks - two at the moment. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?</em></p>

<p>We both had similar goals, so it made sense to pair up. When we first got together to work on our initial pack designs, things really clicked. As far as the future goes, I’m not really much of a planner, just react to things as they come.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WNfoYXw-NxI?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><em>Any intentions of starting to branch out into other segments, for example offering shelters or bivys?</em></p>

<p>For sure! We have both been using our own shelter designs for a while now. But going from an MYOG project to a product for widespread use is a long road.</p>

<p><em>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in the USA that you work with?</em></p>

<p>The manufacturing company in Arizona that does our major production is a bit of a cottage manufacturer, being a small operation and the owner having a small cottage pack company as well. We also have really good relationships with Katabatic and Gossamer Gear. They have been really helpful and supportive to us as we’ve started.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/uP02f6" title="workshop"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1819/43924698051_7c75cf1939_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="workshop" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>And are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada and other places?</em></p>

<p>We are not.</p>

<p><em>Your company is still young and already has been getting good reviews and praise from all over the backpacking community. Is business going well?</em></p>

<p>The business is going well! Our major problem seems to be trying to keep up with demand, as we often sell out of our production runs rather quickly. We have not gone in debt and do not plan to, so this has provided a natural cap so that we do not grow too quickly helps keep the related growing pains down while we develop the processes to continue growing in the future if that is the case.</p>

<p><em>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of your new Joey backpack, and where the inspiration came from?</em></p>

<p>The Joey started with Andrew’s JMT FKT pack in 2014. He basically wanted a simple and lightweight running vest style pack. Then this past year the design process got kickstarted when Joe McConaughy and Joey Camps both went for the self supported AT FKT and used the packs that very closely resemble what the final Joey ended up being.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XMm6d25FUQQ?rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><em>John, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! What kind of new products are you working on at the moment?</em></p>

<p>I’ve been making some shelters I’m pretty excited about. Andrew’s been making some shorts. We’re in the early stages of a framed pack design. Fanny packs. I’ve been using my own fleece sweater recently. I use my own wallet. It’s a bit all over the place and based on what we want and are excited about.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/482VR7" title="P1210712"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1839/43206574614_afa765dc59_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="P1210712" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>And are there any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</em></p>

<p>There are so many possibilities with Dyneema Composite Fabrics. If there are very specific properties you desire out of a fabric you can dial in the layers to match those needs. And in addition to things like abrasion and tear and puncture strengths, you can also get heat weldable and adhesive bonding properties. Talking to Wes, the DSM applications manager, always gets me really excited.</p>

<p><em>How works the R&amp;D at Pa’lante Packs, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems, which then are adopted in the Pa’lante Packs line-up?</em></p>

<p>The start of a product always comes from our own needs. For the Simple Pack and now the V2, it came from gaining back the accessibility you lose when wanting to be uninhibited by hipbelts and large attachable shoulder strap pockets. With the Joey, it started with Andrew wanting a pack that would work well for his JMT FKT.</p>

<p><em>Where do your customer come from, and how do they find you?</em></p>

<p>In the beginning a lot of our brand awareness came from Andrew’s and my social media and trips. Internet chatter at places like r/UL and FB groups plays a big role in people’s gear awareness and decisions. And then I think that the word of mouth on long trails plays a big role. Even before everyone had a smartphone, information spread around the well established trails surprisingly quickly, and now with the proliferation of apps like instagram, hikers are extremely well connected and there are a lot of eyes on them, following their journeys.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/u8q4Tr" title="enchantments"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1832/43206572314_16552ebf65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="577" alt="enchantments" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>When and where was your last trip?</em></p>

<p>I just finished up a section hike on the Pacific Crest Trail in northern California this past week. I really love that trail and it’s always great to be out there on it, even though the weather was less favorable than I’ve experienced during the normal thru-hiking season.</p>

<p><em>And where is your dream backpacking trip taking you?</em></p>

<p>I’ve been looking at northern Canada with increasing frequency lately.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4Th47z" title="jupiter mcafee knob"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1798/43206572214_afddc1f275_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="jupiter mcafee knob" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</em></p>

<p>I take my Katabatic quilt with me on every trip. On an overnight that is often the only thing inside my pack other than food.</p>

<p><em>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the spring in Utah and Arizona?</em></p>

<p>We’re going to be taking a little “business trip” on the Hayduke Trail together this autumn! Both of us have been wanting to do that trail for years, so it will be great to be out there and hike together again.</p>

<p><em>Social Media - on which channels is Pa’lante Packs active?</em></p>

<p>We are on <a href="http://instagram.com/palantepacks">Instagram</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/palantepacks">Youtube</a>!</p>

<p><em>John, I thank you very mucho for taking the time to answer my questions =)</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/8VF15Z" title="adams"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1797/43206575284_ed997f7b23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="adams" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cottage Interview: Tom Gale of Atom Packs]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/06/cottage-interview-tom-gale-of-atom-packs.html"/>
    <updated>2018-06-11T19:08:30+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/06/cottage-interview-tom-gale-of-atom-packs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the 3rd <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">Cottages Interview</a> of 2018 we get to know Tom Gale of Atom Packs 🇬🇧</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/57g3oq" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1740/42680475452_76781e0371_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em><a href="https://www.atompacks.co.uk">Atom Packs</a> I found when Alex Roddie tweeted about the company earlier this year, and like Alex I think the packs which Tom makes are really great looking with smart details. As I was making the list of companies to interview for this series Tom has one of the first ones I contacted, and I am very happy that he agreed to participate (he’s super-busy and hasn’t had a day off in four weeks, so order your pack AFTER you read this interview, OK ;). Without much further ado - here’s Tom’s Interview!</em></p>

<p><strong>Tom, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking, and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>Who am I? Whoa now, this could get deep. I guess I’m a hiker: It is at the core of nearly everything I do.</p>

<p>I started long distance hiking in 2009, setting off on the Appalachian Trail like so many others under a crippling load with as many things strapped to the outside of my bag as were inside. I think I also had maybe 8L of water with me. Urgh. That guy. The longer I hiked, the more content and quiet my busy brain became and I swiftly began to feel that this had to be something that I built my life around. I came home and began working towards becoming a professionally certified Outdoor Guide and, within a few years, was doing what I loved and sharing my passions with others every day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/3w2A25" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1742/42680476092_9b0ecaf815_b.jpg" width="1024" height="846" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</strong></p>

<p>Hahaha, less so now than I would like. I tend to get out on my mountain bike for at least an hour a day. This business expanded much quicker than I’d anticipated but I try and find the time, normally I work until about 7pm and then get out for an hour, chasing the sunset through the trees on one of the mountains near my house. I’m pretty well situated for some incredible riding, even if I’m exhausted it always makes me feel better.</p>

<p><strong>Are you more of a “weekend warrior” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong></p>

<p>I’m a huge fan of micro adventure. I try and get out most weekends but the reality is that currently I don’t get much time off - Hopefully soon things will come back under a little more control. I live surrounded by mountains and lakes and it’s very easy to just grab a pack and go, but I suppose my priorities are currently with growing my business.</p>

<p>I have hiked some 12,000 miles now on the big three trails in the US, the Te Araroa and another few thousand miles around the coast of England. I don’t plan on stopping any time soon, this business might try and stop me but, hey, I’m thirty years old and it’s about time I tried some of this so-called “adulting”. I promised myself I’d give the business three years and see where I am at, only then will I decide if it was a dumb idea.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/623M9Q" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1737/42680476172_c33442b8d2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Hiking in Finland Readers &amp; me, we are gear-nerds! What is your typical baseweight?</strong></p>

<p>That’s a great question. I actually have no idea. Somewhere between 3 - 5 kg. I used to count every gram but after my third major hike I realised it didn’t actually make much difference to me - I’m a big guy, 6ft7 and 100 kg and I eat an absolutely OBSCENE amount of food, at least 2kg a day when on trail so my pack weight is always pretty heinous when leaving town. I also realised it was completely relative – my 3.5kg base weight felt just at terrible the day I left town on the PCT in 2015 as it did leaving town on the AT in 2009 with a 9kg base weight. It doesn’t matter what your baseweight is – your bag will ALWAYS feel like shit the day you leave town. Why worry about a couple of ounces here and there when you are about to hike out an entire rotisserie chicken, three avocados, a bunch of bananas, some beer and whole loaf of bread out of town… It’s good training. I’m not belittling the gram counting approach – for people who have some control over there caloric intake I’m sure it’s very justified – I will just always completely fill my bag with food regardless of how long it is to the next town so the base weight becomes a pretty small percentage of that.</p>

<p>There are a lot of hikers who can starve themselves on trail and come into town with zero calories i.e. without a morsel of food left in their bags. This is the elusive thru hiking “gold star” but, the reality of achieving that largely gives me an anxiety attack, I think I’ve only ever done it twice in 12,000 miles and I nearly fainted. It’s completely out of my control.</p>

<p>I do try to stay under 3.5kg but my process on a thru hike is always the same. I start heavier than I want to, then pare my gear down over the first couple of months, shedding everything I can, and then I realise I’m cold and uncomfortable and in as amazing hiking shape as I’ll ever be and then start adding luxuries items again. I’d say I’m at my most ultra light eight weeks into a hike.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Kn5436" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1727/28856277618_9e24f89dab_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “Atom Packs” came from, and what it stands for.</strong></p>

<p>I was trying to think of the smallest, lightest thing that I could. Initially the name was Atomic Ultralight but try typing that into Google and you’ll quickly realise why I changed it, you just can’t compete with the entire spectrum of information on quantum physics. I was stuck on the name for ages and then one day the name <a href="https://www.atompacks.co.uk">Atom Packs</a> came to me. The fact it’s got my name in it as well is just a very happy accident – A-Tom Packs. People give me credit for that. They shouldn’t.</p>

<p><strong>What makes Atom Packs different from other cottages?</strong></p>

<p>I make durable, lightweight gear (Dura-lite if you will!). I build the best packs that I can out of the best materials available to me. Sure, there may be lighter materials available, but that comes at a cost of either durability or comfort. The way I see it, there has to be some sense behind design: A backpack has the hardest job of any piece of gear that you carry, it is responsible for holding onto literally everything else that you take with you into the wilds and an extra few grams in its design can greatly increase both the durability of the pack and the carrying comfort of the user - In my view that is well worth the weight penalty. If you design a pack right, you won’t know that it’s heavier because the weight is working FOR you, not AGAINST you.</p>

<p>I think, in essence, most companies are all in this for the same reason: There isn’t the gear that we desire available to us, so we make our own. Every hiker on the planet has a different way of doing things, so I aim to create the gear that individual people want. Sure, some people will say that another brand/ fabric/ method is better, and they could well be right when it comes to their way of hiking, but I have designed my brand to be flexible to peoples needs so, I’d ask that person to shoot me an email and lets talk. It’s a great learning experience for me as well as people force me to step out of my comfort zone and design something new – quite a few of these requests have actually become part of my daily designs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/D1Ge7D" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1731/42680475722_25128f21b6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="890" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Is Atom Packs your full-time job or “just a hobby”?</strong></p>

<p>It’s now full time! Argh! I have some token bits of guiding work over the summer but the reality is that I can’t really afford the time away from the business at present so, yep, I now sew for 70+ hours a week. It’s pretty intense.</p>

<p><strong>Atom Packs makes lightweight and stylish backpacks and backpack accessories. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?</strong></p>

<p>It mostly came from a need to create the gear that I wanted - I’m so tall that any off the shelf backpack/ daypack that I bought ended up with its hipbelt somewhere below my nipples. Combine this with a natural curiosity for the unknown and I found myself sitting at a sewing machine making quite a horrible mess. That is basically the process that is still ongoing today, if not a little more refined!</p>

<p>In the coming weeks I am moving into a proper workshop. Here I will expand my production to cope with demand and begin training up an employee or two. I know that this business cannot possibly expand any more than it currently is with me crouched over a sewing machine for 70+hours a week. The danger is that I eventually have some kind of sewing-induced break down and run bare-assed and screaming into the cold night, never to be seen again. A lot of cottage companies have gone the same way and I’m trying really hard to not make the same mistakes. I’m still slipping and sliding my way along the learning curve but my processes are getting more refined with each day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/71118j" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1727/28856276158_a294c57d60_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Any intentions of starting to branch out into other segments, for example offering shelters and bivys?</strong></p>

<p>Yes… but lets not get ahead of ourselves.</p>

<p><strong>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in the United Kingdom that you work with?</strong></p>

<p>Not at present. Everyone I have spoken with has been very supportive though! I’d love to team up with a few brands in the future, that way we can all benefit.</p>

<p><strong>And are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada, the USA and other places?</strong></p>

<p>Other than a few messages/ comments via Instagram, not currently. There are some great companies making some great kit out there, Instagram gives you a nice peek into what they’re up to.</p>

<p><strong>Your company is a just several months old and already has been getting good reviews and praise from all across Europe. Is business going well?</strong></p>

<p>Haha, yes it blew up pretty quickly didn’t it!? I properly launched the website at the end of February and quickly got far more orders than I knew what to do with. I don’t advertise or spend money on promotion, I’m just trying to let it naturally grow by putting the product out there to be seen. Any product worth its salt will succeed, given the chance, I’m just very wary of outstripping my production capacity. I think that’s always the issue with cottage companies – when you are one guy in a shed it is easy to get overwhelmed and something that started off as creative and fun becomes a great, snarling monster that consumes most of your life. It’s been quite a journey, that’s for sure.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/m55c9N" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1727/28856276218_a3784e81ee_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of The Atom pack, and where the inspiration came from?</strong></p>

<p>I used to work with Adrian Moore at Aiguille Alpine Equipment and he used to say that “if you take away everything else, a rucksack at its most basic is just a potato sack with straps”. <a href="https://www.atompacks.co.uk/product-page/the-atom">The Atom</a> came from stripping back everything that I knew about backpacks and starting from the ground up. I wanted people to be able to start with a tube and add whatever they wanted to it, The Atom as you see it is exactly the pack that I would want on a thru-hike, it just happens that that has become the standard design.</p>

<p>I have to give some credit to “Dubstep”, my esteemed hiking companion of 5000 miles. I asked her to design her perfect backpack and she, not taking the process particularly seriously, designed a pack with rockets on the side pockets. That’s what inspired some of the Atom’s aesthetic, I was trying to make it look like a rocket.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/1C640E" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1750/28856276118_7a1db6739b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Tom, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! What kind of new products are you working on at the moment?</strong></p>

<p>Removable carbon frames. They’re the future!</p>

<p><strong>And any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong></p>

<p>Liteskin by Dimension Polynant. I bought a bunch of it and have been experimenting with it a little. KS Ultralight have been using it but I’ve not seen any long term reviews yet. It strikes me as a really solid fabric that, for its weight, is pretty incredible. I designed a 35L Atom with a padded hipbelt that came in at under 380g - that’s pretty special! The big test will be how well it holds up. I’ve been working with Andrew Sherry (@thehikingstory on Instagram) – I’m keen to send him one to try and break it just to see how well it holds up as there have been no real long term tests done yet and everyone, myself included, are a little twitchy.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/VEnfyk" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1760/28856276628_2eb647b7aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at Atom Packs, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems, which then are adopted in the Atom Packs line-up?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, I think I sort of answered this before. I have already solved the problems that I have encountered, so when people come to you with new issues it can really help to develop the product forwards.</p>

<p><strong>And where do your customer come from, and how do they find you?</strong></p>

<p>I put something on Reddit in February and it sort of went a bit wild from there. I sell a lot of packs to Germany and Scandinavia, I’ve also sent packs to New Zealand, USA, Canada and even Brazil. Basically anywhere. I’ve been amazed at how the Internet has driven this business forward, it has been simultaneously humbling and terrifying – the world is a very small place these days.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last trip?</strong></p>

<p>My last big hike was the Continental Divide Trail, I’ve only just properly gotten over it mentally 🤣. Otherwise I try and get out on day hikes where I can. It’s good for the soul and a great excuse to test backpacks.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/HE3707" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1737/28856276898_7ba145f6aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream trip taking you?</strong></p>

<p>The Te Araroa south island was about as happy as I have ever been. It was also the most amount of times I have ever nearly died in a period of time. I’d hike it again in a heartbeat! I’m aiming to go for the Arizona Trail this October but can not figure out if I can stop this runaway train I’m currently sitting on. I guess the dream trip is the next one you are undertaking or the one you are currently on. And there are so many trails! Argh!</p>

<p><strong>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong></p>

<p>I picked up an <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/msr-blizzard-tent-stakes-tent-stakes/?pid=10239">MSR Blizzard Stake</a> on the CDT and quickly fell in love. They cost $5, weigh 1 oz and I use it for both camping and digging cat holes (because everybody poops). Not only do you feel like you can dig forever but I also put a bit of duct tape on the inside edge and would use it as a water spout to get water out of slow trickling springs, it was amazingly effective!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/5u0449" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1733/28856277268_8c0927d4bc_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the summer in the United Kingdom?</strong></p>

<p>I would like to start a continuous walk around the Wainrwrights, these are 214 fells situated in the Lake District National Park. I doubt I’d be able to do it in one go but I can dream! Otherwise I am determined to hike the AZT in October. There are a load of 200 mile hikes in my vicinity. It’s just having the time!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/3n67QU" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1747/42680475572_e43c10ea46_b.jpg" width="1024" height="684" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Social Media - on which channels is Atom Packs active?</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/atom_packs/">@atom_packs on Instagram</a>. I need to get Facebook and Twitter set up properly so watch this space. It’s very distracting though.</p>

<p><strong>Tom, I thank you very mucho for taking the time to answer my questions =) Is there something you would like to add?</strong></p>

<p>I guess I’d like to encourage those who are seeking out their first UL setup go with their gut and not just the status quo. It takes many hundreds, if not thousands, of miles to truly understand what you need and don’t need. Just because you want a pack with a padded hipbelt does not mean you are no longer qualified to call yourself ultralight, no matter what they say on the forums.</p>

<p>Instead of obsessing over gear lists or whatever everyone else is doing, just throw some stuff in a bag and go hiking. If it works for you, keep it, if it’s cheap, even better. There are many thousands of ways to spend many thousands of dollars on gear. The best way to know what works is to go and actually do it yourself and then slowly, piece by piece, replace items for lighter alternatives. Once you understand an items use and, more importantly how you interact with it, then you can make a truly informed decision. Otherwise the danger is buying every piece of gear three or four times before you get it right – and that doesn’t leave you much money for hamburgers and beer. Thanks for your time, see you down the trail ☺</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/7S5h45" title="Tom Gale, Atom Packs"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1744/28856277078_b1251c4c84_b.jpg" width="819" height="1024" alt="Tom Gale, Atom Packs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this article <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cottage Interview: Maj and Kajo from GramXpert]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-maj-and-kajo-from-gramxpert.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-28T18:52:19+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-maj-and-kajo-from-gramxpert</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">Cottages Interviews 2018 Series</a> continues with the brothers Maj and Kajo, who together run GramXpert from Slovenia!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/6H528S" title="Interview1"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1724/41618983464_bf13cc332e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="713" alt="Interview1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>I first became aware of <a href="https://www.gramxpert.eu">GramXpert</a> as their Gear popped up in the German Ultraleicht Trekking Forum. Since then their <a href="https://www.trekking-lite-store.com/gramxpert-ultralight-backpack-34-4.html">backpacks</a> and <a href="https://www.trekking-lite-store.com/gramxpert-elite-quilt-apex-267.html">quilts</a> are also sold at the trekking-lite-store.com, and their kit is light and looks good, with some unique solutions. Reason enough to get in touch with the two brothers and hear their story!</em></p>

<p><strong>Maj and Kajo, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking, and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>We are two brothers with a passion for anything active and outdoorsy. Hiking is almost folklore in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2012/09/ultralight-summit-daytrippin.html">Slovenia</a> so we’ve been at it from a very young age. The biggest influence was our father. He regularly took us on multi-day hiking and biking trips when we were kids, and those adventures sparked our interest. We still have fond memories of our first bike tour at the age of 8. It was a 4 day, 120km tour and we rode fully loaded 20” bikes with only 6 gears :) Similar adventures on bike &amp; foot were on the menu every summer vacation since. As we got older we started planning our own trips. They became longer and more challenging and with that came better and more elaborate gear.</p>

<p>Kajo: 
I am interested in many outdoor activities, I am not taking anything as a competitive sport but rather as an adventure. I was into rock climbing for a long time, but lately caving and paragliding got my attention. I am responsible for designing new gear and coordinating custom orders, also the main craftsman and tester. I am also finishing my degree in geotechnical engineering so at the moment I can only work part-time.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4XkWCU" title="kajo"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/873/41439554545_c026ff7f65_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="kajo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Maj: My approach when it comes to life is holistic. I’m a trained chef and passionate about nutrition. I’m currently also an assistant coach, a Tuina masseur, and a TCM student. I am also an advocate for animal rights and a promoter of sustainable lifestyle. 
I’m the one that takes care of the bureaucratic side of the business, but I enjoy customer service, various daily tasks and of course sewing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/xK1BaZ" title="maj"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1743/41618981894_9a1a92b535_b.jpg" width="760" height="1024" alt="maj" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</strong></p>

<p>As often as we can be. We are very busy these days, but we always make sure to take some time off and go outside in order to recharge our batteries. We take every opportunity we can to go out, test our prototypes and work out the kinks.</p>

<p><strong>Are you two more of “weekend warriors” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong></p>

<p>We regularly go on two or three day hikes and one or two week-long trips per year. Too busy for anything longer at the moment. 
We want to experience thru hikes also, we just weren’t able to do it so far. Hopefully sometime in the near future.</p>

<p><strong>Hiking in Finland Readers &amp; me, we are gear-nerds! What is your typical baseweight?</strong></p>

<p>Kajo: It depends, but generally about 3-3.5kg for a 3 season setup. While I am very selective about each individual piece of gear, I never really weigh the total pack or bother with the LW/UL/SUL tags. I also still have quite a bit of room to optimize the setup.</p>

<p>Maj: I have similar base weight as Kajo, but I usually carry heavier food (fresh if possible). Thankfully it counts as a consumable :)</p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “GramXpert” came from, and what it stands for.</strong></p>

<p>As you might expect Gram comes from grams. As for the Xpert, we would never claim to know everything and are always happy to learn more, but we felt like our experience and almost obsessive research of design and materials justified the Xpert part :)</p>

<p><strong>What makes GramXpert different from other cottages?</strong></p>

<p>We really try to keep up with our short lead times, keeping the products at high quality levels and most importantly providing good customer service. Our products are also highly customizable. Each person has different needs and wants and we are always willing to adjust and adapt to every individual’s wishes.</p>

<p><strong>Is GramXpert your full-time job or “just a hobby”?</strong></p>

<p>Maj: A little bit of both. At the moment we are also busy doing a bunch of other things as we mentioned before, so we are not sure if this will be a full time job for both of us. I would like to keep working halftime at GramXpert so I can simultaneously work on other projects, but Kajo will put more effort into it in the future, after he graduates. European market for UL gear is quite small and most people (at least here in Slovenia) are day hikers and tend to sleep in huts. Despite that the business is on a positive trajectory and steadily growing. Our mantra is: “Find a job you enjoy doing, and you will never have to work a day in your life.”</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/N565Z1" title="hike"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/886/41439556645_15d7ae98ed_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="hike" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>GramXpert makes lightweight and stylish quilts, accessories and a backpack. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?**</p>

<p>It started with us trying to tweak the gear we bought so it would fit our needs. Then we made the first quilts for ourselves and our friends. The key moment was when Kajo’s plan to thru-hike the PCT fell apart due to bureaucratic obstacles. He realized he wouldn’t get the necessary visa in time, so he invested his savings in the company instead.</p>

<p>We’re very enthusiastic and full of ideas and plans for the future. We spend most of our free time thinking about our craft, our mission, and our vision. We’re aware of the areas in which we are lacking, but we always strive to improve. We never want to sacrifice quality in order to get a few extra sales, so while we definitely want to grow and flourish, we plan on doing it strategically.</p>

<p><strong>Any intentions of starting to branch out into other segments, for example offering shelters and bivys?</strong></p>

<p>Yes! Eventually we would like to branch out and offer most items backpackers need. R&amp;D takes a lot of time especially if you want to test the gear thoroughly. Bivys will be available soon. Later we will add some clothing items that are currently in the development phase. Branching out proved to be quite challenging seeing as different gear requires different sewing machine settings, or sometimes an entirely separate machine if you want to do it right. We learned a lot while we were launching our backpacks and we hope we can optimize the process and streamline the workflow in the future. Our workspace is quite limited, we’re currently cramped in a 20 square meter room and this makes some things an impossible task. We would like to produce shelters as well, but first we need to move to a bigger workshop.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/1c0rfr" title="delavnica1"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/889/41618984514_30e1b40594_b.jpg" width="1024" height="585" alt="delavnica1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
 
<strong>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in Slovenia that you work with?</strong></p>

<p>No, we are not aware of any other similar cottage manufacturers nearby, but we do collaborate with a couple of independent local suppliers.</p>

<p><strong>And are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada, the USA and other places?</strong></p>

<p>Not at the moment, but we are open for collaboration. It might be interesting to work on some joint projects.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/f4NA1h" title="machine"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1756/41439561425_9d0d444413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="machine" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Your company is still young and already has been getting good reviews and praise from all across Europe. Is business going well?</strong></p>

<p>We’re slowly but surely increasing the visibility and hopefully building a good reputation. We are very happy with how things are going, but it will take a while before everything will run smooth. We’re planning on expanding our product range so we can reach more people, but like we said, quality over quantity.</p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of eLite quilt, and where the inspiration came from?</strong></p>

<p>Kajo: Our past experiences inspire all of our products. The same thing happened with eLite. I remember winter camping a few years ago. Trying to find those tiny cordlocks to completely close the footbox in the middle of the night drove me crazy. As soon as I came home I designed a new quilt with a handy closure. With eLite you can close the footbox in a breeze, even with your gloves on.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Y99p2E" title="DSC02064new"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1731/41618983844_b022e02cc6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="534" alt="DSC02064new" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Kajo and Maj, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! What kind of new products are you working on at the moment?</strong></p>

<p>There are many prototypes of different gear in the works and you can certainly expect new and exciting things in the near future. Insulated balaclava and backpack accessories will be out in the upcoming months. We’re also currently testing two bivy models along with a simple rectangular 1P tarp/ ponchotarp.</p>

<p><strong>And are there any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong></p>

<p>Not really, but we’re looking forward to the day when super light and breathable DCF will be available :) 10g/m² or lighter shell fabric for quilts would be really awesome.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/0Q4F5B" title="quilt"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/877/41439559695_e24e189e42_b.jpg" width="963" height="1024" alt="quilt" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at GramXpert, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems, which then are adopted in the GramXpert line-up?</strong></p>

<p>The “base” products are mostly inspired by our own experiences. We design the prototypes, then incorporate any improvements we might feel are needed. Due to our gear being highly customizable, we can always consult each individual customer and figure out a solution for their specific needs.</p>

<p><strong>Where do your customer come from, and how do they find you?</strong></p>

<p>All over the world, but mostly from Europe. Some find us organically, but it seems that most of our customers discover us through word of mouth.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last trip?</strong></p>

<p>We took a two day trip two weeks ago. We hiked through Kamnik-Savinja Alps, mainly because we live nearby, so it was really convenient on top of being gorgeous. Our last week-long trip was last autumn. We did a section hike of Slovenian mountain trail.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Q4791o" title="bivy"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1725/41618985814_014999499c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="bivy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream backpacking trip taking you?</strong></p>

<p>Kajo: My dream backpacking trip is constantly changing. Currently it’s PNT (Pacific-Northwest Trail).</p>

<p>Maj: I enjoy taking short trips all over the world, but if I had to choose, the ultimate backpacking experience would be exploring South America.</p>

<p><strong>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong></p>

<p>Kajo: That would probably be my wind jacket. It’s super convenient if you are always a bit cold like I am. In the colder seasons I always bring a pair of Climashield pants with me to keep me warm and cozy.</p>

<p>Maj: I also never leave home without my wind jacket, but other than that, I always pack my knife so I can prepare fresh meals.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/wTxzZ5" title="triglav"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1739/41618973534_3f9a6d3d06_b.jpg" width="1024" height="654" alt="triglav" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the spring in the Julian Alps?</strong></p>

<p>Our trips are mostly planned a day or two before they actually happen. There is still a lot of snow in the Julian Alps, so we’re focused on other areas at the moment. Our next trip will probably be somewhere in the coastal region. What we really like about Slovenia, and in particular the area near the capital, is that a short 1 hour drive can take you to a sub-mediterranean climate at SW, alpine at NW and continental in the eastern parts of the country. So on a good winter day you can choose between snowshoeing or rock climbing in a T-shirt :)</p>

<p><strong>Social Media - on which channels is GramXpert active?</strong></p>

<p>We’re not very active on social media at the moment, but we plan to change that in the future. We occasionally post on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/GramXpert/">Facebook</a> and you can also find us on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/gramxpert/">Instagram</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/86oZ0X" title="tent"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/878/41439558095_2c558bdcd5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="tent" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Maj &amp; Kajo, I thank you very much for taking the time to answer my questions =) Is there something you would like to add?</strong></p>

<p>We’re really happy that the ultralight community is growing and supportive when it comes to smaller manufacturers.  Hvala Hendrik for this opportunity to showcase our work, and all the best to you and your readers!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cottage Interview: Paul Stokes of Tread Lite Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-paul-stokes-of-tread-lite-gear.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-21T20:46:59+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-paul-stokes-of-tread-lite-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">Cottages Interviews 2018 Series</a> is a go and kicking things off is Paul from Tread Lite Gear, who makes amazing kit in the UK 🇬🇧!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4m3931" title="Scotland"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/908/42203328842_b94266a2e6_b.jpg" width="960" height="540" alt="Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>I know Paul and <a href="http://www.treadlitegear.co.uk">Tread Lite Gear</a> since several years and have interacted with him on Twitter on and off. Paul’s gear gets very good reviews from other bloggers and the wallets I bought from him a few weeks ago are very nice indeed. Paul has found a niche and serves it really well. But enough from me, here’s Paul’s answers!</em></p>

<p><strong>Paul, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking, and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>Hello all, Im Paul, im 47 and hail from Coventry in the UK. Its about as central in the UK as you can get and is also about as far as you can get from anywhere interesting to walk. Im married and have a 12 year old daughter. Back in my youth I was in the scouts and my Dad also took me on some hiking trips. I think that’s where my love of all things outdoors started. I suspect like many people life gets busy and you put things on the back burner whilst you chase a career, get married and have a family etc. I started getting back out maybe 10 years ago. At the time Ray Mears was doing his thing and for me it started with bushcraft. I quickly realised that what I really wanted to do was get out in the hills and I started to put away the all the heavy kit and look to ways to lighten my load so I could have a more comfortable journey. I also love to hammock and tend to hang in the winter months. If only there were more forests at altitude.</p>

<p><strong>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</strong></p>

<p>Back when I was in employment I tried to get out at least once a month. After starting the company I was permanently broke and reinvesting everything to get it off the ground so trips were pretty thin on the ground. Last year saw a few health issues that kept me off anything too strenuous but hopefully that’s behind me now and im really looking forward to some proper summit time this year. I have already got two long weekends in the diary for end of May and middle of June. It will be a bit of a shock to my legs im sure!</p>

<p><strong>Are you more of a “weekend warrior” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong></p>

<p>These days I’m mostly out on the weekends but back in the days when I had paid holidays I did a few longer trips in Norway, Estonia and Scotland. I think Norway is a stunning country, its hard in the UK to enjoy my love of a hammock but combine it with walking any great distance. My first time was just a week walking around the Nordmarka. It was cool to walk out of Oslo station and get the metro to the trail head. Easy walking and trees on top of most peaks made for some great hangs. My other Norway trip was very different as I headed off to Karasjok way up in the arctic circle for a winter trip. Pulling a toboggan along frozen rivers was truly fantastic. The Estonia trip was great too. Another winter getaway to Laheema National Park. Living in a temperate climate I’d never seen the sea frozen so that was pretty cool. Im hoping to do something special for my 50th in a few years so need to get my thinking cap on for a destination. I’m never likely to get the time to do anything epic but maybe I could do a few sections of one of the big American trails. I hear the AT is pretty hammocky so that appeals.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/786DoS" title="Estonia"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/973/28376482688_fc04c899d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Estonia" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Hiking in Finland Readers &amp; me, we are gear-nerds! What is your typical baseweight?</strong></p>

<p>It is getting there now. Back in the first year of the business I sold pretty much all my high end kit to keep the lights on. At the time it was painful but looking back it did allow me to start with a clean slate. Like most folks I’d learned a lot of lessons over the years about what worked for me and what didn’t so I was able to assemble my ideal kit list as funds permitted. Im at about 4kg base for 3 season ground camping. I recently got hold of a lightly used DCF Khufu from <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/interview-jotaro-yoshida-from-locus-gear.html">Locus Gear</a> and it’s a really quality bit of kit. The inner I find a little tight on length so I’ve just ordered an EE recon bivy to give a bit more room. My go to pack is an old GG Mariposa, it’s a vintage version in silnylon with acres of external mesh pockets. I don’t like to go into my pack until I hit camp so the mesh works great for stuff I need to access through the day. It’s a bit big for most trips but at just over 500g I’m happy to pack my sleep kit loose to pad it out. I always think its strange when I look at the current model and it weighs nearly double. <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2009/11/interview-glen-van-peski-from-gossamer-gear.html">Gossamer Gear</a>, if you are reading this how about an anniversary special that hits the old weights? A 1.5oz DCF body Mariposa would be my dream pack. I have two so maybe one day I might get busy rebuilding one. My sleep mat is a GG Airbeam XL. Sadly no longer made but I love the extra width over my Neoair. I use a Cumulus 250 quilt from spring through autumn and an EE Enigma 10f for winter. Cooking is a Toaks 850 with titanium cone from Stormin Stove Systems and a Speedster alcohol stove all wrapped up in a Tread Lite bag for 179g total. I own a lot of ti pots but the Toaks is great. I can get a meal and a coffee from one boil and the handles located right at the top means its great in a cone and you don’t get hot handles. I won’t bore you with the whole list, but these are the main ones!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/AG283Y" title="Coffee Caddy"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/823/28376483168_5c86c9ee90_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Coffee Caddy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “Tread Lite Gear” came from, and what it stands for.</strong></p>

<p>Getting a name was a nightmare! You start off thinking of every word associated with being light only for a quick google to reveal someone got there first. I wanted something that reflected the UL sector I was aiming at but that also covered all the bases and didn’t pigeon hole any future product plans. In the end a short list was quickly whittled to Tread Lite Gear on the basis it was the only one I could get the domain for. I like it though, I think it sums up what the company is about and it rolls off the tongue nicely.</p>

<p><strong>What makes Tread Lite Gear different from other cottages?</strong></p>

<p>I think the main thing would be the focus on just hiking accessories. Most cottages offer a full service from the small stuff right up to packs, shelters and sleep systems. I wanted to be able to offer off the shelf products with no long waiting time to a high standard and at a reasonable price point. It’s a very simple ethos. It’s just me, one guy, one product at a time. I’m small enough that I get to interact with my customers on a more personal level and I think people like that connection, I know I do!</p>

<p>I don’t do mailshots or undertake paid marketing. I wanted to take a very organic approach to growing the business at a pace that was comfortable. I get sick of emails asking me to review my purchase so that’s a feature I’ll never implement on the site. Life is too short. I also took the decision not to give away kit for review. It’s not that im tight, it’s just that I believe a review carries more weight if someone has parted with money to get it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Uje400" title="Pot and Stove bags"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/829/42203334392_5d4a238a69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pot and Stove bags" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Is Tread Lite Gear your full-time job or “just a hobby”?</strong></p>

<p>I’m full time. I work long hours but I wouldn’t change it. It’s very rare that it actually feels like work. I get to sit and watch box sets on Prime or Netflix all day while I work. Some people say I’m really a TV critic and sewing is a by-product of the process =) I remember after I finished watching Breaking Bad that I’d love to convert a big camper van into a mobile sewing studio!</p>

<p>I love what I do though. I choose my own hours so there is great flexibility and I find it really rewarding. I think I’m probably unemployable now in the real world and every day I’m thankful that I don’t have to put on a suit, get in a car and drive ridiculous distances at the beck and call of others and tow the line. Its taken me a long time to find what I’m happiest doing and I’d never go back. Paying income tax in one go each year takes some getting used to though!</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>I love what I do. I choose my own hours so there is great flexibility and I find it really rewarding.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Tread Lite Gear makes lightweight lanterns and a massive amount of different pockets and bags accessories. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?</strong></p>

<p>In my old life I was a surveyor. I worked in the public sector for a large funding body providing capital funding for education. I left that to go into private practice on the other side of the table preparing property strategies and funding bids for clients. It was a great job and provided a comfortable life but it was stressful and involved a huge amount of travel and staying away from home. When the credit crunch hit, government funding collapsed. I managed to stay in employment and even started my own consultancy company. Eventually there were too many people chasing too little money and work started to be hard to come by. I kept it going a little too long. Usual story of flogging a dead horse when I should have cut and run. So one day I woke up with a pile of debt and no clue about where I wanted to go next but I knew I needed a change. With little cash to fund my gear I started playing at making my own. I bought a singer 201k sewing machine on ebay for £50 and a knackered MSR Hubba Bubba. I cut up the tent and made some awful looking monstrosities haha! I found I really enjoyed it though and after a few weeks of practice stuff started to look good. I thought the UK market was under represented and had potential so I shut the surveying business, flogged my car to release some funds and started the company. My wife went back to work full time to support us while I slowly set about building the business. Year 1 was really tough and I considered chucking it in more than once but deep down I thought it had the legs to go somewhere. Year 2 was much better and Year 3 finally saw the point where it seemed to start to gather some momentum.</p>

<p>In my mind I thought that summers would be really busy and winters would be quiet allowing me to hike more but it didn’t work like that and I seem to be busy year round. December is probably the only time I get to take a proper rest over Christmas and we usually rent a cottage in Norfolk. Long dog walks on huge beaches with big skies are a family favourite and it’s nice to switch off and relax.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4e61e4" title="Tryfan Summit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/952/28376483398_90f46dd160_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Tryfan Summit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I still use the same sewing machine for the majority of my work. It was built in the 1950s and it is still perfect. I like the juxtaposition of sewing space age fabrics on an old machine. I do have a bit of a habit of picking up more Singer 201s. There are 8 in the loft as we speak. A good investment though as prices are going through the roof.</p>

<p>The future is something im thinking about now a lot. Im about at the limit of what one guy can do in a small workshop. I think I’ll tough it out this year but next year I’m going to need some bigger premises and maybe some staff if growth continues. I have a largish garden and would have loved to construct a workshop but alas it’s a big investment so I’ll end up leasing I think. Expansion brings all sorts of extra hassle and more risk but we’ll cross that bridge when we get there.</p>

<p><strong>Any intentions of starting to branch out into other segments, for example offering backpacks or stoves?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t see it but I never say never. There are a few barriers that make it difficult. The UK has lost much of its fabric manufacturing base over the years and the type of materials customers want need to be imported. Packs, and shelters in particular use huge swathes of fabric and I’m not in a position to import tons of fabric at costs that make the economics work. My workshop is pretty compact too which means I don’t have the space for a huge cutting table. Watch the Workshop tour Video to get an idea:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BhC3Rm9cAd0?rel=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>In the short time I’ve been doing this I’ve seen many cottages go to the wall or have huge problems. The online communities are full of stories of people folding and still taking money from people for gear that doesn’t arrive. They always seem to be big ticket items where payment is taken up front and lead times can be huge. There are some very sad stories behind some of these situations and whilst you can empathise, I never want to be in the position of needing to take up front payment or suddenly having a workload that is out of control. Life throws things at you that you have to deal with and always at a time that is inconvenient. Although people cut cottages a lot of slack, when all said and done it’s a business and, you need to act accordingly and fulfil your obligations. For that reason if I ever did branch out into big ticket stuff I would only sell what I could put on the shelf.</p>

<p><strong>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in the United Kingdom that you work with?</strong></p>

<p>Not at this time.</p>

<p><strong>And are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada, the USA and other places?</strong></p>

<p>Not really although there are often interactions on social media.</p>

<p><strong>Your company is now three years old has been getting good reviews and praise from all across Europe. Is business going well?</strong></p>

<p>Yes it’s good. Cash is always tight but each year gets a little easier. I launched the website this year so that’s brought a new dimension to things. I kind of thought that ebay sales would subside as the web became more popular but ebay seems to continue to grow as does the website. In time I hope to get off ebay as it’s a terribly expensive platform to sell on and they are making it more and more admin intensive and bureaucratic for businesses. Im already introducing lines that won’t go on ebay.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/M5E9UJ" title="Packing Cells"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/967/42203326782_192201d601_b.jpg" width="1024" height="961" alt="Packing Cells" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of Chest Pack / Front Pouch, and where the inspiration came from?</strong></p>

<p>The chest pack in itself is very simple in its construction. I’d always liked the idea of a chest pouch and it’s something that customers asked for a lot. Reaching for side pockets can be a pain so it is nice to have somewhere easy to get to. The problem was always attachment to the pack. I’d tried some commercial versions in the past like the OMM trio and a Salomon one and always found them hard to mount to my pack and the weights were poor. I tried a few prototypes of my own but never quite got something that I thought would be a universal fit. The current model seems to tick those boxes and feedback has been great.</p>

<p><strong>Paul, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! What kind of new products are you working on at the moment?</strong></p>

<p>As I mentioned in another question im about at the limit of my time so I don’t have anything major planned. As I write this I’ve finally added cuben packing cells in a few sizes to the website which I’d only ever done previously on a custom basis. My focus over the summer will be weeding out the stuff that’s not really cutting it on the rosta, improving some of the photography and getting more pictures of gear in use whilst expanding some of the options on stuff that’s already there. My time outdoors is precious to me and I hate taking work out with me but I do appreciate studio photos are not as nice as stuff pictured on the hill. I seldom take a camera out with me. It’s too easy to live trips looking through a lens so I tend to just drink it in. I am also a little camera shy.</p>

<p>I’d also like to get a budget range of gear up on the website too as I’m always conscious that we don’t all have unlimited funds to splash out with. It is hard though as the labour costs and overhead are the same no matter what the fabric cost.</p>

<p><strong>Any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong></p>

<p>Not really, DCF (I still prefer the <em>cuben</em> name) is still really the benchmark and I don’t see anything to challenge it in the near future. I see lots of new, heavier weight fabrics that I like though, particularly from the racing sail side of the industry, but obviously their UL appeal is limited. I’m not a huge fan of the recreational lite skin for instance but some of the racing sail lite skin laminates are beautiful.</p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at Tread Lite Gear, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems?</strong></p>

<p>I think it’s a mixture. UL hikers are very knowledgeable. I mean we all spend hours on end looking for solutions and looking at Gucci kit to shave a few more g’s and for sure customers are your biggest asset when it comes to product development. You can’t make every customer suggestion work due to practicalities or economics but you can often implement small changes that make gear more useable. A good exampIe would be the roll top camera strap pocket which came into being after it was requested by Ed and Robin on the trek lite forum. Took me a while to get something I was happy with but they are very popular now.</p>

<p>I’m always kicking around ideas with the guys I walk with too. On my last trip to the Lakes I was testing a new UL rechargeable cuben lantern. Rich and Chiseller quickly made a few suggestions to improve the design and it was on sale the following week. Cheers chaps!</p>

<p>I do love doing something new as it breaks up the routine. I have a list of stuff that I’d like to make or develop when time permits. Some of that is customer driven and some are my own musings on gaps in my lineup.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/CfGa2r" title="Haweswater"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/28376482518_d2d96d62a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haweswater" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Where do your customer come from, and how do they find you?</strong></p>

<p>Last financial year 66% of sales were in the UK and 34% overseas. USA and Germany are about equal as the biggest overseas markets but I ship pretty much everywhere there is a reliable postal service. The UK decision to leave the EU has had a big impact on the strength of Sterling and it has been good for exports. It’s a double edged sword though with most of my input costs being in Dollars or Euros. I’m nervous about the deal that will be put in place post Brexit. It all seems a bit of a mess currently but hopefully it will get hashed out. Whatever happens I guess you just have to adapt. Filling in customs paperwork is already the bane of my life so I hope there isn’t a need for more of it. Politics eh? Its enough to make you go hiking =)</p>

<p>I’m on social media and forums so that is a big pathway to my door. I’ve been lucky to have some exposure from other areas which I’ll mention later if I may. Ebay and Google are probably a big route too.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last trip?</strong></p>

<p>Ennerdale in the Lake District late March for a couple of nights in the hammock. It was dry too. That’s probably my last low level camp this year. It is time to get some high level stuff in, get my fitness back and escape the midge season!</p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream backpacking trip taking you?</strong></p>

<p>I was recently chatting to a Norwegian customer who is about to embark on a trip from the far SW of Norway right up to North Cape (3000km). It’s not a recognised trail but of all the backpacking I’ve done in Norway just makes me glow inside. I think some of that has to do with the great company of people I went with, the warm welcome from local people we met as well as the great beauty of the place. So yea I reckon something similar.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/47Kg3J" title="At the Summit!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/28376483258_412a7231e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="At the Summit!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong></p>

<p>Too many! I love my little cuben lanterns and there is one clipped to all my shelters and hammocks. They weigh very little and its nice not to burn the battery on my head torch in camp and it saves the need to carry a spare cell. I’m a coffee fuelled entity too so my little cuben coffee caddy bag is something that sees a lot of use. Other stuff I’m never without is my Zebralight head torch. It has never let me down. My swing lite flex brolly, my old school Mariposa pack and a Fenix 5 watch for route tracking and data. I never thought an Umbrella would be something I’d take but it’s surprisingly useful and hey it is orange! I do like bright colours and own very little stuff in earthy tones. Top of my wish list is the new Garmin Inreach Mini. I seldom have a phone signal when hiking so it would be nice to text the wife to tell her I’m alive once in a while. I’ll wait a while and see what people think of it in use.</p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the spring in the United Kingdom?</strong></p>

<p>Yes indeed. Lake District end of May and middle of June. May to meet up with a few mates and June to meet some of the friends I’ve never met from the excellent <a href="http://trek-lite.com/index.php">Trek-Lite.com forum</a>. After that I’d like to get over to Snowdonia for a few trips. I like my mountains craggy and gnarly. Tryfan and the Glyders are a favourite.</p>

<p><strong>Social Media - on which channels is Tread Lite Gear active?</strong></p>

<p>I am on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/treadlitegear/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Treadlitegear/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/@treadlitegear">Twitter</a> for work and active on the Trek-Lite.com forum which I try to keep for more personal enjoyment although work does creep in as you’d expect. I recently culled a lot of the Facebook groups I’m active on a personal level as my feed was just solid hiking related and sometimes it’s nice to see what my family and friends are up to. I read BPL from time to time but I prefer smaller more close knit places. Hammock forums is somewhere I visit too and Reddit occasionally as I’m not mad on the interface although the content is good. I probably spend too much time online but most of the people I hike with I met through online community meetups. I don’t think I’ve ever met anyone I didn’t get on with and it’s always nice to put a face to a name.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/RvuFDD" title="Morning glory"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/946/28376483348_5c858970fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Morning glory" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Paul, I thank you very much for taking the time to answer my questions =) Is there something you would like to add?</strong></p>

<p>Well firstly thanks for reaching out to do the interview Hendrik. I’ve been lucky to have a lot of other people help in getting my name out there too so I would like to also offer them some thanks if that’s OK.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theoutdoorsstation.co.uk/2017/01/no-424-tread-lite-gear/">Bob Cartwright at the Outdoor Station</a> interviewed me last year which I really enjoyed and definitely had a positive impact on the business. To <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com">Chris Townsend</a> and the <a href="https://www.tgomagazine.co.uk">TGO Magazine</a> team who recently did a feature which has again given a boost to things and rather impressed my daughter at the same time. She took great delight in going to buy a copy and then texting pictures to everyone.</p>

<p>Thanks also to all the people on Facebook, Twitter, Insta, blog writers and Youtubers who share my posts and mention my products - many of whom have become friends!</p>

<p>My wife deserves special praise for her support, allowing me to steal away time working when I should be spending it with the family and yet still encouraging me to get out and hike.</p>

<p>Last but no means least, my customers. I get tons of messages offering thanks and encouragement. You keep the dream alive! It is deeply appreciated!</p>

<p>Happy Trails,</p>

<p>Paul</p>

<hr />

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this interview &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Greg Grenzke, Apparel Designer at Arc'teryx]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/03/mountain-people-greg-grenzke-apparel-designer.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-25T18:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/03/mountain-people-greg-grenzke-apparel-designer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“There is no bad weather, only bad clothes.”</em></p>

<p>That’s a popular saying here in the North, and it is easy to imagine that this saying drives <a href="http://arcteryx.com/">Arc’teryx</a> Designer Greg Grenzke and his team forward to design the best possible apparel for their <a href="http://arcteryx.com/ProductFind.aspx?language=EN&amp;Collection=Ascent">Ascent Line</a>. What goes into designing garments that are lightweight, functional and durable enough to survive in the mountains but are timeless in appearance you can read in this <em>Mountain People interview</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com" title="Greg Grenzke, Craftsmanship"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7634/16923034802_92c6824283_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Greg_Craftsmanship_AM0W9770" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Greg, thank you for taking the time for answering my questions.  Could you please introduce yourself briefly so we have an idea  what’s  your background?</strong></p>

<p>I studied industrial design at the University of Cincinnati as part of the DAAP (Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning program). Part of this program is cooperative education where they require the students to rotate between school and internships every 3 months year round for the last 4 years of the 5 year program. I did various internships throughout school such as with companies like Salomon Sports, Specialized Bicycles, and design firms. Anytime I had the opportunity to select the type of product I could work on it was always outdoor/ sports related, pretty much to the point my classmates would make fun of me because that was always my focus. This really helped me get my foot into the sports industry as I started building a portfolio of concepts/ products that I was really passionate about. I was offered a job before I graduated University from Specialized Bicycles. I worked there for 8 years designing all sorts of products such as footwear, bikes, bike graphics, helmets, saddles, gloves, really a huge variety of different products utilizing both hard goods and soft goods. The design approach was very hands on at Specialized which is also how things work at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a>. I have been at Arc’teryx now for over 3,5 years where I am the Designer/ Design Manager of the Ascent Apparel category. It’s been a fun challenge resolving soft good problems with more of an industrial design approach and methodology.</p>

<p>I have been active outdoors for as long as I can remember growing up in Michigan. Once I could drive (age 16 back then) that was really my door to freedom. I would borrow my mom’s car and go on road trips with friends to bike, hike, climb, ski, any opportunity I could typically heading west to the mountains.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16898393366" title="Greg bootpackin' by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr'"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8694/16898393366_a4e282d544_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="gg bootpackin" /></a>
©Rich Kupskay</p>

<p><strong>As a Category Manager for the Ascent line I imagine you’re a mountaineer and climber yourself. What are some of your favourite  routes and places?</strong></p>

<p>I still feel like I’m on vacation living in Coastal Mountain Range in North Vancouver as it’s somewhere I would come for vacation if I didn’t live here. You know you live in a pretty incredible place when you are traveling to other naturally beautiful countries and you still just want to get back home.</p>

<p>Some of my favorite places are very local like the Tantalus Mountain Range for alpine climbing which is about a 45 minute drive near Squamish BC, Canmore Alberta where I just went for my first time ice climbing with some of our athletes, and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html">Chamonix</a> where there are endless options! One of my other passions is ski touring/ mountaineering where again BC continues to stun me with its vast space and mountains where you often don’t encounter another soul sometimes for days at end.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16301931724" title="Greg and Tanja Schmitt, photo credit Matthias Scherer"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7627/16301931724_253140ddc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Greg and Tanja Schmitt, photo credit Matthias Scherer_Austria" /></a></p>

<p><strong>We met at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy 2014</a> at the “Insulation  types  for alpine environments” Seminar, where you introduced us with your  colleague Jon to the synthetic &amp; down insulation garments from  Arc’teryx. Some of these garments just came out - but can you give  us  a brief glimpse at what we could expect in the next season from  Arc’teryx?</strong></p>

<p>Well, let’s just say you can expect to see more insulation from us building upon our current offerings. There is a lot happening in the insulation world with new technologies and manufacturing processes. We are pretty conservative until we can prove the technology is substantially better than what we currently use and that it can stand the test of time. However, we are always experimenting with new ideas and technologies.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14784519783" title="Heatgun by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3847/14784519783_f6aee8fa98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Heatgun" /></a></p>

<p><strong>The Arc’teryx down insulation line has been available since 2013,  has it been more popular than your synthetics line?</strong></p>

<p>I’m not a sales guy so I’m definitely not the one to ask about sales numbers. However, the down line was a huge success after the 2013 launch and it is really growing extremely fast.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16304283443" title="Design Room"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8702/16304283443_9a7406a0f8_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-45" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What’s your own favourite layering setup when you head out into  the  mountains for a day of mountaineering or climbing?</strong></p>

<p>This really depends on where I am, weather conditions, how long I plan on being out, etc. But if I were to take a versatile system that works in many different situations I prefer to use something like a <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;model=Solo-Hoody">Solo Hoody</a> using our very hydrophobic Thermatek insulation as a belay/insulation layer, an <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;model=Alpha-FL-Jacket">Alpha FL shell</a> as it is very light weight, durable, and very breathable utilizing Gore-Tex Pro, a mid layer with high air permeability that provides light insulation but can dump heat/ moisture when you are pushing hard, and a slight synthetic base layer.   </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16923318411" title="Greg in Canmore"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8740/16923318411_1906e7e4ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="greg_canmore" /></a>
©Jon Rockefeller</p>

<p><strong>How long do you on average work on designing a garment? Is it a  couple of weeks from idea to prototype to fabrication sample, or  can  many months or even years go by?</strong></p>

<p>This also depends on if the product is a new style or a redesign of an existing style. Sometimes all the answers are in your head and the design time could be very quick. Other times, yes it can take months or even years to validate a design and it may not even make it to the market.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16923316131" title="Craftsmanship in the Arc'teryx Design Room"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8754/16923316131_2288edaba7_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-90" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Can you walk us through the different steps that go into making e.g. a Alpine climbing jacket like the Alpha FL?</strong></p>

<p>The first step is always defining the users need for a product. The Alpha FL is for travelling light &amp; fast while trying not to sacrifice durability. We had a really good starting point with the previous Alpha FL but we knew we could improve the product by minimizing seams, seam tape width, unnecessary glue/ fabric, and using a more durable face fabric with the Gore-Tex Pro membrane. We had various prototypes we tested in the field as well as in a lab for breathability testing. We ended up with a much more durable product at almost the same weight, about 69% less surface area from seam tape, more breathable, and more ergonomic feature set.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16301928864" title="Design tools"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8743/16301928864_22360c83f6_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-63" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are you &amp; your colleagues inspired by ideas from other companies  that make alpine climbing lines, or do you try to work in a vacuum  and  insulate yourself from what the others are doing?</strong></p>

<p>Ha, well North Vancouver can be a bit of a vacuum. We have a pretty unique work atmosphere and designers often challenge each other to make better products. Just walking around seeing what others are working on can be very inspiring and that’s where a lot of ideas stem from. We like to look forward and think about what could be done and not what has been done.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16304283403" title="2014-Northwoods-HO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8752/16304283403_723db53bf1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="2014-Northwoods-HO" /></a></p>

<p>  <strong>What role do your athletes have in the design process? Are they  involved from the start or does their feedback first come in when  they  are using what you have designed?</strong></p>

<p>We have some pretty amazing athletes in that they are so down to earth and easy to work with. They are some of the best testers we have as they literally live in the product. If their needs aren’t being met they will let us know and we will work with them to fill that need. Sometimes they will have ideas and we will make some prototypes for them to test. We do typically try to involve them early in the design process. We spend as much time with our athletes as we can, especially in the field as it’s a good excuse to get out of the office. Many of them are more like friends, as we share the same passions.    </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14731353344" title="Self-arrest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/14731353344_f604fca9f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Self-arrest" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What are the three most important attributes when you’re setting  out  designing a garment?</strong></p>

<p>Designing for longevity is typically one of the most important attributes that is always on our mind. This is really in the dna of the brand and it’s always rewarding to hear the stories of how someone’s jacket has lasted them over a decade, you can just see their face light up when they are telling you about it.</p>

<p>Another element of designing for longevity is building in timelessness. The brand has a very strong design language and we continue to build off this strong foundation. Although the materials and constructions continue to improve we want a product we design today to still look modern in 5 or 10 years. If you look at the lineage of something like the Beta AR or SV jacket, you can look at one from ten years ago and see the commonality. When we build in this timelessness we are also building in value.  </p>

<p><strong>Arc’teryx is well known for not resting on its laurels and  pushing  the boundaries. You’ve developed better water-resistant zippers,  were  one of the first companies to laminate seams, minimizing cuts so  that  seams are at an absolute minimum and many other innovations. Can we  expect another such innovation breakthrough from Arc’teryx in the  next  years?</strong></p>

<p>Arc’teryx always strives to push the boundaries and challenge conventional thinking. We still have some of the genius minds that helped create what the brand is today, as well as many new additions. We are definitely working on various future concepts but first we need to validate that they are feasible.</p>

<p><strong>Greg, thank you for taking the time for answering my questions!</strong></p>

<p><em>Liked this? Then please share this post with your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://arcteryx.com/" title="Screen Shot 2015-03-25 at 14.00.13 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8711/16738448720_5cfc100c7d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="598" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-25 at 14.00.13" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
