<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: interviews | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/interviews/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-05-21T12:38:44+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cottage Interview: Paul Stokes of Tread Lite Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-paul-stokes-of-tread-lite-gear.html"/>
    <updated>2018-05-21T20:46:59+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/05/cottage-interview-paul-stokes-of-tread-lite-gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/announcing-the-cottages-interviews-2018.html">Cottages Interviews 2018 Series</a> is a go and kicking things off is Paul from Tread Lite Gear, who makes amazing kit in the UK 🇬🇧!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4m3931" title="Scotland"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/908/42203328842_b94266a2e6_b.jpg" width="960" height="540" alt="Scotland" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><em>I know Paul and <a href="http://www.treadlitegear.co.uk">Tread Lite Gear</a> since several years and have interacted with him on Twitter on and off. Paul’s gear gets very good reviews from other bloggers and the wallets I bought from him a few weeks ago are very nice indeed. Paul has found a niche and serves it really well. But enough from me, here’s Paul’s answers!</em></p>

<p><strong>Paul, please briefly introduce yourself and tell us who you are. Since when are you backpacking, and how did you start?</strong></p>

<p>Hello all, Im Paul, im 47 and hail from Coventry in the UK. Its about as central in the UK as you can get and is also about as far as you can get from anywhere interesting to walk. Im married and have a 12 year old daughter. Back in my youth I was in the scouts and my Dad also took me on some hiking trips. I think that’s where my love of all things outdoors started. I suspect like many people life gets busy and you put things on the back burner whilst you chase a career, get married and have a family etc. I started getting back out maybe 10 years ago. At the time Ray Mears was doing his thing and for me it started with bushcraft. I quickly realised that what I really wanted to do was get out in the hills and I started to put away the all the heavy kit and look to ways to lighten my load so I could have a more comfortable journey. I also love to hammock and tend to hang in the winter months. If only there were more forests at altitude.</p>

<p><strong>How often are you outdoors nowadays?</strong></p>

<p>Back when I was in employment I tried to get out at least once a month. After starting the company I was permanently broke and reinvesting everything to get it off the ground so trips were pretty thin on the ground. Last year saw a few health issues that kept me off anything too strenuous but hopefully that’s behind me now and im really looking forward to some proper summit time this year. I have already got two long weekends in the diary for end of May and middle of June. It will be a bit of a shock to my legs im sure!</p>

<p><strong>Are you more of a “weekend warrior” or do you have some long distance trips under your belt?</strong></p>

<p>These days I’m mostly out on the weekends but back in the days when I had paid holidays I did a few longer trips in Norway, Estonia and Scotland. I think Norway is a stunning country, its hard in the UK to enjoy my love of a hammock but combine it with walking any great distance. My first time was just a week walking around the Nordmarka. It was cool to walk out of Oslo station and get the metro to the trail head. Easy walking and trees on top of most peaks made for some great hangs. My other Norway trip was very different as I headed off to Karasjok way up in the arctic circle for a winter trip. Pulling a toboggan along frozen rivers was truly fantastic. The Estonia trip was great too. Another winter getaway to Laheema National Park. Living in a temperate climate I’d never seen the sea frozen so that was pretty cool. Im hoping to do something special for my 50th in a few years so need to get my thinking cap on for a destination. I’m never likely to get the time to do anything epic but maybe I could do a few sections of one of the big American trails. I hear the AT is pretty hammocky so that appeals.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/786DoS" title="Estonia"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/973/28376482688_fc04c899d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Estonia" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Hiking in Finland Readers &amp; me, we are gear-nerds! What is your typical baseweight?</strong></p>

<p>It is getting there now. Back in the first year of the business I sold pretty much all my high end kit to keep the lights on. At the time it was painful but looking back it did allow me to start with a clean slate. Like most folks I’d learned a lot of lessons over the years about what worked for me and what didn’t so I was able to assemble my ideal kit list as funds permitted. Im at about 4kg base for 3 season ground camping. I recently got hold of a lightly used DCF Khufu from <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2011/01/interview-jotaro-yoshida-from-locus-gear.html">Locus Gear</a> and it’s a really quality bit of kit. The inner I find a little tight on length so I’ve just ordered an EE recon bivy to give a bit more room. My go to pack is an old GG Mariposa, it’s a vintage version in silnylon with acres of external mesh pockets. I don’t like to go into my pack until I hit camp so the mesh works great for stuff I need to access through the day. It’s a bit big for most trips but at just over 500g I’m happy to pack my sleep kit loose to pad it out. I always think its strange when I look at the current model and it weighs nearly double. <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2009/11/interview-glen-van-peski-from-gossamer-gear.html">Gossamer Gear</a>, if you are reading this how about an anniversary special that hits the old weights? A 1.5oz DCF body Mariposa would be my dream pack. I have two so maybe one day I might get busy rebuilding one. My sleep mat is a GG Airbeam XL. Sadly no longer made but I love the extra width over my Neoair. I use a Cumulus 250 quilt from spring through autumn and an EE Enigma 10f for winter. Cooking is a Toaks 850 with titanium cone from Stormin Stove Systems and a Speedster alcohol stove all wrapped up in a Tread Lite bag for 179g total. I own a lot of ti pots but the Toaks is great. I can get a meal and a coffee from one boil and the handles located right at the top means its great in a cone and you don’t get hot handles. I won’t bore you with the whole list, but these are the main ones!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/AG283Y" title="Coffee Caddy"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/823/28376483168_5c86c9ee90_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="Coffee Caddy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Please tell us where the name “Tread Lite Gear” came from, and what it stands for.</strong></p>

<p>Getting a name was a nightmare! You start off thinking of every word associated with being light only for a quick google to reveal someone got there first. I wanted something that reflected the UL sector I was aiming at but that also covered all the bases and didn’t pigeon hole any future product plans. In the end a short list was quickly whittled to Tread Lite Gear on the basis it was the only one I could get the domain for. I like it though, I think it sums up what the company is about and it rolls off the tongue nicely.</p>

<p><strong>What makes Tread Lite Gear different from other cottages?</strong></p>

<p>I think the main thing would be the focus on just hiking accessories. Most cottages offer a full service from the small stuff right up to packs, shelters and sleep systems. I wanted to be able to offer off the shelf products with no long waiting time to a high standard and at a reasonable price point. It’s a very simple ethos. It’s just me, one guy, one product at a time. I’m small enough that I get to interact with my customers on a more personal level and I think people like that connection, I know I do!</p>

<p>I don’t do mailshots or undertake paid marketing. I wanted to take a very organic approach to growing the business at a pace that was comfortable. I get sick of emails asking me to review my purchase so that’s a feature I’ll never implement on the site. Life is too short. I also took the decision not to give away kit for review. It’s not that im tight, it’s just that I believe a review carries more weight if someone has parted with money to get it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/Uje400" title="Pot and Stove bags"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/829/42203334392_5d4a238a69_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pot and Stove bags" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Is Tread Lite Gear your full-time job or “just a hobby”?</strong></p>

<p>I’m full time. I work long hours but I wouldn’t change it. It’s very rare that it actually feels like work. I get to sit and watch box sets on Prime or Netflix all day while I work. Some people say I’m really a TV critic and sewing is a by-product of the process =) I remember after I finished watching Breaking Bad that I’d love to convert a big camper van into a mobile sewing studio!</p>

<p>I love what I do though. I choose my own hours so there is great flexibility and I find it really rewarding. I think I’m probably unemployable now in the real world and every day I’m thankful that I don’t have to put on a suit, get in a car and drive ridiculous distances at the beck and call of others and tow the line. Its taken me a long time to find what I’m happiest doing and I’d never go back. Paying income tax in one go each year takes some getting used to though!</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>I love what I do. I choose my own hours so there is great flexibility and I find it really rewarding.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Tread Lite Gear makes lightweight lanterns and a massive amount of different pockets and bags accessories. Can you tell us how the idea to start the company emerged and how you see its future?</strong></p>

<p>In my old life I was a surveyor. I worked in the public sector for a large funding body providing capital funding for education. I left that to go into private practice on the other side of the table preparing property strategies and funding bids for clients. It was a great job and provided a comfortable life but it was stressful and involved a huge amount of travel and staying away from home. When the credit crunch hit, government funding collapsed. I managed to stay in employment and even started my own consultancy company. Eventually there were too many people chasing too little money and work started to be hard to come by. I kept it going a little too long. Usual story of flogging a dead horse when I should have cut and run. So one day I woke up with a pile of debt and no clue about where I wanted to go next but I knew I needed a change. With little cash to fund my gear I started playing at making my own. I bought a singer 201k sewing machine on ebay for £50 and a knackered MSR Hubba Bubba. I cut up the tent and made some awful looking monstrosities haha! I found I really enjoyed it though and after a few weeks of practice stuff started to look good. I thought the UK market was under represented and had potential so I shut the surveying business, flogged my car to release some funds and started the company. My wife went back to work full time to support us while I slowly set about building the business. Year 1 was really tough and I considered chucking it in more than once but deep down I thought it had the legs to go somewhere. Year 2 was much better and Year 3 finally saw the point where it seemed to start to gather some momentum.</p>

<p>In my mind I thought that summers would be really busy and winters would be quiet allowing me to hike more but it didn’t work like that and I seem to be busy year round. December is probably the only time I get to take a proper rest over Christmas and we usually rent a cottage in Norfolk. Long dog walks on huge beaches with big skies are a family favourite and it’s nice to switch off and relax.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/4e61e4" title="Tryfan Summit"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/952/28376483398_90f46dd160_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Tryfan Summit" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I still use the same sewing machine for the majority of my work. It was built in the 1950s and it is still perfect. I like the juxtaposition of sewing space age fabrics on an old machine. I do have a bit of a habit of picking up more Singer 201s. There are 8 in the loft as we speak. A good investment though as prices are going through the roof.</p>

<p>The future is something im thinking about now a lot. Im about at the limit of what one guy can do in a small workshop. I think I’ll tough it out this year but next year I’m going to need some bigger premises and maybe some staff if growth continues. I have a largish garden and would have loved to construct a workshop but alas it’s a big investment so I’ll end up leasing I think. Expansion brings all sorts of extra hassle and more risk but we’ll cross that bridge when we get there.</p>

<p><strong>Any intentions of starting to branch out into other segments, for example offering backpacks or stoves?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t see it but I never say never. There are a few barriers that make it difficult. The UK has lost much of its fabric manufacturing base over the years and the type of materials customers want need to be imported. Packs, and shelters in particular use huge swathes of fabric and I’m not in a position to import tons of fabric at costs that make the economics work. My workshop is pretty compact too which means I don’t have the space for a huge cutting table. Watch the Workshop tour Video to get an idea:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BhC3Rm9cAd0?rel=0" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>In the short time I’ve been doing this I’ve seen many cottages go to the wall or have huge problems. The online communities are full of stories of people folding and still taking money from people for gear that doesn’t arrive. They always seem to be big ticket items where payment is taken up front and lead times can be huge. There are some very sad stories behind some of these situations and whilst you can empathise, I never want to be in the position of needing to take up front payment or suddenly having a workload that is out of control. Life throws things at you that you have to deal with and always at a time that is inconvenient. Although people cut cottages a lot of slack, when all said and done it’s a business and, you need to act accordingly and fulfil your obligations. For that reason if I ever did branch out into big ticket stuff I would only sell what I could put on the shelf.</p>

<p><strong>Are there any other cottage manufacturers in the United Kingdom that you work with?</strong></p>

<p>Not at this time.</p>

<p><strong>And are you in touch with other cottage manufacturers in Europe, Japan, Canada, the USA and other places?</strong></p>

<p>Not really although there are often interactions on social media.</p>

<p><strong>Your company is now three years old has been getting good reviews and praise from all across Europe. Is business going well?</strong></p>

<p>Yes it’s good. Cash is always tight but each year gets a little easier. I launched the website this year so that’s brought a new dimension to things. I kind of thought that ebay sales would subside as the web became more popular but ebay seems to continue to grow as does the website. In time I hope to get off ebay as it’s a terribly expensive platform to sell on and they are making it more and more admin intensive and bureaucratic for businesses. Im already introducing lines that won’t go on ebay.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/M5E9UJ" title="Packing Cells"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/967/42203326782_192201d601_b.jpg" width="1024" height="961" alt="Packing Cells" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Can you tell us a bit how you went about the design process of Chest Pack / Front Pouch, and where the inspiration came from?</strong></p>

<p>The chest pack in itself is very simple in its construction. I’d always liked the idea of a chest pouch and it’s something that customers asked for a lot. Reaching for side pockets can be a pain so it is nice to have somewhere easy to get to. The problem was always attachment to the pack. I’d tried some commercial versions in the past like the OMM trio and a Salomon one and always found them hard to mount to my pack and the weights were poor. I tried a few prototypes of my own but never quite got something that I thought would be a universal fit. The current model seems to tick those boxes and feedback has been great.</p>

<p><strong>Paul, we love to be let in on the work-in-progress stuff! What kind of new products are you working on at the moment?</strong></p>

<p>As I mentioned in another question im about at the limit of my time so I don’t have anything major planned. As I write this I’ve finally added cuben packing cells in a few sizes to the website which I’d only ever done previously on a custom basis. My focus over the summer will be weeding out the stuff that’s not really cutting it on the rosta, improving some of the photography and getting more pictures of gear in use whilst expanding some of the options on stuff that’s already there. My time outdoors is precious to me and I hate taking work out with me but I do appreciate studio photos are not as nice as stuff pictured on the hill. I seldom take a camera out with me. It’s too easy to live trips looking through a lens so I tend to just drink it in. I am also a little camera shy.</p>

<p>I’d also like to get a budget range of gear up on the website too as I’m always conscious that we don’t all have unlimited funds to splash out with. It is hard though as the labour costs and overhead are the same no matter what the fabric cost.</p>

<p><strong>Any new lightweight materials that have you all excited?</strong></p>

<p>Not really, DCF (I still prefer the <em>cuben</em> name) is still really the benchmark and I don’t see anything to challenge it in the near future. I see lots of new, heavier weight fabrics that I like though, particularly from the racing sail side of the industry, but obviously their UL appeal is limited. I’m not a huge fan of the recreational lite skin for instance but some of the racing sail lite skin laminates are beautiful.</p>

<p><strong>How works the R&amp;D at Tread Lite Gear, do you have a need yourself that you try to fix, or do some of your clients inspire you for new products and ask you for solutions to their problems?</strong></p>

<p>I think it’s a mixture. UL hikers are very knowledgeable. I mean we all spend hours on end looking for solutions and looking at Gucci kit to shave a few more g’s and for sure customers are your biggest asset when it comes to product development. You can’t make every customer suggestion work due to practicalities or economics but you can often implement small changes that make gear more useable. A good exampIe would be the roll top camera strap pocket which came into being after it was requested by Ed and Robin on the trek lite forum. Took me a while to get something I was happy with but they are very popular now.</p>

<p>I’m always kicking around ideas with the guys I walk with too. On my last trip to the Lakes I was testing a new UL rechargeable cuben lantern. Rich and Chiseller quickly made a few suggestions to improve the design and it was on sale the following week. Cheers chaps!</p>

<p>I do love doing something new as it breaks up the routine. I have a list of stuff that I’d like to make or develop when time permits. Some of that is customer driven and some are my own musings on gaps in my lineup.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/CfGa2r" title="Haweswater"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/28376482518_d2d96d62a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Haweswater" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Where do your customer come from, and how do they find you?</strong></p>

<p>Last financial year 66% of sales were in the UK and 34% overseas. USA and Germany are about equal as the biggest overseas markets but I ship pretty much everywhere there is a reliable postal service. The UK decision to leave the EU has had a big impact on the strength of Sterling and it has been good for exports. It’s a double edged sword though with most of my input costs being in Dollars or Euros. I’m nervous about the deal that will be put in place post Brexit. It all seems a bit of a mess currently but hopefully it will get hashed out. Whatever happens I guess you just have to adapt. Filling in customs paperwork is already the bane of my life so I hope there isn’t a need for more of it. Politics eh? Its enough to make you go hiking =)</p>

<p>I’m on social media and forums so that is a big pathway to my door. I’ve been lucky to have some exposure from other areas which I’ll mention later if I may. Ebay and Google are probably a big route too.</p>

<p><strong>When and where was your last trip?</strong></p>

<p>Ennerdale in the Lake District late March for a couple of nights in the hammock. It was dry too. That’s probably my last low level camp this year. It is time to get some high level stuff in, get my fitness back and escape the midge season!</p>

<p><strong>And where is your dream backpacking trip taking you?</strong></p>

<p>I was recently chatting to a Norwegian customer who is about to embark on a trip from the far SW of Norway right up to North Cape (3000km). It’s not a recognised trail but of all the backpacking I’ve done in Norway just makes me glow inside. I think some of that has to do with the great company of people I went with, the warm welcome from local people we met as well as the great beauty of the place. So yea I reckon something similar.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/47Kg3J" title="At the Summit!"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/964/28376483258_412a7231e4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="At the Summit!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Any favourite piece of gear which you always carry with you?</strong></p>

<p>Too many! I love my little cuben lanterns and there is one clipped to all my shelters and hammocks. They weigh very little and its nice not to burn the battery on my head torch in camp and it saves the need to carry a spare cell. I’m a coffee fuelled entity too so my little cuben coffee caddy bag is something that sees a lot of use. Other stuff I’m never without is my Zebralight head torch. It has never let me down. My swing lite flex brolly, my old school Mariposa pack and a Fenix 5 watch for route tracking and data. I never thought an Umbrella would be something I’d take but it’s surprisingly useful and hey it is orange! I do like bright colours and own very little stuff in earthy tones. Top of my wish list is the new Garmin Inreach Mini. I seldom have a phone signal when hiking so it would be nice to text the wife to tell her I’m alive once in a while. I’ll wait a while and see what people think of it in use.</p>

<p><strong>Are you planning to get out for a trip soon, and enjoy the spring in the United Kingdom?</strong></p>

<p>Yes indeed. Lake District end of May and middle of June. May to meet up with a few mates and June to meet some of the friends I’ve never met from the excellent <a href="http://trek-lite.com/index.php">Trek-Lite.com forum</a>. After that I’d like to get over to Snowdonia for a few trips. I like my mountains craggy and gnarly. Tryfan and the Glyders are a favourite.</p>

<p><strong>Social Media - on which channels is Tread Lite Gear active?</strong></p>

<p>I am on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/treadlitegear/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Treadlitegear/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/@treadlitegear">Twitter</a> for work and active on the Trek-Lite.com forum which I try to keep for more personal enjoyment although work does creep in as you’d expect. I recently culled a lot of the Facebook groups I’m active on a personal level as my feed was just solid hiking related and sometimes it’s nice to see what my family and friends are up to. I read BPL from time to time but I prefer smaller more close knit places. Hammock forums is somewhere I visit too and Reddit occasionally as I’m not mad on the interface although the content is good. I probably spend too much time online but most of the people I hike with I met through online community meetups. I don’t think I’ve ever met anyone I didn’t get on with and it’s always nice to put a face to a name.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/gp/hendrikmorkel/RvuFDD" title="Morning glory"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/946/28376483348_5c858970fb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Morning glory" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><strong>Paul, I thank you very much for taking the time to answer my questions =) Is there something you would like to add?</strong></p>

<p>Well firstly thanks for reaching out to do the interview Hendrik. I’ve been lucky to have a lot of other people help in getting my name out there too so I would like to also offer them some thanks if that’s OK.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theoutdoorsstation.co.uk/2017/01/no-424-tread-lite-gear/">Bob Cartwright at the Outdoor Station</a> interviewed me last year which I really enjoyed and definitely had a positive impact on the business. To <a href="http://www.christownsendoutdoors.com">Chris Townsend</a> and the <a href="https://www.tgomagazine.co.uk">TGO Magazine</a> team who recently did a feature which has again given a boost to things and rather impressed my daughter at the same time. She took great delight in going to buy a copy and then texting pictures to everyone.</p>

<p>Thanks also to all the people on Facebook, Twitter, Insta, blog writers and Youtubers who share my posts and mention my products - many of whom have become friends!</p>

<p>My wife deserves special praise for her support, allowing me to steal away time working when I should be spending it with the family and yet still encouraging me to get out and hike.</p>

<p>Last but no means least, my customers. I get tons of messages offering thanks and encouragement. You keep the dream alive! It is deeply appreciated!</p>

<p>Happy Trails,</p>

<p>Paul</p>

<hr />

<p><em>How much did you spent on your last piece of outdoor gear? And how much did you support your favourite blogs in the last months? If you enjoyed this interview &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Greg Grenzke, Apparel Designer at Arc'teryx]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/03/mountain-people-greg-grenzke-apparel-designer.html"/>
    <updated>2015-03-25T18:49:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/03/mountain-people-greg-grenzke-apparel-designer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>“There is no bad weather, only bad clothes.”</em></p>

<p>That’s a popular saying here in the North, and it is easy to imagine that this saying drives <a href="http://arcteryx.com/">Arc’teryx</a> Designer Greg Grenzke and his team forward to design the best possible apparel for their <a href="http://arcteryx.com/ProductFind.aspx?language=EN&amp;Collection=Ascent">Ascent Line</a>. What goes into designing garments that are lightweight, functional and durable enough to survive in the mountains but are timeless in appearance you can read in this <em>Mountain People interview</em>.</p>

<p><a href="http://hikinginfinland.com" title="Greg Grenzke, Craftsmanship"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7634/16923034802_92c6824283_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Greg_Craftsmanship_AM0W9770" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Greg, thank you for taking the time for answering my questions.  Could you please introduce yourself briefly so we have an idea  what’s  your background?</strong></p>

<p>I studied industrial design at the University of Cincinnati as part of the DAAP (Design, Architecture, Art, and Planning program). Part of this program is cooperative education where they require the students to rotate between school and internships every 3 months year round for the last 4 years of the 5 year program. I did various internships throughout school such as with companies like Salomon Sports, Specialized Bicycles, and design firms. Anytime I had the opportunity to select the type of product I could work on it was always outdoor/ sports related, pretty much to the point my classmates would make fun of me because that was always my focus. This really helped me get my foot into the sports industry as I started building a portfolio of concepts/ products that I was really passionate about. I was offered a job before I graduated University from Specialized Bicycles. I worked there for 8 years designing all sorts of products such as footwear, bikes, bike graphics, helmets, saddles, gloves, really a huge variety of different products utilizing both hard goods and soft goods. The design approach was very hands on at Specialized which is also how things work at <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a>. I have been at Arc’teryx now for over 3,5 years where I am the Designer/ Design Manager of the Ascent Apparel category. It’s been a fun challenge resolving soft good problems with more of an industrial design approach and methodology.</p>

<p>I have been active outdoors for as long as I can remember growing up in Michigan. Once I could drive (age 16 back then) that was really my door to freedom. I would borrow my mom’s car and go on road trips with friends to bike, hike, climb, ski, any opportunity I could typically heading west to the mountains.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16898393366" title="Greg bootpackin' by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr'"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8694/16898393366_a4e282d544_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="gg bootpackin" /></a>
©Rich Kupskay</p>

<p><strong>As a Category Manager for the Ascent line I imagine you’re a mountaineer and climber yourself. What are some of your favourite  routes and places?</strong></p>

<p>I still feel like I’m on vacation living in Coastal Mountain Range in North Vancouver as it’s somewhere I would come for vacation if I didn’t live here. You know you live in a pretty incredible place when you are traveling to other naturally beautiful countries and you still just want to get back home.</p>

<p>Some of my favorite places are very local like the Tantalus Mountain Range for alpine climbing which is about a 45 minute drive near Squamish BC, Canmore Alberta where I just went for my first time ice climbing with some of our athletes, and <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/learn-mountaineering-at-the-2015-arcteryx-alpine-academy.html">Chamonix</a> where there are endless options! One of my other passions is ski touring/ mountaineering where again BC continues to stun me with its vast space and mountains where you often don’t encounter another soul sometimes for days at end.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16301931724" title="Greg and Tanja Schmitt, photo credit Matthias Scherer"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7627/16301931724_253140ddc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Greg and Tanja Schmitt, photo credit Matthias Scherer_Austria" /></a></p>

<p><strong>We met at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/arcteryx-alpine-academy-2014.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy 2014</a> at the “Insulation  types  for alpine environments” Seminar, where you introduced us with your  colleague Jon to the synthetic &amp; down insulation garments from  Arc’teryx. Some of these garments just came out - but can you give  us  a brief glimpse at what we could expect in the next season from  Arc’teryx?</strong></p>

<p>Well, let’s just say you can expect to see more insulation from us building upon our current offerings. There is a lot happening in the insulation world with new technologies and manufacturing processes. We are pretty conservative until we can prove the technology is substantially better than what we currently use and that it can stand the test of time. However, we are always experimenting with new ideas and technologies.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14784519783" title="Heatgun by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3847/14784519783_f6aee8fa98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Heatgun" /></a></p>

<p><strong>The Arc’teryx down insulation line has been available since 2013,  has it been more popular than your synthetics line?</strong></p>

<p>I’m not a sales guy so I’m definitely not the one to ask about sales numbers. However, the down line was a huge success after the 2013 launch and it is really growing extremely fast.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16304283443" title="Design Room"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8702/16304283443_9a7406a0f8_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-45" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What’s your own favourite layering setup when you head out into  the  mountains for a day of mountaineering or climbing?</strong></p>

<p>This really depends on where I am, weather conditions, how long I plan on being out, etc. But if I were to take a versatile system that works in many different situations I prefer to use something like a <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;model=Solo-Hoody">Solo Hoody</a> using our very hydrophobic Thermatek insulation as a belay/insulation layer, an <a href="http://arcteryx.com/product.aspx?language=EN&amp;gender=mens&amp;model=Alpha-FL-Jacket">Alpha FL shell</a> as it is very light weight, durable, and very breathable utilizing Gore-Tex Pro, a mid layer with high air permeability that provides light insulation but can dump heat/ moisture when you are pushing hard, and a slight synthetic base layer.   </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16923318411" title="Greg in Canmore"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8740/16923318411_1906e7e4ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="greg_canmore" /></a>
©Jon Rockefeller</p>

<p><strong>How long do you on average work on designing a garment? Is it a  couple of weeks from idea to prototype to fabrication sample, or  can  many months or even years go by?</strong></p>

<p>This also depends on if the product is a new style or a redesign of an existing style. Sometimes all the answers are in your head and the design time could be very quick. Other times, yes it can take months or even years to validate a design and it may not even make it to the market.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16923316131" title="Craftsmanship in the Arc'teryx Design Room"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8754/16923316131_2288edaba7_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-90" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Can you walk us through the different steps that go into making e.g. a Alpine climbing jacket like the Alpha FL?</strong></p>

<p>The first step is always defining the users need for a product. The Alpha FL is for travelling light &amp; fast while trying not to sacrifice durability. We had a really good starting point with the previous Alpha FL but we knew we could improve the product by minimizing seams, seam tape width, unnecessary glue/ fabric, and using a more durable face fabric with the Gore-Tex Pro membrane. We had various prototypes we tested in the field as well as in a lab for breathability testing. We ended up with a much more durable product at almost the same weight, about 69% less surface area from seam tape, more breathable, and more ergonomic feature set.  </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16301928864" title="Design tools"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8743/16301928864_22360c83f6_b.jpg" width="864" height="576" alt="S15 Craftsmanship_DesignRoom_Dec13-63" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Are you &amp; your colleagues inspired by ideas from other companies  that make alpine climbing lines, or do you try to work in a vacuum  and  insulate yourself from what the others are doing?</strong></p>

<p>Ha, well North Vancouver can be a bit of a vacuum. We have a pretty unique work atmosphere and designers often challenge each other to make better products. Just walking around seeing what others are working on can be very inspiring and that’s where a lot of ideas stem from. We like to look forward and think about what could be done and not what has been done.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16304283403" title="2014-Northwoods-HO by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8752/16304283403_723db53bf1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="2014-Northwoods-HO" /></a></p>

<p>  <strong>What role do your athletes have in the design process? Are they  involved from the start or does their feedback first come in when  they  are using what you have designed?</strong></p>

<p>We have some pretty amazing athletes in that they are so down to earth and easy to work with. They are some of the best testers we have as they literally live in the product. If their needs aren’t being met they will let us know and we will work with them to fill that need. Sometimes they will have ideas and we will make some prototypes for them to test. We do typically try to involve them early in the design process. We spend as much time with our athletes as we can, especially in the field as it’s a good excuse to get out of the office. Many of them are more like friends, as we share the same passions.    </p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/14731353344" title="Self-arrest by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/14731353344_f604fca9f0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Self-arrest" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What are the three most important attributes when you’re setting  out  designing a garment?</strong></p>

<p>Designing for longevity is typically one of the most important attributes that is always on our mind. This is really in the dna of the brand and it’s always rewarding to hear the stories of how someone’s jacket has lasted them over a decade, you can just see their face light up when they are telling you about it.</p>

<p>Another element of designing for longevity is building in timelessness. The brand has a very strong design language and we continue to build off this strong foundation. Although the materials and constructions continue to improve we want a product we design today to still look modern in 5 or 10 years. If you look at the lineage of something like the Beta AR or SV jacket, you can look at one from ten years ago and see the commonality. When we build in this timelessness we are also building in value.  </p>

<p><strong>Arc’teryx is well known for not resting on its laurels and  pushing  the boundaries. You’ve developed better water-resistant zippers,  were  one of the first companies to laminate seams, minimizing cuts so  that  seams are at an absolute minimum and many other innovations. Can we  expect another such innovation breakthrough from Arc’teryx in the  next  years?</strong></p>

<p>Arc’teryx always strives to push the boundaries and challenge conventional thinking. We still have some of the genius minds that helped create what the brand is today, as well as many new additions. We are definitely working on various future concepts but first we need to validate that they are feasible.</p>

<p><strong>Greg, thank you for taking the time for answering my questions!</strong></p>

<p><em>Liked this? Then please share this post with your friends on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/1/b/105082905705272949032/105082905705272949032/posts">Google+</a>!</em></p>

<p><a href="http://arcteryx.com/" title="Screen Shot 2015-03-25 at 14.00.13 by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8711/16738448720_5cfc100c7d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="598" alt="Screen Shot 2015-03-25 at 14.00.13" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Joe Grant, Mountain Runner]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/02/mountain-people-joe-grant.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-25T21:05:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/02/mountain-people-joe-grant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Running is a wonderful activity to enjoy the outdoors, push yourself and stay fit. Joe Grant is an Ultrarunner who has run in the Copper Canyon, on the Annapurna trail and around Mont Blanc. Why he loves to run, especially in the mountains and on long Ultras races, you read in this <em>Mountain People interview</em>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16457882128" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8660/16457882128_e0db3343aa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Joe, thanks for taking the time to answer my questions =) Could you please briefly introduce yourself and tell us what you do?</strong></p>

<p>I have a pretty eclectic background having studied international management with a focus on nonprofit work. I worked in nonprofits for several years after college, but started my own business <a href="http://alpine-works.com">Alpine Works</a> about 4 years ago which encompasses my work as a mountain runner, coach, writer and photographer. I’ve been running consistently for about 10 years and started racing Ultras 7 years ago.</p>

<p><strong>You have been changing location often, living a semi-nomadic life. Do you foresee that you’ll continue to be a nomad, living where you like it, or that you settle down once you maybe have found a place you want to call home?</strong></p>

<p>I travel a lot, mainly for races, but own a home in Gold Hill, Colorado just outside of Boulder. I was born in the UK, grew up in France and have been living in the US on and off for the past 10 years. Most of my travel is related to work and I call Colorado home.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16459281759" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8576/16459281759_2ca7c495f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Well, lets move away from standing still and take a run. You’ve run across the globe - is there a trail that really stands out for you?</strong></p>

<p>I’m partial to the San Juan mountains in Southern Colorado, but it’s hard to really pin point one particular trail that really stands out. Any trail in a unique, wild environment is appealing to me.</p>

<p><strong>And is there a trail that you still want to run?</strong></p>

<p>I’d like to spend more time in Alaska and the Himalayas. The grandeur of both places is very inspiring to  me.</p>

<p><strong>Tell us please how you plan for a race like the one you ran in Costa Rica - how does it start, what all needs to be done before you leave home?</strong></p>

<p>Well, <a href="http://alpine-works.com/2015/02/the-coastal-challenge/">The Coastal Challenge</a> is a tough race to prepare in Colorado in the winter.  I did my best to get into reasonable shape mainly skiing and biking and some running to get the legs moving a bit. My specific preparation was far from ideal. Since the race transports all of your gear from camp to camp, I did pack judiciously to have enough food, clean clothes and books to really recover well between stages. Recovery during the event is a key piece to stage racing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16619534966" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8622/16619534966_a3e484fe4c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Do you have a FKT Attempt planned this year?</strong></p>

<p>I have a quite a few FKTs I want to attempt such as Nolan’s 14 or The Bob Graham Round to name a few, but the race calendar this year is pretty full for me to fit any of these into the season. After The Coastal Challenge, I’ll be racing TransGrancanaria, Ultra Fiord 100 in Patagonia, Western States 100 and UTMB.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16644042711" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8620/16644042711_bec1f586b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Besides running you also like ski-mountaineering, fastpacking and riding a Fatbike as I saw on your <a href="https://instagram.com/alpineworks/">Instagram</a> stream. Are these 100% pleasure or also part of your training?</strong></p>

<p>Both. I enjoy doing self-propelled activities in the mountains and in the winter for example skiing is most of the time a much more suited activity to where I live than running. All these activities do help my running though whether for strength, endurance or just taking a break from the pounding. Fastpacking is a great way to really immerse myself in nature for more extended periods of time.</p>

<p><strong>Any other past-times in the outdoors that you enjoy?</strong></p>

<p>I like climbing and scrambling a lot, often as an extension of running in the mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16644452922" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8614/16644452922_83e6dd8995_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Trailrunning is a trend sport across the globe right now and though the majority of trailrunners enjoy it because they can be running outside in the forests &amp; mountains only a small percentage also participates in races. Do you think taking part in a race should be on every trailrunners list? If so, what’s a good start?</strong></p>

<p>I think runners should do whatever motivates and inspires them. Most races have a great community aspect and provide a relatively safe environment to push oneself. Races can be limiting too because of permitting and other restriction so it’s sometimes better to just create your own adventure. I’d suggest choosing a race that inspires you, but that you can also adequately prepare for so I can enjoy your time.</p>

<p><strong>As a coach you help runners to train for a race or event. If a complete novice runner would ask you for (free) advice on training, nutrition and gear, which three tips would you give him?</strong></p>

<p>Be consistent, eat real food and keep it simple.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16619535406" title="Joe Grant, Alpine Works by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8600/16619535406_3e0351394f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Joe Grant, Alpine Works" /></a></p>

<p><strong>What does your own training at home look like?</strong></p>

<p>During the running season, I run an average of 2-3 hours a day in the mountains with longer runs once of twice a week that are more specific to the race I’m preparing. In the winter I don’t run as much, but stay in shape skiing, biking and climbing.</p>

<p><strong>Do you pursue a special diet?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t. I try to eat mainly whole, organic foods. My wife and I cook most of our meals. We also like eating out and don’t worry about occasional indulgences.</p>

<p><strong>Joe, thank you so much for taking the time to answer my questions. Any parting words?</strong></p>

<p>Thank you very much for featuring me on your site.</p>

<p><em>Joe writes at <a href="http://alpine-works.com">Alpine Works</a> and has a column at <a href="http://www.irunfar.com/category/columns/from-my-doorstep">iRunFar</a>. He is sponsored by <a href="http://www.inov-8.com/">inov-8</a>, <a href="http://arcteryx.com/">Arc’teryx</a>, <a href="http://www.buffwear.com">Buff</a>, <a href="http://www.drymaxsocks.com">Drymax</a>, <a href="http://www.julbousa.com">Julbo</a> and <a href="http://www.tailwindnutrition.com">Tailwind Nutrition</a>. You can follow him on <a href="https://twitter.com/@AlpineWorks">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Alpine-Works/188901357810995">Facebook</a>.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Said Belhaj, Climber]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/02/mountain-people-said-belhaj.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-11T22:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/02/mountain-people-said-belhaj</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Travelling, climbing, family and training - how do you fit that all into a year well spent without going to a nine-to-five job? If you’re Said Belhaj, a professional climber from Sweden, it’s easy. You train three months at home and then travel the world and climb each day! <em>A <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/mountain-people/">Mountain People Interview</a>.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16504232795" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7299/16504232795_1aab6675e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hi Said, I know you a bit - but my reader’s don’t. Could you please briefly introduce yourself and tell us what you do?</strong></p>

<p>I was born and raised in Göteborg, Sweden to a father from Morocco and mother from Finland. I have 2 brothers and I live with my girlfriend. I’m 33 years old and have been climbing for over 20 years, 14 years as pro. We have an appartment in Stockholm with my girlfriend but are renting it out as we are travelling so much for the moment. Right now I’m staying in Santiago, Chile. Tomorrow - who knows?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15881673364" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7396/15881673364_1af82e9851_b.jpg" width="1024" height="658" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>We met at the Abisko Ice Climbing Festival in Sweden in February 2014 - was that the first time for you to climb ice, or have you been secretly planning your alpine climbing career and soon will stand on an 8.000 m peak in the Himalayas?</strong></p>

<p>I’ve ice climbed a little bit in my life, when I’ve gotten the chance. I like to try a bit of everything but unfortunately there is not always time. I don’t see myself on top of a 8000 meter peaks in the near future but at the same time who knows? I started climbing because I was seeking the adventure and the unknown, a 8000 meter climb would probably be both!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16316772330" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7375/16316772330_bac20af718_b.jpg" width="1024" height="698" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>In your “20 years as a climber” presentation you highlighted how you started climbing - from “free-soloing” as a kid to trad climbing to sports climbing - all outdoors. Nowadays most people start climbing indoors at gyms, and just a small percentage of them head outside to climb on rock. How do you feel about that?</strong></p>

<p>For me it’s strange to do an outdoor activity indoors - it’s impossible. My life and climbing has always been about beeing outdoors. Indoor climbing is good for training, comps and meeting people sometimes. I can totally see why people who start indoors stay indoors and it’s the easy access to indoor walls that have made climbing grow. At the same time it’s starnge to be out climbing in areas that used to be packed with people 20 years ago and find them almost empy now. But I wonder what would happen if all those indoor climbers went out on real rock?!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16318319937" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7320/16318319937_067a5137ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="752" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>You are nowadays - thanks to the great <a href="http://www.rockandice.com/lates-news/the-seeker-said-belhaj">Rock &amp; Ice portrait</a> - probably best known for hard sport climbing, but you also do some bouldering. Is bouldering for you something to keep fit for rock climbing, or do you see bouldering as an art of climbing in itself that you enjoy?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t categorize myself as a certain type of climber; all my climbing life I’ve been doing trad, sport, boulder, big-wall, comps and even some ice. I just love to climb and like all types. I think this is what makes climbing so unique: all types, their all fun, I never get bored, always something new to learn and discover. I do more of some dicipline during certain periods of the year but would never say no to any of them - they are all climbing and thats what we do every day.</p>

<p><strong>You’ve climbed across the globe - is there a route or crag that you did that really stands out for you, and that you would recommend to any climber to visit?</strong></p>

<p>It’s almost an impossible question as I’ve climbed in hundreds of different places in about 40 countries. I think you can’t compare them, they are just different. I’ve had amazing experiences in one way or another in all of them exept some boring days of training in the gym maybe.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16478236376" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7457/16478236376_a8611e0c60_b.jpg" width="685" height="1024" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Is there a rock climbing route somewhere that you look forward to on leaving behind for others to enjoy?</strong></p>

<p>Well, I’ve put up quite a few routes on the Swedish Westcoast that people are climbing, some of them yet looking for a 2nd ascent. But because of the stupid political bolting situation in the area I’ve stopped for the moment. I’ve also put up trad routes and boulders but they never get mentioned. Anyway, I thinks it always destroys creativity when there are people who only criticize when we are trying to do something for everybody. We still have many things to learn as  humans and this can especially be said about climbers!</p>

<p><strong>How do you go about planning a climbing trip, how much time does it take to plan nine months of travelling and climbing?</strong></p>

<p>I don’t need so much time to plan these days. Usually I have some fixed plans for the year and leave some parts open. I usually do trips between 2 weeks - 3 months.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16503220012" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7302/16503220012_b10df947ac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="682" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Who are your sponsors and how do they support you?</strong></p>

<p>My main partners are <a href="http://www.haglofs.com/">Haglöfs</a>, <a href="http://www.petzl.com/">Petzl</a>, <a href="http://www.sportiva.com">La Sportiva</a> and <a href="http://www.c2safety.com">C2</a> who support me with gear and money. Then I also have some other brands that support me with gear and food such as Clif Bar, <a href="http://hilleberg.se">Hilleberg</a>, <a href="http://www.primus.eu">Primus</a> and Nokia. With these partners I can do that I want and I have never really had a “normal” job in my life. I will never get really rich but I’ve always done what I wanted in life - the biggest wealth if you ask me.</p>

<p><strong>Where does your next trip take you?</strong></p>

<p>For the moment I’m climbing in Perú, Bolivia and Chile in South America. In the spring I’m planning to go back to Spain &amp; France which I do every year. I also have plans for next summer and autumn but let’s first see what happens in the near future.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16502501731" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8561/16502501731_ddcbbf1351_b.jpg" width="1024" height="680" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Your family is living across the globe - your father is from Morocco, your mother from Finland and you grew up in Sweden. You travel a lot and speak six languages fluently. How do they see your career, and is it hard to see them not that often?</strong></p>

<p>I think my family didn’t like my choise in life at first, mainly because they were afraid. But they have accepted and realized I’m taking care of myself. Not seeing my family &amp; friends as often as I’d like it’s the prize I’ve had to pay to do what I do. All great things in life come to a high prize.</p>

<p><strong>You wrote on your blog that your usual yearly schedule is to train January to March at home and then travel the rest of the year. What does your training at home look like?</strong></p>

<p>I follow a 12 week training program that we’ve put together with Carlos Cabrera. I do about 10 sessions per week indoor and if possible I try to get outside on rock once a week -to stay sane. This might sound crazy but it’s totally worth it, then I can climb on rock for the rest of the year. Also, it gives me time to be in Sweden and see my family and friends.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/15881673704" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8577/15881673704_cd8efa54fd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="734" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Andy Kirkpatrick, a mountaineer from the UK, made in his essay “How To Hone Your Alpine Psyche” his first point to not have kids. You’re not yet a father, which makes climbing hard and travelling a lot easier. But do you think that at some point in time you will settle down and start a family?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, of course I’d love to have a family and get married soon. I don’t want to end up being this dirtbag dude who lives out of his van alone when I’m 50! But this doens’t mean I will stop climbing, climbing is for life.</p>

<p><strong>Said, gracias for taking the time to answer my questions.</strong></p>

<p><em>You can follow Said via his <a href="http://www.said-belhaj.com">blog</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/darsaidbelhaj">Facebook</a>.</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16503220122" title="Said Belhaj by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7456/16503220122_9084374669_b.jpg" width="768" height="1024" alt="Said Belhaj" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain People: Ulrika Rogeman, Product Designer at Hilleberg the Tentmaker]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/01/mountain-people-ulrika-rogeman.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-21T18:30:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/01/mountain-people-ulrika-rogeman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Where would you want to work if you love the outdoors and have studied design? If you live in Sweden and also like shelters then <a href="http://hilleberg.se">Hilleberg the Tentmaker</a> would be a good call. That’s also what Ulrika Rogeman thought - and now works as a Product Designer at Hilleberg. She is also the designer of the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2014/07/outdoor-news-2014-day-2.html">Hilleberg Enan</a>, the lightest Hilleberg tent yet! <em>Read this <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/mountain-people/">Mountain People Interview</a> to find out about what goes into designing an ultralight tent that can carries the Hilleberg name!</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16323243841" title="Hilleberg Enan Magnus Brogren Jämtland by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7506/16323243841_0e412a686a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hilleberg Enan Magnus Brogren Jämtland" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Hej Ulrika, thanks for taking the time to answer my questions. Could you please introduce yourself briefly, so we have an idea what’s your 
background?</strong></p>

<p>My name is Ulrika Rogeman and I am 30 years old. I have been working at Hilleberg with Product Design for three years. Since September my responsibilities has extended to include Material Development as well. I came straight from University when I started at Hilleberg. I have a degree in Mechanical Engineering, but my education did focus on product development as well - and especially development of outdoor products. So the job at Hilleberg is exactly what I studied to work with!</p>

<p>I have always been an outdoor person and I enjoy any activity that takes me to the mountains. The last years there has been a lot of trailrunning, biking and ski mountaineering in my life. It is extra fun to develop a lightweight tent like Enan when I really can see myself use it when for example I go running in the mountains.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16332748675" title="Ulrika Rogeman by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8587/16332748675_acce85f67d_o.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Ulrika Rogeman" /></a></p>

<p><strong>We met at the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/blog/categories/outdoor-fair-2014/">OutDoor</a> and you showed me the new <a href="http://hilleberg.se/news/enan-new-2015">Hilleberg Enan</a> - your design! How was the idea born to create the Enan, as Hilleberg has two tents - the Anjan and Akto - which potentially could suit the space the Enan now takes?</strong></p>

<p>The plan to make a one person 3-season tent (at Hilleberg we call the 3-season tents <em>Yellow Label</em>) started when we made Anjan and Rogen, the other Hilleberg Yellow Label models. We definitely believe that there is room for a 1,1 kg Hilleberg tent between Anjan and Akto, for those who really need to prioritize weight but still want the security and quality that a Hilleberg tent offers.</p>

<p><strong>You told me the Enan is based on the footprint of the Akto and also uses some design features of this tent. Would it be correct to think that the Enan has been designed for Akto enthusiasts which want a 3-Season tent?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, definitely! Although Enan is not just an Akto with lighter materials. Once you start to use Enan you will see that there are several design details that are different in order to make the tent lighter. All these details have been thought through carefully so that we have a light tent but still a tent that is true to the other Hilleberg principles: Reliability, Adaptability, Ease of Use, Durability and Comfort.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16137655470" title="Hilleberg Enan by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7548/16137655470_69b8386b54_b.jpg" width="1024" height="592" alt="Hilleberg Enan" /></a></p>

<p><strong>How long have you been working on the Enan - from the idea was born till the final production model?</strong></p>

<p>About two years. First I made initial sketches of interesting designs, then sketches were transformed into 1-to-1 scale cord-skeletons just to get a feeling of the design and its behaviour. Then I made patterns and sew prototypes for the most interesting designs. These were tested out in the nature, but I also tested them in our wind machine, which actually is a snow cannon. At the same time as I was testing the design there were several different materials tested in the tent in order to find the best combination between low weight and strength. For example we tested using poles with a smaller diameter, but realized that in strong wind these poles did not have the strength that we looked for so instead we use the same strong 9 mm pole that we have in Akto.</p>

<p>When I finally found a design that matched both low weight and strength it was time to work with the details. One example is that I have tried to use the tent in rainstorm by adding water to the wind machine. It is the result of that test that the shutters that can cover the short ends were developed. In most weather they are absolutely unnecessary and it is much better to go with full ventilation. But when the rain is close to horizontal they will give you the extra security to prevent your outdoor adventure from turning into a nasty, unsafe experience.</p>

<p>When the tent was almost as perfect as we want it to be, it was time to send it out with people that are not working at Hilleberg to get their opinion of the tent. In total Enan has been outdoors more than 140 nights before we introduced the tent.</p>

<p><strong>Have you looked at other tent designs while designing the Enan? As it has some similarities with the <a href="http://www.tarptent.com/moment.html">Tarptent Moment</a> - would you say that’s coincidence and just shows that a good design can be conceived on opposite places of the world (like the Pyramids, which have been built by the Mayans and Egyptians)?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, I have looked at other tents, as a product developer you have to be aware of other products, maybe not because of the design, more in order to know the weight and price of the products that are in the same product range. But honestly, there are quite a few lightweight tents that resemble each other. I believe that Enan has more in common with Hilleberg’s own Akto rather than any model from another brand.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16332748705" title="Enan on Mallorca by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8595/16332748705_4f450e1fa2_o.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="Enan on Mallorca" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Hilleberg also has for the first time created a tent that’s very close to the 1 kg packed weight limit, while keeping the Hilleberg principles of strength and durability. You’re using the new Kerlon 600 fabric as a shell for this tent, how did you set the specifics for this material?</strong></p>

<p>Ones again we have to go back to the Hilleberg principles. A low weight will always mean that we have to compromise with the other principles, but we are only willing to take the compromise to a certain limit. The initial specifications were set from the long experience of tent making that we have at Hilleberg. From these initial specifications different material designs were tested at the Mid Sweden University Textile Laboratory that we have access to. As I mentioned before, different fabrics were also tested in the different tent designs. Eventually we felt that Kerlon 600 was the fabric that matched our demands the best. It is also Kerlon 600 that has been used during the more than 140 nights that Enan has been out. Throughout all these tests we have been able to verify that the initial specification match what we need the fabric to perform. </p>

<p><strong>What are other design details of the Enan you are really proud of?</strong></p>

<p>I am mostly proud of how simple the tent is, the tent design talks for itself and you do not have to be an engineer to use it correctly. Simplicity in combination with high quality gives a thought through product. It takes a lot of work and thinking to find out how a product can be simplified but still be a high quality product. It is the things that are removed that I am most proud of.</p>

<p><strong>You said the Enan fits two persons in a pinch - you have used it with your partner in Lapland, if I recall correctly - so do you think we’ll  see Adventure Racers use your tents in the future, or is Hilleberg maybe even sponsoring some Adventure Racing teams with the Enan?</strong></p>

<p>Yes, or well I have used it when me and my partner have been out running in the mountains of Jämtland, the region where the Hilleberg office is located. One time when we were out the weather was really bad and we were soaking wet when we stopped running and pitched the tent. But to hang out, two persons, in the tent the rest of the evening was really not a problem. Although I suggest that you know each other quite well!</p>

<p>I absolutely believe that Enan will be used in adventure races. Actually we have already lent out the tent during some competitions. For example our Hilleberg friend <a href="http://hilleberg.se/christine-hägglund">Christine Hägglund</a> used it with her teammate during the mountain orienteering race <a href="http://www.bamm.nu">BAMM</a> that takes place in the far north of Sweden.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16306801456" title="Pesonaltur 2014, Photographer: Magnus Brogren by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7492/16306801456_f9def5f54a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pesonaltur 2014, Photographer: Magnus Brogren" /></a></p>

<p><strong>The Enan will be available in 2015 to consumers - do you think it will be popular?</strong></p>

<p>I hope so! Or to be more specific, I hope that people that really need a low weight tent likes Enan. I think that if you want comfort and a long lasting tent you should look for one of our <a href="http://hilleberg.se/product/saivo">Black Label</a> models. </p>

<p><strong>Ulrika, I thank you for taking the time for answering my questions! Any closing words?</strong></p>

<p>Go out and enjoy the mountains, fjells and wilderness!</p>

<p><em>Don’t miss future Mountain People Interviews and other posts and follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> or subscribe to the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">RSS feed</a>!</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
