<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: footwear | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/footwear/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2021-07-22T13:04:52+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/03/la-sportiva-crossover-2-dot-0-gtx.html"/>
    <updated>2020-03-05T10:19:03+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/03/la-sportiva-crossover-2-dot-0-gtx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gore-Tex trailrunning shoes for backpacking and hiking? If you want to keep your feet drier longer, I found the La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX a great shoe with it’s integrated ankle-high gaiter.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49621594928/in/dateposted-public/" title="In cover"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49621594928_c8c4b847e7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="In cover" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> <em>I’m sponsored by La Sportiva BUT <strong>I bought these shoes with my own money</strong>. This did not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>I bought the <a href="https://www.lasportiva.com/en/crossover-20-gtx">La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX</a> in April 2018, and have used them since then pretty much on every backpacking trip: <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/05/microadventure-sipoonkorpi-national-park.html">Sipoonkorpi National Park</a>, at <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/09/camp-ousland.html">Camp Ousland</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/Zr6Ev1MFxBw">Backpacking in Vålådalen</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/m8EstxnC8uQ">Backpacking in the Pyrenees</a> and also on my <a href="https://youtu.be/-AYVkZf61UE">backpacking trip in Hammastunturi Wilderness</a>. Additionally, in winter I also use these shoes all the time, so they easily have seen over 360 days of use so far, and I estimate that I have hiked over 1.500 km in them.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/44199759745/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Storådörren Valley from the other side n better weather"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1903/44199759745_b4b7e1753e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Storådörren Valley from the other side n better weather" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>Shoes give you protection and grip on your hiking &amp; backpacking trips, and depending on the environment you are likely to pick different shoes: If I’m hiking in super-warm weather the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals OSO</a> are my pick, if I am in the mountains I usually opt for an <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2017/08/la-sportiva-tx2-review.html">approach shoe like the TX2</a>, and if I’m hiking in the autumn off-the-beaten track or expect wet and cold weather, then I put on the Crossover 2.0 GTX as they keep my feet drier and warmer than an unlined shoe.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49622382887/in/dateposted-public/" title="Snow in the Pyrenees"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49622382887_684869ba23_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Snow in the Pyrenees" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<p>The Crossover 2.0 has these features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Grippy sole with AT Grip zone for enhanced hold on snowy and icy terrain (FriXion AT Sole with Impact Brake System and AT Grip zone)</li>
  <li>“Easy-in” speed fitting system</li>
  <li>Ortholite Mountain Running Ergonomic Footbed</li>
  <li>10 mm Drop</li>
  <li>Water-repellent Gaiter fabric with YKK water-repellent transversal zip and integrated tension adjustment system</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744616467/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744616467_485a1ea011_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2>

<p>Integrating a gaiter into a running shoe isn’t new, but La Sportiva has done an absolute amazing job with this shoe as it is durable in all aspects which matter to me.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48744150896/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48744150896_7c8434f706_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>I have used this shoe for almost two years in autumn, winter and spring, in the Pyrenees, Finnish swamps, on snow &amp; asphalt and forest trails and have never found anything wrong with them. They’re always comfortable for my feet with a good fit in the heel, and the toe box is wide enough to accommodate my toes. The zipper holds up AMAZINGLY well, and still functions flawless. Also the heel - commonly an area where you see the wear &amp; tear first - is still without any damage. And I have been hiking a lot off-trail with these shoes, though shrubbery and whatnot, and the upper + gaiter still look in great shape.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49622393437/in/dateposted-public/" title="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX Gaiter"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49622393437_212637952d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX Gaiter" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49622394247/in/dateposted-public/" title="Open Gaiter of the La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49622394247_e1c76d0d8c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Open Gaiter of the La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>One shoe weighs in at 358 g in Size 42 which makes the pair 716 g heavy.</p>

<h2 id="sustainability--recyclability">Sustainability &amp; Recyclability</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.lasportiva.com/en/one-percent-for-the-planet">La Sportiva is a 1% For The Planet Member</a>, and they have a <a href="https://www.lasportiva.com/en/recycle-program">Recycle Program</a> for the waste resulting from their manufacturing process in Val di Fiemme. The company is <a href="https://www.lasportiva.com/en/environmental-care">ISO 14.001 certified</a> and all that and more you can read in their <a href="https://www.lasportiva.com/en/csr">Sustainability Report</a>. BUT how do you <em>“recycle”</em> your La Sportiva shoes at the end of their life-cycle? In most countries shoes belong into the residual waste bin. Or if they still have some life left in them, you can drop them into a clothing recycling bin or donate them to a place which takes old clothes and shoes. You also can look for the shop or place which is part of the <a href="https://www.nike.com/sustainability">Reuse-A-Shoe program</a>, where they recycle your sneakers and transform them into Nike Grind material.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49621589093/in/dateposted-public/" title="La Sportiva Sustainability Report"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49621589093_e10c3c1562_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="La Sportiva Sustainability Report" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>As always, this is the most important part of the whole article - get a cup of coffee and then read on.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40337489450" title="Chilling at Sunset"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/976/40337489450_c4f9faa8f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chilling at Sunset" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>First things first: This is a Gore-Tex shoe, but that does not mean that I always had dry feet in them. If it are good, clear trails and it’s raining - dry feet, <em>mucho awesome</em>. Hiking through shrubbery, overgrown paths and through grass heavy with dew or wet from the rain, expect to have wet feet in a few minutes. The inner material also holds on to wetness well, so once the shoes are wet they are wet till you’re drying them over a stove. The wet shoes are not really a problem if you have some good <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/02/wrightsock-review.html">Merino Wool Socks</a> on and have the <em>hiking in wet shoes is not a problem</em> mind set, but it’s something I need to mention. Gore-Tex or waterproofness in shoes in general only goes so far really, but for me the benefit of having dry &amp; warm feet in the rain, when the trail conditions are right, outweigh the downside of hiking in a wet Gore-Tex shoe that needs longer to dry. I have found that drying the shoes overnight next to a wood stove is possible, and also in the tent they do dry out a wee bit if the air is not really saturated with moisture.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49622385937/in/dateposted-public/" title="Drying in the sun"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49622385937_4b31f879fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Drying in the sun" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49621605448/in/dateposted-public/" title="Drying the La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49621605448_048c0d04c6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Drying the La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The shoe has a 10 mm Drop which is usually more than I like, but it’s still acceptable for me and as I have used these shoes so much I have got used to it. I also don’t particularly like that La Sportiva has used in the inner construction a material which holds moisture so long, I wish they would have used something more meshy that dries super-fast. But as this shoe is intended for winter trailrunning I get why they have made the shoe warmer instead of more breathable. It being a “warm” shoe also means that it isn’t really suitable to really warm weather - for me the ideal temperature to use the shoe is between -5°c and 15°C. If it is more than 15°C I get really warm and sweaty feet, on the other side of the thermometer it’s not a problem to take the shoes down to -15°C and still have toasty feet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/29797398117/in/album-72157673511250268/" title="Reflections"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/1878/29797398117_bd0490474c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reflections" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28214430548/in/album-72157695044886921/" title="Lunch with a View"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/946/28214430548_d6e7bd5625_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lunch with a View" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Grip wise these shoes are absolutely fantastic. Wet rocks in the Pyrenees, boulder-hoping down a field of scree: No problem. Traversing wet swamps: No Problem. Hiking on forest trails with roots and stones: Ideal terrain. Snow: Hi there, I’m at home here. The Crossover has superb grip thanks to it profile and the La Sportiva FriXion AT Sole. On wet boulders I am more careful than with a Vibram Megagrip sole, but I haven’t slipped on wet rocks yet. Given how much I have used these shoes I also am super-happy with the durability of the soles, they still have a few longer backpacking trips in them.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/48743965103/in/album-72157710871736122/" title="Hammastunturi Wilderness"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/48743965103_54ef2c5fa5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hammastunturi Wilderness" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49621607523/in/dateposted-public/" title="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX Sole"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49621607523_9dff1ecd9c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX Sole" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The integrated gaiter of the Crossover 2.0 is what gives this shoe a great advantage over normal trailrunning shoes in my opinions - the zipper is really well designed, the gaiter can be adjusted in width (tightness) at the top so it doesn’t slip down, and the material keeps rain, snow and debris like dirt and small stones out of your shoe. It also gives the shoe a great look, and I wear the shoe with the laces always done and only slip in and close the gaiter, ready to go.</p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I know that this shoe is made for trailrunning in winter, which is why it is made warmer. I’d like to see the same shoe - maybe with a Vibram Megagrip sole for even better grip on wet rocks - with a lighter inside construction which dries faster when it is wet, and I also can imagine it’d be good to decrease the Drop to 6 mm or less. This is more wishing La Sportiva building the ideal hiking shoe for wet weather, though 😃</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49622375682/in/dateposted-public/" title="Hi Gecko!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49622375682_d6a4337f8d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Hi Gecko!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>I have hiked for 9+ years in unlined shoes as that’s the Ultralight Backpacking Mantra. Light shoes without a (waterproof) liner are lighter and dry faster when wet. That is true, with the caveat that it depends on the material of the shoes how quickly they will dry. But I got so frustrated year after year that I had wet feet as soon as it rained a tiny wee bit or I went slightly off-trail, that I decided I want some more protection from water - hence I bought these shoes. I don’t look back at all. I love these shoes and will purchase a 2nd pair once these are nearing the end of their lifecycle, for me they really are a fantastic pair of shoes which helps me to keep my feet dry longer, with great grip on all the terrain I backpack in, and I really love the integrated gaiter of the shoe.</p>

<p><strong>Convinced?</strong> Buy the Crossover 2.0 GTX via these affiliate links and I’ll get a small commission without extra costs to you!</p>

<p>The La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX is available at <a href="https://www.alpinetrek.co.uk/la-sportiva-crossover-20-gtx-trail-running-shoes/?pid=10239">Alpinetrek.co.uk</a> in the UK and at <a href="http://tidd.ly/ed40ce05">Bergzeit.de</a> and <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/la-sportiva-crossover-20-gtx-trail-running-shoes/?pid=10239">Bergfreunde.eu</a> in Europe. Readers from Germany, Switzerland and Austria can also find the shoe at any of the shops in the underneath widget:</p>

<script async="" src="//z0a.de/outtra-982.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=39198" type="text/javascript" id="outtrapricecomparewdgt17339198" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapcwdgt="39198"></script>

<p>You can see more photos of the La Sportiva Crossover 2.0 GTX in this <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157713370037663">Flickr Album</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49622385247/in/album-72157713370037663/" title="Boulders are my friends"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49622385247_317fb637f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Boulders are my friends" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Look at the Arc'teryx 2016 Footwear]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/06/arcteryx-acrux-ar-alpine-boot.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-23T23:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/06/arcteryx-acrux-ar-alpine-boot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the 2015 <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/06/arcteryx-alpine-academy-chamonix-2015.html">Arc’teryx Alpine Academy</a> I got a sneak peek at the new Arc’teryx Acrux AR Alpine Boot, the first alpine climbing boot from Arc’teryx. I was lucky enough to try it on and play around with it in Chamonix, and also take a look at the two new Approach and Crag shoes, the Acrux SL and Arakys.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19052626366" title="The 2016 Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear News - Outsides by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/444/19052626366_d607d066f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="521" alt="The 2016 Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear News - Outsides" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="acrux-ar-alpine-boot">Acrux AR Alpine Boot</h2>

<p>The goal of Arc’teryx with the Acrux AR was to create a light, durable, weatherproof and well fitting double boot. The boot we saw and tried on at the Arc’teryx Academy arrived just that morning and so was an early pre-production model, but it should be relatively close to the boot that will be standing in the stores in 2016. I will share my impressions on the Arc’teryx boot and compare them to my <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx.html">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/04/scarpa-phantom-ultra-boots.html">Scarpa Phantom Ultra Boots</a>, both boots that I think are damn near perfect.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18458184033" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot in its natural Habitat by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3695/18458184033_16a7489781_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot in its natural Habitat" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18427468573" title="I &lt;3 my Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX Boots by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/290/18427468573_44079149bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="I &lt;3 my Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX Boots" /></a></p>

<h2 id="the-lightness-of-being">The Lightness of Being</h2>

<p>My Rebel Ultra GTX are 773 g per boot in Size 42,5 or 1.546 g for the pair, and the Phantom Ultra Boots are 918 g per shoe in Size 42,5 or 1.845 g for the pair. Keep in mind that these both are single boots! The Acrux AR GTX is a double boot - it has a removable liner - and one boot will weigh 940 g or 1.880 g for the pair in UK Size 8.5. So it is better to compare it to something like the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/scarpa-phantom-6000-schuhe-orange-38/">Scarpa Phantom Ultra 6000</a> (2.000 g per pair in Size 42) and the <a href="http://www.bergzeit.de/la-sportiva-spantik-schuhe-grey-yellow-grey-yellow-38/">La Sportiva Spantik</a> (2.400 g per pair in Size 42). These are quite a bit more heavy than the Acrux AR GTX, and I am not aware of a lighter alpine double boot (there are lighter skiing boots available).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18891197418" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/370/18891197418_1fe5583699_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot" /></a></p>

<h2 id="durable--weatherproof-construction">Durable &amp; Weatherproof Construction</h2>

<p>The boot is made to last - how long that is depends on how often you’re out in the mountains. If that’s just once a year for two weeks these probably will last you several years, while if you’re a Mountain Guide they only might last a season or two. The boot made a very sturdy impression on me, with the weakest link probably being the T-Zip Zipper which makes the gaiter waterproof. Maybe a quick look at the construction is in order:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Inside you find a <strong>Removable Gore-Tex Liner Booty</strong> which also packs some insulation and so keeps your feet warm</li>
  <li>The Boot has on the inside a <strong>PE Inner Shell</strong> construction which does not absorb moisture and has a lacing system for a secure and good fit</li>
  <li>On the outside we have a <strong>Laminated Waterproof Gaiter</strong> which closes with the T-Zip zipper for complete protection from snow, water and the cold</li>
  <li>Around the bottom of the boot there’s a <strong>Laminated Watertight Construction</strong> which has a 0,6 mm thick TPU film for high abrasion and puncture resistance</li>
  <li>The <strong>Midsole</strong> is very elaborate and made from six pieces which are custom made for this boot, in every size! It’s made up of a Carbon Fibre frame, an EVA Midsole and is protected by a wrapped TPU moulded heel and toe cap</li>
  <li>And underneath this all is a <strong>Vibram Mountaineering Outsole</strong></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18458178933" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot Sole Parts by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/420/18458178933_c6fb463767_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot Sole Parts" /></a></p>

<p>This all creates a durable boot which will be great for your alpine adventures and ice climbing alike. Oh, and a really cool is that the shoe can be re-soled, despite the elaborate sole construction.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19082087401" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/435/19082087401_7f2ebc7519_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot" /></a></p>

<p>The goal of the Acrux AR GTX Boot was to make a double liner boot that low in volume - more akin to the Scarpa Phantom Ultra - while bing warmer than the Rebel Ultra GTX. The boot we saw certainly achieved that goal, and was not much bigger than the Rebel Ultra GTX in volume, and lower in volume than the Phantom Ultras I have. I find low volume boots not just aesthetically better, but they also more practical in use in my opinion: I can climb better in a low volume boot, find easier foot holds in tight spots and it’s easier to get your pants over them, too.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18458165843" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/528/18458165843_aa936d77db_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot" /></a></p>

<h2 id="impressions--conclusions">Impressions &amp; Conclusions</h2>

<p>I’m used to very light footwear - <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2014/08/luna-sandals-oso.html">Luna Sandals</a> I love for hiking and every day use, and on the trail I often sport a pair of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/10/inov-8-trailroc-235.html">trailrunners</a> - so boots always will feel heavy to me. I tried the Acrux AR GTX Boot on and walked a bit around in them - not really a test thus - and they certainly felt heavy to me, especially since I also had my Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX boots along for my clinics. But they weren’t uncomfortably heavy and of course it is better to evaluate them when using them in cold weather in the mountains and not in front of a Restaurant, where they will probably not feel heavy anymore, but I’d likely appreciate their warmth at -5°C at 3.800 m altitude.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18458171633" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3832/18458171633_4aa257f560_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot" /></a></p>

<p>The boot was comfortable on my foot, the inside lacing enabled a secure fit with a Velcro Strap which held it in place. The Gaiter is adjusted via a Drawstring in the back and the gaiter is easy to open and close with the T-Zip zipper. The liner was warm and comfortable, and the adaptive fit will mould the liner over time to your foot for a personal fit. The seamless construction of the liner should minimize blisters and pressure points if that’s something you have problems with in other boots, and because it can be removed you can dry it faster or use it as a hut/ camp bootie.</p>

<p>The <strong>Conclusion</strong> is that the Arc’teryx Acrux AR GTX Alpine Boot certainly is a boot waiting for if you’re often out on Multi-Day adventures in the mountains. At 600€ it is competitively priced, the low volume and being a double boot sets it apart from the competition and it is very well made. I hope to be able to put them through their paces in the future and share a detailed review on them after a lot of use.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/18891192148" title="Acrux SL Men&#x27;s &amp; Women&#x27;s + Arakys Men&#x27;s by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/377/18891192148_e57cbdc64a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Acrux SL Men&#x27;s &amp; Women&#x27;s + Arakys Men&#x27;s" /></a></p>

<h2 id="acrux-sl--arakys-shoes">Acrux SL &amp; Arakys Shoes</h2>

<p>Besides the Acrux AR Alpine Boot Arc’teryx will also launch a <strong>S</strong>uper<strong>L</strong>ight version of the Acrux, which will tip the scales at 300 g per shoe. It has no Gote-Tex lining (Yay!), a Vibram Megagrip sole and is made for demanding approaches and descents. The Acrux SL comes in a Men’s and Women’s Version in four colours each. I think this will be a great crag/ every day outdoor shoe that will be popular, I certaily would pick a pair up.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19082127781" title="Acrux SL Women&#x27;s Above by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/308/19082127781_e5d1fcf646_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Acrux SL Women&#x27;s Above" /></a></p>

<p>And the other new shoe is the Arakys. Arc’teryx promotes it as a “<em>ultralight bouldering and single pitch approach shoe designed for indoor and outdoor climbers</em>”. The closure system can be operated with one hand and is easy to switch from climbing (closed) to belaying (open). The heel is collapsible and turns it into a slipper. It will weigh about 270 g per shoe in UK Size 8.5, has a Vibram MegaGrip sole and comes also in a Men’s and Women’s Version with four colours per sex. I probably wouldn’t use it for climbing &amp; bouldering, but for approaches, at the crag and scrambles it probably would be very nice.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19082093501" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Arakys Men&#x27;s Side by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/319/19082093501_3cc742e332_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Arakys Men&#x27;s Side" /></a></p>

<p>That’s the first look at the 2016 Arc’teryx Footwear line. There’s <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157654541709680">more photos on Flickr</a>, if you liked this post share it with your mates on <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/19082131411" title="Complete Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear Line-up by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/303/19082131411_8c1b5d2c9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Complete Arc&#x27;teryx Footwear Line-up" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/03/panama-jack-bambina-igloo-boots.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-19T10:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2014/03/panama-jack-bambina-igloo-boots</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ladies, are you looking for a pair of warm winter boots that look good in the city and on day hikes? Then hear what my wife has to say about the <a href="https://www.panamajackshop.com/woman/footwear/bambina-igloo-b2">Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13264850834/" title="Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3737/13264850834_79ba73db5c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Winter here in Finland is almost over now, and I decided to take my <a href="https://www.panamajackshop.com/woman/footwear/bambina-igloo-b2">Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots</a> for their last stroll in the nature before packing them up for the next winters to come. I believe we will be having many good years together - after all, the first Panama Jacks I bought in Spain 5 years ago are still as good as new.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13264494815/" title="Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2834/13264494815_434228a938_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots" /></a></p>

<p>These Spaniards are born to cold climates, icy roads and cold breezes. This winter was particularly short, but we had the chance to experience up to - 20 degrees together. My feet were perfectly warm, assuming that I was mostly on the move while being outside and I wore thin, wool socks. Special thanks to the rubber outsoles that kept me on my feet also when walking on plain ice - where other boots’ sole behave like ice skates, these had a solid grip.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13264494165/" title="Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7128/13264494165_d48c69ea4f_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots" /></a></p>

<p>The leather in both pairs of Panama Jack shoes I have is especially hard wearing, and the shoes are durable and carefully crafted. They’re also extremely comfortable to wear, and look good in the city and on day hikes alike. I am looking forward to seeing this pair again in November 2014!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/13264645033/" title="Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots by HendrikMorkel, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3675/13264645033_8b18024797_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Panama Jack Bambina Igloo Boots" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
