<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: skiing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/skiing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2018-03-02T16:10:48+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions from the Salzburger Lungau]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau.html"/>
    <updated>2018-02-05T19:17:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/02/impressions-from-the-salzburger-lungau</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After the ISPO I did the only smart thing: Leave the city behind and head to Austria to go ski-touring. These are some first impressions from a too-short trip to the Salzburger Lungau Region.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225607357/in/dateposted/" title="Albert on the way to the summit of the Seeköpfl."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4620/25225607357_aa885b504c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert on the way to the summit of the Seeköpfl." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Salzburger Lungau Tourism who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225608777/in/dateposted/" title="St. Margarethen im Lungau"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4698/25225608777_5329e81066_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="St. Margarethen im Lungau" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After a very busy fair I met my brother and we made the trip down south to the <a href="https://www.lungau.at/en/your-lungau/15-villages/?_wb=en/your-lungau/15-villages/&amp;lang=EN">Salzburger Lungau</a> Region, a place we have visited before and really liked. We arrived at our <a href="https://www.grizzly-resort.at">Hotel</a>, had a tasty dinner and then it was off to bed as early in the morning we would meet Albert again, our <a href="http://www.geführte-skitouren.at">Ski-touring Guide</a> with whom we had the pleasure to go skiing already in the past.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225601117/in/dateposted/" title="Start of the tour."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4770/25225601117_d228306e86_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Start of the tour." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225604887/in/dateposted/" title="And what a view again!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4724/25225604887_f11df71d25_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And what a view again!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Albert had two other clients along and our little group was great, we had a lot of fun on the ascent and descent. It was a beautiful sunny day with great views - just the snow could have been a wee bit better.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225603587/in/dateposted/" title="Through the less-than-perfect snow down."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4761/25225603587_f2d6bb985b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Through the less-than-perfect snow down." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225603357/in/dateposted/" title="Albert showing how it&#x27;s done."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4713/25225603357_6a8f10e645_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Albert showing how it&#x27;s done." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The view from the Hotel wasn’t bad at all, either. We witnessed the #SuperBlueMoon rising behind the forest as we sat in the Sauna, not a bad place at all!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225606417/in/dateposted/" title="Timelapse."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4673/25225606417_0a106ea3e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Timelapse." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next day we hot the slopes. With a big ski resort right in front of the hotel it was not a long approach, and the skiing was good - though I really prefer soft snow on wild mountains. A good thing that a 80 cm dump of powder was forecast for the next day!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225605937/in/dateposted/" title="Snow? Yeps."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4760/25225605937_fa563906a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow? Yeps." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225610547/in/dateposted/" title="Germknödel, still a favourite meal of mine."><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4614/25225610547_fa07863ea4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Germknödel, still a favourite meal of mine." /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And so my brother and me headed again to the secluded Thomatal Valley and started from the Dr. Josef-Mehrl Hütte up into the mountains, not to be disappointed by the amount of snow.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25225609357/in/dateposted/" title="The fantastic Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4666/25225609357_ef4df5c352_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The fantastic Dr. Josef-Mehrl-Hütte" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Stay tuned for the full trip-report in the next few weeks! In the meanwhile you already can take a look some more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157663383796697">Flickr Album</a> and on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Family Skiing in Vuokatti]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/skiing-in-vuokatti.html"/>
    <updated>2018-01-22T19:37:57+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2018/01/skiing-in-vuokatti</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love winter, skiing and my family. So naturally the best thing is to combine all these things into one week of family fun and head to Vuokatti!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/27053282929/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="Vuokatti Ski Slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4542/27053282929_903586e363_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Vuokatti Ski Slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure:</strong> <em>This trip was made possible with the help of Visit Vuokatti who arranged accommodation and activities for us. This does not influence the article as I maintain full editorial control of the content published on this site. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on affiliate links &amp; blogger transparency.</em></p>

<h2 id="off-to-vuokatti">Off to Vuokatti</h2>

<p>For the third time in a row - after a visit to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html">Pyhä</a> and <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/hetta-winter-adventures-in-finnish-lapland.html">Hetta</a> in the previous years - we packed our winter gear, warm socks and skis and travelled North to experience a proper Finnish winter. Though while in the years before we travelled really far we didn’t want to put that stress on us and our kids of then 1 and 5 years, so after some research we found out about Vuokatti, one of the most snow-secure ski resorts in what we still consider Southern Finland (technically it’s probably the South of Lapland, but lets just say it ain’t as far North as Ylläs, Hetta and Saariselkä). To Vuokatti from Vaasa it are only 400 km which you can drive in a day with some proper planning and keeping the kids entertained, which made it the perfect destination for us. Vuokatti actually is also very easy reached by train and bus, and with many accommodation options being within walking distance of the slopes you can also get around without a car.</p>

<p>Vuokatti is a fantastic destinations for families that want to ski together but don’t want to sit 12 or more hours in the car to get far up North. The <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/Vuokatti-Slopes">13 slopes in Vuokatti</a> are wide &amp; easy, there’s a Fun park with a Halfpipe and some nice big kickers, a Snowboard Tunnel and of course you can rent all the equipment right there so don’t need to travel there with all the gear along. Here’s the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/loader.aspx?id=e3625da0-e490-45b2-a45f-508558f77279">slope map</a> to give you an idea; what I missed is some <em>Lähi offarit</em> - lift-accessible backcountry runs through the forests, but that’s really just a case of getting rid of some trees to make that possible 😜!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39836691081/in/dateposted/" title="Sunny Vuokatti slopes!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4675/39836691081_d8917ae008_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunny Vuokatti slopes!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="lets-go-skiing">Lets go skiing!</h2>

<p>Did I mention that I love skiing? Ah yeah, right there at the beginning 😄. Well, my son learned to ski at age 4 in Levi and enjoyed a short refresher with one of the wonderful ski teachers at the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/Vuokatti-Slopes/Vuokatti-Ski-School">Vuokatti Ski School</a> and then hit the slopes on his own. We decided to not push him and let him go at his own speed, which we found was the right way for us because so he gradually wanted to try bigger &amp; bigger slopes and became more confident skiing them. It’s just beautiful to see your child share the same love for an activity you have yourself, and we are very blessed that our kids love to be outdoors and active as much as we.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804532442/in/dateposted/" title="Vuokatti Slopes"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4677/39804532442_8567e515cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Vuokatti Slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It also was the first time for my wife to stand on Downhill skis, and she too enjoyed the great teaching of the Vuokatti Ski School - which is the 2nd Oldest Ski School in Finland! After a couple of days of being taught the principles of skiing she was skiing down the hills on her own, getting more and more confident and loving the experience. The best thing probably was after that week that she told me <em>“I now understand why you love skiing so much!”</em>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127039344/in/dateposted/" title="Ski School 001"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4651/39127039344_9471592108_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski School 001" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/25963527478/in/dateposted/" title="Ski School 004"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4661/25963527478_d85395b83b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski School 004" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057808909/in/dateposted/" title="Ski Sirkus"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/28057808909_16189acf99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Sirkus" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057800749/in/dateposted/" title="Ski Carousel"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4671/28057800749_f25c3c402a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Carousel" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And while there were some really small kids skiing we shared the parenting of our one-year old daughter, and I was taking care of her in the morning while my son &amp; wife were skiing, and then when it was lunch time we ate a small snack at the slopes before the rest of the family went home for naps, playing Lego and relaxing I went skiing. The slopes were for me quite a good training, it was after all only the 2nd season that I stood again on skis after a break of around 16 years! Skiing in a resort is excellent for that, ingraining these movements into ones body and mind. I usually started on one side of the resort and then skied every slope till I reached the other side, where I could step out of the skis and walk with the skis on my shoulder in ten minutes back to our accommodation at the Vuokatti Suites. There’s three main lifts which all bring you all up the slope, with some shorter connecting lifts which help you to get from one end to the other one. <a href="http://www.movescount.com/moves/move148262268">This is how a usual day on the slopes looked</a> according to my Suunto Spartan Ultra.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38937896925/in/dateposted/" title="First down!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4610/38937896925_49699d7595_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="First down!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127057454/in/dateposted/" title="Skiing with my son"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4758/39127057454_b7cc181cac_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skiing with my son" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="kids-love-vuokatti">Kids Love Vuokatti!</h2>

<p>After skiing in the mornings we enjoyed family activities in the afternoons, it’s how we roll and really like it. The highlight of the trip for our son was most definitely at the Angry Birds themed <a href="https://superpark.fi/park/vuokatti/">SuperPark Vuokatti</a>, it’s a memory he looks with a smile back to and he regularly comes up to me and says <em>“Dad, we need to go back to the Angry Birds Park, it was so fun!”</em>. It’s memories like these that makes travelling with the family so beautiful, I myself have these kinds of memories of travelling with my parents and siblings, and it just gives kids so much more than some tangible thing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127083144/in/dateposted/" title="Welcome to Angry Birds Park Vuokatti!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4751/39127083144_60eb74128e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Welcome to Angry Birds Park Vuokatti!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127074864/in/dateposted/" title="Slides are fun!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4669/39127074864_ede59200f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Slides are fun!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057824409/in/dateposted/" title="Red!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/28057824409_110ee0b823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Red!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38937888245/in/dateposted/" title="Trying bikes at Angry Birds Park Vuokatti"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4746/38937888245_47a700a3f6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trying bikes at Angry Birds Park Vuokatti" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On another day we went to play bowling at <a href="http://www.vuokattibowling.fi/">Vuokatti Bowling</a>, which is again a memory our son recalls with joy - actually just this morning he told us the scores from our visit at Vuokatti Bowling (Him: 148, my wife: 120, me: 84 😄). The bowling alley in Vuokatti was also really child-friendly, they had a playing room for kids which had large windows which allowed our daughter to play inside but always see us. The staff was friendly and helped me figure out the “complicated” bowling computer (you’d think I’d know these things being a geek!), and the best thing is that the bowling allies are child-friendly as when our son bowled rails went up which prevented the bowling ball going into the gutter. All in all this was a great experience and we might just need to have a visit to a bowling alley with the kids again soon!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804546062/in/dateposted/" title="Vuokatti Bowling"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4718/39804546062_52189d6587_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vuokatti Bowling" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then we went one afternoon to the Spa and swimming pools at the <a href="https://www.holidayclubresorts.com/fi/kohteet/katinkulta/kylpyla-ja-hoidot/">Holiday Club Katinkulta</a>. Going to the Spa with the kids is all about sharing the time of who watches the kids when, so that both parents can go in piece to the Sauna, Jacuzzi or swimming. Happily our kids love water and there was both a small kids pool and a slide, which made watching the kids easy &amp; fun. So while one of us was relaxing the other one was taking care of the kids, and after a while we high-fived and switched!</p>

<p>But this isn’t everything! We enjoyed some afternoons just exploring Vuokatti on foot (you can for example drive up the slopes from the other side and walk to the Café on the top!) and walking on the frozen lake in front of the hotel and watching the sunset. You also can go on a <a href="http://www.vuokattisafaris.com/en/tour/husky-safaris/">Husky Safari</a> in Vuokatti, enjoy the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/All-year-round/Skiing">massive XC skiing tracks</a> or check out the Vuokatti Ski tunnel. There’s definitely more than enough options for none-skiing activities in Vuokatti, so just have a look at <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Activities/In-winter">what is possible</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39127093244/in/dateposted/" title="Hiking in Vuokatti"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4604/39127093244_7125a940c7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking in Vuokatti" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804531052/in/dateposted/" title="Ripa&#x27;s Slope Café"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4712/39804531052_91ac5f6820_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ripa&#x27;s Slope Café" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="hungry-heres-where-to-eat-in-vuokatti">Hungry? Here’s where to eat in Vuokatti!</h2>

<p>We loved the breakfast at Vuokatti Suites where we stayed (it was hands-down the best breakfast I have eaten at any Hotel) but we were lucky enough to not needing to cook in the evenings as we went to eat out. Vuokatti gathers to many different tastes, from high-class Menus like we enjoyed at <a href="https://www.sokoshotels.fi/en/vuokatti/sokos-hotel-vuokatti/meetings-and-events/meeting-room?id=466583_392858">Restaurant Kippo</a> and really good and tasty food at <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/en/Services/Vuokatti/Restaurants">À la Katti</a> and <a href="https://vuokattisport.fi/en/ravintolapalvelut/">O’las Restaurant</a> to more basic but good food at <a href="https://olearys.fi/holiday-club-katinkulta/">O’Learys</a>, <a href="https://www.ravintolamessi.fi">Ravintola Messi</a> and <a href="https://www.raflaamo.fi/en/sotkamo/amarillo-vuokatti">Amarillo</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804549022/in/dateposted/" title="Restaurant Kippo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4720/39804549022_1db02d4a9b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Restaurant Kippo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804547392/in/dateposted/" title="Starter at Kippo"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4667/39804547392_d55553a89c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Starter at Kippo" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804528872/in/dateposted/" title="Amarillo Menu"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4745/39804528872_bd92bd9f99_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Amarillo Menu" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="would-we-go-again">Would we go again?</h2>

<p>We loved our stay in Vuokatti, and so did the kids. The memories we made as a family are more worth to us than a car, TV or other tangible goods - we try to raise our kids and show them that you spending time with the ones you love is the best use of money &amp; time. It’s thus no surprise that family holidays are high on our list, and a perfect family vacation like we experienced in Vuokatti gives you memories for a lifetime. The small town just had it all: Great slopes for beginner skiers, fun and versatile activities for the afternoons, comfortable accommodation and tasty food. Add in that the people we met in Vuokatti - from the Ski instructors over the Café and Restaurant Staff to everyone else - was super-friendly and great with kids! So to answer the question in the heading: YES! We totally would go again to Vuokatti, and when our daughter is four or five we might need to return so she can learn to ski!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39836691701/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="Learning to love skiing!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4649/39836691701_9f7c2691cb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to love skiing!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p>As always, you can find more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157689199140311">Vuokatti Flickr Album</a>.</p>

<h2 id="where-to-stay">Where to stay</h2>

<p>We stayed at <a href="http://www.hotellivuokatti.fi/en/suites">Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites</a> and had a gorgeous Suite with lots of space for us four. Our son had his own room and our daughter slept with us in the big bed, which meant in the evenings we parents could have a glass of wine on the comfortable Sofa and watch a movie on TV (which we can’t do at home as we don’t own a TV!). There was a fully-equipped kitchen in which we prepared our afternoon coffee and evening snacks for the kids, and we had our own Sauna in the Suite which was used almost every evening. The Suite had a drying cabinet which we used to dry moist ski boots, gloves and hats, and the view from the balcony over the lake was beautiful. And if the room was an indication for the whole operation, the breakfast we enjoyed each morning at the main Hotel building was just the best ever. Kids can be tricky with new foods, but at Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites they served everything we’d have at home plus some. The delicious fried eggs, Karelian pastries and lots of <em>fresh</em> fruit made for a good start into a new day, and the coffee was good, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057804579/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Living Room"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4703/28057804579_fa56016097_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Living Room" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/28057805089/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Own Sauna"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4714/28057805089_8849bb91ae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Own Sauna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804540312/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Ski Storage"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4660/39804540312_53040f1343_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites - Ski Storage" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/39804533732/in/dateposted/" title="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites from the top!"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4749/39804533732_2c9760f298_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="Hotelli Vuokatti &amp; Suites from the top!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-there">How to get there</h2>

<p>As I said, you can travel by train &amp; bus to Vuokatti and stay close to the slopes and use the <a href="http://www.vuokatti.fi/loader.aspx?id=643138b3-51fb-405a-a15f-d9e7cee95549">free Vuokatti SkiBus</a> so that a car is not needed. That being said, a (rental) car does make things a bit easier if you come with two kids and ski gear or want to eat in the town in the evenings. From Vaasa it is a 400 km drive to Vuokatti, which takes with breaks in winter around six hours. You also can <a href="https://www.finnair.com/fi/gb/offers?OFFER_ID=62287">fly with Finnair to Kajanni</a> via Helsinki and take the <a href="http://www.akyllonen.fi/airbus/?lang=en">Airport shuttle bus</a> and then use the aforementioned free SkiBus around town.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/38798598622/in/album-72157689199140311/" title="In the middle, a river"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4538/38798598622_90929ef9cc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="767" alt="In the middle, a river" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc'teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/12/arcteryx-voltair-avalanche-airbag.html"/>
    <updated>2015-12-16T23:18:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/12/arcteryx-voltair-avalanche-airbag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The second big news from last weeks <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> media event in Vancouver was the launch of the Voltair Avalanche Airbag. As I was able to use and deploy it over three days in the Canadian backcountry what follows are more insights on this game-changing avalanche airbag.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23716165196/in/dateposted/" title="Arc’teryx Designer Gord Rose skiing with his creation, the Voltair Avalanche Airbag"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5734/23716165196_6633e02f0d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Designer Gord Rose skiing with his creation, the Voltair Avalanche Airbag" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-tech">The Tech</h2>

<p>No, it has no similarities with the JetForce Technology. Both are powered by a battery, but that’s already what these two technologies have in common. And the Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag battery allows the bag to be deployed up to 8 times on a fully charged battery, which is two times as often as the Jetforce lets you deploy the ballon. It’s even more at warmer temperatures, and less at -30°C - but then again, not many will be out skiing at -30°C.</p>

<p>Gordon Rose started to dabble in Avalanche packs around ten years ago, but the Voltair project started in February 2010 for real. Since then Gordon and his colleague Peter Hill, who is responsible for the backpack part of the Voltair, have been working on this avalanche pack. The inspiration for Gordon came from RC Models - he and a colleague where talking about how fast model planes can go, the short comings of compressed gas airbag, and saw possibilities of RC Technology for avalanche bags. Gordon went through many tests of propellor and centrifugal blowers until he settled on a mixed flow centrifugal blower. Advanced Design Technology in London, UK, helped him and Arc’teryx design the optimal propellor and after 21 designs and tests they had the perfect one for their pack.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23447243040/in/dateposted/" title="Gordon Rose with the tech guts of the Voltair Avalanche Airbag"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5798/23447243040_c612e0e1b1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gordon Rose with the tech guts of the Voltair Avalanche Airbag" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next step was to get the battery right. Gordon settled on a Lithium Polymer battery design as these work well at cold temperatures and are the most efficient. Powertraveller helped design and manufacture the battery, and the one in the Voltair now allows you to deploy the ballon up to 8 times at -15°C - more at warmer temperatures, less at -30°C. The benefit of this should be obvious: It allows you to practice to deploy the airbag. If you know how it behaves, you’re less likely to hesitate to pull the trigger and deploy the ballon. Each of us popped the ballon a couple of times in a test environment, and then up in the mountains again. In the case of an avalanche this means you don’t wait and pull the trigger and deploy the ballon. The battery is charged via a cable and goes from empty to full in 2,5 hours, and weighs 800 g - a weight that Arc’teryx hopes to improve in the future.</p>

<p>For the release trigger Arc’teryx decided to use a mechanical system - while the possibility to use an electronic system is tempting, they decided in harsh conditions there’s just too much which can go wrong with a electronic release, and a reliable pull trigger is the best way to go. The Trigger is easy to unlock, but even in a locked position it is easy to release the ballon with just a small twist. The trigger is custom-molded and easy to grip with mitts and gloves, and connects via a steel cable to the ballon compartment. A pull on the trigger pops the closure open, this in turn connects to an electronic trigger which starts up the centrifugal blower which inflates the ballon in less than five seconds.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23716201286/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Release Trigger Locked"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/675/23716201286_fc4b267027_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Release Trigger Locked" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next design hurdle was the Brushless DC Motor, which are difficult to make reliable at cold weather. After tracking down many designers across the globe Gord found the right guy just five minutes from the Arc’teryx Design HQ, and he helped him design a reliable engine which also performs at -30°C. 90% of the other technology in the pack is also custom-made, from flexible wires to the circuit board and release notch, Arc’teryx spent nearly six years to make this backpack the best in its category. To learn more, please watch this exclusive video where Gordon Rose and Peter Hill talk about the Voltair Avalanche Airbag:</p>

<iframe width="1280" height="720" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xjq-NAQUK-k" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>(<em>Interview video coming soon!</em>)</p>

<h2 id="the-pack">The Pack</h2>

<p>The goal of Peter Hill was to make a classic, timeless Arc’teryx backpack which still looks great in five years. Constructed from the AC² material with taped seams and glued-in Sidewinder zippers, the pack is waterproof and keeps your gear dry. As it rained &amp; snowed all the time as we were up in the mountains it was a good test for the pack, and it performed great: Everything stayed dry inside.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23633782422/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag - Side"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5797/23633782422_324efe2db1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag - Side" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The Voltair has three compartments: A ballon compartment, an avalanche Kit compartment and a main compartment. Available in two sizes these pack are real 20 l and 30 l packs, unlike some packs of competitors which barely let you pack a puffy jacket and thermos bottle in their claimed volumes. I carried in my 30 l test pack two extra pairs of gloves, my <a href="http://bit.ly/1P2NxEx">Arc’teryx Cerium SV Jacket</a>, my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/norroena-lyngen-alpha100-vest-kunstfaserweste/?pid=10239">Norrona Lyngen Alpha100 Vest</a>, a water bottle, sandwiches and snacks, my <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.de/contour-hybrid-mix-130-skifelle/?pid=10239">countour Hybrid skins</a>, a tripod, two cameras and I had plenty of room to spare. If I compare that to my <a href="https://www.bergzeit.co.uk/black-diamond-dawn-patrol-25-ski-rucksack-deep-torch-black-m-l/?pid=81">Black Diamond Dawn Patrol 25 pack</a> that’s a massive difference, where it gets pretty hard to get so much gear in.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23716247456/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Avalanche Kit Pocket"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/738/23716247456_a1a40505f3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Avalanche Kit Pocket" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The carrying system of the Voltair is very comfortable and is fully adjustable. The hipbelt has some freedom of movement so you can turn those hips for your turns, and if you want to save weight you can remove the stays. The hipbelt also can be turned around for transport, and the chest strap can be removed if you feel you don’t need it. The leg loop strap is very easy to use which is very important: It’s the piece of gear that ensures you stay connected to the backpack and ballon if you get into an avalanche. It is super easy to clip in and out - also with mitts on - and the design is inspired by ice clippers as you might know them from ice climbing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23742317785/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Leg loop clip-in point"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5829/23742317785_aa47814a51_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Leg loop clip-in point" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The pack isn’t ultralight, even if Arc’teryx tried to use the lightest &amp; most durable materials and technology in the pack. The 20 l pack is 3.235 g and the 30 l pack is 3.465 g - the tech inside is a big part of that, with the battery itself already being a wee bit over 800 g. Arc’teryx hopes that this weight will be decreased in the not-too-distant future, especially since major players are heavily infesting into energy storage solutions.</p>

<h2 id="in-use">In Use</h2>

<p>I was able to use the pack for three days out at <a href="http://www.callaghancountry.com">Callaghan Country</a>, which gave me a good understanding how this pack carries and deploys. The first thing you realize is the comfortable carrying system, which carries also (for an ultralight backpacker) very well, even with a pretty full pack. Also the leg loop is wonderfully intuitive and unobtrusive: It clips in and out super easy even with thick gloves on, and you don’t realize it is there while skinning and skiing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23633780212/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag at Callaghan Country"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5702/23633780212_2243ce5e36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc’teryx Voltair Avalanche Airbag at Callaghan Country" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As I haven’t used Avalanche Airbags before I have nothing to compare the Voltair to, but chatting with Lou of <a href="http://wildsnow.com">Wildsnow</a> and my other colleagues at the event it became evident that the Voltair is a well-designed Avalanche backpack which compares very good with other packs in the market. The advantages of battery-powered packs in comparison to compressed air backpacks are evident: You can practice and test the release of the ballon at home, it is much easier to travel with as you don’t need to find a place to fill up the air cartridge before you hit the slopes at your destination, and being able to release the ballon in the Voltair up to eight times means using this pack on long outings adds a lot of safety.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23659988171/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Packing the Ballon 1"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5703/23659988171_0fef0d05d5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Packing the Ballon 1" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Packing the ballon is a thing of two to five minutes, depending on your level of practice. The ballon deflates via a valve which you slide in. Happily the ballon does not need to be folded in a special way - just stuff it back into the ballon compartment, close the zipper, pop the hatch back in and you’re ready. I discussed at length with Peter and Gordon about the use of zippers for the ballon compartment as it’s most certainly the thing I like least, but as every other avalanche pack on the market uses zippers (they work!) and in a pinch you can use the ballon even if the zipper is broken, I am convinced that it is OK.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23115555973/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Ballon compartment"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/579/23115555973_03b5921fd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ballon compartment" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Putting the system on and releasing the ballon is also easy. You put the battery on and get a re-assuring short whirr which means the system is on and ready to go. The green LED lamp at the outside will blink green indicating that all is good to go, then you just turn the handle to the green dot side and you’re ready to skin up and ski down. In the case of an avalanche you pull the trigger and <em>POP!</em> the ballon deploys, helping you to hopefully stay on top thanks to the inverse segregation principle, which sorts larger particles to the top of the avalanche. The handle of the Voltair is also always accessible and can not be stowed away, this again minimizes the risk of user error and is different from other avalanche packs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23742279705/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="POW Turns"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5814/23742279705_0876730dd4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="POW Turns" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>You can carry skis/ snowboard and an ice axe at the front of the pack, just make sure to put the ice axe with the tip down (ballons and steel tips don’t work well together). The side compression straps help to minimize volume if you are out with a small load, and the front hipbelt is comfortable and carries well. All buckles are easy to open in cold weather with gloves, and the zippers have tabs which makes them easy to operate with gloves on.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23374347639/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Crossing streams"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/654/23374347639_0df435ac5f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Crossing streams" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Finally, the battery and control unit of the circuit collect data of the pack in use, with the aim to further the knowledge base of avalanche airbags in use. This data can be downloaded - should the user agree - when the pack is sent in for inspection. Arc’teryx works close together with Pascal Haegeli of the Simon Fraser University in Vancouver, one of the premier avalanche researchers on the planet.</p>

<h2 id="the-bottomline">The Bottomline</h2>

<p>The Voltair is a beautifully designed avalanche pack which is spacious and easy to use. The tech inside is all custom-made and designed to the highest standards, so that it can operate at -30°C and for many years in the harsh conditions of the backcountry. It is easy to learn how to deploy the ballon, pack it back in and then carry all your gear on your backcountry ski-tours. Fully waterproof it keeps your kit inside dry, and the possibilities for human error minimized it hopefully helps you to survive an avalanche if you should ever get into one. The packs will retail for 1650€ for the 30 l pack and 1550€ for the 20 l and will be available in autumn 2016. <em>Of course using the pack for just three days is not enough for a long-term review, but I am confident that with a sample pack showing up hopefully soon I can put it through its paces during the many ski-touring trips I have planned for this winter and then can get a more detailed review up by spring.</em></p>

<p>A lot more <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157662401963745">high resolution photos are in the Flickr Album</a>, and if you enjoyed this article <strong><a href="http://bit.ly/1HGCWMS">buy me a coffee</a></strong>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23115487673/in/album-72157662401963745/" title="Skinning up"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/758/23115487673_22ec0ed64b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skinning up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Arc'teryx Procline Carbon Lite Ski Boot]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/12/arcteryx-procline-carbon-lite-ski-boot.html"/>
    <updated>2015-12-11T23:55:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/12/arcteryx-procline-carbon-lite-ski-boot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>1.190 g light, freedom of movement and great for alpinists and ski-tourers alike: The Arc’teryx Procline Carbon Lite Ski Boot and its siblings, the Procline Men’s Lite &amp; Procline Women’s Lite.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23233644179/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5694/23233644179_77ae9e38a8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I was lucky enough to witness on Monday afternoon the unveiling of the <a href="http://arcteryx.com">Arc’teryx</a> ski boot line. It was a much rumoured development and what we saw today was even better than what the rumors suggested. As I have a severe Jetleg I will just make this a short and sweet post with some key points, and after (possibly maybe) having used the boot a bit more over the following few days up in the mountains I will update this post, so please stay tuned. It is smart to follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> as with some luck there will be live updates from the mountains about this boot and the new Voltair Avalanche Airbag there, too.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23519476391/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/709/23519476391_c5e65555f2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Coming in Fall 2016 are the <strong>six alpine touring ski boots from Arc’teryx</strong>, and together with eight colleagues from Europe and North America I am heading out to test these new boots and the Voltair Avalanche Airbag over the next three days so I will be able to give more insights on those on Friday. Here’s what I can tell you from trying on the boot and checking it out today at the exclusive product launch. The Six models are called</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Procline Carbon Lite</strong>, the top of the line Unisex model which tips the scales at 1.190 g and will cost 730€ retail.</li>
  <li>The <strong>Procline Carbon Support</strong> will be 1.260 g in MP Size 27.5 abd costs 700€</li>
  <li>The <strong>Procline Men’s Lite</strong> will be 580€, 1.190 g in MP Size 27.5 while the <strong>Procline Men’s Support</strong> is 1.260 g and 550€</li>
  <li>The <strong>Procline Women’s Lite</strong> tips the scales at 1.060 g and the <strong>Procline Women’s Support</strong> is 1.120 g - prices are the same as the Men’s models but both have a women’s last</li>
</ul>

<p>The difference between the Lite and Support models are the liners and cuffs. The Lite liners are about 90 g lighter as the support liners and fully thermo-mouldable. Both liners are designed in-house, but are different: The <em>Lite Liner</em> is made for uphill agility and great if you have a talented ski boot fitter at hand, while the <em>Support Liner</em> is slightly better for ski performance and if you don’t have access to a ski boot fitter. The Support Liner also has, as the name suggests, more tongue and collar support. The Women’s model will have a women’s last, and all liners have a removable strap closure system.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23306141770/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5788/23306141770_d7edb81816_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The special thing about the boot - besides the ridiculously light weight of 1.190 g for the Procline Carbon Lite - is the agility it gives you. The 360° Rotating Cuff makes the boot feel more like the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2015/01/scarpa-rebel-ultra-gtx.html">Scarpa Rebel Ultra GTX</a>. Unlike normal cuffs this cuff - available in two different configurations, one from Carbon fibre with over-injected Grilamid and in the Men’s and Women’s models the cuff is made from carbonfibre charged Grilamid  - is cut in half. Yes, you read that right: The cuff is cut in half in the back of your calf. Together with the rest of the cuff his gives you a <strong>Lateral rotation of 23° inwards and 13° outwards</strong>, which should make it much more better for skinning up difficult, steep snow or make it more agile for climbing.</p>

<p>Speaking of alpine climbing, one of the re-occurring points the designer <strong>Federico Sbrissa</strong> (keep that name in mind, I have a feeling we can expect much more great footwear innovations to come from him!) made is that these boots were <em>designed for the alpinists and also great for every ski-tourer</em>. It’s a point worth thinking about, because the things alpinist (climbers) want in boots often will be much appreciated by skiers. I mean, more agility in your boot that allows you to skin longer and keep the crampons in your pack? Great! More edge control on steep snow traverses? Yes please! More agility when using crampons? Heck yeah!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23234109229/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/583/23234109229_7920fba1dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Nice about these carbon fibre cuffs is also that the pivot points - the places where metal rivets go through them - are made from plastic. And they connect to plastic. Which makes them a lot more durable than 100% carbon cuffs, which tend to wear out at the points where they touch metal. As here plastic touches plastic, they should last much longer, which is pretty cool. Once you decide to ski pull the buckle down and can hit the pow. Locking pins on the divided cuff lock into the rear spine and you have a nice, stiff boot to go down.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22975559223/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot -Cuff inside"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/659/22975559223_96c5b221af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot -Cuff inside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23520236251/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot - Cuff Pivot Point"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/573/23520236251_2211b8dfc9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot - Cuff Pivot Point" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The other great innovation - well, there’s many more, but I have that jetleg and tomorrow’s another long day - is the full coverage gaiter. Made from Cordura with a PVC coating it is waterproof, a thing that both climbers and skiers will appreciate: If you climb ice in boots you don’t want ice or water coming in, and on Champagne Powder days you neither want snow in your boot, be it skinning up or shredding down. This gaiter, which is integrated with the boot shell, gives you a lot of protection and toasty feet in any conditions, be it skiing down or climbing up.</p>

<p>The Hybrid Closure System is a mix of buckle and lacing - think a Boa® closure that actually stays shut. The buckle is integrated with the cable, has 15 different positions for adjustment for an individual fit, and as the cable is connected to the buckle - once the buckle is locked in, it stays put! The cable is made from steel and the buckle from aluminium, and it is pretty amazing how well you can adjust the fit on these.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/23519518161/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot - Hybrid Closure System"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/707/23519518161_b99c9dfedf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot - Hybrid Closure System" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There’s a lot more - a Power Strap without Velcro, buckles that keep in place when opened, a rockered tow, Dynafit certified toe and heel inserts, a crampon optimized toe shape with rubber cover and a Vibram sole - but I’ll tell you more about these on Friday. Until then check the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157661451499809">photos in high-res on Flickr</a>, follow along on <a href="http://facebook.com/hikinginfinland">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a> and read <a href="http://backcountrymagazine.com">what</a> my <a href="https://www.wildsnow.com">colleagues</a> <a href="http://www.fall-line.co.uk">have</a> to <a href="http://www.friflyt.no/Ski/ArcteryxProcline">say</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/22973797184/in/dateposted/" title="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5717/22973797184_35af5922aa_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Arc&#x27;teryx Procline Carbon Boot" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Family Adventures in Pyhä-Luosto]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto.html"/>
    <updated>2015-04-08T23:41:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2015/04/winter-family-adventures-in-pyha-luosto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The common human relationship with winter seems to go like this: As a child you love winter. In your twenties you could life without it. And from your thirties onwards you fall in love with winter &amp; snow again. In our family we’re all winter lovers, and as winter didn’t really visit us in Vaasa we decided to find it up north at <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/eng/">Pyhä Tunturi</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075087012" title="That one next, dad! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7599/17075087012_e945efd6da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="That one next, dad!" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="prologue">Prologue</h2>

<p>Climate change is a real bummer for winter lovers in Southern Finland. While I did get to ski and fatbike in the snow a bit back home, winter in Vaasa was a mix of snow + cold and then rain + warm temperatures which resulted in a less than nice winter. With a week of winter vacation that we could each take of, M and me decided to search winter in Lapland. After some discussions of what we wanted we quickly settled on the <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/eng/">Pyhä Ski Resort</a> as the best destination for us this year as it had plenty of fun winter activities to offer for all three of us, from skiing and hiking over sledding to ice climbing and fatbiking, with great <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/accommodation/">accommodation</a> options, too.</p>

<p>A car was rented, <a href="www.airbnb.com/c/hmorkel?s=8">AirBnB accommodation</a> in Oulu was organized and the luggage was packed. It was a nice Sunday morning as we started the drive north, and it was around Oulu - 300 km from Vaasa - that we saw the first signs of Winter again. The next day we continued via a stop in Rovaniemi onwards to Pyhä, and already from a distance we could see the iconic fjells of the ski resort and <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/pyha-luostonp">National Park</a>, with lots of snow around us and a beautiful bluebird sky promising a great week of winter fun! We checked in to the <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1128&amp;submenu=3657">Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartment</a>, heated up the Sauna and enjoyed seeing the stars in the crisp, black sky.</p>

<h2 id="winter-fun-for-kids">Winter fun for Kids</h2>

<p>We found Pyhä a great location for our three year old. He loved the snow and we were daily at the sled hill, which was a five minutes walk from the <a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/pyha-luostonluontokeskus">Nature Centre Naava</a> (which is in the centre of the village and hence an easy reference point). The two sled hills were good fun and E didn’t get tired of sledding for many hours each day, with little rest breaks at the conveniently located open hut at the foot of the hill. Being allowed to throw another log of wood on the fire was equally nice as making snow angles and sledding together <em>superfast</em> with dad.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889011560" title="Pyhä Sled Hill by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7713/16889011560_3351fc57fa_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Pyhä Sled Hill" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076568685" title="Sled Hill break hut by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8752/17076568685_cb2b65aa11_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Sled Hill break hut" /></a></p>

<p>There’s a ski school for kids in Pyhä too, though we decided to wait for another year to put him on downhill skis. There were lots of kids skiing, though, and the Family slopes were full with parents and kids of all ages. Close to our apartment was also a reindeer enclosure and visiting Rudolph and his friends was every time again fascinating. E also enjoyed looking how other people skied down the hills so fast, and going up with the Polar Express to the top of the fjell made him smile from ear to ear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075825821" title="Top of the fjell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8798/17075825821_e54ca475a2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Top of the fjell" /></a></p>

<h2 id="skiing">Skiing</h2>

<p>M and me have the same shoe size, which was convenient as we loaned cross country skis and boots. M enjoyed skiing the tracks while I went a bit off-piste and explored the nearby National Park and swamp on skis. There’s surely a hundred kilometre or more of groomed cross-country skiing tracks at Pyhä and M liked the little huts and Laavus along the tracks, as they were ideal to have a short break and then ski back. The tracks vary in difficulty, from a super easy loipe that goes around a mire with zero elevations to more demanding loipes. You even can ski around the whole Pyhä-Luosto National Park on groomed tracks, which is - depending on the route you choose - between 70 or more kilometres. For early morning and late night skiers there’s also a pretty long illuminated track which is lighted up from 6 in the morning till 23 at night.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075080162" title="Skiing by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8687/17075080162_2149394d66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Skiing" /></a></p>

<p>But of course cross-country skiing is just one sort of skiing you can do in Pyhä! It’s very well known in Finland to be <em>the</em> Backcountry destination, as you can take the lift up and then pretty much ski down where you please. Sadly my <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2015/03/ispo-2015-news-3.html">DPS Tour 1 skis</a> didn’t arrive in time otherwise I would have been out on the slopes and made some pretty turns after skinning up the hills. There are lots of great ski-touring options at Pyhä, so if that’s your kind of skiing make sure to take your gear along! Also for downhill and Freeskiers Pyhä is a great destination, with 9 lifts, 14 prepared slopes - the longest slope being 1800 m - and the same ski pass being valid at Ruka as well Pyhä is a great destination to go snowboarding and skiing. Add in that the lifts are working super efficient and queues were non-existent and you have the ingredients for lots of skiing and fun.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16890340699" title="Top of the fjell by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8716/16890340699_d85b8eda66_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Top of the fjell" /></a></p>

<h2 id="ice-climbing">Ice climbing</h2>

<p>One of the reasons why Pyhä won for us as a destination is that you can go <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/ice-climbing/customized-ice-climbing/">ice climbing at Tajukangas</a> which is a short stroll from the slopes and the Pyhätunturi Hotel. My friends from <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/">Bliss Adventure</a> run the ice climbing crag there, and I was very happy that my friend <a href="http://aleksimehtonen.fi/">Aleksi</a> and his colleague Mikko were there with me and were the belay masters while I was whacking some ice. And whacking ice I did!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16454119254" title="My first ice lead at Tajukangas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7665/16454119254_4f6f3c878e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="My first ice lead at Tajukangas" /></a></p>

<p>After a couple of warm-ups and checking out the routes I did my first ice lead ever, and while I was a bit nervous while tying in to my <a href="http://www.bergzeit.fi/en/mammut-genesis-8-5-half-rope-red/?pid=81">Mammut 8.5 Genesis Ropes</a> and racking up the new <a href="http://www.bergfreunde.co.uk/petzl-laser-speed-ice-screw/">Petzl Laser Speed ice screws</a> as soon as I was on the ice and put my mind on the task ahead the fear was gone, tranquility and enjoyment flowing through me. As far as ice leads go this wasn’t the most difficult route ever, though I found the company and encouragement from Aleksi &amp; Mikko superb and they helped me to trust myself and lead on ice. Now I’m hungry for more and hope that next winter will be much better than this one, so that there will be much more ice climbing and leading!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075086492" title="My first ice lead at Tajukangas by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8723/17075086492_4b88107d6d_b.jpg" width="576" height="1024" alt="My first ice lead at Tajukangas" /></a></p>

<h2 id="hungry">Hungry?</h2>

<p><a href="http://pyhawurst.fi/">Pyhä Wurst</a> is a cozy little Restaurant/ Café at the bottom of the Northern Slope. They serve, as the name suggest, a variety of different sausages, and all three of us really found our food extremely tasty. Our son devoured a Hotdog - his first one! - and would have liked a second one, while M and me enjoyed a Bratwurst Hotdog and a Riistakäristys. They place was very popular with skiers &amp; snowboarders, walkers, cross-country skiers and families alike, so check them out when you’re in Pyhä and would like to taste some good Wurst!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050601976" title="PyhäWurst by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8732/17050601976_5f89cb12f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="PyhäWurst" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.cafeloimu.fi/en/">Café Loimu</a> was another Café which we enjoyed visiting almost daily as they served some super-tasty pancakes and good coffee. They’re located in the same building as the Nature Centre Naava so kids can even go and explore the museum on their own while the parents can enjoy a moment in the Café. Café Loimu is right in the middle of the village and also has an Á la carte Menu if you want to eat a bit more than pancakes or a sandwich.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://ski.pyha.fi/restaurants/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1019&amp;submenu=138">Hotel Pyhätunturi Restaurant</a> has a gorgeous Panorama view over the surroundings and is an ideal place to conclude a nice day outdoors, especially if the Northern Lights decide to show up and play a show over the forests and mires. M ate the best Sautéed reindeer (<em>poronkäristys</em> in Finnish) in her life at the Restaurant and found it so tasty that she still talks about how good it was. I enjoyed <em>The Poro</em> which was equally delicious, while E had problems finishing his kids meal of spaghetti and meatballs. The atmosphere and service at the Hotel Pyhätunturi Restaurant were excellent and if you stay in Pyhä we strongly recommend that you visit the restaurant.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16457137153" title="The Poro by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8686/16457137153_4fe83a661d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="659" alt="The Poro" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.huttu-uula.fi/">Restaurant Huttu-Uula</a> has won an Chaîne des Rôtisseurs award and is located at the foot of the Polar slope. Every Thursday it serves a <a href="http://www.huttu-uula.fi/files/uula_puffee.pdf">Lappish Food Buffet</a> with lots of delicious dishes from Lapland. The friendly atmosphere together with the good buffet food make this a recommended visit on a Thursday evening, though you should reserve well in advance as the Buffet is very popular and was fully booked out when we were there.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16889741440" title="Leipäjuusto by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7681/16889741440_7557737323_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Leipäjuusto" /></a></p>

<h2 id="fatbiking">Fatbiking</h2>

<p>Since I got my <a href="http://salsacycles.com/bikes/mukluk">Fatbike</a> cycling has been a lot of fun in winter. Riding over the frozen Baltic Sea, shredding over the single track in the forest and doing laps on the groomed trails are just a lot of fun, so of course I took the opportunity to go on a <a href="http://www.blissadventure.fi/en/fatbikes/">Fatbike Adventure at Pyhä</a>. I was very lucky that my friend Artturi was my guide for the morning, and after familiarizing myself with bike and hearing what Artturi had planned for us we hit the trails.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16888790748" title="Fatbiking, skiing or hiking? by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7676/16888790748_0235d89209_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fatbiking, skiing or hiking?" /></a></p>

<p>After some beautiful, flow-y single track trails we arrived at a large mire which was a lot of fun to ride across. We had a short break at a bird watching tower which allowed for wide views over the National Park, before continuing across the mire - fat tires rock in that terrain! Slowly narrow tracks brought us back to our starting point, and after a nice climb back up to the Hotel this little Fatbike adventure was done. You also can rent a Fatbike for half a day or longer from Bliss in case you want to explore the National Park on your own. Hats off to Bliss Adventure for offering this service, I think they’re spot on with it and I saw daily very happy fatbike cyclists riding on the trails and snow.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076575735" title="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8797/17076575735_d5ec086d2d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16456411083" title="Selfietime! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7610/16456411083_2d9c29dd7c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfietime!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17076574115" title="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7714/17076574115_7c29a3b793_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Artturi Kröger fatbiking in Pyhä-Luosto National Park" /></a></p>

<h2 id="snowshoe-hiking">(Snowshoe) Hiking</h2>

<p>There is a dedicated <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2010/01/video-msr-lightning-ascent-review.html">snowshoe</a> hiking trail in Pyhä, though it was so hard packed that one didn’t need snowshoes to walk on it. So we had a nice little family hike to the Isokuru gorge and back, which includes a steep descent and climb from the nice Isokuru Kota. The hike seems to take the route of the summer nature trail as we passed quite a few signs which gave information about the forest and land, and is ideal if you’d like to be outdoors for a couple of hours.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050611986" title="Danger! by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8813/17050611986_396e0e5472_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Danger!" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16456419973" title="Family Hike by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8687/16456419973_19757d8746_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Family Hike" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075086052" title="Fire by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7633/17075086052_af66532256_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Fire" /></a></p>

<h2 id="nature--silence">Nature &amp; Silence</h2>

<p>Despite all the activities you can do in Pyhä, there are two things in Pyhä-Luosto everywhere, and they’re for free: Nature and Silence. Even with a Baltic Ski Cup going on while we were in the village, we just needed to walk for five minutes towards the <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/en/pyha-luostonp">National Park</a> and there was a calmness that was just once in a while interrupted by birdsong or the wind blowing through the trees. Pyhä-Luosto National Park is home to the southern most big fjells in Finland, beyond them towards the south starts the flat land. Though this does make them popular I had at no time the feeling that there were too much people around me, for example the lines at the lifts were pretty much non-existent despite there being a bunch of people, and also in the Cafés and Restaurants there were never masses of people. As someone who values silence a lot I found Pyhä a great place, with easy access to nature and the possibility to <em>“escape”</em> the main slopes and head into the National Park, where even on blue bird days I didn’t meet more than a handful of people.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16869172217" title="Silver by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7613/16869172217_7c288c4b9e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Silver" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17050598466" title="Snow &amp; Birch by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8690/17050598466_e512ff6074_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Snow &amp; Birch" /></a></p>

<h2 id="practicalities">Practicalities</h2>

<p><strong>Where to stay?</strong></p>

<p>We stayed at a <a href="http://www.ski-inn.fi/majoitus.asp?prodtype=30&amp;lang=eng&amp;tunturi=&amp;day=&amp;endDay=">Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartment</a> which was ideally located right next to the slopes. The apartment was super family-friendly and had two bedrooms, a small kitchen, living room, balcony, a own Sauna and a drying cabinet to dry wet garments and gear (super handy with kids!). There are plenty more options in town, from the nice <a href="http://www.ski-inn.fi/majoitus.asp?prodtype=41&amp;lang=eng&amp;tunturi=&amp;changeMonth=">Ski-Inn Hotel Pyhätunturi</a> to many, many cozy <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=cabins&amp;submenu=3660">cabins</a> and even a <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/accommodation/?file=target_exec&amp;id=1106">caravan site</a> if you’re coming with your own accommodation. You’ll surely find something to your liking, keep an eye out for deals, though, as at e.g. the Ski-Inn PyhäSuites Apartments ski passes can be included in the price saving you a bunch of money!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16869175557" title="PyhäSuites by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7703/16869175557_09002a90bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="PyhäSuites" /></a></p>

<p><strong>How to get there?</strong></p>

<p>As we don’t own a car we rented one for a week and drove up north. Vaasa - Pyhä is around 660 km and with a toddler along we decided to split the journey in two and spend a night in Oulu. If you come from abroad you might want to fly directly to Rovaniemi and take the <a href="http://www.pyha.fi/summer/info/?file=content_exec&amp;id=2292&amp;submenu=3890">SkiBus</a> to Pyhä, or take the (overnight) train from Helsinki and then jump on the SkiBus. In the village you can walk pretty much everywhere within 15 minutes, and there’s a variety of shops to suit your needs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/sets/72157651506091295/">More Photos on Flickr</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/16454124174" title="No sledding by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8787/16454124174_baa0f5cd6b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="No sledding" /></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/17075081902" title="Aurora Borealis by Hendrik Morkel, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7644/17075081902_4025b6fd68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Aurora Borealis" /></a></p>

<p><em>Thanks to the Pyhä Ski Resort and their Partners which invited us up north.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
