<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: skiing | Hiking in Finland]]></title>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//blog/categories/skiing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//"/>
  <updated>2020-06-16T13:31:37+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hendrik Morkel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WRIGHTSOCK Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/02/wrightsock-review.html"/>
    <updated>2020-02-26T19:07:05+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/02/wrightsock-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No more blisters when hiking and skiing, and good-bye sweaty feet? Sounds too good to be true? Then read on to find out if WRIGHTSOCK socks can keep their promises!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591465078/in/dateposted-public/" title="Bushbuddy Ultra + WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591465078_2c0367097a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bushbuddy Ultra + WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This review was supported financially and with socks from WRIGHTSOCK. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<h2 id="tldr">tl;dr</h2>

<p>I found the WRIGHTSOCK Escape and Merino Stride socks good for hiking and every-day use, but got blisters on my shins when using the Merino Coolmesh II otc socks for skiing. When hiking and in normal use I didn’t get any Blisters, and my feet were less sweaty, but I still had moist feet after a day of hiking. Overall I think they’re good socks for colder weather and activities where you usually get really sweaty feet.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591965436/in/dateposted-public/" title="Hello, spring!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591965436_e5ea5e4f2b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hello, spring!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="time">Time</h2>

<p>My WRIGHTSOCK package arrived in late November, and contained a pair of COOLMESH II Merino, ESCAPE crew and MERINO STRIDE crew, all in Size Large (which fits feet between 41,5 and 45). They have been used all for several weeks, mostly for day hikes and normal, every-day use.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49592209382/in/dateposted-public/" title="A package of WRIGHTSOCK socks!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49592209382_0542d0f3e8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="A package of WRIGHTSOCK socks!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="function">Function</h2>

<p>The function of a sock is to absorb perspiration (= sweat!) as your feet are one of the biggest producers of sweat. Socks help to absorb the sweat from your feet and transport it to areas where air can evaporate the perspiration. And in cold weather, socks should insulate the foot and keep it toasty.</p>

<h2 id="features">Features</h2>

<ul>
  <li>All of the WRIGHTSOCK socks I tested were at least partly made from Dri-Wright, which is a Polyester fibre. Polyester dries quickly and keeps it shape/ form well, hence it is a good material for socks.</li>
  <li>All socks have an inner and outer layer, this construction is supposed to protect from blisters and help you keep dry feet</li>
  <li>Some of the socks I tested also had a Merino wool layer/ fabric, which made them less smelly and warmer</li>
  <li>And all socks also had a “stabilization zone” knitted into the metatarsal area</li>
</ul>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49592208062/in/dateposted-public/" title="Merino Stride socks"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49592208062_b86754082d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Merino Stride socks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591962146/in/dateposted-public/" title="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks inside-out"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591962146_c3ed568698_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks inside-out" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="quality">Quality</h2>

<p>The socks have held up well over the past three months and still look good. They can be washed at 40° which gets them nice and clean after a few days of use, and I expect them to hold at least another year or two of regular use.</p>

<h2 id="weight">Weight</h2>

<p>The weight of the socks, as a pair (so both socks!), in Size Large, are as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://wrightsockshop.de/wrightsock/sockenhoehen/otc-kniehoch/19/merino-coolmesh-ii-otc">Merino Coolmesh II otc socks</a>: 88 g</li>
  <li><a href="https://wrightsockshop.de/wrightsock/sportarten/outdoor-wandern/177/merino-stride-crew">Merino Stride socks</a>: 64 g</li>
  <li><a href="https://wrightsockshop.de/wrightsock/sportarten/outdoor-wandern/180/escape-crew">Escape socks</a>: 84 g</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="in-use">In use</h2>

<p>I’ll look at two different use-cases here: Using the Merino Coolmesh II otc socks for skiing and using the Escape and Merino Stride socks for hiking and every-day use. Lets start with skiing and the Merino Coolmesh II otc socks. I sweat a LOT when I ski, and it doesn’t matter if it is skitouring and skinning up a mountain or just riding the whole day in the front country - I have soaking wet socks after a day on skis. I used the Merino Coolmesh II otc with my <a href="http://tidd.ly/5d07ff6d">La Sportiva Synchro</a> in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2020/02/father-son-ski-trip.html">Ruka</a> for two days, and already after the first day I had a strange feeling on my shins, but didn’t pay any attention to it. That was a mistake.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547590647/in/dateposted-public/" title="DPS Cassiar 87"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547590647_7d16bb5e33_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Cassiar 87" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591466298/in/dateposted-public/" title="Merino Coolmesh II otc socks"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591466298_f76f4d55d8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Merino Coolmesh II otc socks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the second day on the slopes I had on each leg a big blister on my shins. I never had blisters on my shins, ever before, so you can imagine I was really surprised to find blisters on my legs from using socks which claim they don’t give you blisters! Needless to say, I didn’t use the socks for skiing after that anymore, and would not use the socks for skiing ever again. This is even more surprising as I was literally only downhill skiing, in a light boot which was fastened as usual. On the plus side, my feet were slightly less sweaty, but they still were moist when I took the socks off.</p>

<p>Which brings me to the Escape and Merino Stride socks, which I used for hiking and in everyday use. Currently we have the shittiest winter ever and no snow, but temps still drop down to -11°C or more in the mornings, and only slowly it rises throughout the day. In this weather these socks have been really good, and they kept my feet toasty and warm, even if I wore less warm shoes like the new <a href="http://tidd.ly/e9815221">Black Diamond Mission LT</a> shoes (I usually wear in the colder months the <a href="http://tidd.ly/ed40ce05">La Sportiva Crossover 2.0</a>). The Merino Stride socks are ideal for daily use as they can dry nicely inside, and they are toasty warm outside in the cold weather. The Escape is also great, though maybe a tiny bit less warm. Overall, as this are double-layer socks, they are warmer than other socks of a comparable weight, as in between the layers air is trapped, which helps keep your feet warm.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49592210972/in/dateposted-public/" title="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks + Black Diamond Mission LT"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49592210972_99ca71d410_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks + Black Diamond Mission LT" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Two things, though: I usually never get Blisters anymore as I use good shoes for hiking, backpacking, trailrunning and in every-day use, so I can not say that the claim of not getting Blisters when hiking with these socks works. Secondly, I still had moist feet when I took the socks off after a day outside, however, they were less sweaty than with normal socks. So while I still got sweaty feet they were less moist than with a normal pair of socks. I also liked the extra “cushioning” these socks had because of the two layers, and they also felt nice and comfortable on my feet - the white inner sock has a minimal amount of seams, which is really positive in my book.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591961861/in/dateposted-public/" title="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591961861_e98909d904_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="WRIGHTSOCK Escape socks" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="could-be-better">Could be better</h2>

<p>I don’t have suggestions for improvement, to be honest.</p>

<h2 id="bottomline">Bottomline</h2>

<p>Overall I liked the WRIGHTSOCK Escape and Merino Stride socks, and will use the Merino Coolmesh II otc socks for normal use when it’s cold, but not for skiing anymore. The Escape and Merino Stride socks are both well suited for backpacking and hiking, and the Escape sock definitely is the better pick for multi-day backpacking trips as it is made completely from synthetic materials and hence should dry faster than the Merino Stride socks. However, as most ultralight backpackers are well-used to hiking in wet footwear and hence moist socks, I think also the Merino Stride socks should be fine for backpacking. Especially if you have a problem with Blisters and really sweaty feet you might want to try these socks (<em>and please let me know if the “No Blisters System” works for you!</em>)!</p>

<script async="" src="//z0a.de/outtra-739.js?publisher_id=173&amp;widget_id=5490" type="text/javascript" id="outtraproductwallwdgt1735490" data-publisherid="173" data-outtrapwwdgt="5490"></script>

<p><strong>Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><img src="https://173.publisher.outtra.com/226724467/87225/qM7e5yBe2v/" width="0" height="0" style="display: none;" /></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49591645988/in/dateposted-public/" title="At the Beach &#x3D;)"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49591645988_5c5690ca78_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the Beach &#x3D;)" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Father-Son Ski Trip to Ruka, Finland]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/02/father-son-ski-trip.html"/>
    <updated>2020-02-18T14:33:09+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/02/father-son-ski-trip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A month ago my son and me went on a father-son winter trip: XC skiing, Ice-fishing and of course downhill skiing was our program for a week, in which we had a lot of fun and got to know each other better.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546854623/in/dateposted-public/" title="Gondel Cabins"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546854623_bfd21b191e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gondel Cabins" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This journey was supported by the local tourism bureau and partners, but I did not get paid to write about this trip. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>Travelling with kids, it can be a hassle. We found the best way to do it for us is to do it in sections with longer breaks in the middle, plenty of comics to read and some candy &amp; snacks. With that strategy the 9-ish hour trip from Vaasa to Ruka went by without problems, and my 8-year old son and me arrived nice and punctual with the Skibus in the village of <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/04/spring-skiing-in-ruka.html">Ruka</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546855563/in/dateposted-public/" title="On the road"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546855563_14c0513681_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the road" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>From the bus stop it was a one minute walk to our accommodation, the Ski-Inn right in the middle of Ruka Village. My skis were in the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/04/packing-for-ski-touring.html">Douchebag</a> and our clothes in the <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.eu/arcteryx-v110-rolling-duffel-luggage/?pid=10239">Arc’teryx V110 Rolling Duffle</a> which made it easy for me to pull all our stuff while my son only had to carry his own backpack. Once we checked in to our room - a very nice apartment with our own kitchen, Sauna and two bed rooms - we went for a walk to the supermarket in the village to get some Müsli and dinner, and as we were sitting for 9 hours on our butts it also was good to go for a walk in the village, and explore more of Ruka, before going to our Sauna and hitting the hay - because we had some full, exciting days ahead for us =)</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546857568/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ski Inn Apartment"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546857568_616545944b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Inn Apartment" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546856673/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ski Inn Apartment"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546856673_1500cbf2a4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Inn Apartment" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547360371/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ski Inn Apartment Sauna"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547360371_bfb3e159de_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Inn Apartment Sauna" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="skiing">Skiing</h2>

<p><strong>Or: Getting ready for off-piste adventures</strong></p>

<p>Day 1 in Ruka, and our first stop after breakfast is the <a href="https://ski.ruka.fi/en/pisterental">Piste Rental Shop</a> in the Village to pick up my son’s skis and our ski passes. Getting the gear is a fast affair and 10 Minutes later we’re outside again, sitting in the Gondola to Ruka Valley my son has a refresher session with <a href="https://new.ruka.fi/en/ski-school">Ruka Ski School</a>. We start on the brand-new Rosa &amp; Rudolf Slopes, where five belt lifts bring ski and snowboard beginners to the top of the fenced-in slope. After two runs the ski school teacher decides we will go to the real slopes right away as the young student is good enough.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546859573/in/dateposted-public/" title="Rosa &amp; Rudolf Ski Park"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546859573_6fbbc3d591_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rosa &amp; Rudolf Ski Park" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546859748/in/dateposted-public/" title="Belting up"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546859748_6e7615bf8f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Belting up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547587057/in/dateposted-public/" title="At the new Ruka Kids slope"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547587057_3f44a14c98_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="At the new Ruka Kids slope" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547587437/in/dateposted-public/" title="On the hill"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547587437_e110d40358_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the hill" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After an hour on the slopes and having skied down some red and blue slopes it’s time to explore the ski resort on our own, with the tips and advice from our great ski school teacher in mind. The one thing I love about Ruka Ski Resort is how easy it is to explore the different sides and hills of the area, and I take my son towards Maasto, the <em>“Off-the-beaten-track”</em> slopes in the east of the area. There’s substantially fewer people here skiing - and in the middle of January there’s already <em>REALLY</em> few people here! But we like it more silent, and the landscape with the snow-covered trees is here especially pretty, and there’s no-one waiting at the T-lift at the bottom of the slope either.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546859283/in/dateposted-public/" title="hanging"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546859283_367ef9e9ce_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="hanging" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547588942/in/dateposted-public/" title="Lighten up!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547588942_f93abf85f7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lighten up!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547362996/in/dateposted-public/" title="Downhill"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547362996_ceb4712b25_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Downhill" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And that’s how we spent several hours of the week each day. My son is a careful skier, and once we identified his favourite runs we would hit these first thing every day and then ski from left to right and back across the whole resort. We had some short breaks at the various huts or the Cafés along the slope, refilling energy levels with a hot chocolate and some Pulla, before it was back to the chair or T-Bar lifts and enjoy the finely prepared slopes anew.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547364836/in/dateposted-public/" title="Adventure Route"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547364836_980c0c861b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Adventure Route" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547590897/in/dateposted-public/" title="Brake at the Fire"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547590897_825d42a518_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Brake at the Fire" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547590647/in/dateposted-public/" title="DPS Cassiar 87"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547590647_7d16bb5e33_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="DPS Cassiar 87" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547590052/in/dateposted-public/" title="Kakao brake"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547590052_6343d8ec73_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kakao brake" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Night skiing is a thing when the sun goes up at 10:30 am and sets at 2:00 pm, and thanks to very well illuminated slopes it’s not a problem at all to ski in darkness. This is especially useful when a parent still has energy to go skiing while a child would rather read comics at home 😉</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547364316/in/dateposted-public/" title="#7"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547364316_44bb26e52f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="#7" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547590177/in/dateposted-public/" title="Night on the slopes"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547590177_80e882d091_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night on the slopes" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547595267/in/dateposted-public/" title="Night"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547595267_05d8538dfd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Night" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Overall I really had a great time skiing with my son at Ruka Ski Resort. I love the variety of runs and how easy it is to hit some off-piste terrain between the slopes. There are also enough easy routes and slopes which see less people, which makes it ideal if you’re there with kids.</p>

<h2 id="ice-fishing">Ice-fishing</h2>

<p><strong>Or: Learning to wait for the bait</strong></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547592972/in/dateposted-public/" title="Lake"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547592972_3ce980d304_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lake" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Besides daily skiing in the Ski resort we also had some other activities while we were in Ruka. One which my son and me enjoyed a lot was the visit to the <a href="https://www.palosaarenporotila.fi/en/">Reindeer and Fishing Farm Palosaari</a> closer to Kuusamo. We started our visit off with a ride on the reindeer sled, which was a lot of fun and my son got his <strong>Reindeer Driving License</strong> that day 😊</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547366726/in/dateposted-public/" title="On the sled"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547366726_f1e976b1f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the sled" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We continued down to the lake. This was an oasis of peace for me - I’m very sensitive to noise, and over here there was no disturbing noise as I hear it every day in the city. Out here on this calm lake there was only the wind which moved the snow-covered branches, and the occasional chirping of some Siberian Jays. Other than that there was only silence. Beautiful, natural silence.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547593567/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ice fishing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547593567_93955f3311_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ice fishing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Owner Mika showed us how to drill holes into the ice, clean the hole from slushy ice water, and then how to move our rods to entice the trout and bass in the lake to <em>go on the hook</em>. We discussed strategies - does it make sense to move every five minutes if you don’t have a contact or should you remain stationary for hours to wait till the fish come and visit you? The answer is, it depends. On the lake, you, the weather and temperature and the fish in the lake.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546864618/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ice fishing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546864618_c40fec0eba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ice fishing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547593837/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ice fishing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547593837_0dc5dfd3f2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ice fishing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547594057/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ice fishing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547594057_c018a5824a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ice fishing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547366996/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ice fishing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547366996_b6fbe2bc1d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ice fishing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We adopted a strategy of moving every 20 to 30 minutes, but even after a few times of drilling new holes and trying our best to present the bait in the most tasty fashion, no fish was around to fall for our tasty maggots and shiny baits. Ah well, a good thing that Mika had a back-up plan 😉 After a few hours out on the lake we walked up to the lean-to shelter, where a fire was already burning and hot juice &amp; coffee as well as tasty, home-made treats were served. We sat around the fire, discussed developments in the region and how they affect reindeer farmers and tourism in the area, and again I was left wondering while our politicans make decisions which no one I spoke to wants, and which only benefit large multi-national companies, to the detriment of the local environment and people. I finished up my second cup of tasty coffee and then we walked back to the lake, with new motivation and hope to catch one of these elusive inhabitants of the lake.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547367571/in/dateposted-public/" title="Brake while Ice fishing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547367571_0a8e7abeb7_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Brake while Ice fishing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Alas, also after another hour on the lake, moving and drilling several new holes into the ice, we had to admit that the fish were too smart for us (or simply not hungry 😃), as we didn’t catch a single one of them. However, my son, Anna-Riitta, Mika and me, we had a great time here on the silent lake, and so we were not at all disappointed when we packed up our fishing gear and headed back to the farm. Mika handed us our <a href="https://www.palosaarenporotila.fi/en/">Reindeer and Fishing Farm Palosaari</a> Reindeer Driving license, which now allows us to manoeuvre sleds pulled by Rudolf and his siblings, and then we made us on the way back to Ruka and hit the slopes for some afternoon skiing!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547368061/in/dateposted-public/" title="Lake II"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547368061_13caf81748_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lake II" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="ice-climbing">Ice climbing</h2>

<p><strong>Or: Why am I still this good?</strong></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547357471/in/dateposted-public/" title="Tools of the Trade"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547357471_3bb20f9e5d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tools of the Trade" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The long-time reader knows <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2013/03/ice-climbing-in-korouoma.html">I love ice climbing</a> but also is likely aware that I haven’t climbed much ice in recent years. The winters have been bad, I have discovered skitouring as a beautiful way to explore the outdoors in winter, and I also don’t have a lot of friends that climb ice anymore.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546854623/in/dateposted-public/" title="Gondel Cabins"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546854623_bfd21b191e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Gondel Cabins" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>That all would change during our visit to Ruka, and to top things off my 8-year old son would also get to climb his first ice route! <a href="https://www.outdoorpassion.fi/en/">Outdoor Passion Finland</a>, which is run by Jussi and his wife Lotta, took us under their wings and both thought my son and rekindled my love for ice climbing. Lotta and Jussi are perfect with kids, and after we were kitted out with crampons, gaiters, harness, helmets and ice tools we hiked like John Wayne to the ice fall, which is in the middle of the ski resort and a spectacular 35 m high. But before we were allowed to climb, Jussi gave us a introduction to climbing on ice, from foot and tool placement to how to get back down.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546862903/in/dateposted-public/" title="Learning to ice climb"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546862903_780c26c9b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Learning to ice climb" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546854893/in/dateposted-public/" title="Little man high up"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546854893_a26904bd3f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Little man high up" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>My son was very brave and climbed his route really well, and I am very proud of him that he climbed this ice fall! I too did some ice climbing, and surprised myself quite a bit as I seemed to be able to climb the different routes without any issues. I haven’t climbed ice (or rock, or plastic 😟) in the past two years, so it was a bit of a shock that even on the steep route I had no problem with placing tools and crampons, climbing onto smaller ledges, and that there were also no screaming barfies. I even raced up the simplest route and got to the anchor in under two minutes…</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546854458/in/dateposted-public/" title="Selfie"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546854458_80330d8b7e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfie" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After all the climbing Lotta and Jussi took us to explore the Ground-Ferrata which they had built in the nearby forest. It’s basically a track which takes you through the snow-covered forest, through the snow-covered spruce trees 🌲 ❤️ and back to the ice wall. It was simple, but very beautiful and a great experience to go through the snow tunnel under the tree and climb back out!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547591822/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ground Ferrata"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547591822_f11b71e2b4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ground Ferrata" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546863463/in/dateposted-public/" title="Hiking"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546863463_2e0902058c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hiking" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547592182/in/dateposted-public/" title="Shadows"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547592182_8b04a95927_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Shadows" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="xc-skiing">XC Skiing</h2>

<p><strong>Or: There and Back again</strong></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547369956/in/dateposted-public/" title="XC skiing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547369956_11f93fc12d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="XC skiing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On our last full day in Ruka we decided to go XC skiing. My son usually goes XC skiing at school, but due to climate change and the ongoing disastrous winter winter we have in Vaasa he hasn’t been even once skiing with school, and as it is also an activity I enjoy a lot I felt it would be a good thing to do. What I didn’t account for was the strong, cold wind which was blowing across Lapland that morning, and which would bring a lot more snow over the following days to the North of the country…</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547596542/in/dateposted-public/" title="XC skiing 2"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547596542_608363c97a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="XC skiing 2" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547585032/in/dateposted-public/" title="XC skiing 3"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547585032_bedcf5c170_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="XC skiing 3" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We started again at the <a href="https://ski.ruka.fi/en/pisterental">Piste Rental Shop</a> where we loaned our XC skiing gear, and then we took the Gondola to Ruka Valley from where we would ski around 3,5 km to a Café. So far the plan. The reality was that the weather really wasn’t very favourable, as we were skiing into the wind and snow, which my son didn’t enjoy particularly much. However, with the promise of a hot chocolate and pancakes or waffles we made it in the end to the small, cozy Café, where we enjoyed our break.</p>

<p>The way back, as these things usually go, was easier. With the wind in our back, and some tasty treats in our bellies, as well as some gentle, fun downhills, we were back at the Gondola Station in Ruka Valley in some 30 minutes! We were also really lucky as just as we arrived a Gondola came in, and so we were sitting down in one of the cabins to get back to Ruka Village.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546856213/in/dateposted-public/" title="XC skiing 4"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546856213_a923e977da_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="XC skiing 4" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547358706/in/dateposted-public/" title="XC skiing V"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547358706_31ecf8d7c1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="XC skiing V" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547584502/in/dateposted-public/" title="XC skiing maisemat"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547584502_3ced9f5aae_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="XC skiing maisemat" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="polar-night-light-festival">Polar Night Light Festival</h2>

<p><strong>Or: Did you see that?!</strong></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49412716163/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ruka Slopes during the Polar Night Light Festival"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49412716163_a1d440894c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Slopes during the Polar Night Light Festival" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The <a href="http://lightfestival.fi">Polar Night Light Festival</a> is an annual Festival which transforms the slopes of Ruka into a colourful wonderland, with amazing light installations all across the village and slopes. It’s always in January as then it is still really dark up North, and definitely worth a visit. As a photographer I absolutely loved to see this Festival, and I highly recommend you take a good Tripod, footwear with good grip and warm clothes along if you plan to photograph them, as it does get cold on the slopes at night. Also take care of the Pistenbullies and snowmobiles which might ride on the slopes at night and prepare everything for skiers and snowboarders! Of course you also can just enjoy the installations when you go skiing after the sun set at 2:00 pm 😆</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413388392/in/dateposted-public/" title="Polar Night Light FestivalIV"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413388392_a855685a20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Polar Night Light FestivalIV" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49412716533/in/dateposted-public/" title="Blacklight Art at the Polar Night Light Festival"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49412716533_b5e57b5480_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Blacklight Art at the Polar Night Light Festival" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413389232/in/dateposted-public/" title="Blacklight Art at the Polar Night Light Festival"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413389232_2fa531705b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Blacklight Art at the Polar Night Light Festival" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413190121/in/dateposted-public/" title="Seeing Red at the Polar Night Light Festival"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413190121_36cd237050_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Seeing Red at the Polar Night Light Festival" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413189246/in/dateposted-public/" title="Polar Night Light Festival II"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413189246_ce6ca1c0ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Polar Night Light Festival II" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="being-a-good-parent">Being a good parent</h2>

<p><strong>Or: Learning to put others first</strong></p>

<p>My son and me, we can be like water &amp; fire, OR then we can be best friends. When it is just the two of us, and he gets all my attention, things definitely are a lot easier and we get along really well. I also am more relaxed, and try to remember to put his wants &amp; needs before mine. For example, if he gets tired or has no motivation to hit the slopes after a while, I usually have a hard time to accept that, but the smart, emphatic side of my brain then tells me to just let him go back to the apartment and chill &amp; read comics, while I continue to ski. That way be both are happy, and skiing (or other activities) don’t get a bad connotation for him, which means in the long-run he’s more likely to enjoy these activities as much as me. After all, we were here to have a good time together, and when one is not enjoying something it’s not smart to force him to do it. With high costs for renting gear and lift passes it’s easy to forget these things, but in the long-term I feel it’s better for all involved, and it definitely worked well for us on this and past trips.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49412715153/in/dateposted-public/" title="😛"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49412715153_1e233c3f00_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="😛" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="what-to-eat--where-to-stay">What to Eat &amp; Where to Stay</h2>

<p>We stayed at the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/rukasuites">Ski Inn</a> in the centre of Ruka Village, and had a super-nice apartment. We enjoyed the Sauna every evening together, and the small kitchen was all I needed to cook some simple meals for us two. The Supermarket was a stone-throw away, as were a handful of restaurants and Cafés. There are plenty more <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/where-to-stay">places to stay in Ruka</a> for any budget, and especially the brand-new <a href="https://www.ski-inn.fi/en/majoitus/ruka/hotel-rukavalley">Ruka Valley</a> Hotel &amp; Apartments look like a great choice for families as the Kids Slope are in front of the building!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546860063/in/dateposted-public/" title="Kids slop"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546860063_8a486a894d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kids slop" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We ate in a variety of places during our stay, from the new <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/campkitchen">CAMP Kitchen</a> which serves a super-tasty Vegan Bowl and a good kids Burger, to <a href="https://ruokburger.fi">RUOK</a> and <a href="http://www.hankibaari.fi">Hankibaari</a> which have very good options for people with all kind of diets. We also cooked at least once a day in our apartment, basics like Pesto-Pasta and Pizza kept the food expenses low and were really good, too!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49547595512/in/dateposted-public/" title="Menu at CAMP"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49547595512_c36d4f48e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Menu at CAMP" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49546867443/in/photostream/" title="&#x27;burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49546867443_9a7af7657a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="&#x27;burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="getting-to-ruka">Getting to Ruka</h2>

<p>As I have <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2019/04/spring-skiing-in-ruka.html">said in the past</a>: The most convenient way is to take the <a href="http://vr.fi">train</a> and <a href="https://matkahuolto.fi">bus</a> to Ruka, or if you come from abroad you can fly to the <a href="https://www.finavia.fi/en/airports/kuusamo">Kuusamo Airport</a> and take the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/getting-around">Ski Bus</a> to the village and Ruka Valley. In the winter <a href="https://www.onnibus.com/">OnniBus</a> has direct connections from the south to Ruka which are really affordable and a really good option as one doesn’t need to change. On the train you can sleep, work and walk around, and during the bus trip you can enjoy the beautiful Finnish landscape while listening to your favourite tunes. We downloaded the Finnish version of the Donald Duck Comic magazine which allowed us to download hundreds of comics to the iPad, which made for a relaxing trip as my son was reading hours at a time on the bus &amp; train. Also some salty and sweet treats were handed out every now and then, and longer breaks were scheduled in so we didn’t need to stress in case a train or bus were running late.</p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on a Discord Chat with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413188991/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ruka Village"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413188991_f92d1acdd3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Village" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions from our Father-Son Ski Trip]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/01/impressions-from-our-father-son-ski-trip.html"/>
    <updated>2020-01-20T10:13:50+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2020/01/impressions-from-our-father-son-ski-trip</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Need some Monday Morning Motivation? Here’s some photos from our father-son trip to Ruka in Lapland, where we found lots of snow!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49412715153/in/dateposted-public/" title="😛"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49412715153_1e233c3f00_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="😛" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This journey was supported by the local tourism bureau and partners, but I did not get paid to write about this trip. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>The skiing season 2020 started in Ruka for me, and I was really happy to have my 8-year old son along. These kind of trips are great to bond with the kids, learn more about them, and of course also share my passion for the outdoors with them. Plenty of hot chocolates where consumed, Pokemons were caught, and of course we also had a lot of fun on the slopes of the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/">Ruka Ski Resort</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49412715208/in/dateposted-public/" title="Maasto"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49412715208_16869e6bfe_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Maasto" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413386762/in/dateposted-public/" title="Adventure Track"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413386762_c48763f994_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Adventure Track" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Besides skiing the slopes every day, we also had a few activities planned. Ice climbing with <a href="https://www.outdoorpassion.fi/en/">Outdoor Passion Finland</a> for example.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413186941/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ice-climbing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413186941_8b54b68a19_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ice-climbing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413385092/in/dateposted-public/" title="Selfie time at 35 m above the ground"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413385092_1de74d05c1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfie time at 35 m above the ground" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49412716003/in/dateposted-public/" title="Fun at the Ice Wall"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49412716003_1355e0ab81_b.jpg" width="683" height="1024" alt="Fun at the Ice Wall" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And ice fishing and a reindeer ride at the <a href="https://www.palosaarenporotila.fi/en/">Palosaari Reindeer and Fishing Ranch</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413187326/in/dateposted-public/" title="I have one!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413187326_d9892ca569_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="I have one!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413385707/in/dateposted-public/" title="Peaceful Pond II"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413385707_65afd1192d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Peaceful Pond II" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49412717983/in/dateposted-public/" title="Racing with Rudolph"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49412717983_38307261dc_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Racing with Rudolph" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And we were pretty lucky that the <a href="">Polar Night Light Festival</a> kicked off while we were there - it’s on till the 1st of February if you wanna see it yourself!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413188991/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ruka Village"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413188991_f92d1acdd3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Village" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49412716163/in/dateposted-public/" title="Ruka Slopes during the Polar Night Light Festival"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49412716163_a1d440894c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Slopes during the Polar Night Light Festival" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413388392/in/dateposted-public/" title="Polar Night Light FestivalIV"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413388392_a855685a20_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Polar Night Light FestivalIV" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There also was some Nordic XC Skiing, eating tasty food, and relaxing in the Sauna at our flat. That and more I’ll tell you about in my article, which comes in the end of January!</p>

<p>If you enjoyed this teaser <strong>support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong> <em>and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on Discord with me, and Discount codes for kit from partners!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikmorkel/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/49413188451/in/dateposted-public/" title="Rudolf"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/65535/49413188451_0c3ba068ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Rudolf" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Skiing in Ruka]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/spring-skiing-in-ruka.html"/>
    <updated>2019-04-08T19:04:43+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/04/spring-skiing-in-ruka</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The skiing season 2019 isn’t over just yet - there’s still great snow to be shredded in the far North of Finland, as I experienced last weekend in Ruka.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646623965/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Spring Powder"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7858/46646623965_b78d7ffb1e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Spring Powder" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This journey was supported by the local tourism bureau and partners, but I did not get paid to write about this trip. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>As part of me trying to minimize my environmental footprint but unwilling to not ski I travelled last weekend by train and bus to Ruka-Kuusamo, some 500 kilometres from Vaasa away. Even with short stop-overs between switching from the train to the Bus it’s almost a 10 hour journey to get to Ruka, though as you can walk around in the train, there’s good internet and you can work there’s nothing to worry about. Though I was happy that I was able to get out on the hills once I arrived in Ruka, and with the lifts being open till 19 o’clock I got in a few hours of skiing on the slopes after a full day of travelling - not a bad start! And to make it even better, it had been snowing the whole Thursday and would continue throughout the night.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685356208/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Thursday Evening Skiing"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7894/33685356208_52fecd4a85_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Thursday Evening Skiing" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After the skiing I went to have Dinner at <a href="https://ruokburger.fi">RUOK Burger</a> which is just next door from my apartment in the <a href="https://www.ski-inn.fi/en/majoitus/ruka">Ruka Village Ski-Inn</a>. Their Portobello Burger was the only vegetarian option and super-tasty, and I accompanied it with a local Craft Beer from Rovaniemi, a nice Amber Lager. After that I retired to my cozy apartment, heated up the Sauna and watched how it was snowing outside. Being on ski holidays it is always great to watch it snow ❄️ as that means fresh powder the next day when you’re outside on the hills!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646623875/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="RUOK Burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7829/46646623875_4970e1c601_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="RUOK Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685357508/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="RUOK Burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7842/33685357508_757fa2a7c0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="RUOK Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646623605/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Super-Tasty Portobello Burger at RUOK Burger"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7847/46646623605_f97ab2cb84_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Super-Tasty Portobello Burger at RUOK Burger" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619681437/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="LOCAL BEER!"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7837/32619681437_6e36cc1bc8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="LOCAL BEER!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning a bright blue sky woke me up, and all signs were on an amazing day on and off the slopes. There’s just something great about hitting the slopes and being one of the first ones there. I love painting my curves into the still un-shredded corduroy, and then Veera and me went into the side-country to look for some powder. And powder we found.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619681717/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Fresh Corduroy"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7837/32619681717_97340350c9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Fresh Corduroy" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619681817/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Untouched snow"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7926/32619681817_95d39fa4c5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Untouched snow" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646624275/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Chair lifts galore"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7865/46646624275_60b6b2977c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Chair lifts galore" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It really feels amazing to surf through the fluffy snow and throw up big swoops of the white gold. Veera and me both had big smiles on our faces after cruising through the powder-filled forests, so once it was noon we went to <a href="http://www.hankibaari.fi">Hanki Baari</a> for lunch, where I ate a tasty vegan Mie Goreng. Hanki Baari is either way an amazing place to chill after a day on the slopes, listening to music and drinking some fancy beers, though right now we just needed some good nutrition before hitting the slopes again.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619682177/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Vegan Mie Goreng Lunch at Hanki Baari"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7802/32619682177_ce4405d1bf_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Vegan Mie Goreng Lunch at Hanki Baari" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646624635/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ski Pride Ruka Weekend"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7818/46646624635_608e794bd0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Pride Ruka Weekend" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>So, after a coffee ☕️ it was time to go ride some more. After all, the sun was shining, the slopes were in prime condition and the lifts would be running till 23 o’clock (Fridays the Ruka Ski Resort’s lifts run so late because those who journey after work to Ruka still can hit the illuminated slopes!). However, we wouldn’t ski that long, as we had another plan.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619683337/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Disembark"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7899/32619683337_d41391c1cd_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Disembark" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646626385/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Them views"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7813/46646626385_f4b0109446_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Them views" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596169873/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="In the Shadows"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7836/40596169873_f159cf0de1_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="In the Shadows" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We went on a little powder hunt with friends of Veera, which resulted in a short but exhausting climb through hip-deep snow back to the slopes from the lake 🤣 After that I went for a few more laps on the slopes before calling it a day. A quick shower later I was sitting in the <a href="https://www.pizzeriaruka.fi/en/">Pizzeria Ruka</a> which is probably the best Pizza you can get in Ruka. It’s a five minute stroll from the centre of the village to the Pizzeria, and their wood-fired oven served me in no time a delicious Tartufo Pizza. That’s exactly what I needed after almost six hours of skiing, and gave me enough energy for the hike we had planned for the evening.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596170443/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Pizza"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7810/40596170443_c0d176d536_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Pizza" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596170753/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Tasty Slices at Pizzeria Ruka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7845/40596170753_19d235de5a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tasty Slices at Pizzeria Ruka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As a <a href="https://www.hendrikmorkel.com">photographer</a> I hate it to spend a gorgeous sunset inside, so I was happy that Veera and her dog were up for a sunset mission to Konttainen, a hill some 10 minutes away from Ruka. A steep 11 minute climb later we were on the top of Konttainen, and strolled towards the best spot in the house while the show was just starting. It’s soooooo much better to be outside in nature when the sun sets than sitting inside, and this definitely was an evening well spent. After the sun disappeared from view we gazed for a while onto the illuminated slopes of Ruka, and for a moment I was tempted to jump back into my <a href="http://bit.ly/2D2JtFL">ski boots</a> and go for some night skiing. But then I remembered my warm Sauna and the cold beer which were waiting for me, so I skipped the night skiing and relaxed in my apartment before calling it a night.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596171763/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Sunset Show just staring"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7817/40596171763_a31c40d077_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Sunset Show just staring" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619686237/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Getting better"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7880/32619686237_1dd76bc6a0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Getting better" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619687547/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Excitement is rising"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7851/32619687547_15fce8cfa6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Excitement is rising" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596172983/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Almost there"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7882/40596172983_e03b838190_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Almost there" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596173143/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="And almost down"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7802/40596173143_cec399d4e3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="And almost down" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619688517/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka&#x27;s Slopes illuminated"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7874/32619688517_26d6af67f8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka&#x27;s Slopes illuminated" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The next morning white clouds hung over the mountain and gave the slopes and village a sci-fi feel. I’s the kind of weather where you ponder if you should just stay inside and chill-lax, but as I wanted to get my skis on that didn’t happen and early on Saturday morning Veera and me where again on the slopes, searching for some untracked pockets of powder.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596173853/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Misty Mornings"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7917/40596173853_5b147ff40c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Misty Mornings" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562164731/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Coming from the future"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7851/47562164731_dc69c53e4a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Coming from the future" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596174403/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="First lines"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7826/40596174403_e2e0553318_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="First lines" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596174683/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Dystopian Future"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7848/40596174683_8f912da413_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Dystopian Future" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And slowly but surely the sun was burning through the clouds and as the day progressed the views came out again, and we also were lucky by finding some fine lines of untouched powder not far from the hustle and bustle of the slopes.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646634175/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Views again"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7819/46646634175_d07a221fc4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views again" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596175043/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="POW POW"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7891/40596175043_239e14fdb3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="POW POW" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47509265442/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Maasto"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7876/47509265442_18aae9f36f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Maasto" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After all that off-piste skiing it was time to join the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/ski-pride">Ruka Ski Pride</a> Parade. I really ❤️ that Ruka has this event which celebrates equal rites and diversity on the slopes, and the vibe was so positive and fun - I really enjoyed to be part of it 🌈 Besides this parade there were inclusive events the whole weekend, with concerts and DJs, and of course some good skiing!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685355138/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ski Pride 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7915/33685355138_926a6e9038_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Pride 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33685354418/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7841/33685354418_a365919e9f_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/32619676697/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7857/32619676697_618d2b6e71_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Ski Pride Parade 2019" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And then the day was almost over again. But not before I skied one final time from the East to the West, and from the North to the South across the whole resort. I love to ski fast and go from one end of a resort to the other one, shredding down the slopes and throwing up clouds of slushy spring snow, and at the end of this Saturday my trusty <a href="https://www.bergfreunde.de/suunto-spartan-ultra-black-multifunktionsuhr/?pid=10239">Suunto Spartan Ultra</a> told me I had skied almost 50 km of distance this day, and I could tell by how my legs felt.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562166431/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Tuntori"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7825/47562166431_77d3603d05_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ruka Tuntori" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562167221/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="SUPER PIPE"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7801/47562167221_1a1b79536c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="SUPER PIPE" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46838345644/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="The Ruka Gondola"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7831/46838345644_293ff94e4e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="The Ruka Gondola" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562152021/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Towards the sun"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7909/47562152021_744e195d9a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Towards the sun" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596162833/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Views for days"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7823/40596162833_a85297ed36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Views for days" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After some relaxing I met Mats for Dinner at <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/villisika">Villisika</a> from where you have the best view over the slopes, so while we were eating we could see how the snow groomers got the hill ready for the next day. Sadly, the next sunny day I wouldn’t be shredding the groomers, as I was sitting in the train and bus back south. But I have a feeling that I will travel North once more for more skiing before the winter truly ends ❄️</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562151491/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Tasty Dinner at Villisika"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7814/47562151491_0ff6a3b8e6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tasty Dinner at Villisika" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47509251882/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Blueberry Dessert at Villisika"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7841/47509251882_02dd732888_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Blueberry Dessert at Villisika" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As always, there’s more photos in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157707789591555">Photo Album</a>.</p>

<h2 id="spring-skiing-in-ruka">Spring Skiing in Ruka</h2>

<p>As you can see above, winter isn’t over just yet in Finnish Lapland, even if it may feel like it here in the south where most of the snow is already gone. Until early May there’s plenty of great skiing to be had in Northern Finland, and if you’re like me and can not get enough of skiing and winter then you too should steal away for a weekend to Ruka for some spring skiing. The slopes in <a href="https://www.ruka.fi">Ruka</a> are open till early May, and between now and the closing of the slopes there’s every weekend a weekend of fun to be had: Next weekend, from the 11.4. - 14.4.2019 is the legendary <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/spring-break">Ruka Spring Break</a> which will enlighten those who like to Party between hitting the groomers. The <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/easter">Easter Weekend</a> has winter activities for the whole family on offer, and the first of May is the traditional <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/wappulounas">Wappulounas</a>, a get-together of the international snowboard community on the slopes of Ruka. So don’t ponder longer - go and get some of that spring snow!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562152531/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Higher"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7910/47562152531_d8bef744e9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Higher" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="where-to-stay">Where to Stay</h2>

<p>I stayed at the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/rukasuites">Ski Inn</a> and liked my apartment in the centre of the village. It was a two minute stroll to the Gondola and lift, a one minute walk to the supermarket, and Hanki Baari was even in the same building so I didn’t had to go far for a beer! There’s plenty more <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/where-to-stay">places to stay in Ruka</a> for any budget, and if you’re pondering where to eat: Just follow my recommendations above or try any of the other restaurants in the village and it’s surroundings.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46646624975/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ruka Village Ski-Inn"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7834/46646624975_6c51f4fbd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="650" alt="Ruka Village Ski-Inn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/40596173453/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="My apartment at the Ski-Inn"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7923/40596173453_1f5d8249d0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="My apartment at the Ski-Inn" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<h2 id="getting-to-ruka">Getting to Ruka</h2>

<p>The most convenient way is to take the <a href="http://vr.fi">train</a> and <a href="https://matkahuolto.fi">bus</a> to Ruka, or if you come from abroad you can fly to the <a href="https://www.finavia.fi/en/airports/kuusamo">Kuusamo Airport</a> and take the <a href="https://www.ruka.fi/en/getting-around">Ski Bus</a> to Ruka. On the train you can sleep, work and walk around, and during the bus trip you can enjoy the beautiful Finnish landscape while listening to your favourite tunes.</p>

<p><strong>Enjoyed this article?</strong> Support me on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a> and get some useful rewards (like hanging out on a Discord Chat with me, where you can pick my brains!) or <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/47562151761/in/album-72157707789591555/" title="Ski Pride Ruka"><img src="https://live.staticflickr.com/7814/47562151761_f7e96bc0f5_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ski Pride Ruka" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions from Åre, Winter Edition]]></title>
    <link href="http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/02/impressions-from-are.html"/>
    <updated>2019-02-01T13:52:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hikinginfinland.com//2019/02/impressions-from-are</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Impressions from a family skiing trip to Åre, Sweden!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947576641/in/dateposted/" title="Frozen sky"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7913/46947576641_fd428e6402_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Frozen sky" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>Disclosure</strong>: <em>This journey was supported by the local tourism bureau and partners, but I did not got paid to write about this trip. As you know: I’m keepin’ it real and tell you how it is - I maintain full editorial control of the content published on Hiking in Finland. Read the <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/about/">Transparency Disclaimer</a> for more information on blogger transparency and affiliate links.</em></p>

<p>After my visit to <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/10/active-holidays-in-are-sweden.html">Åre in the autumn</a> I knew I wanted to come back, and that I should bring my family so we can experience the beauty of the Swedish mountains together! Again we travelled by ferry and train to this little village, which is in the midst of preparing for the Åre 2019 FIS Alpine World Ski Championship which start next week! As usual, this is a photo-intensive article which gives you a taste of the stories which will come when I return from the ISPO 2019 in Munich and some skiing in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2016/09/family-adventures-in-vorarlberg.html">Vorarlberg</a>!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/33072013328/in/dateposted/" title="Our 3-year old is learning to ski"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7880/33072013328_840ef2cb4e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Our 3-year old is learning to ski" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Our 3-year old daughter learned to ski ❤️ The smile on her face is amazing, and we are so proud of her!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947607191/in/dateposted/" title="Hermelinbacken"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7842/46947607191_d781491601_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Hermelinbacken" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Similarly, our 7 year old son also improved his skiing by bounds! While he learned to ski some years ago in <a href="https://hikinginfinland.com/2018/01/skiing-in-vuokatti.html">Vuokatti</a> this year in Åre he went big and bold! I had many great runs with him, and look forward to many more!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947604541/in/dateposted/" title="Off to Åre!"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7806/46947604541_0766fe9f36_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Off to Åre!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Also my wife and me had some time with one of the friendly Ski School instructors! I got a reminder on how to better control my skis and tips on getting down steep, shitty runs.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947605971/in/dateposted/" title="Illuminated runs"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7863/46947605971_ecec5f9340_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Illuminated runs" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There also was some night skiing.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947606531/in/dateposted/" title="Åre Railway Station"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7914/46947606531_f3802ba8af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Åre Railway Station" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947604951/in/photostream/" title="Piza at Werséns"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4835/46947604951_bd41f8dac4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Piza at Werséns" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46033621125/in/dateposted/" title="Good coffee inside"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4867/46033621125_f0c5094248_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Good coffee inside" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And visits to the village for some Pizza, swimming, coffee and grocery shopping.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947607411/in/dateposted/" title="Up &amp; Down"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4809/46947607411_0193794260_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Up &amp; Down" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947606851/in/dateposted/" title="At the top"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7802/46947606851_d83eabfe6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="At the top" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Of course there was lots and lots of great skiing on the slopes.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46033622585/in/dateposted/" title="Morning Glory Reloaded"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7894/46033622585_32aeceafeb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Morning Glory Reloaded" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947608011/in/dateposted/" title="Pastel Colours"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4832/46947608011_1e16bf8f19_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="Pastel Colours" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>And even a superb ski tour to the top of Åreskutan!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947606261/in/dateposted/" title="ÅRE 2019 is coming to town aka FIS Alpine World Ski Championships"><img src="https://farm5.staticflickr.com/4817/46947606261_ba8ee0c5a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="576" alt="ÅRE 2019 is coming to town aka FIS Alpine World Ski Championships" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Everywhere there were signs of the <a href="https://are2019.com">Åre 2019 FIS Alpine World Ski Championship</a> - if you want to see more from Åre and the world-class ski stars, make sure to check out the <a href="https://are2019.com">Åre 2019</a> website to follow the spectacle. You also could just hop on a train to Åre and view it live - and if the weather forecast holds on, it should be quite a good time for some of your own skiing, too! <em>After my visit to Munich and Vorarlberg I’ll write up in detail everything there is to know about a family skiing visit to Åre, so make sure to <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/atom.xml">subscribe via RSS</a> to not miss any post! You already can view some more photos on in the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/albums/72157706387355144">Åre 2019 Album</a> on Flickr.</em></p>

<p><strong>I am now on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/hendrikmorkel">Patreon</a></strong>. If you feel that you get value out of my articles and videos - become a Patron for as low as a cup of coffee a month! <em>Or if you enjoyed this &amp; other articles <a href="https://paypal.me/hendrikmorkel">buy me a coffee on PayPal</a> - I work Full-Time on Hiking in Finland to bring you inspiring trip reports, in-depth gear reviews and the latest news from the outdoors. You also could <a href="http://hikinginfinland.us2.list-manage1.com/subscribe?u=b29c2acd04d959eace48da780&amp;id=46b5d0326f">subscribe to the rarer-than-ever Newsletter</a> and follow along on <a href="https://instagram.com/hendrikm/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hendrikmorkel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hikinginfinland/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/hendrikmorkel">Youtube</a> for more outdoorsy updates!</em></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/hendrikmorkel/46947608831/in/dateposted/" title="Selfie!"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7883/46947608831_8e6d67713e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Selfie!" /></a><script async="" src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
